<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd"
     xml:id="nnan145466">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>coinage of the second Saffarid dynasty in Sistan</title>
            <author>
               <name>Walker, John, 1900-1964</name>
               <idno type="URI">http://viaf.org/viaf/94905946</idno>
            </author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>TEI P5 XML markup in conformance with the TEI DTD</resp>
               <name>AEL Data</name>
            </respStmt>
            <funder>The Andrew W. Mellon Foundation</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <name>American Numismatic Society</name>
               <idno type="URI">http://numismatics.org/authority/american_numismatic_society</idno>
            </publisher>
            <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
            <date>1936</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">This work is made available under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International license</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Numismatic Notes and Monographs</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">72</biblScope>
            <idno type="URI">http://numismatics.org/library/195778</idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>Donum</title>
               <idno type="URI">http://numismatics.org/library/145466</idno>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <title>Worldcat</title>
               <idno type="URI">http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/1013747820</idno>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <title>Worldcat Works</title>
               <idno type="URI">http://worldcat.org/entity/work/id/5185319</idno>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://nomisma.org/">
               <term ref="http://nomisma.org/id/islamic_numismatics">Islamic Numismatics</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2018-04-02">Ran TEI file through XSLT process, detailed in the Mellon EBook migration Google Document.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div1 xml:id="d70e30" type="cover">
            <pb/>
            <figure xml:id="fig-1">
               <graphic url="NNM72_01.jpg"/>
            </figure>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d70e34" type="frontma">
            <pb/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="bold">PUBLICATIONS</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi rend="bold">The American Journal of Numismatics, 1866–1920.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Monthly, May, 1866–April, 1870.</p>
            <p>Quarterly, July, 1870–October, 1912.</p>
            <p>Annually, 1913–1920.</p>
            <p rend="hang">With many plates, illustrations, maps and tables. Less than a half-dozen complete sets of the Journal remain on hand. Price on application.</p>
            <p rend="hang">The numbers necessary to complete broken sets may in most cases be obtained. An index to the first fifty volumes has been issued as part of Volume LI. It may be purchased separately for $3.00.</p>
            <p rend="hang">The American Numismatic Society. Catalogue of the International Exhibition of Contemporary Medals. March, 1910. New and revised edition. <placeName>New York</placeName>. 1911. xxxvi, 412 pages, 512 illustrations. $10.00. Price to members, $5.00.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d70e57" type="frontma">
            <pb/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="bold">NUMISMATIC NOTES AND MONOGRAPHS</hi>
            </head>
            <p/>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d70e63" type="dedication">
            <pb/>
            <p>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">Numismatic Notes and Monographs</hi> is devoted to essays and treatises on subjects relating to coins, paper money, medals and decorations, and is uniform with Hispanic Notes and Monographs published by the Hispanic Society of <placeName>America</placeName>, and with Indian Notes and Monographs issued by the Museum of the American Indian—Heye Foundation.</p>
            <list>
               <head>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">Publication Committee</hi>
               </head>
               <item>
                  <persName>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">Agnes Baldwin Brett</hi>
                  </persName>, <hi rend="italic">Chairman</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <persName>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">Stephen H. P. Pell</hi>
                  </persName>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <persName>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">Thomas O. Mabbott</hi>
                  </persName>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">Editorial Staff</hi>
               </head>
               <item>
                  <persName>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">Sydney Philip Noe</hi>
                  </persName>, <hi rend="italic">Editor</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <persName>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">Howland Wood</hi>
                  </persName>, <hi rend="italic">Associate Editor</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d70e109" type="colophon">
            <pb/>
            <p>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">Copyright, 1936, By The American Numismatic Society</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">waverly press, inc.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <placeName>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">baltimore, md.</hi>
               </placeName>
            </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d70e121" type="frontma">
            <pb/>
            <figure xml:id="fig-2">
               <graphic url="NNM72_06.jpg"/>
            </figure>
         </div1>
         <titlePage>
            <pb/>
            <docTitle>
               <titlePart type="main">THE COINAGE OF THE SECOND SAFFARID DYNASTY IN SISTAN</titlePart>
            </docTitle>
            <byline>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">by</hi> JOHN WALKER
</byline>
            <figure xml:id="fig-3">
               <graphic url="NNM72_07.jpg"/>
            </figure>
            <docImprint>
               <publisher>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">the american numismatic society</hi>
               </publisher>
               <pubPlace>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">broadway at 156th street</hi>
               </pubPlace>
               <pubPlace>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">new york</hi>
               </pubPlace>
               <date>1936</date>
            </docImprint>
         </titlePage>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div1 xml:id="d70e149" type="chapter">
            <pb n="1"/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="bold">THE COINAGE OF THE SECOND SAFFARID DYNASTY IN <placeName>SISTAN</placeName>
                  <ref target="#CH1-n1">*</ref>
               </hi>
            </head>
            <byline>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">By John Walker</hi>
            </byline>
            <p>In 1877 when <persName>Lane-Poole</persName> published vol. III of his <hi rend="italic">Catalogue of Oriental Coins</hi> the British Museum contained only 14 specimens of the coinage of the Saffarid Governors in <placeName>Sistan</placeName> (A.H. 296–399, A.D. 908–1008). This number has since been more than trebled, which is by far the largest collection of these rare coins in any museum. The additional examples have come from two private collections, namely, (1) that of <persName>Mr. G. P. Tate</persName> and (2) that of <persName>Lt. Col. Sir A. H. McMahon</persName>. Although the late <persName>Dr. Oliver Codrington</persName> published a few cursory notes on most of
<pb n="2"/>
these in the Journal of the Royal Asiatic Society, 1905 (pp. 549–551) and 1911 (pp. 781–3) respectively, he had to confess his inability to read certain of the marginal legends, which had likewise puzzled <persName>Lane-Poole</persName>. After a careful examination of the assembled material I have managed to decipher these, and as one of them reveals a Koranic text hitherto unknown to Muhammadan Numismatics it provides additional reason for publication. Besides, there are important questions of chronology and attribution involved, and so in the hope of throwing some light on such, I have considered it advisable to collect all the known numismatic data surviving of what is, I am afraid, somewhat arbitrarily termed, the Second Saffarid Dynasty in <placeName>Sistan</placeName>.</p>
            <p>No attempt has yet been made to assemble the fragmentary information existing in historical records concerning these rulers, regarding whom there has been what amounts to a conspiracy of silence. <persName>Juzjani</persName>, the author of the <hi rend="italic">Tabakat-i-Nasiri</hi>, actually passes over all mention of them although he deals with the First Saffarid Dynasty as well as with the later rulers of <placeName>Nimruz</placeName> or <placeName>Sistan</placeName>. In the Encyclopædia of Islam there is but a brief account of some of these princes by <persName>Büchner</persName> in his articles on <hi rend="italic">
                  <placeName>Sistan</placeName>
               </hi> and <hi rend="italic">Samanids</hi>, while Haig's article on the <hi rend="italic">Saffarids</hi> dismisses them in a sentence. <persName>Lane-Poole's</persName>
               <hi rend="italic">Mohammadan Dynasties</hi> (1894) is strangely devoid of specific mention of any of the members of this dynasty, although it does refer in a footnote (p. 130) to the historical résumé contained in Sauvaire's <hi rend="italic">Lettre sur un</hi>
               <pb n="3"/>
               <hi rend="italic">fels Saffaride.</hi> This omission however is rectified by <persName>Zambaur</persName> in his <hi rend="italic">Manuel de Généalogie</hi> (pp. 200–1) where a list is given of the successive rulers of <placeName>Sistan</placeName> during this period, as well as a useful genealogical table and bibliography. The skeleton table of the dynasty which I subjoin has been largely based on this, and to a lesser degree on Justi's <hi rend="italic">Iranisches Nahmenbuch</hi> (1895, p. 439) although the transliteration of the Arabic proper names is necessarily different. I have also included in this series the coins of the two rebellious governors <persName>Kathir ibn Ahmad</persName> (No. 4) and <persName>Husain ibn Tahir</persName> (No. 55).</p>
            <p>A brief historical synopsis of events is no doubt desirable. The First Saffarid Dynasty was founded by a quondam bandit leader <persName>Ya'kub</persName> the son of <persName>al-Laith</persName> surnamed the <persName>Coppersmith (al-Saffar)</persName>, who contrived to gain possession of <placeName>Sistan</placeName> c. A.H. 253, A.D. 867. He was succeeded in turn by his brother '<persName>Amr</persName> and the latter's grandson <persName>Tahir</persName>, under whom the First Dynasty may be said to have terminated A.H. 296, A.D. 908. These three rulers are indicated on the accompanying table as A. B. and C. The members of what may be called the Second Saffarid Dynasty struggled during the following century to recapture and maintain their hold on <placeName>Sistan</placeName>. Of the six rulers (marked 1, 2, 3, 4, 5 and 6 on the table) we possess coins of four besides the issues of the two usurpers above mentioned.</p>
            <p>Although it is with <hi rend="italic">their</hi> period of unstable tenure that we are here concerned, yet a rough tabulation of the coins of the First Saffarid Dynasty in the British
<pb n="4"/>
Museum (12 of which are so far uncatalogued) may provide a useful approach to the subject proper. [B.M.C. = British Museum Catalogue, vol. II, or vol. IX; N.C. = not catalogued. In each case I have indicated the appearance on the obverse or the reverse of the name of the '<persName>Abbasid Caliph</persName> of <placeName>Baghdad</placeName>, the nominal overlord, and/or of the Saffarid Ruler. V. = Vasmer: <hi rend="italic">Über die Münzen der Soffariden und ihrer Gegner in <placeName>Fars</placeName> und Hurasan</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Numismatische Zeitschrift</hi>, <placeName>Vienna</placeName>, 1930, pp. 131–162.]</p>
            <p>At the period with which we are dealing the 'Abbasid Caliphate at <placeName>Baghdad</placeName> had fallen on evil days. Although the name of the Caliph is placed on their coins by the various independent Saffarid, Samanid, Buwaihid and Ghaznavid rulers of the day, his over-lordship was seldom more than a polite figment. The following is a list of the Caliphs of <placeName>Baghdad</placeName> who are recognized on the coins of the Saffarid governors (of the first and second dynasties).</p>
            <table rows="11" cols="3">
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <persName>al-Mu'tamid 'ala'llah</persName>.</cell>
                  <cell>A.H. 256–279</cell>
                  <cell>A.D. 870–892</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <persName>al-Mu'tadid billah</persName>.</cell>
                  <cell>279–289</cell>
                  <cell>892–902</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <persName>al-Muktafi billah</persName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>289–295</cell>
                  <cell>902–908</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <persName>al-Muktadir billah</persName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>295–320</cell>
                  <cell>908–932</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <persName>al-Kahir billah</persName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>320–322</cell>
                  <cell>932–934</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <persName>al-Radi billah</persName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>322–329</cell>
                  <cell>934–940</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <persName>al-Muttaki lillah</persName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>329–333</cell>
                  <cell>940–944</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <persName>al-Mustakfi billah</persName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>333–334</cell>
                  <cell>944–946</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <persName>al-Muti' lillah</persName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>334–363</cell>
                  <cell>946–974</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <persName>al-Ta'i' lillah</persName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>363–381</cell>
                  <cell>974–991</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <persName>al-Kadir billah</persName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>381–422</cell>
                  <cell>991–1031</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Zambaur in his <hi rend="italic">Contributions</hi> pt. I p. 14 makes the erroneous statement that <persName>Tahir</persName>, the grandson of '<persName>Amr</persName>, was carried off to <placeName>Baghdad</placeName> (288) and assassinated (289, A.D. 902) although he is aware (cf. his footnote <hi rend="italic">ibid.</hi>) that the coins flatly contradict this. In the same article he praises the succinct account of the Saffarids given by <persName>Müller</persName> in his <hi rend="italic">Der Islam im Morgen- und Abendland.</hi> It looks very much as if he has been misled by <persName>Müller's</persName> statement (p. 34): "<hi rend="italic">Ssedschestan allein überliess Motadid dem <persName>Tahir</persName>
               </hi>, <hi rend="italic">einem Enkel des <persName>Amr</persName>
               </hi>; <hi rend="italic">dieser selbst ward 288</hi> (<hi rend="italic">901</hi>) <hi rend="italic">nach <placeName>Bagdad</placeName> geschafft und kurz nach dem Tode des Chalifen</hi> (<hi rend="italic">289 = 902</hi>) <hi rend="italic">im Gefängnisse umgebracht.</hi>" Obviously he has confused <persName>Tahir</persName> with his grandfather '<persName>Amr</persName> who was put to death in that year. (Justi wrongly dates his death as A.D. 908.) In <persName>Ibn al-Athir</persName> (VIII, 42) we read of <persName>Tahir's</persName> capture by his adversary Subkari (سبكرى) and his being sent along with his brother <persName>Ya'kub</persName> to the <persName>Caliph Muktadir</persName> at <placeName>Baghdad</placeName>. According to the same historian (VIII, 100) we find <persName>Tahir</persName> and <persName>Ya'kub</persName> being invested with robes of honour by the same Caliph in the year 310.<ref target="#CH1-n2">
                  <hi rend="sup">1</hi>
               </ref>
            </p>
            <p>However with the capture of <persName>Tahir</persName> and his brother <persName>Ya'kub</persName> the First Dynasty may be said to have ended, although <persName>Ya'kub's</persName> son '<persName>Amr</persName>, as we shall see, was recognized in 300, A.D. 912 for a brief nine months
<pb n="6"/>
               <table rows="16" cols="6">
                  <head>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">First Saffarid Dynasty</hi>
                  </head>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Metal</cell>
                     <cell>Mint</cell>
                     <cell>Year</cell>
                     <cell>Reference</cell>
                     <cell>Obverse</cell>
                     <cell>Reverse</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell cols="6">
                        <hi rend="italic">
                           <persName>Ya'kub ibn al-Laith</persName>
                        </hi> (253–265) A.D. 867–879</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell cols="6">يعقوب بن الليث</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <graphic url="NNM72_13.jpg"/>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Ahwaz</cell>
                     <cell>264</cell>
                     <cell>N.C. = V. 10</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <persName>al-Amir Ya'kub</persName>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <persName>al-Mu'tamid 'ala'llah</persName>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <graphic url="NNM72_13.jpg"/>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Banjahir</cell>
                     <cell>260</cell>
                     <cell>B.M.C. = V. 3</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <persName>Ya'kub</persName>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <persName>al-Mu'tamid 'ala'llah</persName>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <graphic url="NNM72_13.jpg"/>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Faris</cell>
                     <cell>264</cell>
                     <cell>B.M.C. = V. 6</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <persName>Ya'kub</persName>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <persName>al-Mu'tamid 'ala'llah</persName>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell cols="6">
                        <hi rend="italic">'<persName>Amr ibn al-Laith</persName>
                        </hi> (265–288) A.D. 879–900</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell cols="6">عمرو بن الليث</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell></cell>
                     <cell>Jannaba</cell>
                     <cell>275</cell>
                     <cell>B.M.C. = V. 36</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <persName>al-Muwaffak billah 'Amr ibn al-Laith</persName>
                        <ref target="#CH1-n3">
                           <hi rend="sup">2</hi>
                        </ref>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <persName>al-Mu'tamid 'ala'llah Ahmad</persName> son of <persName>al-Muwaffak billah</persName>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <graphic url="NNM72_13.jpg"/>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Arrajan</cell>
                     <cell>275</cell>
                     <cell>B.M.C. = V. 37</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <persName>al-Muwaffak billah 'Amr ibn al-Laith</persName>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <persName>al-Mu'tamid 'ala'llah Ahmad</persName> son of <persName>al-Muwaffak billah</persName>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <graphic url="NNM72_13.jpg"/>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Shiraz</cell>
                     <cell>280</cell>
                     <cell>N.C. = V. 46</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <persName>'Amr ibn al-Laith</persName>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <persName>al-Mu'tadid billah</persName>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <graphic url="NNM72_13.jpg"/>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Shiraz</cell>
                     <cell>281</cell>
                     <cell>N.C. = V. 53</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <persName>'Amr ibn al-Laith</persName>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <persName>al-Mu'tadid billah</persName>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb n="7"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <graphic url="NNM72_13.jpg"/>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Faris</cell>
                     <cell>267</cell>
                     <cell>N.C. = V. 23</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <persName>al-Muwaffak billah 'Amr</persName>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <persName>al-Mu'tamid 'ala' llah</persName>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <graphic url="NNM72_13.jpg"/>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Faris</cell>
                     <cell>273</cell>
                     <cell>N.C. = V. 33</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <persName>al-Mu'tamid 'ala'llah Muhammad ibn 'Amr</persName>
                        <ref target="#CH1-n4">
                           <hi rend="sup">3</hi>
                        </ref>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <persName>al-Mu'tamid 'ala' llah 'Amr ibn al-Laith</persName>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <graphic url="NNM72_13.jpg"/>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Nisabur</cell>
                     <cell>269</cell>
                     <cell>N.C. = V. 15</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <persName>al-Muwaffak billah Mansur</persName>
                        <ref target="#CH1-n5">
                           <hi rend="sup">4</hi>
                        </ref>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <persName>al-Mu'tamid 'ala'llah 'Amr</persName>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <graphic url="NNM72_13.jpg"/>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Nisabur</cell>
                     <cell>282</cell>
                     <cell>N.C. = V. 65</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <persName>Abu Hafs 'Amr ibn al-Laith</persName>
                        <ref target="#CH1-n6">
                           <hi rend="sup">5</hi>
                        </ref>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <persName>al-Mu'tadid billah</persName>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <pb n="8"/>
               <table rows="10" cols="6">
                  <row>
                     <cell cols="6">
                        <hi rend="italic">
                           <persName>Tahir ibn Muhammad</persName>
                        </hi> (288–296) A.D. 900–908</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell cols="6">طاهر بن محمد</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <graphic url="NNM72_13.jpg"/>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Madinat Zaranj</cell>
                     <cell>295</cell>
                     <cell>B.M.C. = V. 84</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <persName>al-kadr lillah</persName>
                        <ref target="#CH1-n7">
                           <hi rend="sup">6</hi>
                        </ref>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <persName>al-Muktafi billah Tahir ibn Muhammad</persName>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <graphic url="NNM72_13.jpg"/>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Faris</cell>
                     <cell>290</cell>
                     <cell>N.C. = V. 74</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <persName>Tahir ibn Muhammad</persName>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <persName>al-Muktafi billah</persName>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <graphic url="NNM72_13.jpg"/>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Faris</cell>
                     <cell>291</cell>
                     <cell>N.C. = V. 75</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <persName>Tahir ibn Muhammad</persName>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <persName>al-Muktafi billah</persName>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <graphic url="NNM72_13.jpg"/>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Faris</cell>
                     <cell>292</cell>
                     <cell>N.C. = V. 76</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <persName>Tahir ibn Muhammad</persName>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <persName>al-Muktafi billah</persName>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <graphic url="NNM72_13.jpg"/>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Faris</cell>
                     <cell>293</cell>
                     <cell>N.C. = V. 77</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <persName>Tahir ibn Muhammad</persName>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <persName>al-Muktafi billah</persName>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <graphic url="NNM72_13.jpg"/>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Faris</cell>
                     <cell>294</cell>
                     <cell>B.M.C. = V. 78</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <persName>Tahir ibn Muhammad</persName>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <persName>al-Muktafi billah</persName>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <graphic url="NNM72_13.jpg"/>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Faris</cell>
                     <cell>295</cell>
                     <cell>N.C. = V. 79</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <persName>Tahir ibn Muhammad</persName>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <persName>al-Muktafi billah</persName>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <graphic url="NNM72_13.jpg"/>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Faris</cell>
                     <cell>296</cell>
                     <cell>B.M.C. = V. 86</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <persName>Tahir ibn Muhammad</persName>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <persName>al Muktadir billah</persName>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <pb n="9"/>
               <figure xml:id="fig-4">
                  <head>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">Genealogical Table of First and Second Saffarid Dynasties</hi>
                  </head>
                  <graphic url="NNM72_16.jpg"/>
               </figure>
               <ref target="#CH1-n8">
                  <hi rend="sup">7</hi>
               </ref>
               <pb n="10"/>
by the insurgents in <placeName>Sistan</placeName>; while his daughter <persName>Banu</persName> was the mother of <persName>Khalaf</persName>, the most distinguished member of the Second Dynasty.</p>
            <p>
               <persName>Ibn al-Athir</persName> (VIII, 43,44) tells us that in 297, A.D. 909 <persName>Laith ibn 'Ali</persName> advanced into the rich province of <placeName>Fars</placeName> and drove Subkari off to Arrajan. When the tidings reached <placeName>Baghdad</placeName> however, the Caliph sent a punitive force under Munis, who successfully routed the troops from <placeName>Sistan</placeName>, captured their leader <persName>Laith</persName>, and carried him off to <placeName>Baghdad</placeName>. There are but three coins extant of his mintage. The one in the British Museum (No. 3), although dated 298, A.D. 910 may have been issued from the town of <placeName>Bust</placeName> before the news of the recent defeat had arrived or, more probably, as an expression of the citizens' loyalty to their captive prince.<ref target="#CH1-n9">
                  <hi rend="sup">8</hi>
               </ref>
            </p>
            <p>
               <persName>Mu'addal</persName>, a brother of <persName>Laith</persName>, succeeded him as Sahib or Master of <placeName>Sistan</placeName> (in 298, A.D. 910), and the same year witnessed the advance of the Samanid<ref target="#CH1-n10">
                  <hi rend="sup">9</hi>
               </ref> power from <placeName>Bukhara</placeName> under <persName>Husain ibn 'Ali</persName> the general of <persName>Ahmad ibn Isma'il</persName>. A third brother <persName>Muhammad</persName>
               <pb n="11"/>
was ordered to protect the territory around the towns of <placeName>Bust</placeName> and <placeName>al-Rukhkhaj</placeName> in the forefront of the invading forces. The Samanid general was victorious however, and when <persName>Mu'addal</persName> learned of the defeat and capture of his brother <persName>Muhammad</persName>, he capitulated. It is not known whether he issued any coins during his brief period of government.</p>
            <p>One of the first things the Samanid <persName>Amir Ahmad</persName> did after the surrender of <persName>Mu'addal</persName> was to appoint <persName>Mansur ibn Ishak</persName> (his cousin) as Governor of <placeName>Sistan</placeName> for the Samanids. But the country was far from pacified. In 300, A.D. 912 a religious sectarian (one of the ubiquitous Khawarij), named <persName>Ibn Hurmuz</persName>, provoked a popular rising in favour of the Saffarids. Under a powerful adventurer named <persName>Ibn-al-Haffar</persName> they seized control, imprisoned the Samanid Governor <persName>Mansur</persName> and offered <placeName>Sistan</placeName> with their allegiance to <persName>'Amr</persName>, the son of their captive prince <persName>Ya'kub</persName>.</p>
            <p>This led to a second invasion of the land on the part of the Samanid general <persName>Husain ibn 'Ali</persName> who this time besieged the capital <placeName>Zaranj</placeName> for nine months. Whether it was the premature decease of their religious instigator <persName>Ibn Hurmuz</persName>, or the rigours of the siege, at all events <persName>'Amr</persName> and his generalissimo <persName>Ibn al-Haffar</persName> sued for terms. In the rôle of captives they pass from the pages of history and a new Samanid Governor <persName>Simjur al-Dawati</persName> (سيمجور الدواتى) was appointed over <placeName>Sistan</placeName>. It is not surprising that there is no numismatic evidence known of this disastrous revolt.</p>
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>In the year 301, A.D. 913 the Samanid ruler, <persName>Ahmad ibn Isma'il</persName>, was assassinated, leaving behind him as heir <persName>Nasr</persName>, his eight year old son. The masterly fashion in which the delicate situation of the succession was handled on behalf of this terror-stricken child by a scion of the Saffarid family named <persName>Ahmed ibn Muhammad</persName>, who was at the time prefect (متولى امر) in <placeName>Bukhara</placeName>,<ref target="#CH1-n11">
                  <hi rend="sup">10</hi>
               </ref> was destined to be rewarded some years later as we shall see. But in the meantime, the Samanid dynastic crisis led to the withdrawal from <placeName>Sistan</placeName> of <persName>Simjur al-Dawati</persName> and the occasion was apparently seized by the Caliph <persName>Al-Muktadir</persName> to appoint his own representative <persName>Badr al-Kabir</persName> as governor of the land (<persName>Ibn al Athir</persName> VIII, 59).</p>
            <p>
               <placeName>Sistan</placeName> at this period was never destined to be long at peace. In 304, A.D. 916 a usurper, named <persName>Kathir ibn Ahmad</persName>,<ref target="#CH1-n12">
                  <hi rend="sup">11</hi>
               </ref> apparently not a member of the Saffarid family, rose in revolt, an act which at once called for reprisals from <placeName>Baghdad</placeName>. An army from <placeName>Fars</placeName> almost defeated <persName>Kathir</persName>, but when the inhabitants of <placeName>Sistan</placeName> heard that the Caliph's envoy <persName>Zaid</persName> was bringing chains and fetters for their chief men and increased taxation for themselves, they joined with <persName>Kathir</persName>, repulsed the Caliph's forces and took <persName>Zaid</persName> prisoner
<pb n="13"/>
ignominiously. <persName>Kathir</persName> wrote to the Caliph to exculpate himself and laid the blame on the people. The Caliph's answer was to order <persName>Badr ibn 'Abdallah</persName>, the Governor of <placeName>Fars</placeName>, to advance in person with his troops against <placeName>Sistan</placeName>. On hearing this <persName>Kathir</persName> in apprehension hastened to agree to terms, an annual payment of 500,000 dirhams and the recognition of his status as Governor in <placeName>Sistan</placeName> [<persName>Ibn al-Athir</persName>, VIII, 77]. We have no record of the length of his governorship but coin no. 4 indicates his presence in power two years later (306, A.D. 918).</p>
            <p>Sauvaire<ref target="#CH1-n13">
                  <hi rend="sup">12</hi>
               </ref> on the supposed authority of <persName>Ibn al-Athir</persName> discovers a new Governor of <placeName>Sistan</placeName> for the year 307 named <persName>'Amr ibn al-Laith</persName>. His error has arisen through failing to understand the passage in <persName>Ibn al-Athir</persName> (VIII, 86, 87). The Arabic historian under the year 307, A.D. 919, is recounting the story of <persName>Ahmad ibn Sahl</persName>, the quondam representative of <persName>'Amr ibn al-Laith</persName> at <placeName>Marw</placeName>, whom <persName>'Amr</persName> had arrested and carried off to imprisonment in <placeName>Sistan</placeName>. Sauvaire failed to observe that <persName>Ibn al-Athir</persName>, as the latter expressly states (p. 86 ونحن نذكر حاله من اوّله), is relating Ahmad's history anterior to the year 307 and that the <persName>'Amr ibn al-Laith</persName> who is mentioned, is none other than the second ruler of the First Saffarid dynasty who, as we saw above, was assassinated at <placeName>Baghdad</placeName> in 289, A.D. 901.</p>
            <pb n="14"/>
            <p>In 310<ref target="#CH1-n14">
                  <hi rend="sup">13</hi>
               </ref> the Samanid overlord, <persName>Nasr</persName>, having now reached his majority, demonstrated his gratitude to <persName>Ahmad ibn Muhammad</persName>, the Saffarid vassal who had supported his claim to the throne of his father, by appointing him Governor of <placeName>Sistan</placeName>. It was a popular choice, since the Sistanese, constantly disaffected at this period, welcomed the return of a member of the Saffarid ruling house. It is ten years later (320, A.D. 932) however, before any numismatic evidence of his rule is forthcoming. Thereafter until his death c. A.H. 349, A.D. 960 his name appears fairly regularly on the coinage of <placeName>Sistan</placeName>.</p>
            <p>That it was some years before <persName>Ahmad</persName> established his position as governor of <placeName>Sistan</placeName> may be gathered from the scanty references of the historians supplemented by the contemporary records of the coins. We know that in the year A.H. 316, A.D. 928,<ref target="#CH1-n15">
                  <hi rend="sup">14</hi>
               </ref> a nameless Kharijite, or religious sectarian, intended to march an army from <placeName>Sistan</placeName> into the province of <placeName>Fars</placeName> but before he reached there he was put to death by his own partisans and the expedition abandoned. We also learn from the same source (VIII, p. 164) that in 318, A.D. 930 the Caliph <persName>al-Muktadir</persName> appointed his son <persName>Harun</persName> as Governor of <placeName>Fars</placeName>, <placeName>Kirman</placeName>, <placeName>Sistan</placeName> and <placeName>Makran</placeName>, while in the following year (319, A.D. 931) we find him investing <persName>Abu Bakr Muhammad</persName>
               <pb n="15"/>
               <persName>ibn Yakut</persName> with the governorship of <placeName>Sistan</placeName> (<hi rend="italic">ibid</hi> p. 165). The coins however tell us nothing about these.</p>
            <p>On the other hand certain coins of 320–321, A.D. 932 besides bearing the name of <persName>Ahmad ibn Muhammad</persName> also preserve for us another name, that of <persName>al-Husain ibn Bilal</persName> who is apparently otherwise unknown in historical documents. <persName>Prof. Vasmer of Leningrad</persName>, who has given me the benefit of his advice on the matter, informs me that about twelve years ago he lost much time in perusing certain oriental writers in the hope of finding something concerning this personage, but without success. So for the present, at any rate, <persName>al-Husain ibn Bilal</persName> must remain an enigma. Whoever he may have been, the year 321 saw his name displaced on the coins by that of <persName>Abu Ja'far</persName> (or Father of <persName>Ja'far</persName>) which was the additional name or <hi rend="italic">kunya</hi> of <persName>Ahmad ibn Muhammad</persName> with reference to his son <persName>Ja'far</persName>.</p>
            <p>There are many points of interest about the coinage of <persName>Ahmad ibn Muhammad</persName>. One is the presence of the name <persName>Khalaf</persName>. This occurs with and without the name of the governor himself <persName>Ahmad ibn Muhammad</persName>, and his <hi rend="italic">kunya</hi>
               <persName>Abu Ja'far</persName>. <persName>Khalaf</persName> was both the name of his grandfather and of his celebrated son who succeeded him. Perhaps the appearance of the name on the early gold coins (nos. 5, 6, 7) may be accounted for by the fact that <persName>Ahmad's</persName> son <persName>Khalaf</persName> was born about that time (326, A.D. 937). Another interesting point, of historical importance, is to be
<pb n="16"/>
seen in nos. 20, 41 and 42. The last two coins unmistakably have the date 346, in spite of the fact that <placeName>Codrington</placeName> declared it illegible, while no. 20, a fragment in the <placeName>Ermitage</placeName>, is of the year 349. They are issued in the name of <persName>Ahmad ibn Muhammad</persName>, with the Caliph's name and that of <persName>Khalaf</persName>. <persName>Zambaur</persName> gives 344, A.D. 955 as approximately the last year of <persName>Ahmad's</persName> reign, but these coins definitely prove that he was alive and in power at all events as late as 349, A.D. 960. The re-appearance of the name <persName>Khalaf</persName> at this late date seems to indicate the ascription of a certain measure of political prominence to the heir apparent. But in what year the latter succeeded his father is still wrapped in obscurity. We know from history<ref target="#CH1-n16">
                  <hi rend="sup">15</hi>
               </ref> that <persName>Ahmad's</persName> son <persName>Khalaf</persName> was restored to the governorship of <placeName>Sistan</placeName> in the year 353, A.D. 964 by the Samanid <persName>Mansur ibn Nuh</persName>, but the earliest extant examples of his coinage are more than ten years later (nos. 43, 49). In view of these facts it is not at all improbable that <persName>Ahmad</persName> died c. 353, A.D. 964.</p>
            <p>
               <placeName>Codrington</placeName> (Journal of the Royal Asiatic Society,
<pb n="17"/>
1911, p. 782) mentions a bronze coin of <persName>Ahmad ibn Muhammad</persName> with the obverse <hi rend="italic">"filled with a star of six leaves radiating from a central circle with pellets between the rays and a marginal circle of annulets between two of plain lines."</hi> He read the date as 338. Unfortunately he did not illustrate this and it is not among the coins from the <persName>McMahon</persName> Collection that were presented to the British Museum. Its present whereabouts is unknown to me. But judging by his description of the obverse, I have no hesitation in asserting that the coin in question is not Saffarid but <persName>'Abbasid</persName>, in fact similar in character if not in date to the one published by Lavoix, <hi rend="italic">Cat. des Monnaies musulmanes</hi> vol. I, Paris 1887, No. 1593, plate IX, and minted at Sijistan A.H. 194.</p>
            <p>
               <persName>Khalaf ibn Ahmad</persName>, the next Saffarid governor, has left behind him the reputation of being one of the most enlightened men of his generation.<ref target="#CH1-n17">
                  <hi rend="sup">16</hi>
               </ref>
               <persName>Yakut</persName> (III, p. 44) gives his name as <persName>Abu Ahmad Khalaf ibn Ahmad ibn Khalaf ibn al-Laith ibn Farkad al-Sijizi</persName>, but in so doing he omits several generations (see table above p. 9). He also tells us that besides being a king (ملك) in <placeName>Sistan</placeName>, he was amongst the most learned and honourable of men. <persName>Al-Biruni</persName>
               <ref target="#CH1-n18">
                  <hi rend="sup">17</hi>
               </ref> in mentioning a certain <hi rend="italic">contretemps</hi> between him and his Samanid overlord, <persName>Nuh ibn Mansur</persName> records the fact that
<pb n="18"/>
               <persName>Khalaf</persName> had the title of <hi rend="italic">Wali al-Daula</hi> (ولى الدولة), which agrees with the <placeName>Berlin</placeName> specimen given below (no. 56). His relations with the Samanid power were always rather strained, and the internal politics of <placeName>Sistan</placeName> seldom left him much certainty of security of tenure; even his sons as we shall see plotted against him. Finally succumbing before the advance of the great <persName>Sultan Mahmud</persName> of <placeName>Ghazna</placeName> in 393, A.D. 1002, he lingered for a few more years, and died in A.H. 399 (A.D. 1008).</p>
            <p>A brief account of the main events of his exciting reign may serve as a setting for the few surviving coins of this period described below. Not long after his accession in 353, <persName>Khalaf</persName> left the government in the hands of a relative by marriage, named <persName>Tahir ibn Husain</persName>, and went off on pilgrimage as a pious Moslem, to Mecca. On his return in the following year (354) he was ousted by <persName>Tahir</persName>, who had fomented a revolt against him. With the help of <persName>Mansur ibn Nuh</persName>, the Samanid ruler at <placeName>Bukhara</placeName>, he managed to regain possession of his domain for a short time, but a second revolt sent him again seeking aid from <placeName>Bukhara</placeName>. <persName>Tahir</persName> at this crucial moment died, to be succeeded by his son, <persName>Husain</persName>, who carried on the rebellion, and a specimen of whose gold coinage is described below (no. 55). <persName>Khalaf</persName>, however, once more won back his kingdom and <persName>Husain</persName> was forced to retire for the time being to the Samanid court. For some time all was well, but as soon as <persName>Khalaf</persName>
               <pb n="19"/>
stopped sending tribute money and robes of honour to his Samanid overlord, he found the old civil strife resumed, this time with the Samanid forces in league with the former usurping governor <persName>Husain ibn Tahir</persName>. <persName>Khalaf</persName> found himself besieged by them in his citadel at <placeName>Zaranj</placeName> for a period of seven years. At length the Samanid ruler <persName>Nuh ibn Mansur</persName>, sent the famous general <persName>Abu'l-Hasan</persName>, son of the <persName>Simjur al-Dawati</persName> mentioned above, to end the protracted campaign. The latter who was friendly with <persName>Khalaf</persName> devised with him a strategic move which completely succeeded in defeating <persName>Husain ibn Tahir</persName> and once more leaving <persName>Khalaf</persName> in undisputed possession of <placeName>Sistan</placeName>.</p>
            <p>But his dynastic troubles were not at an end. One of his sons <persName>'Amr</persName>, who had suffered an ignominious defeat at the hands of the Buwaihid governor of <placeName>Kirman</placeName>, and had returned in disgrace to <placeName>Sistan</placeName>, was imprisoned and, for some unknown reason, put to death by his father's orders in A.H. 382, A.D. 992. Another son, called <persName>Tahir</persName>, revolted against <persName>Khalaf</persName> in A.H. 391, A.D. 1000, who once more found himself taking refuge in one of his citadels. By means of an act of treachery he captured his unfilial son in an ambush and according to one account is said to have killed him with his own hands. It seems a most inhuman act for one who was renowned for his piety and learning. Hence the importance of the unique coin in the <placeName>Ermitage</placeName> (no. 57) which, although the mint and date are both unfortunately missing, must have been issued by <persName>Tahir ibn Khalaf</persName> after 393—
<pb n="20"/>
since it bears the name of Mahmud—the year in which <placeName>Sistan</placeName> was irrevocably wrenched from <persName>Khalaf</persName> and he was driven into retirement until he died in 399. If these facts are so, then <persName>Tahir</persName> must have survived his unsuccessful mutiny. According to the his-torians, however, <persName>Khalaf</persName> was succeeded either by another son, named <persName>Abu Hafs</persName>, or by a grandson named <persName>Tahir</persName>. But it is difficult to explain away the coin evidence, which clearly indicates that <persName>Tahir</persName>, <persName>Khalafs</persName> son, issued coins, presumably in <placeName>Sistan</placeName>, with the name of the Caliph <persName>al-Kadir</persName> and also that of his overlord <persName>Mahmud</persName> of <placeName>Ghazna</placeName>.</p>
            <p>One interesting result of a fresh study of these coins has been the elucidation of a hitherto unrecorded coin legend. It is found on the gold coins of <persName>Khalaf</persName> (nos. 50, 51, 52, 53) and by patching together the fragments I have been able to read it as follows:</p>
            <p>وَ مَنْ يُوقَ شُحَّ نَفْسِهِ فَأولَئِك هُمُ المُفْلِحُونَ</p>
            <p>This is the end of a verse which occurs twice in the Koran (LIX, 9 and LXIV, 16) and may be translated as follows: <hi rend="italic">"And those who are saved from their own covetousness shall be prosperous."</hi>
               <persName>Prof. Vasmer</persName>, to whom I communicated my reading, has written to me expressing his agreement. In order to illustrate, and justify, my decipherment of the above legend, and also of the one on the bronze coins (nos. 23, 24 and 30), it is perhaps advisable to tabulate the examples as follows to show how the remnants of one legend supplement the other.</p>
            <pb n="21"/>
            <p>no.23 <graphic url="NNM72_28a.jpg"/>
            </p>
            <p>no.24 <graphic url="NNM72_28b.jpg"/>
            </p>
            <p>no.30 <graphic url="NNM72_28c.jpg"/>
            </p>
            <p>koran xxx.3. لله الامر من قبل ومن بعد</p>
            <p>no.50 <graphic url="NNM72_28d.jpg"/>
            </p>
            <p>no.51 <graphic url="NNM72_28e.jpg"/>
            </p>
            <p>no.52 <graphic url="NNM72_28f.jpg"/>
            </p>
            <p>no.53 <graphic url="NNM72_28g.jpg"/>
            </p>
            <p>koren Lix.9.شح نفسه فاولئك هم المفلحون (or ومن يوق (يق</p>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n1">
               <seg type="note-symbol">*</seg>
               <p>In the transliteration of Arabic words a very simplified form has been adopted. An apostrophe has been employed to mark that consonant which is so characteristic of Semitic languages, the '<hi rend="italic">ain.</hi> Apart from this no ligatures or logotypes have been used, and no attempt has been made to indicate long vowels. To have followed any precise system would have involved much additional expenditure that would not have been counterbalanced by any great gain in general accuracy.</p>
               <p>I am indebted to the authorities of the Kaiser Friedrich Museum, <placeName>Berlin</placeName>, and of the <placeName>Ermitage</placeName>, Leningrad, for permission to publish certain coins in their cabinets.</p>
               <p>In the publishing of this monograph I have been very generously assisted in the presentation of the material in typescript and the correction of proofs by <persName>Mr. Howland Wood</persName>. To him, and to the Publications Committee of the American Numismatic Society, are due my sincerest thanks.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n2">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">1</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>These seem to be the same two persons, <hi rend="italic">pace</hi> Raverty, <hi rend="italic">Tabakat-i-Nasiri</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Bibliotheca Indica</hi>) London 1881 I, p. 185, who regards them as grandsons of <persName>Laith ibn 'Ali</persName>.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n3">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">2</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>
                  <persName>Al-Muwaffak</persName> was the brother and the associate of the <persName>Caliph al-Mu'tamid</persName>. The name of his son <persName>Ahmad</persName>, who succeeded his uncle as the next <persName>Caliph al-Mu'tadid</persName>, appears on the reverse.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n4">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">3</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>
                  <persName>Muhammad 'Amr's</persName> son died in 274 in retreating from the Caliph's army (<persName>Ibn al-Athir</persName> VII, 298).</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n5">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">4</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>
                  <persName>Abu Talha Mansur</persName>, the representative of <persName>'Amr</persName>.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n6">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">5</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>
                  <persName>'Amr</persName> is here given the additional name (or <hi rend="italic">kunya</hi>) of <persName>Abu Hafs</persName>, i.e., Father of <persName>Hafs</persName>, his son.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n7">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">6</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>I.e., fate rests with Allah. <persName>Lane Poole</persName> read it as <hi rend="italic">alkudra lillah</hi> which would be "Power belongs to Allah" and his reading is naturally repeated by <persName>Vasmer</persName>.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n8">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">7</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>See note in Tiesenhausen's article in the <hi rend="italic">Numismatische Zeitschrift</hi>, III, p. 178; see also footnote below p. 16. Justi's genealogy is erroneous in this branch.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n9">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">8</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>He died in 317 A.D. 929, see <persName>Vasmer</persName>, p. 154.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n10">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">9</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>The Samanids, originally governors in Transoxania, founded a powerful dynastic line whose dominion embraced the greater part of modern <placeName>Iran</placeName>. Their sway lasted from A.D. 874–999 after which they were displaced by the Buwaihids. They did much to foster a Persian national literature and were the patrons of great physicians and philosophers such as <persName>Avicenna (Ibn Sina)</persName> and <persName>Rhazes (al-Razi)</persName>. From their capital <placeName>Bukhara</placeName> they maintained a strong opposition to the Caliph at <placeName>Baghdad</placeName> whose overlordship was purely nominal.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n11">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">10</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>
                  <persName>Ibn al Athir</persName> (VIII, 58) calls him simply <persName>Ahmad ibn Muhammad ibn al-Laith</persName> thus omitting several stages in his genealogy (see table on page 9).</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n12">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">11</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>There is no reason why the name should be read in a diminutive form as is done by <persName>Lane-Poole (Kutheyyir)</persName> and by <persName>Weil</persName> in his <hi rend="italic">Geschichte der Chali'en</hi> (Kutheir).</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n13">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">12</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Num. Chron.</hi> 1881, p. 132. "Ebn al Atir nous apprend <hi rend="italic">implicitement</hi>."</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n14">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">13</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>Sachau, <hi rend="italic">Verzeichnis</hi> p. 11 (based on the work of <persName>Munajjim Bashi</persName>). <persName>Büchner</persName> however, in the Encycl. of Islam, art <hi rend="italic">
                     <placeName>Sistan</placeName>
                  </hi> p. 459 gives the date as 309.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n15">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">14</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>
                  <persName>Ibn al Athir</persName> VIII, 46.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n16">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">15</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>
                  <persName>B. de Jenisch</persName>: <hi rend="italic">Historia Priorum Regum Persarum</hi> (ex Mirchond) <placeName>Vienna</placeName>, 1782, p. 107. <hi rend="italic">A Mansuro, filio Nuhi, in regnum Sistaniae a.h. 353 et seq. restitutus.</hi> Hence no doubt, the date given in Justi for the beginning of <persName>Khalaf's</persName> reign, though he makes the latter the son of <persName>Ahmad ibn Isma'il</persName> who died in 942 (A.H. 331). This is obviously quite incorrect. See table above p. 9. The investiture of <persName>Khalaf</persName> by the Caliph is described by <persName>Ibn Miskawaih</persName> under the year 354 (quoted by <placeName>Codrington</placeName>, op. cit. 1911 p. 782).</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n17">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">16</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">"Une des gloires du Sedjestan"</hi>
                  <persName>C. Barbier de Meynard</persName>: <hi rend="italic">Dictionaire de la Perse,</hi> Paris, 1861 p. 305.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n18">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">17</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">The Chronology of Ancient Nations</hi>, ed. Sachau, p. 330.</p>
            </note>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d70e1826" type="chapter">
            <pb n="22"/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="bold">CATALOGUE</hi>
            </head>
            <div2 xml:id="d70e1831" type="section">
               <head>
                  <persName>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">al-Laith ibn 'Ali</hi>
                  </persName>
               </head>
               <p>الليث بن علي</p>
               <p>A.H. 296–298 = A.D. 908–910 [†A.H. 317]</p>
               <p>1. <placeName>(Madinat) Zaranj</placeName>. A.H. 296 = A.D. 908. <graphic url="NNM72_13.jpg"/>
               </p>
               <p>Fraehn: <hi rend="italic">Recensio</hi>, p. 37, No. 8 = <persName>Vasmer</persName> 91.</p>
               <p>2. Faris. A.H. 297 = A.D. 909. <graphic url="NNM72_13.jpg"/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <persName>Lane-Poole</persName> in <hi rend="italic">Numismatic Chronicle</hi>, 1892, p. 162 = V. 92.</p>
               <p>Outside obv. and rev. margins:</p>
               <p>بالنصر | والظفر | واليمن | والسعادة</p>
               <p>With help and victory and success and happiness.</p>
               <p>3. <placeName>(Madinat) Bust</placeName>. A.H. 298 = A.D. 910. <graphic url="NNM72_13.jpg"/>
               </p>
               <p>1.05, wt. 40.2 grains (2.6 grams).</p>
               <p>
                  <persName>B. M. Cat.</persName>, II, No. 250 = V. 93.</p>
               <p>لا اله الا | الله وحده | لا شريك له | الليث بن على</p>
               <p>There is no god except Allah alone. He has no associate.<ref target="#CH1-n19">
                     <hi rend="sup">18</hi>
                  </ref>
                  <persName>al-Laith ibn ,Ali</persName>.</p>
               <p>Inner margin:</p>
               <p>بسم الله ضرب هذا الدرهم بمدينة بست سنة ثمان وتسعين ومائتين</p>
               <pb n="23"/>
               <p>In the name of Allah this dirham was minted in the town of <placeName>Bust</placeName>, in the year 298.</p>
               <p>Outer margin:</p>
               <p>لله الامر من قبل ومن بعد ويومئذ يفرح المؤمنون بنصر الله</p>
               <p>Authority belongs to Allah before and after, and on that day the believers shall rejoice in the help of Allah (Koran XXX, 3, 4).</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> لله | محمد | رسول |الله | المقتدر بالله</p>
               <p>To Allah!<ref target="#CH1-n20">
                     <hi rend="sup">19</hi>
                  </ref>
                  <persName>Muhammad</persName> is the apostle of Allah. <persName>al-Muktadir billah</persName> (the Abassid Caliph at <placeName>Baghdad</placeName> who was nominal overlord).</p>
               <p>Margin:</p>
               <p>محمد رسول الله ارسله بالهدى ودين الحق ليظهره على الدين كله ولو كره المشركون</p>
               <p>
                  <persName>Muhammad</persName> is the apostle of Allah, who has sent him with Guidance and the Religion of Truth that he may make it prevail over all religion, even if the syntheists<ref target="#CH1-n21">
                     <hi rend="sup">20</hi>
                  </ref> are averse (Koran IX, 33).</p>
               <p>Plate I. 1</p>
               <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n19">
                  <seg type="note-symbol">
                     <hi rend="sup">18</hi>
                  </seg>
                  <p>Part of the Muslim <hi rend="italic">credo.</hi> The latter part (taken from Koran VI, 163) is a direct hit at the <persName>Christian</persName> doctrine of the Trinity which <persName>Muhammad</persName> confused with some form of syntheism.</p>
               </note>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d70e1957" type="section">
               <head>
                  <persName>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">al-Mu'addal ibn 'Ali</hi>
                  </persName>
               </head>
               <p>المعدّل بن على</p>
               <p>A.H. 298–299 = A.D. 910–911</p>
               <p>No coins known.</p>
               <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n20">
                  <seg type="note-symbol">
                     <hi rend="sup">19</hi>
                  </seg>
                  <p>For a discussion of the meaning of the phrase see an article by the present writer in the <hi rend="italic">Numismatic Chronicle</hi>, Fifth Series, XIV, p. 292.</p>
               </note>
               <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n21">
                  <seg type="note-symbol">
                     <hi rend="sup">20</hi>
                  </seg>
                  <p>Cf. note 18.</p>
               </note>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d70e1983" type="section">
               <pb n="24"/>
               <head>
                  <persName>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">'Amr ibn Ya'kub</hi>
                  </persName>
               </head>
               <p>عمرو بن يعقوب</p>
               <p>A. H. 300 = A.D. 912</p>
               <p>No coins known.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d70e1995" type="section">
               <head>
                  <persName>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">Kathir ibn Ahmad</hi>
                  </persName>
               </head>
               <p>كثير بن احمد</p>
               <p>[Usurper]</p>
               <p>c. A.H. 304–306 = A.D. 916–918</p>
               <p>4. Sijistan.<ref target="#CH1-n22">
                     <hi rend="sup">21</hi>
                  </ref> A.H. 306. <graphic url="NNM72_13.jpg"/>
               </p>
               <p>1.15, wt. 54.8 (3.55).</p>
               <p>
                  <persName>B. M. Cat.</persName>, III, No. 29.</p>
               <p> كثير بن احمد | بالعدل| as No. 3 | والوفا</p>
               <p>As No. 3 but with name of <persName>Kathir ibn Ahmad</persName> and legend:—With equity and honesty.</p>
               <p>Inner margin as No. 3, but</p>
               <p>بسجستان سنة ست وثلثمائة</p>
               <p>In Sijistan in the year 306.</p>
               <p>Outer margin (Koran XXX, 3, 4).</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> Legends as on No. 3, but with * at bottom of centre legend.</p>
               <p>Margin: (Koran IX, 33), as No. 3.</p>
               <p>Plate I, 2</p>
               <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n22">
                  <seg type="note-symbol">
                     <hi rend="sup">21</hi>
                  </seg>
                  <p>I.e., <placeName>Sistan</placeName> or Seistan (Sakastana, the land of the Sakae) also called <placeName>Nimruz</placeName> ("mid-day" land, south of Khurasan). The chief mint was at the capital <placeName>Zaranj</placeName>.</p>
               </note>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d70e2058" type="section">
               <pb n="25"/>
               <head>
                  <persName>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">(Abu Ja'far) Ahmad ibn Muhammad</hi>
                  </persName>
               </head>
               <p>احمد بن محمد</p>
               <p>c. A.H. 310–349 (?) = A.D. 922–960 (?)</p>
               <p>(a) <hi rend="italic">Without the Caliph's name</hi>
               </p>
               <p>5. Mint obliterated. A.H. 324, 7 or 9? </p>
               <p>0.45, wt. 11.7 (0.76).</p>
               <p>
                  <persName>B. M. Cat.</persName>, III, No. 32.<ref target="#CH1-n23">
                     <hi rend="sup">22</hi>
                  </ref>
               </p>
               <p>There is no god except Allah alone. He hath no associate.</p>
               <p>Margin: Date.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> As No. 3, but the name of Khalaf added instead of that of the Caliph.</p>
               <p>Margin: Part of Koran XXX, 3, partly cut off.</p>
               <p>Plate I, 3</p>
               <p>(b) <hi rend="italic">With the Caliph's name</hi>
               </p>
               <p>6. <placeName>Zaranj</placeName>.<ref target="#CH1-n24">
                     <hi rend="sup">23</hi>
                  </ref> A.H. 332? </p>
               <p>0.5, wt. 11.5 (0.75).</p>
               <p>
                  <persName>B. M. Cat.</persName>, III, No. 30.</p>
               <p>There is no god except Allah; <persName>Muhammad</persName> is the apostle of Allah.</p>
               <p>Margin: Mint and date.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> To Allah! <persName>Al-Muttaki lillah</persName> (i.e. the Abbasid Caliph) <persName>Khalaf</persName>.</p>
               <p>Margin: As on No, 3, but only as far as "truth." (Koran IX, 33).</p>
               <p>Plate I, 4</p>
               <pb n="26"/>
               <p>7. <placeName>Zaranj</placeName>.<ref target="#CH1-n24">
                     <hi rend="sup">23</hi>
                  </ref> A.H. 334. </p>
               <p>0.6, wt. 15.2 (0.98).</p>
               <p>
                  <persName>B. M. Cat.</persName>, III, No. 31.</p>
               <p>Same as No. 5 but last line <persName>Khalaf</persName>.</p>
               <p>Margin:</p>
               <p>بسم الله ضرب هذا الدينر بزونج سنة اربع و ثلثن وثلثمائة</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi>
                  <persName>Muhammad</persName> is the apostle of Allah, and the name of the Abbasid Caliph <persName>al-Mustakfi-billah</persName>.</p>
               <p>Margin as preceding.</p>
               <p>Plate I, 5</p>
               <p>8. Sijistan. A.H. 343.</p>
               <p>0.9, wt. 33.2 (2.15).<ref target="#CH1-n25">
                     <hi rend="sup">24</hi>
                  </ref> </p>
               <p>
                  <placeName>Codrington</placeName> (<persName>Tate</persName>). J. R. A. S. 1905, p. 549, illustrated in J. R. A. S. 1911, fig. 5.</p>
               <p>There is no god etc. and with the names of <persName>al-Muti' lillah</persName>, the Abbasid Caliph, <persName>Ahmad ibn Muhammad</persName> and <persName>Khalaf</persName>.</p>
               <p>Margin: As usual, but with mint name Sijistan and date 343.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> Allah is one! Allah the Eternal! He begetteth not nor is He begotten, and there is none other like unto him. (Koran CXII, 1–4).</p>
               <p>This is regarded as the quintessence of the Koranic teaching. It expressly attacks the
<pb n="27"/>
Divinity of Christ. Because it appears so frequently on the coins of the Umaiyad Caliphs it is often reffered to as the Umaiyad symbol.</p>
               <p>Margin as No. 3.</p>
               <p>Plate I, 6</p>
               <p>(a) <hi rend="italic">With names of the Caliph, <persName>al-Husain ibn Bilal</persName> and <persName>Ahmad ibn Muhammad</persName>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>9. Sijistan. A.H. 320. <graphic url="NNM72_13.jpg"/>
               </p>
               <p>1.1, wt. 34.1 (2.21).</p>
               <p>
                  <placeName>Ermitage</placeName>, Leningrad.<ref target="#CH1-n26">
                     <hi rend="sup">25</hi>
                  </ref>
               </p>
               <p>As No. 3 but with name of <persName>al-Husain ibn Bilal</persName>.</p>
               <p>Inner margin similar to above but with date 320.</p>
               <p>Outer margin as No. 3, (Koran XXX, 3, 4).</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> As No. 3, but after the Caliph's name <persName>al-Muktadir</persName> that of <persName>Ahmad ibn Muhammad</persName>.</p>
               <p>Margin as No. 3, (Koran, IX, 33).</p>
               <p>Part of the coin is missing.</p>
               <p>Plate II, 7</p>
               <p>10. Sijistan. A.H. 321. <graphic url="NNM72_13.jpg"/>
               </p>
               <p>1.25. Kaiser-Friedrich Museum, <placeName>Berlin</placeName>. See Weyl: <hi rend="italic">Verzeichniss der Fonrobert'schen Sammlung.</hi> 1878, No. 6741, and <hi rend="italic">Zeitschrift für Numismatik</hi>, <placeName>Berlin</placeName>, 1882, p. 16.</p>
               <p>As above, but date 321.</p>
               <pb n="28"/>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> As above, only with name of the Caliph <persName>al-Kahir billah</persName>.</p>
               <p>There is an outer marginal band on both obverse and reverse.</p>
               <p>Plate II, No. 8</p>
               <p>10a. Mint and date cut off. <graphic url="NNM72_13.jpg"/>
               </p>
               <p>0.7. <placeName>Ermitage</placeName>, Leningrad.</p>
               <p>As No. 9, but the epigraphy of the governor's name more cursive.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> As No. 9, but the epigraphy more cursive. This fragment, from which all marginal legends are cut off, was found, as <persName>Prof. Vasmer</persName> informs me, in the hoard of <placeName>Berozy</placeName>, district of <placeName>Dmitrowsk</placeName>, 1910. Since it bears the name of the Caliph <persName>Al-Muktadir</persName> it must be not later than 320.</p>
               <p>Plate II, 8a</p>
               <p>(b) <hi rend="italic">With names of the Caliph, <persName>Abu Ja'far</persName> and <persName>Ahmad ibn Muhammad</persName>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>11. Sijistan. A.H. 321. <graphic url="NNM72_13.jpg"/>
               </p>
               <p>1.2, wt. 41.9 (2.72).</p>
               <p>
                  <placeName>Ermitage</placeName> = Markow p. 109, No. 1.</p>
               <p>As above, but fourth line <persName>Abu Ja'far</persName> (i.e. the additional name or <hi rend="italic">kunya</hi> of <persName>Ahmad ibn Muhammad</persName>). Date 321.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> As above, but the Caliph's name indistinct.</p>
               <p>Plate II, 9</p>
               <p>This coin was described by Tiesenhausen (in <hi rend="italic">Numismatische Zeitschrift III</hi>, p. 178 f.) who
<pb n="29"/>
read the name as that of <persName>al-Radi billah</persName> although this Caliph did not begin to reign until 322. It might be read as <persName>al-Kahir billah</persName>.</p>
               <p>12. Sijistan. A.H. 323. <graphic url="NNM72_13.jpg"/>
               </p>
               <p>1.2, wt. 32.1 (2.08).</p>
               <p>
                  <placeName>Ermitage</placeName> = Markow, p. 109, No. 2.</p>
               <p>As above but date 323.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> As above but Caliph's name clearly <persName>al-Radi billah</persName>.</p>
               <p>Fragmentary. This is Tiesenhausen (<hi rend="italic">op. cit.</hi>) No. 22, p. 179.</p>
               <p>Plate II, 10</p>
               <p>13. Sijistan. A.H. 324. <graphic url="NNM72_13.jpg"/>
               </p>
               <p>1.25, wt. 50.5 (3.27).</p>
               <p>
                  <placeName>Ermitage</placeName> = Markow, p. 109, No. 3.</p>
               <p>As above but date 324.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> As above.</p>
               <p>Outer marginal band on obverse and reverse. This is Tiesenhausen (<hi rend="italic">op. cit.</hi>) No. 23, p. 179.</p>
               <p>Plate II, 11.</p>
               <p>14. Another of same mint and date. <graphic url="NNM72_13.jpg"/>
               </p>
               <p>1.25, wt. 35.1 (2.27).</p>
               <p>
                  <placeName>Ermitage</placeName> = Markow, p. 109, No. 4.</p>
               <p>Plate II, 12</p>
               <p>(c) <hi rend="italic">With name of the Caliph, <persName>Ahmad (ibn Muhammad)</persName>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>15. (Madinat) Sijistan (?) A.H. 343 or 346. <graphic url="NNM72_13.jpg"/>
               </p>
               <p>0.65, wt. 5.9 (0.38).</p>
               <p>B. M. (McMahon) unpublished. With name of the Caliph <persName>al-Muti'lillah</persName>.</p>
               <pb n="30"/>
               <p>Margin:</p>
               <p>سجستان (؟) سنة يد (؟) اربعين وثلثمائة</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> With name of <persName>Ahmad ibn Muhammad</persName>.</p>
               <p>Margin:</p>
               <p>بسم الله ضرب هذا الد[رهم] بمدينة</p>
               <p>The coin is of very thin fabric, and the marginal legend begins on the reverse and is continued on the obverse, which is most unusual.</p>
               <p>Plate II, 13</p>
               <p>16. No mint. A.H. 339. <graphic url="NNM72_13.jpg"/>
               </p>
               <p>0.4, wt. 4.2 (0.27).</p>
               <p>
                  <persName>B. M. (McMahon)</persName>, unpublished.</p>
               <p>There is no god but Allah alone. He hath no associate.</p>
               <p>Margin: Date 339.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> With names of the Caliph <persName>al-Muti'</persName> and <persName>Ahmad</persName>.</p>
               <p>Margin as on obverse.</p>
               <p>Plate II, 14</p>
               <p>17. No mint. A.H. 340. <graphic url="NNM72_13.jpg"/>
               </p>
               <p>0.4, wt. 5.3 (0.34).</p>
               <p>
                  <persName>B. M. (McMahon)</persName> unpublished.</p>
               <p>As above.</p>
               <p>Margin as above but date 340.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> As above.</p>
               <p>Margin illegible.</p>
               <p>Plate II, 15</p>
               <p>18. No mint, date illegible. <graphic url="NNM72_13.jpg"/>
               </p>
               <p>0.35, wt. 4.2 (0.27).</p>
               <pb n="31"/>
               <p>
                  <persName>B. M. (McMahon)</persName> unpublished.</p>
               <p>As above but margin illegible.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> As above but margin illegible.</p>
               <p>Plate II, 16</p>
               <p>19. Mint and date illegible. <graphic url="NNM72_13.jpg"/>
               </p>
               <p>0.35, wt. 4.6 (0.30).</p>
               <p>
                  <persName>B. M. (McMahon)</persName> unpublished.</p>
               <p>As above.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> As above.</p>
               <p>The above unusual silver denominations are only known during this reign.</p>
               <p>Plate II, 17</p>
               <p>(d) <hi rend="italic">With names of the Caliph, <persName>Khalaf</persName> and <persName>Ahmad ibn Muhammad</persName>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>20. Sijistan. A.H. 349. <graphic url="NNM72_13.jpg"/>
               </p>
               <p>Wt. 24.2 (1.59).</p>
               <p>Fragment. <placeName>Ermitage</placeName>.</p>
               <p>With names of the Caliph <persName>al-Muti'</persName>, <persName>Ahmad ibn Muhammad</persName> and <persName>Khalaf</persName>.</p>
               <p>Margin shows part of mint name and 49 of the year.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> As on No. 8.</p>
               <p>Margin: Part of Koran IX, 33, as on No. 3.</p>
               <p>Plate II, 18</p>
               <p>
                  <persName>Prof. Vasmer</persName> informs me that this fragment is from a hoard found in 1923 at <placeName>Vaskovo</placeName>, district of <placeName>Velikiya Luki</placeName>, in the govt, of <placeName>Pskov</placeName>, <placeName>N. W. Russia</placeName>.</p>
               <pb n="32"/>
               <p>(a) <hi rend="italic">With name of <persName>Khalaf</persName>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>21. Sijistan. A.H. 3xx.<ref target="#CH1-n27">
                     <hi rend="sup">26</hi>
                  </ref> Æ</p>
               <p>0.95, wt. 41.4 (2.68).</p>
               <p>
                  <persName>B.M. Cat.</persName>, III, No. 33.</p>
               <p>ولى (؟)  | لا اله الا | الله وحده | لاشريك<ref target="#CH1-n28">
                     <hi rend="sup">27</hi>
                  </ref>
               </p>
               <p>له | ح ح</p>
               <p>ح = initial letter of <persName>Khalaf</persName> (?).</p>
               <p>Margin:</p>
               <p>بسم الله ضرب هذا [الفلسر? ] بسجستان </p>
               <p>(sic) سنه ا ى ثلثين ثلثما ئة </p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>لله | محمد | رسول | الله | خلف</p>
               <p>Margin: Koran XXX, 3, 4, as on obverse of No. 3.</p>
               <p>Plate III, 19</p>
               <p>22. Sijistan. Date illegible. Pierced. Æ</p>
               <p>1.05, wt. 39.5 (2.56).</p>
               <p>
                  <persName>B.M. (Tate)</persName> unpublished.</p>
               <p>As above but not so clear in places.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> As above.</p>
               <p>Plate III, 20</p>
               <p>(b) <hi rend="italic">With name of <persName>Abu Ja'far Ahmad ibn Muhammad</persName>.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>23. <placeName>Zaranj</placeName>. A.H. 327. Æ</p>
               <p>0.8, wt. 24.3 (1.57).</p>
               <pb n="33"/>
               <p>
                  <placeName>Codrington</placeName> (<persName>McMahon</persName>) No. 2, fig. 2.</p>
               <p>As No. 11.</p>
               <p>Margin with name of <placeName>Zaranj</placeName> and date.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> As No. 11, but with the Caliph's name omitted.</p>
               <p>Margin: Koran XXX, 3.</p>
               <p>Plate III, 21</p>
               <p>
                  <placeName>Codrington</placeName> dates this 334, but the date is certainly either 327 or 329. As for the reverse margin, characteristic of the copper coins of this group, both <persName>Lane-Poole</persName> and <placeName>Codrington</placeName> considered the legend illegible. See page 21.</p>
               <p>24. <placeName>Zaranj</placeName>. A.H. 327. Æ</p>
               <p>0.85, wt. 27.6 (1.79).</p>
               <p>
                  <persName>B. M. (McMahon)</persName>.</p>
               <p>As above; date clearer. See page 21.</p>
               <p>Plate III, 22</p>
               <p>25. <placeName>Zaranj</placeName>. A.H. 328. Pierced. Æ</p>
               <p>1, wt. 32.2 (2.09).</p>
               <p>
                  <persName>B. M. (McMahon)</persName>.</p>
               <p>As No. 16.</p>
               <p>Margin: As above but date 328.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> With name of <persName>Abu Ja'far</persName>.</p>
               <p>Margin: (ordered by) the <persName>Amir Ahmad ibn Muhammad</persName>. May Allah magnify him.</p>
               <p>Plate III, 23</p>
               <p>26. <placeName>Zaranj</placeName>. A.H. 328. Æ</p>
               <p>0.75, wt. 29.7 (1.92).</p>
               <p>
                  <persName>B.M. (McMahon)</persName>. <placeName>Codrington</placeName>, fig. 3 (<hi rend="italic">obv</hi>).</p>
               <pb n="34"/>
               <p>He was unable, however, to date coins of this type.</p>
               <p>As above but in two lines, below, <persName>Abu Ja'far</persName>.</p>
               <p>Margin as above.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> As above.</p>
               <p>Margin: Border of annulets.</p>
               <p>Plate III, 24</p>
               <p>27. Zaranj. A.H. 32[8?] Æ</p>
               <p>0.85, wt. 34.8 (2.26).</p>
               <p>
                  <persName>B. M. (McMahon)</persName>.</p>
               <p>As above, but date not so clear.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> As above.</p>
               <p>Plate III, 25</p>
               <p>28. Another probably of the same year. Æ</p>
               <p>0.8, wt. 27.7 (1.79).</p>
               <p>
                  <persName>B. M. (McMahon)</persName>.</p>
               <p>As above.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> As above but without لله at top.</p>
               <p>Plate III, 26</p>
               <p>29. No mint or date. Æ</p>
               <p>0.85, wt. 40.4 (2.62).</p>
               <p>
                  <persName>B. M. (McMahon)</persName>
                  <placeName>Codrington</placeName>, fig. 4.</p>
               <p>This interesting freak combines the reverse of No. 27 with the reverse of No. 28.</p>
               <p>Plate III, 27</p>
               <p>(c) <hi rend="italic">Without the name of the Caliph or <persName>Abu Ja'far</persName>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>30. Zaranj. A.H. 319? or 329? Æ</p>
               <p>0.85, wt. 30.4 (1.97).</p>
               <p>
                  <persName>B. M. (McMahon)</persName>.</p>
               <pb n="35"/>
               <p>As No. 16.</p>
               <p>Margin: (Within double circle and outer border of annulets) mint and date.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> As No. 9, but with Caliph's name omitted.</p>
               <p>Margin: Koran XXX, 3. See page 21.</p>
               <p>Plate III, 28</p>
               <p>(d) <hi rend="italic">With the name of the <persName>Caliph</persName> and <persName>Ahmad ibn Muhammad</persName>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>31. Sijistan. A.H. 337. Edge partly broken. Æ</p>
               <p>0.8, wt. 25.3 (1.64).</p>
               <p>
                  <persName>B. M. (Tate)</persName> unpublished.</p>
               <p>In circle:  بن |  احمد | محمد, (with point in the centre of the <hi rend="italic">mim</hi> of <persName>Ahmad</persName>).</p>
               <p>Margin: In the name of Allah this fals (i.e. copper coin) was minted in Sijistan. (The <hi rend="italic">nun</hi> of Sijistan omitted).</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> In circle: المطيع | لله (The name of the <persName>Caliph al-Muti' lillah</persName>).</p>
               <p>Margin: In the year 337.</p>
               <p>Plate III, 29</p>
               <p>I have read the date 337 rather than 339 because the numeral in question is سبع and not تسع.</p>
               <p>32. Sijistan. A.H. 339. Æ</p>
               <p>0.8, wt. 26.4 (1.71).</p>
               <p>
                  <persName>B. M. (Tate)</persName>.</p>
               <pb n="36"/>
               <p>As above.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> As above, but date 339.</p>
               <p>Plate III, 30</p>
               <p>33. Sijistan. A.H. 339. Æ</p>
               <p>0.8, wt. 24.3 (1.57).</p>
               <p>
                  <persName>B. M. (Tate)</persName>.</p>
               <p>Almost obliterated.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> As above.</p>
               <p>Plate III, 31</p>
               <p>A similar coin was described by Bartholomaei in the <hi rend="italic">Revue de la Numismatique Belge</hi>, 1861, pp. 34–36 (plate III, No. 1) but as he was unable to read the mint name he wrongly ascribed it to the Shahs of Khwarizm.</p>
               <p>34. Sijistan. A.H. 340. Æ</p>
               <p>0.85, wt. 26 (1.68).</p>
               <p>
                  <persName>B. M. Cat.</persName>, III, No. 34.</p>
               <p>As No. 31 but mint name written correctly.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> As above but date 340.</p>
               <p>Plate III, 32</p>
               <p>35. Sijistan. A.H. 340. Æ</p>
               <p>0.85 wt. 29.3 (1.90).</p>
               <p>
                  <persName>B. M. (Tate)</persName>.</p>
               <p>As above, but less distinct.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> As above, but less distinct.</p>
               <p>Plate IV, 33</p>
               <p>36. Sijistan. A.H. 341. Æ</p>
               <p>0.85, wt. 30.1 (1.95).</p>
               <pb n="37"/>
               <p>
                  <persName>B. M. (Tate)</persName>.</p>
               <p>As above.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> As above, but date 341.</p>
               <p>Plate IV, 34</p>
               <p>37. Sijistan. A.H. 342. Æ</p>
               <p>0.9, wt. 41.0 (2.66).</p>
               <p>
                  <persName>B. M. (Tate)</persName>.</p>
               <p>As above.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> As above, but date 342.</p>
               <p>Plate IV, 35</p>
               <p>38. Sijistan. A.H. 343. Æ</p>
               <p>0.85, wt. 36.1 (2.34).</p>
               <p>
                  <persName>B.M. Cat.</persName>, III, No. 35.</p>
               <p>As above.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> As above, but date 343.</p>
               <p>Plate IV, 36</p>
               <p>39. Sijistan. A.H. 343. Æ</p>
               <p>0.85, wt. 36.6 (2.37).</p>
               <p>
                  <persName>B. M. (Tate)</persName>.</p>
               <p>As above.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> As above.</p>
               <p>Plate IV, 37</p>
               <p>40. Sijistan. A.H. 344. Æ</p>
               <p>0.85, wt. 29.5 (1.91).</p>
               <p>
                  <persName>B. M. (Tate)</persName>.</p>
               <p>As above, but partly obliterated.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> As above, but date 344.</p>
               <p>Plate IV, 38</p>
               <pb n="38"/>
               <p>(e) <hi rend="italic">With the name of the <persName>Caliph, Khalaf</persName> and <persName>Abu Ja'far Ahmad ibn Muhammad</persName>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>41. Sijistan. A.H. 346. Æ</p>
               <p>0.9, wt. 21.9 (1.42).</p>
               <p>
                  <persName>B. M. (Tate)</persName>.<ref target="#CH1-n29">
                     <hi rend="sup">28</hi>
                  </ref>
               </p>
               <p>Area in arabesque characters, <persName>al Muti' lillah</persName> and <persName>Khalaf</persName> in three lines.</p>
               <p>Margin as No. 34.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> Area: (This coin is) of what was ordered by the <persName>Amir Abu Ja'far Ahmad ibn Muhammad</persName>. May Allah strengthen him!</p>
               <p>Margin as above, but date 346.</p>
               <p>Plate IV, 39</p>
               <p>42. Sijistan. A.H. 346. Æ</p>
               <p>0.9, wt. 28 (1.81).</p>
               <p>
                  <persName>B. M. (Tate)</persName>.</p>
               <p>As above, with parts of the legend a little clearer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> As above, but less distinct.</p>
               <p>Plate IV, 40</p>
               <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n23">
                  <seg type="note-symbol">
                     <hi rend="sup">22</hi>
                  </seg>
                  <p>
                     <persName>Lane-Poole</persName> gives the date as 33x, but it is decidedly 32x.</p>
               </note>
               <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n24">
                  <seg type="note-symbol">
                     <hi rend="sup">23</hi>
                  </seg>
                  <p>
                     <persName>Lane-Poole</persName> was unable to read the mint name.</p>
               </note>
               <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n25">
                  <seg type="note-symbol">
                     <hi rend="sup">24</hi>
                  </seg>
                  <p>A metal loop has been affixed to the coin, which is badly cracked.</p>
               </note>
               <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n26">
                  <seg type="note-symbol">
                     <hi rend="sup">25</hi>
                  </seg>
                  <p>
                     <persName>Prof. Vasmer</persName> tells me that this coin was found at Friedrichshof in 1913. Cf. <hi rend="italic">Sitzungsberichte der Gelehrten Estnischen Gesellschaft</hi> 1925, p. 44, no. 24.</p>
               </note>
               <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n27">
                  <seg type="note-symbol">
                     <hi rend="sup">26</hi>
                  </seg>
                  <p>
                     <persName>Lane-Poole</persName> reads it as 325 (?). I am inclined to read it as 331, but it is not clear enough.</p>
               </note>
               <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n28">
                  <seg type="note-symbol">
                     <hi rend="sup">27</hi>
                  </seg>
                  <p>Not an ornament as <persName>Lane-Poole</persName> supposed it to be. It possibly refers to Khalafas heir apparent (<hi rend="italic">wali 'ahd</hi>)</p>
               </note>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d70e3195" type="section">
               <head>
                  <persName>(<hi rend="smallcaps">Abu Ahmad</hi>) <hi rend="smallcaps">Khalaf ibn Ahmad</hi>
                  </persName>
               </head>
               <p>خلف بن احمد</p>
               <p>c. A.H. 349 (?)–399 = A.D. 960–1008</p>
               <pb n="39"/>
               <p>(a) <hi rend="italic">With name of the <persName>Caliph al-Muti'</persName>
                  </hi> (334–363)</p>
               <p>43. Sijistan. A.H. 362. </p>
               <p>0.5, wt. 24.4 (1.58).</p>
               <p>Zambaur, <hi rend="italic">Contributions.</hi> No. 436.</p>
               <p>44. Sijistan. A.H.366.<ref target="#CH1-n30">
                     <hi rend="sup">29</hi>
                  </ref> </p>
               <p>0.5, wt. 18.6 (1.21).</p>
               <p>
                  <persName>B.M. Cat.</persName>, III, No. 36.</p>
               <p>In circle: ○ <persName>Muhammad</persName> is the apostle of Allah, and ع</p>
               <p>Margin: There is no god except Allah etc.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> In circle: <persName>Al-Muti' lillah</persName> | <persName>Khalaf ibn Ahmad</persName> | Equity.</p>
               <p>Margin: Mint and date 366.</p>
               <p>Plate IV, 41</p>
               <p>45. Sijistan. Date uncertain.<ref target="#CH1-n31">
                     <hi rend="sup">30</hi>
                  </ref> </p>
               <p>0.55, wt. 19.3 (1.25).</p>
               <p>Ermitage.</p>
               <p>
                  <persName>Muhammad</persName> is the apostle of Allah.</p>
               <p>Margin: Traces of legend.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> As above.</p>
               <p>Margin: Mint and part of date.</p>
               <p>Plate IV, 42</p>
               <p>46. Sijistan. 3xx. </p>
               <p>0.5, wt. 18.0 (1.17).</p>
               <p>
                  <persName>B. M. Cat.</persName>, III, No. 37.</p>
               <pb n="40"/>
               <p>As No. 44, but top cut off.</p>
               <p>Margin as on No. 44.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. As above.</p>
               <p>Margin. Mint and part of date.</p>
               <p>Plate IV, 43</p>
               <p>47. Sijistan [3] x 3. </p>
               <p>0.45, wt. 8.7 (0.56).</p>
               <p>
                  <persName>B. M. Cat.</persName>, III, 39.</p>
               <p>As above, but below. ك, instead of ع</p>
               <p>Margin: Traces of same legend as above.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> As above, but margin showing part of date.</p>
               <p>Plate IV, 44</p>
               <p>48. Sijistan. Date uncertain. </p>
               <p>0.45, wt. 12.0 (0.78).</p>
               <p>
                  <persName>B. M. Cat.</persName>, III, No. 38.</p>
               <p>As No. 44.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi>
                  <persName>Al Muti'|lillah</persName> | | <persName>Khalaf ibn Ahmad</persName>? The fourth line may possibly conceal the <hi rend="italic">kunya</hi> or additional name <persName>Abu Ahmad</persName>.</p>
               <p>Margin: Illegible.</p>
               <p>Plate IV, 45</p>
               <p>49. Sijistan (?) A.H. 361 (?). Æ</p>
               <p>0.85, wt. 20.1 (1.30).</p>
               <p>
                  <persName>B. M. (McMahon)</persName>.<ref target="#CH1-n32">
                     <hi rend="sup">31</hi>
                  </ref>
               </p>
               <pb n="41"/>
               <p>In circle: <persName>Khalaf ibn Ahmad</persName>. Above, arabesque.</p>
               <p>Margin: Traces of inscription with the mint name.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> In circle: <persName>Al-Muti' lillah</persName>. Above, arabesque.</p>
               <p>Margin: Date 361 (?).</p>
               <p>Plate IV, 46</p>
               <p>A better preserved specimen of same mint and date is in Oxford (Lane-Poole, Cat. of the <persName>Mohammedan</persName> coins preserved in Bodleian Library, p. 6).</p>
               <p>(b) <hi rend="italic">With name of <persName>Caliph al-Ta'i'</persName>
                  </hi>, (363–381)</p>
               <p>50. Mint obliterated. A.H. 375. </p>
               <p>0.55, wt. 29.5 (1.91).</p>
               <p>
                  <persName>B. M. Cat.</persName>, III, No. 40.</p>
               <p>In double circle: There is no god but Allah alone, <persName>Khalaf ibn Ahmad</persName>.</p>
               <p>Margin: Date 375.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi>
                  <persName>Muhammad</persName> etc., and name of <persName>Caliph al-Ta'i'</persName>, ornament below.</p>
               <p>Margin: See page 21 for full legend from Koran LIX, 9; LXIV, 16.<ref target="#CH1-n33">
                     <hi rend="sup">32</hi>
                  </ref>
               </p>
               <p>Plate IV, 47</p>
               <pb n="42"/>
               <p>51. Mint obliterated. A.H. 373 or 376. </p>
               <p>0.5, wt. 13.6 (0.88).</p>
               <p>
                  <persName>B. M. Cat.</persName>, III, No.41.</p>
               <p>As above but partly cut off, eight-pointed star below.</p>
               <p>Margin: Date 373 or 376. The missing number arguing from the presence of the tail must be either a three or a six.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> As above, but annulet below.</p>
               <p>Margin: As on No. 50.</p>
               <p>Plate IV, 48</p>
               <p>In the plate the reverse is above and the obverse is below.</p>
               <p>52. Sijistan. A.H. 378. </p>
               <p>0.75, wt. 21.5 (1.39).</p>
               <p>
                  <persName>B. M. (McMahon)</persName>.</p>
               <p>As No. 50, but within single circle; annulet below.</p>
               <p>Margin: As above, but complete, struck at Sijistan, the year 378.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> As No. 50, but different ornament below.</p>
               <p>Margin: As above.</p>
               <p>Plate V, 49</p>
               <p>Illustrated by Codrington J. R. A. S. 1911, fig. 7</p>
               <p>53. Sijistan. A.H. 3[7]9. </p>
               <p>0.8, wt. 25.1 (1.63).</p>
               <p>
                  <persName>B. M. (Tate)</persName>.</p>
               <p>As No. 52, only above الدولة and below ة ة </p>
               <p>Margin: As No. 52, but date 379</p>
               <pb n="43"/>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> As No. 52, below ة.</p>
               <p>Margin: As above.</p>
               <p>Plate V, 50</p>
               <p>Illustrated by Codrington J. R. A. S. 1911, fig. 8. There is an example of this coin in the Ermitage, No. 7C, but the margins have been almost cut off.</p>
               <p>Plate V, 51</p>
               <p>54. Mint obliterated. A.H. 378. Æ</p>
               <p>1.05, wt. 55.3 (3.58).</p>
               <p>
                  <persName>B. M. Cat.</persName>, Add. IX, p. 268.</p>
               <p>In circle of dots, Help is from Allah!</p>
               <p>Inner margin: As on margin of No. 44.</p>
               <p>Outer margin: Date 378.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> In circle of dots, To Allah! <persName>Muhammad</persName> is the apostle of Allah, and with the names of the <persName>Caliph al-Ta'i'</persName> and <persName>Khalaf ibn Ahmad</persName>, ornament below.</p>
               <p>Margin: Authority belongs to Allah before and after, and on that day the believers shall rejoice in the help of Allah. (Koran XXX, end of verse 3 and beginning of verse 4.)</p>
               <p>Plate V, 52</p>
               <p>Lane-Poole was unable to discern (8) ثمان but with a little cleaning the numeral has become clear. He read the central obverse legend as <persName>Nasr ibn Nuh</persName>, instead of the Koranic phrase <hi rend="italic">nasr min Allah</hi> (Help is from Allah).</p>
               <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n29">
                  <seg type="note-symbol">
                     <hi rend="sup">28</hi>
                  </seg>
                  <p>Codrington published this in J. R. A. S., 1905, p. 550, and again in 1911, p. 783 (fig. 6) but he was unable to read the date, which is comparatively legible as above.</p>
               </note>
               <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n30">
                  <seg type="note-symbol">
                     <hi rend="sup">29</hi>
                  </seg>
                  <p>As pointed out by Lane-Poole the Caliph's reign ended in 363 yet the coin is certainly dated 366.</p>
               </note>
               <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n31">
                  <seg type="note-symbol">
                     <hi rend="sup">30</hi>
                  </seg>
                  <p>Prof. Vasmer dates this 365, but I am unable to verify this from the cast he very kindly sent me.</p>
               </note>
               <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n32">
                  <seg type="note-symbol">
                     <hi rend="sup">31</hi>
                  </seg>
                  <p>Illustrated by Codrington, fig. 9, J. R. A. S., 1911, p. 783, although, when he previously described the specimen in the Tate Collection (J. R. A. S., 1905, p. 550), he was unable to read the marginal legends. I have been unable to trace the whereabouts of the other examples of this <hi rend="italic">fals</hi>. Codrington is also wrong in reading the mint name where he does. It is interesting to note the fourfold division of the marginal legends by spaces.</p>
               </note>
               <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n33">
                  <seg type="note-symbol">
                     <hi rend="sup">32</hi>
                  </seg>
                  <p>Neither Lane-Poole nor Codrington deciphered this fragmentary reverse marginal legend (see No. 51).</p>
               </note>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d70e3575" type="section">
               <pb n="44"/>
               <head>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">
                     <persName>Al-Husain ibn Tahir</persName>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>الحسين بن طاهر</p>
               <p>[Usurper]</p>
               <p>55. Mint and date cut off. </p>
               <p>0.5, wt. 18.9 (1.22).</p>
               <p>
                  <persName>B. M. Cat.</persName>, III, No. 42.</p>
               <p>In circle, as on No. 44, but with "to Allah" instead of annulet; ع = initial for عدل equity.</p>
               <p>Margin cut off.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> In circle, <persName>al-Ta'i' lillah</persName>, <persName>al-Husain ibn Tahir</persName> in three lines.</p>
               <p>Margin cut off.</p>
               <p>Plate V, 53</p>
               <p>The name of the <persName>Caliph al-Ta'i'</persName> limits the date to the period between A.H. 363 and 381, but whether the coin was struck during the first or second usurpation (see above p. 18) it is impossible to decide with any certainty.</p>
               <p>Zambaur (<hi rend="italic">op. cit.</hi> p. 201) regards <persName>Husain</persName> as the grandson of <persName>Khalaf</persName>. This I feel sure is incorrect.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">With the name of the <persName>Caliph al-Kadir</persName>
                  </hi> (381–422)</p>
               <p>(With <persName>Khalaf's</persName> title of <persName>Wali al Daula</persName>)</p>
               <p>56. Sijistan. A.H. 384. <graphic url="NNM72_13.jpg"/>
               </p>
               <p>1.2, wt. 94.1 (6.1).</p>
               <p>Berlin Museum.</p>
               <p>In centre, in highly ornamental characters: There is no god except Allah alone, he hath no
<pb n="45"/>
associate. Below eight-pointed star and triangle of annulets, and single annulet.</p>
               <p>Margin: In the name of Allah this dirham was minted at Sijistan in the year 384.</p>
               <p>Outside circle of dots.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> In center, in ornamental script as on No. 54, and with the name of the <persName>Caliph al-Kadir billah</persName>, and below that <persName>Wali al-Daula</persName>, and <hi rend="italic">'adl</hi> = equity. All within circle of dots.</p>
               <p>Margin: As on reverse of No. 3. (Koran IX, 33).</p>
               <p>Plate V, 54</p>
               <p>This interesting coin must have been struck shortly after <persName>Khalaf</persName> had won back his kingdom from the usurper <persName>Husain ibn Tahir</persName>. It is the only coin, as yet known, that bears his new title of <persName>Wali al-Daula</persName> (cf. p. 18 above)</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d70e3686" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">
                     <persName>Tahir ibn Khalaf</persName>
                  </hi>
               </head>
               <p>طاهر بن خلف</p>
               <p>[Usurping son of <persName>Khalaf</persName>]</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">With name of Ghaznavid overlord</hi>
               </p>
               <p>57. Mint and date cut off. Billon</p>
               <p>0.85, wt. 35.8 (2.32).</p>
               <p>Ermitage = Markow, 4th Suppl. 966, No. 4a.</p>
               <p>In centre within plain circle: There is no God but Allah alone, and with name of <persName>Tahir ibn Khalaf</persName>.</p>
               <p>Margin: Fragment of the date inscription.</p>
               <pb n="46"/>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> In centre within plain circle; as on No. 54, and with name of the <persName>Caliph al-Kadir billah</persName> and below that, the name of <persName>Mahmud</persName>, the Ghaznavid ruler who had conquered Sistan in A.H. 393 = A.D. 1002.</p>
               <p>Margin: As on No. 56 (part of Koran IX, 33).</p>
               <p>Plate V, 55</p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div1 xml:id="d70e3731" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="bold">SECOND SAFFARID DYNASTY</hi>
            </head>
            <div2 xml:id="d70e3736" type="section">
               <head>PLATE I</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-5">
                  <graphic url="NNM72_54.jpg"/>
               </figure>
               <pb/>
               <figure xml:id="fig-6">
                  <graphic url="NNM72_55.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d70e3744" type="section">
               <pb/>
               <head>PLATE II</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-7">
                  <graphic url="NNM72_56.jpg"/>
               </figure>
               <pb/>
               <figure xml:id="fig-8">
                  <graphic url="NNM72_57.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d70e3753" type="section">
               <pb/>
               <head>PLATE III</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-9">
                  <graphic url="NNM72_58.jpg"/>
               </figure>
               <pb/>
               <figure xml:id="fig-10">
                  <graphic url="NNM72_59.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d70e3762" type="section">
               <pb/>
               <head>PLATE IV</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-11">
                  <graphic url="NNM72_60.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d70e3768" type="section">
               <pb/>
               <head>PLATE V</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-12">
                  <graphic url="NNM72_61.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d70e3774" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">
                  <hi rend="bold">Numismatic Notes and Monographs</hi>
               </hi>
            </head>
            <list type="numbered">
               <item n="9.">
                  <persName>David Eugene Smith</persName>, LL.D. Computing Jetons. 1921. 70 pp. 25 pls. $1.50.</item>
               <item n="10.">
                  <persName>Edward T. Newell</persName>. The First Seleucid Coinage of Tyre. 1921 40 pp. 8 pls. $1.00.</item>
               <item n="12.">
                  <persName>Howland Wood</persName>. Gold Dollars of 1858. 1922. 7 pp. 2 pls. 50c.</item>
               <item n="13.">
                  <persName>R. B. Whitehead</persName>. Pre-Mohammedan Coinage of N. W. <placeName>India</placeName> 1922. 56 pp. 15 pls. $2.00.</item>
               <item n="14.">
                  <persName>George F. Hill</persName>. Attambelos I of Characene. 1922. 12 pp. 3 pls. $1.00.</item>
               <item n="15.">
                  <persName>M. P. Vlasto</persName>. Taras Oikistes (A Contribution to Tarentine Numismatics). 234 pp. 13 pls. $3.50.</item>
               <item n="17.">
                  <persName>Agnes Baldwin</persName>. Six Roman Bronze Medallions. 1923. 39 pp. 6 pls. $1.50.</item>
               <item n="18.">
                  <persName>Howland Wood</persName>. Tegucigalpa Coinage of 1823. 1923. 16 pp. 2 pls. 50c.</item>
               <item n="19.">
                  <persName>Edward T. Newell</persName>. Alexander Hoards—II. Demanhur Hoard. 1923. 162 pp. 8 pls. $2.50.</item>
               <item n="20.">
                  <persName>Harrold E. Gillingham</persName>. Italian Orders of Chivalry and Medals of Honour. 146 pp. 34 pls. $2.00.</item>
               <item n="21.">
                  <persName>Edward T. Newell</persName>. Alexander Hoards—III. Andritsaena. 1924. 39 pp. 6 pls. $1.00.</item>
               <item n="22.">
                  <persName>C. T. Seltman</persName>. A Hoard from Side. 1924. 20 pp. 3 pls. $1.00.</item>
               <item n="23.">
                  <persName>R. B. Seager</persName>. A Cretan Coin Hoard. 1924. 55 pp. 12 pls. $2.00.</item>
               <item n="24.">
                  <persName>Samuel R. Milbank</persName>. The Coinage of <placeName>Aegina</placeName>. 1925. 66 pp. 5 pls. $2.00.</item>
               <item n="25.">
                  <persName>Sydney P. Noe</persName>. A Bibliography of Greek Coin Hoards. 1925. 275 pp. $2.50.</item>
               <item n="26.">
                  <persName>Edward T. Newell</persName>. Mithradates of Parthia and Hyspaosines of Characene. 18 pp. 2 pls. 50c.</item>
               <item n="27.">
                  <persName>Sydney P. Noe</persName>. The Mende (Kaliandra) Hoard. 1926. 73 pp 10 pls. $2.00.</item>
               <item n="28.">
                  <persName>Agnes Baldwin</persName>. Four Medallions from the Arras Hoard. 1926 36 pp. 4 pls. $1.50.</item>
               <item n="30.">
                  <persName>Edward T. Newell</persName>. Some Unpublished Coins of Eastern Dynasts. 1926. 21 pp. 2 pls. 50c.</item>
               <item n="31.">
                  <persName>Harrold E. Gillingham</persName>. Spanish Orders of Chivalry and Decorations of Honour. 1926. 165 pp. 40 pls. $3.00.</item>
               <item n="32.">
                  <persName>Sydney P. Noe</persName>. The Coinage of <placeName>Metapontum</placeName>. 1927 (Part I). 134 pp. 23 pls. $3.00.</item>
               <item n="33.">
                  <persName>Edward T. Newell</persName>. Two Recent Egyptian Hoards—Delta and Keneh. 34 pp. 3 pls. $1.00.</item>
               <item n="34.">
                  <persName>Edward Rogers</persName>. The Second and Third Seleucid Coinage of Tyre. 1927. 33 pp. 4 pls. $1.50.</item>
               <item n="35.">
                  <persName>Alfred R. Bellinger</persName>. The Anonymous Byzantine Bronze Coinage. 1928. 27 pp. 4 pls. $1.50.</item>
               <item n="36.">
                  <persName>Harrold E. Gillingham</persName>. Notes on the Decorations and Medals of the French Colonies and Protectorates. 1928. 62 pp. 31 pls. $2.00.</item>
               <item n="37.">
                  <persName>Oscar Ravel</persName>. The "Colts" of <placeName>Ambracia</placeName>. 1928. 180 pp. 19 pls. $3.00.</item>
               <item n="38.">
                  <persName>Howland Wood</persName>. The Coinage of the Mexican Revolutionists. 1928. 53 pp. 15 pls. $2.50.</item>
               <item n="39.">
                  <persName>Edward T. Newell</persName>. Alexander Hoards—IV. Olympia. 1929. 31 pp. 9 pls. $1.50.</item>
               <item n="40.">
                  <persName>Allen B. West</persName>. Fifth and Fourth Century Gold Coins from the Thracian Coast. 1929. 183 pp. 16 pls. $3.00.</item>
               <pb/>
               <item n="41.">
                  <persName>Gilbert S. Perez</persName>. The Leper Colony Currency of Culion. 1929. 10 pp. 3 pls. 50c.</item>
               <item n="42.">
                  <persName>Alfred R. Bellinger</persName>. Two Hoards of Attic Bronze Coins. 1930. 14 pp. 4 pls. 50c.</item>
               <item n="43.">
                  <persName>D. H. Cox</persName>. The Caparelli Hoard. 1930. 14 pp. 2 pls. 50c.</item>
               <item n="44.">
                  <persName>Geo. F. Hill</persName>. On the Coins of Narbonensis with Iberian Inscriptions. 1930. 39 pp. 6 pls. $1.00.</item>
               <item n="45.">
                  <persName>Bauman L. Belden</persName>. A Mint in <placeName>New York</placeName>. 1930. 40 pp. 4 pls. 50 c.</item>
               <item n="46.">
                  <persName>Edward T. Newell</persName>. The Küchük Köhne Hoard. 1931. 33 pp. 4 pls. $1.00.</item>
               <item n="47.">
                  <persName>Sydney P. Noe</persName>. The Coinage of Metapontum. Part II. 1931. 134 pp. 43 pls. $3.00.</item>
               <item n="48.">
                  <persName>D. W. Valentine</persName>. <placeName>The United States</placeName> Half Dimes. 1931. 79 pp. 47 pls. $5.00.</item>
               <item n="49.">
                  <persName>Alfred R. Bellinger</persName>. Two Roman Hoards from <placeName>Dura-Europos</placeName>. 1931. 66 pp. 17 pls. $1.50.</item>
               <item n="50.">
                  <persName>Geo. F. Hill</persName>. Notes on the Ancient Coinage of Hispania Citerior. 196 pp. 36 dble. pls. $4.00.</item>
               <item n="51.">
                  <persName>Alan W. Hazelton</persName>. The Russian Imperial Orders. 1932. 102 pp. 20 pls. $3.00.</item>
               <item n="52.">
                  <persName>O. Ravel</persName>. Corinthian Hoards (Corinth and Arta). 1932. 27 pp. 4 pls. $1.00.</item>
               <item n="53.">
                  <persName>Jean B. Cammann</persName>. The Symbols on Staters of Corinthian Type (A Catalogue). 1932. 130 pp. 14 dble. pls. $3.00.</item>
               <item n="54.">
                  <persName>Shirley H. Weber</persName>. An Egyptian Hoard of the Second Century A. D. 41 pp. 5 pls. 1932. $1.50.</item>
               <item n="55.">
                  <persName>Alfred R. Bellmger</persName>. The Third and Fourth <placeName>Dura</placeName> Hoards. 1932. 85 pp. 20 pls. $1.50.</item>
               <item n="56.">
                  <persName>Harrold E. Gillingham</persName>. South American Decorations and War Medals. 1932. 178 pp. 35 pls. $3.00.</item>
               <item n="57.">
                  <persName>Wm. Campbell</persName>. Greek and Roman Plated Coins. 1933. 226 pp. 190 + pls. $3.50.</item>
               <item n="58.">
                  <persName>E. T. Newell</persName>. The Fifth <placeName>Dura</placeName> Hoard. 1933. 14 pp. 2 pls. $1.00.</item>
               <item n="59.">
                  <persName>D. H. Cox</persName>. The Tripolis Hoard. 1933. 61 pp. 8 pls. 2 maps. $1.50.</item>
               <item n="60.">
                  <persName>E. T. Newell</persName>. Two Hoards from Minturno. 38 pp. 5 pls. $1.00.</item>
               <item n="61.">
                  <persName>Howland Wood</persName>. The Gampola Larin Hoard. 1934. 84 pp. 10 dble. pls. $3.00.</item>
               <item n="62.">
                  <persName>J. G. Milne</persName>. The Melos Hoard of 1907. 1934. 19 pp. 1 pl. $1.00.</item>
               <item n="63.">
                  <persName>A. F. Pradeau</persName>. The Mexican Mints of Alamos and Hermosillo 1934. 73 pp. illus. $1.50.</item>
               <item n="64.">
                  <persName>E. T. Newell</persName>. A Hoard from <placeName>Siphnos</placeName>. 1934. 17 pp. illus. 50c.</item>
               <item n="65.">
                  <persName>C. H. V. Sutherland</persName>. Romano-British Imitations of Bronze Coins of Claudius I. 1935. 35 pp. 8 dble. pls. $2.00.</item>
               <item n="66.">
                  <persName>Harrold E. Gillingham</persName>. Ephemeral Decorations. 1935. 40 pp. 11 pls. $2.00.</item>
               <item n="67.">
                  <persName>Sawyer McA. Mosser</persName>. A Bibliography of Byzantine Coin Hoards. 1935. 116 pp. $1.50.</item>
               <item n="68.">
                  <persName>E. T. Newell</persName>. Five Greek Bronze Coin Hoards. 1935. 67 pp. 9 dbl. pls. $2.00.</item>
               <item n="69.">
                  <persName>Alfred R. Bellinger</persName>. The Sixth, Seventh and Tenth <placeName>Dura</placeName> Hoards. 1935. 75. pp. $1.00.</item>
               <item n="70.">
                  <persName>Frederick O. Waage</persName>. Greek Bronze Coins from a Well at Megara. 42 pp. 3 pls. $1.00.</item>
               <item n="71.">
                  <persName>Sydney P. Noe</persName>. The Thurian Di-Staters. 68 pp. 11 dble. pls. $2.00.</item>
            </list>
         </div1>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
