<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd"
     xml:id="nnan15879">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Alexander coinage of Sicyon</title>
            <author>
               <name>Noe, Sydney P. (Sydney Philip), 1885-1969</name>
               <idno type="URI">http://numismatics.org/authority/noe</idno>
            </author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>TEI P5 XML markup in conformance with the TEI DTD</resp>
               <name>AEL Data</name>
            </respStmt>
            <funder>Open access edition funded by the National Endowment for the Humanities/Andrew W. Mellon Foundation Humanities Open Book Program.</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <name>American Numismatic Society</name>
               <idno type="URI">http://numismatics.org/authority/american_numismatic_society</idno>
            </publisher>
            <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
            <date>1950</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">This work is made available under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International license</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Numismatic Studies</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
            <idno type="URI">http://numismatics.org/library/195779</idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>Donum</title>
               <idno type="URI">http://numismatics.org/library/15879</idno>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <title>Worldcat</title>
               <idno type="URI">http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/789214</idno>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <title>Worldcat Works</title>
               <idno type="URI">http://worldcat.org/entity/work/id/326617800</idno>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <title>HathiTrust</title>
               <idno type="URI">https://hdl.handle.net/2027/mdp.39015010553603</idno>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <particDesc>
            <listPerson>
               <person xml:id="numismatics_noe">
                  <persName>Noe, Sydney P.(Sydney Philip), 1885-1969</persName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://numismatics.org/authority/noe</idno>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="numismatics_newell">
                  <persName>Newell, Edward Theodore, 1886-1941</persName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://numismatics.org/authority/newell</idno>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="nomisma_alexander_iii">
                  <persName>Alexander the Great</persName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/alexander_iii</idno>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="numismatics_demetrius_i">
                  <persName>Demetrius Poliorcetes</persName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/demetrius_i</idno>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="viaf_65453680">
                  <persName>Storrs, Ronald, Sir, 1881-1955</persName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://viaf.org/viaf/65453680</idno>
               </person> 
               <person xml:id="wikidata_Q37122">
                  <persName>Athena</persName>
                  <idno type="URI">https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q37122</idno>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="wikidata_Q165023">
                  <persName>Nike</persName>
                  <idno type="URI">https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q165023</idno>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="wikidata_Q122248">
                  <persName>Heracles</persName>
                  <idno type="URI">https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q122248</idno>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="wikidata_Q34201">
                  <persName>Zeus</persName>
                  <idno type="URI">https://www.wikidata.org/wiki/Q34201</idno>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="viaf_74638710">
                  <persName>Babelon, Ernest, 1854-1924</persName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://viaf.org/viaf/74638710</idno>
               </person>                
               <person xml:id="nomisma_lysimachus">
                  <persName>Lysimachus</persName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/lysimachus</idno>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="nomisma_antigonus_ii">
                  <persName>Antigonus Gonatas</persName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/antigonus_ii</idno>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="viaf_297421082">
                  <persName>Lysippus</persName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://viaf.org/viaf/297421082</idno>
               </person>
            </listPerson>
         </particDesc>
         <settingDesc>
            <listPlace>
               <place xml:id="nomisma_new_york_city">
                  <placeName>New York</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/new_york_city</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="nomisma_macedonia">
                  <placeName>Macedonia</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/macedonia</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="nomisma_macedon">
                  <placeName>Macedon</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/macedon</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="nomisma_athens">
                  <placeName>Athens</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/athens</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="nomisma_sidon">
                  <placeName>Sidon</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/sidon</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="nomisma_tyre">
                  <placeName>Tyre</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/tyre</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="nomisma_ace_ptolemais">
                  <placeName>Ptolemais-Ake</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/ace_ptolemais</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="pleiades_658541">
                  <placeName>Myriandos</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">https://pleiades.stoa.org/places/658541</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="geonames_739598">
                  <placeName>Sinope</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://www.geonames.org/739598</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="nomisma_cyprus">
                  <placeName>Cyprus</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/cyprus</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="pleiades_45635759">
                  <placeName>Seleucid Mints</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">https://pleiades.stoa.org/places/45635759</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="nomisma_olympia">
                  <placeName>Olympia</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/olympia</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="nomisma_london">
                  <placeName>London</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://www.nomisma.org/id/london</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="nomisma_berlin">
                  <placeName>Berlin</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/berlin</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="geonames_2653941">
                  <placeName>Cambridge</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://www.geonames.org/2653941</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="geonames_2618425">
                  <placeName>Copenhagen</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://www.geonames.org/2618425</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="geonames_3176959">
                  <placeName>Florence</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://www.geonames.org/3176959</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="viaf_2867714">
                  <placeName>Munich</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://www.geonames.org/2867714</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="geonames_2640729">
                  <placeName>Oxford</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://www.geonames.org/2640729</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="nomisma_paris">
                  <placeName>Paris</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://www.nomisma.org/id/paris</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="geonames_2761367">
                  <placeName>Vienna</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://www.geonames.org/2761367</idno>
               </place>               
               <place xml:id="nomisma_boeotia">
                  <placeName>Boeotia</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/boeotia</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="nomisma_sicyon">
                  <placeName>Sicyon</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/sicyon</idno>
               </place>
            </listPlace>
         </settingDesc>           
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://nomisma.org/">
               <term ref="http://nomisma.org/id/greek_numismatics">Greek Numismatics</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2016-08-11">Ran TEI file through XSLT process, detailed in the Mellon EBook migration Google Document.</change>
         <change when="2016-08-31">Reprocessed: restructured TOC list into table; added HathiTrust URI; added funder</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <titlePage>
            <pb/>
            <docTitle>
               <titlePart type="main">THE <name type="pname">ALEXANDER</name> COINAGE OF <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_sicyon">Sicyon</name>
               </titlePart>
               <titlePart type="sub">ARRANGED FROM NOTES OF EDWARD <name type="pname">T. NEWELL</name> WITH COMMENTS AND ADDITIONS</titlePart>
            </docTitle>
            <byline>
BY <name type="pname">SYDNEY P. NOE</name>
            </byline>
            <figure xml:id="fig-1">
               <graphic url="NS6_001.jpg"/>
            </figure>
            <docImprint>
               <publisher>THE AMERICAN NUMISMATIC SOCIETY</publisher>
               <pubPlace>NEW YORK</pubPlace>
               <date>1950</date>
            </docImprint>
         </titlePage>
         <div1 xml:id="d1e65" type="copyright">
            <pb/>
            <p>COPYRIGHT, 1950</p>
            <p>THE AMERICAN NUMISMATIC SOCIETY</p>
            <p>
               <name type="place">NEW YORK</name>
            </p>
            <p>PRESS OF INTELLIGENCER PRINTING CO.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="place">LANCASTER,</name> PA.</p>
         </div1>
         <pb/>
         <div1 xml:id="d1e81" type="frontma">
            <head>FOREWORD</head>
            <p>It was <name type="pname">Mr. Newell's</name> definite intention to publish a complete survey of the coinage of <name type="pname" corresp="#nomisma_alexander_iii">Alexander</name> the Great. For years his research and studies were moving in that direction, and most of his published studies contributed toward the final picture. His way was ever to get all material together first; this he had largely done. With his notebooks, casts, data, and published works, there remains the possibility of carrying out his plan. So one can say today that his work, begun so long ago, required only his leisure to put it together. The American Numismatic Society has begun the task of putting together his material. The hope is to carry right on through the survey according to the outline given by <name type="pname">Mr. Newell</name>.</p>
            <p>In making a start, however, it seemed best to begin with a clear and easily defined issue such as <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_sicyon">Sicyon</name>. But this will in no way disturb the actual order of his plan. This city comes in what he planned as his second volume. Naturally one approaches this work with diffidence—a work which would have been so wonderfully carried out by <name type="pname">Mr. Newell</name>—but, with all this material available it would indeed be failing in duty to delay longer in carrying out his plans.</p>
            <p>The American Numismatic Society expresses its appreciation of <name type="pname">Mrs. E. T. Newell's</name> generosity in loaning casts and notebooks as well as for her helpful suggestions and advice. The task of putting together the data collected by <name type="pname">Mr. Newell</name> and of interpreting it has been performed by <name type="pname">Mr. Sydney P. Noe</name>. We are grateful for the eminently successful way in which he has accomplished this work.</p>
            <p>The scope of the task <name type="pname">Mr. Newell</name> set for himself and the means by which he proposed to attain it are best set forth in the words of a draft prepared by himself for its introduction.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d1e119" type="introduction">
            <pb n="4"/>
            <head>DRAFT OF AN INTRODUCTION TO A PROJECTED STUDY OF THE COINAGE OF <name type="pname">ALEXANDER</name> THE GREAT</head>
            <byline>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">By <name type="pname" corresp="#numismatics_newell">Edward T. Newell</name>
               </hi>
            </byline>
            <p>The term "Allexander Coinage" is both grammatically incorrect and partially inexact for the work of which the present volume is the first. The term has, however, after mature deliberation, been finally adopted because of its succinctness and because the great bulk of the coinage here treated does bear the name and types first introduced by the great <name type="place">Macedonian</name>. To grasp the true meaning of the coinage, especially in its later phases, there have been added associate coinages in all metals which were issued from time to time, though they may not bear types in any way connected with those of <name type="pname" corresp="#nomisma_alexander_iii">Alexander</name>. For it so happened that frequently after the latter's death, his successors struck the bulk of their coinage with his types but added to it, for various reasons, principally commercial, an additional coinage in gold, silver or copper bearing their own names and types. Or again, they would strike the bulk of their coinage in numeraries bearing their own types but added to this a smaller issue, say of gold staters, bearing the old <name type="pname" corresp="#nomisma_alexander_iii">Alexander</name> types. As all of these coins would be part of a single issue and would usually be signed by the same magistrates, it has been felt by the writer to be wrong to separate them merely in order to keep within the strict meaning of the chosen title. Furthermore, these various categories of types, in almost every instance, together formed a single coinage and it would completely destroy all coherence and appreciation of the extent, scope and purpose of these coinages to make a separation based upon whether they bore <name type="pname" corresp="#nomisma_alexander_iii">Alexander</name>'s types or not. Therefore, for instance, we should discuss the posthumous Philip coinage along with that of <name type="pname" corresp="#nomisma_alexander_iii">Alexander</name>, because these two coinages were obviously contemporaneous, were struck in the same mints and signed by the same magistrates. Though possibly issued for different purposes they were none-the-less part and parcel of one and the same coinage, and should therefore be treated together in any work which makes some attempt, however slight, at completeness.</p>
            <p>No apology is necessary for attempting once more to describe, elucidate and attribute the enormous coinage which bears the name and types of <name type="pname" corresp="#nomisma_alexander_iii">Alexander</name> of <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_macedon">Macedon</name>. Although this was done with great thoroughness by <name type="pname">Ludwig Müller</name> in 1855, so much new information and so many new varieties have come to light since then, that this would be reason enough to attempt the great task again. Especially is this the case as <name type="pname">Müller</name>, following the universally accepted theories of his times, believed that the majority of the symbols appearing on these coins should be explained as the <hi rend="italic">parasema</hi> of the issuing cities. That this theory was correct in numerous instances time has only proved the more. But time, the repeated observations of various students, the appearance and study of many coin
<pb n="5"/>
hoards has also proved beyond the peradventure of a doubt that the great bulk of monograms and symbols occurring throughout the <name type="pname" corresp="#nomisma_alexander_iii">Alexander</name> coinage could have little or nothing to do with the mints which actually issued it. This fact necessarily brings to nought <name type="pname">Müller's</name> laborious dispersion of the <name type="pname" corresp="#nomisma_alexander_iii">Alexander</name> coins to innumerable mints according to the locality to which a particular symbol would seem to point. Therefore, we can accept a monogram or symbol as being that of the issuing city only after due and carefully weighed consideration of the length of time it was used, the region whence our coins bearing this particular symbol usually come, the style and fabric of the coins themselves, and the inherent probabilities of each separate case. Only in this way can we reach a definite and acceptable conclusion. Where a symbol or monogram is obviously not that of a city, the writer has accepted the opposite conclusion that it is probably the signet of the responsible magistrate; whether this again is strictly true in every case is hardly susceptible of really definite proof. This is inherently probable, but the symbols might conceivably be at times neither more nor less than arbitrarily adopted signs by which various issues could be distinguished by those in authority. On the <name type="pname" corresp="#nomisma_alexander_iii">Alexander</name> coinage we seldom find the elaborate system employed by <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_athens">Athens</name> which, with its symbols and accompanying two or three magistrates names, makes it possible to show that these symbols belong to the principal one of these magistrates and therefore disappear from the coinage with his withdrawal from office. In the following pages, when the writer uses the term magistrate's symbol it should be considered as having been used in a general way (unless there is a distinct statement to the contrary) for the symbol which cannot be the <hi rend="italic">parase</hi>m<hi rend="italic">on</hi> (and therefore a mint-mark in the full term of the word) of the issuing city.</p>
            <p>Obviously the only scientific method to pursue which had any hope of tangible results was a work based upon a careful study and comparison of dies. An initial essay in this field was made by the writer in 1912 in his <hi rend="italic">Reattribution,</hi> where he was able to show that a study of dies proved the fallacy of <name type="pname">Müller's</name> system for the bulk of the <name type="pname" corresp="#nomisma_alexander_iii">Alexander</name> coinage. Later, similar though more advanced studies were made of the <name type="pname">Alexandrine</name> issues of <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_sidon">Sidon</name>, <name type="place">Ake</name>, <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_tyre">Tyre</name>, <name type="place" corresp="#pleiades_658541">Myriandos</name>, <name type="place" corresp="#geonames_739598">Sinope</name> and <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_cyprus">Cyprus</name>. The reception accorded these initial attempts at even a partial solution of the "<name type="pname" corresp="#nomisma_alexander_iii">Alexander</name> question," has encouraged the writer to gird himself for the Herculean task of sorting, studying and attributing the <name type="pname" corresp="#nomisma_alexander_iii">Alexander</name> coinage as a whole. The writer is aware of the many shortcomings which such a work will inevitably present. He has undertaken the colossal task both because a beginning must some time be made, and because he hopes that by his labors at least a little order will have been brought out of chaos. It will then be easier for future students not only to recognize mistakes but to rectify them and to attempt a more complete solution of the many problems presented.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d1e230" type="contents">
            <pb/>
            <head>CONTENTS</head>
            <table>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">Introduction</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>9</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">The Catalogue</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>11</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">Notes to the Catalogue</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>25</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Group I</cell>
                  <cell>25</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Group II</cell>
                  <cell>26</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Group III</cell>
                  <cell>28</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Group IV</cell>
                  <cell>30</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">The <name type="place">Sicyon Hoards</name>
                     </hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>34</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">The</hi>
                     <name type="place">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Sicyon</hi>
                     </name>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">Symbols</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>37</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">Conclusion</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>37</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">Index of Symbols</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>39</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">Index of Letters and Monograms</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>41</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
         </div1>
      </front>
      <body>
         <pb/>
         <div1 xml:id="d1e302" type="chapter">
            <head>INTRODUCTION</head>
            <p>When the collection bequeathed to The American Numismatic Society by Mr. <name type="pname" corresp="#numismatics_newell">Edward T. Newell</name> was received, it was well known that the mintages of <name type="pname">Alexander the Great</name> had received the preponderance of his attention. It is doubtful, however, that anyone had a realization of the thoroughness with which he had pursued the objective he had set himself. The representation of the coins of <name type="pname">Alexander the Great</name> in his cabinet excels any elsewhere, for it comprises not only thousands of <name type="pname">Alexander's</name> coins but casts of unique pieces of all of the great national cabinets and most of the private collections of importance. Even more impressive than the mass of the data was the order in which it had been kept. The purpose of this orderliness is made clear in the general introduction which precedes. This introduction is one of at least two drafts made by <name type="pname">Mr. Newell</name>. It is possible to date the earlier one as having been made sometime after the publication of his "<name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_sidon">Sidon</name> and <name type="place">Ake</name>"—that is, 1915. This one may be dated about 1923 since it mentions having published the study of the coinage of <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_tyre">Tyre</name> (1923). Although this introduction was written not long after 1923, it requires but little thought to understand why the work upon this self-imposed task had never been started. In 1927, the volume on the coins of <name type="pname">Demetrius Poliorcetes</name> appeared. This was not a step aside, for the issues of <name type="pname">Demetrius</name> are invaluable for dating the <name type="pname" corresp="#nomisma_alexander_iii">Alexander</name> types which they supersede. Many of the monographs which followed and which were produced with such ease and fluency have further direct or indirect bearing on the <name type="pname" corresp="#nomisma_alexander_iii">Alexander</name> problems toward which he was consistently working. The volume on the <hi rend="italic">Eastern <name type="place" corresp="#pleiades_45635759">Seleucid Mints</name>
               </hi> which appeared in 1938, to be followed in 1941 by the <hi rend="italic">Western <name type="place" corresp="#pleiades_45635759">Seleucid Mints</name>
               </hi> had the same sort of relationship to the <name type="pname" corresp="#nomisma_alexander_iii">Alexander</name> coinage as did that of <name type="pname">Demetrius Poliorcetes</name>, and were a further preparation for the plan outlined in the introduction. This became more and more evident from his notes although they are in a sort of "shorthand" of his own. Study has made it possible to follow them with some degree of precision.</p>
            <p>The choice of <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_sicyon">Sicyon</name> as the first city to receive attention was dictated by several considerations—one, that the mint output was not very large; two, that its coinage was well represented in <name type="pname">Mr. Newell's</name> Collection and, three, that his notes offered few complications notwithstanding the fact that they had not been revised since 1936, at which time the <name type="pname">Armenak Hoard</name> coins were acquired by him—a hoard which contained coins of <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_sicyon">Sicyon</name> which he did not add to his notes. <name type="place">Sicyon'</name>s coinage began during <name type="pname">Alexander's</name> lifetime, extended beyond the year at which most of <name type="pname">Mr. Newell's</name> publications stop (280) and may have continued to 251 B. C. when <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_sicyon">Sicyon</name> joined the <name type="place">Achaean League</name>. Of the mints treated by him, only <name type="place" corresp="#geonames_739598">Sinope</name> extends beyond 280, although <name type="place">Seleucid</name> issues for <name type="place">Alexandreia Troas</name> and <name type="place">Pergamum</name> provide minor exceptions. Since no one would have had the courage to undertake
<pb n="10"/>
the entire problem broached in <name type="pname">Mr. Newell's</name> introduction, the choice of <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_sicyon">Sicyon</name> offered the most logical beginning.</p>
            <p>Fortunately for us, there had been occasion to touch upon the coinage of <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_sicyon">Sicyon</name> in <name type="pname">Mr. Newell's</name> published works. The monograph devoted to the <name type="place">Demanhur Hoard</name> indicates that publication of the <name type="place">Sicyonian</name>
               <name type="pname">Alexanders</name> was intended;<ref target="#CH1-n1">1</ref> that on the <name type="place">Olympia Hoard</name>
               <ref target="#CH1-n2">2</ref> illustrates new symbols possibly not <name type="place">Sicyonian</name>, while valuable data are to be found in the volume on the coinage of <name type="pname">Demetrius Poliorcetes</name>,<ref target="#CH1-n3">3</ref> especially for dating. Notwithstanding all these aids, there are times when it is clear that a decision has been postponed until further facts were obtained. In discussing the pieces in the <name type="place">Olympia Hoard</name>, <name type="pname">Mr. Newell</name> noted that this hoard showed "in how incomplete a manner the <name type="place">Peloponnesian</name>
               <name type="pname" corresp="#nomisma_alexander_iii">Alexander</name> series has come down to us."</p>
            <p>Discussion which would retard publication has been avoided, but references to such discussion by others, when known, are given in the notes which follow the catalogue. These notes are the work of the compiler and are not to be understood as statements of <name type="pname">Mr. Newell</name>.</p>
            <p>Acknowledgment is gratefully made to the many institutions which have generously furnished casts of their <name type="place">Sicyonian</name>
               <name type="pname">Alexanders</name> as well as to the individuals mentioned in the catalogue.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_new_york_city">New York City</name>
                  <date when="1950-01-04">January 4, 1950.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">
                     <name type="pname" corresp="#numismatics_noe">Sydney P. Noe</name>
                  </hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n1">
               <seg type="note-symbol">1</seg>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="pname">Alexander Hoards</name>
                  </hi> —<hi rend="italic">II</hi>. <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="place">Demanhur</name>
                  </hi> (Num. Notes &amp; Monogr. No. 19). p. 76. Hereafter cited <hi rend="italic">as <name type="place">Demanhur.</name>
                  </hi>
               </p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n2">
               <seg type="note-symbol">2</seg>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="pname" corresp="#nomisma_alexander_iii">Alexander</name> Hoards— <hi rend="italic">IV</hi>. <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_olympia">Olympia</name>
                  </hi> (Num. Notes <hi rend="italic">&amp;</hi> Monogr. No. 39). Plate III. Hereafter cited as <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_olympia">Olympia</name>.</hi>
               </p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n3">
               <seg type="note-symbol">3</seg>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">The Coinages of <name type="pname">Demetrius Poliorcetes</name>
                  </hi> (<name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_london">London</name>, 1927). Hereafter cited as <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="pname">Demetrius</name>
                  </hi>.</p>
            </note>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d1e536" type="chapter">
            <pb/>
            <head>CATALOGUE</head>
            <p>Brevity is the aim in the descriptions which follow; unnecessary repetitions are eliminated. Since each variety is illustrated, the catalogue will be consulted chiefly for the locations and weights of the specimens recorded. Because the dies were not fixed, die-positions have not been given.</p>
            <p>A number has been given to each of the varieties and this number is printed at the beginning of the description of that variety. Thereunder are listed the die-combinations known and each combination is given a number following the decimal point. For example, the first tetradrachm (No. 3) has eight die-combinations— the last of these is therefore numbered 3.8. In the next column, the anvil and punch dies are given numbers preceded by A and P. For this first tetradrachmissue there are four anvil and seven punch dies. Two of the anvil dies carry over to the tetradrachm No. 4. On the plates, such die-combinations are indicated at the bottom of the page. Where the anvil die is connected with more than one reverse die, this is shown by placing a line <hi rend="italic">above</hi> the numbers involved <graphic url="NS6_009a.jpg"/> thus repeating what is shown in the second column of the catalogue. When the combination is one of reverse dies, the connecting line is placed <hi rend="italic">below</hi> the numbers involved <graphic url="NS6_009b.jpg"/>.</p>
            <p>The next column of the catalogue gives the name of the collection from which the piece has come. Here we have used the abbreviations which served in the monograph <hi rend="italic">Kolophon and Its Coinage</hi> (Num. Notes &amp; Monogr. No. 96) by Prof. J. G. Milne. Generally these consist of the initial letter of the city in which the respective cabinet is located. Pieces in the Society's own cabinet are cited as ANS. Those owned by <name type="pname">Mr. Newell</name>, ANS–ETN, with addition of GDAM to indicate the former ownership of the Grand Duke <name type="pname" corresp="#nomisma_alexander_iii">Alexander</name> Michailovitch. Pieces from the collection of Sir <name type="pname" corresp="#viaf_65453680">Ronald Storrs</name>, acquired in large part by the American Numismatic Society in 1947, are abbreviated ANS-Storrs. The chief abbreviations other than these are as follows:</p>
            <list>
               <item>A. <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_athens">Athens</name>
               </item>
               <item>B. <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_berlin">Berlin</name>
               </item>
               <item>C. <name type="place" corresp="#geonames_2653941">Cambridge</name>
               </item>
               <item>Cop. <name type="place" corresp="#geonames_2618425">Copenhagen</name>
               </item>
               <item>F. <name type="place" corresp="#geonames_3176959">Florence</name>
               </item>
               <item>L. <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_london">London</name>
               </item>
               <item>M. <name type="place" corresp="#viaf_2867714">Munich</name>
               </item>
               <item>O. <name type="place" corresp="#geonames_2640729">Oxford</name>
               </item>
               <item>P. <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_paris">Paris</name>;</item>
               <item>V. <name type="place" corresp="#geonames_2761367">Vienna</name>
               </item>
            </list>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e610" type="section">
               <pb n="12"/>
               <head>GROUP I.</head>
               <p>330/25 to <hi rend="italic">c.</hi> 318 B.C.</p>
               <p>1. DISTATER. <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q37122">Athena</name> head to r. wearing crested Corinthian helmet with coiled serpent decoration.</p>
               <p>AΛEΞANΔPOY on r. <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q165023">Nike</name> standing, facing 1., holding <hi rend="italic">stylis</hi> in 1., and wreath in outstretched r. In 1. field, youthful figure with outstretched r. arm, facing 1.</p>
               <table rows="2" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">1.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Al–Pl</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a.</hi> ANS.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.20</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> B. (Prokesch-Östen, <hi rend="italic">Num. Zeit,</hi> Vol. 3, 1871, p. 55, No. 1.)</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>2. STATER Similar to No. 1.</p>
               <p>Similar to No. 1.</p>
               <table rows="3" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">2.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A2–P2</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a.</hi> ANS-ETN.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 8.60</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> L.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 8.59</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">c.</hi> B. (Prokesch-Östen, <hi rend="italic">Inedita,</hi> 1859, No. 18; <hi rend="italic">Nu</hi>m.<hi rend="italic">. Zeit.,</hi> Vol. 3, 1871, p. 55, No. 2.)</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>3. TETRADRACHM. Head of <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q122248">Heracles</name> to r. wearing lion's skin. Circle of dots.</p>
               <p>AΛEΞANAPOY on r. <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q34201">Zeus</name> enthroned to 1., resting 1. hand on sceptre and holding eagle in outstretched r. In 1. field, youthful figure similar to that on Nos. 1 and 2.</p>
               <table rows="10" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">3.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A3–P3</cell>
                     <cell>ANS-ETN.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.15</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">3.2</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A4–P4 ANS-ETN (<name type="place">Demanhur Hoard</name>).</cell>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>gr. 17.55</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">3.3</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P5</cell>
                     <cell>ANS-ETN.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.70</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">3.4</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P6</cell>
                     <cell>ANS-ETN (<name type="place">Demanhur Hoard</name>).</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.30</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">8.8</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P7</cell>
                     <cell>ANS-ETN (<name type="place">Demanhur Hoard</name>).</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.15</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">8.6</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P8</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <name type="pname">Dattari</name> Coll., <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_cairo">Cairo</name> (<name type="place">Demanhur Hoard ?</name>).</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.11</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">3.7</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A5–P8</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a.</hi> ANS-ETN (<name type="place">Demanhur Hoard</name>).</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.15</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b.</hi>
                        <name type="pname">Naville I</name>, 1921 (Pozzi), 901, ex <name type="pname">Egger XL</name>, May 1912, 634.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.24</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">3.8</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A6–P9</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a.</hi> ANS-ETN (<name type="place">Demanhur Hoard</name>).</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.14</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> ANS-Storrs (probably <name type="place">Demanhur Hoard</name>).</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.23</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>4. TETRADRACHM. Similar to No. 3.</p>
               <p>Youthful figure as on No. 3, but with addition of rudder beneath throne.</p>
               <table rows="2" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">4.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A5–P10</cell>
                     <cell>ANS-ETN.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.05</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">4.2</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A6–P11</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <name type="pname">C. Fitzwilliam</name> Museum (Syll., IV, 3, 2137).</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.17</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>5. STATER. (<name type="pname">Müller</name> No6. 640)) Similiar to No. 2.</p>
               <p>Youthful figure as on No. 2, but with rudder beneath r. wing of <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q165023">Nike</name>.</p>
               <table rows="2" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">5.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A7–P12</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a.</hi> L.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 8.58</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> ANS-ETN.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 8.55</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <pb n="13"/>
               <p>6. DISTATER. (<name type="pname">Müller</name> No. 4.) Similar to No. 1.</p>
               <p>Similar to No. 1, but with vertical ful-men in 1. field and A beneath wing.</p>
               <table rows="4" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">6.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A8–P13</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a.</hi> ANS-ETN, ex <name type="pname">Naville XIII</name>, 494.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>ex <name type="pname">Ratto</name>, June 1929, 247.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.20</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> Glasgow, Hunter, Vol. I, p. 296, No. 4.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.17</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">c.</hi>
                        <name type="pname">Hirsch XXI</name>, 1210.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.14</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>7. DISTATER. (<name type="pname">Müller</name> No. 5.) Similar to No. 1.</p>
               <p>Fulmen as on No. 6 but with <graphic url="NS6_sym1.jpg"/> beneath wing.</p>
               <table rows="18" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">7.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A8–Pl4</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <name type="pname">C. Leake</name> (Syll., IV, 3, 2093).</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.13</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">7.2</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P15</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <name type="pname">A. Saroglos</name>, ex <name type="pname">Egger XXXIX</name>, Jan. 1912, 254; ex <name type="pname">Egger XLV</name>, Nov. 1913, 485.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.20</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">7.3</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P16</cell>
                     <cell>Commerce—Platt Fixed Price Cat., Coll. A, 159.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">7.4</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A9–17</cell>
                     <cell>A. ex(?) <name type="pname">Naville XIV</name>, 198 and <name type="pname">Ratto</name>, Apr. 1927, 566.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.21</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">7.5</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A10–P18</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <name type="pname">Turin</name>.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.12</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">7.6</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A11–P 19</cell>
                     <cell>ANS-EXN.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.20</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">7.7</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A12–P20</cell>
                     <cell>The Hague.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">7.8</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P21</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <name type="pname">Naville XIII</name>, 1928, 495.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.19</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">7.9</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A13–P22</cell>
                     <cell>L.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.10</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">7.10</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P23</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <name type="pname">Hirsch XVI</name>, 375.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.17</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">7.11</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P24</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <name type="pname">Hirsch XXIX</name> (<name type="pname">Lambros</name>), 242.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.12</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">7.12</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P25</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <name type="pname">Arthur J. Fecht</name> Coll., ex <name type="pname">Sotheby</name>, June 1911 (<name type="pname">Sandeman</name>), 101.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.23</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">7.13</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P20</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <name type="pname">Egger XLI</name>, Nov. 1912, 377.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.18</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">7.14</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P26</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a</hi>. <name type="pname">Hirsch XXIX</name> (<name type="pname">Lambros</name>), 243.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.17</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b.</hi>
                        <name type="place" corresp="#geonames_2618425">Copenhagen</name>, Sylloge (<name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_macedon">Macedon</name>), 623.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.19</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">7.15</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P27</cell>
                     <cell>Commerce.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">7.16</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P28</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <name type="pname">Naville VI</name> (Bement), 705.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.18</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">7.17</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P29</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <name type="pname">C. Fitzwilliam Museum</name> (Syll., IV, 3, 2092 = <name type="pname">Naville V</name>, 1923, 1385).</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.20</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>8. STATER. Similar to No. 2.</p>
               <p>Similar to No. 7.</p>
               <table rows="1" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">8.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A14–P30</cell>
                     <cell>ANS-ETN.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 8.60</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>9. DISTATER. (<name type="pname">Müller</name> No. 639). similar to No. 1.</p>
               <p>Similar to No. 7, but in 1. held, youth-ful figure with both arms raised, and <graphic url="NS6_sym1.jpg"/> beneath wing of <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q165023">Nike</name>.</p>
               <table rows="5" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">9.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A15–P31</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a.</hi>
                        <name type="pname">A. Saroglos</name>.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b.</hi>
                        <name type="pname">Cotha</name>.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">c.</hi>
                        <name type="pname">Egger XXXIX</name>, Jan. 1912, 257.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.20</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">d.</hi> B.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">9.2</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P32</cell>
                     <cell>ANS-ETN.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.20</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>10. DISTATER. Similar to No. 9.</p>
               <p>Youthful figure as on No. 9, but with olive leaf in r. field.</p>
               <table rows="1" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">10.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Al5–P33</cell>
                     <cell>Coll. Prof. <name type="pname">Dr. M. Ros, Zurich</name>, cf. <hi rend="italic">
                           <name type="pname">Rev.Suisse</name>,</hi> XXX, 1943, p. 21</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.43</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>11. STATER. (<name type="pname">Müller</name> No. 639b). Similar to No. 9.</p>
               <p>Youthful figure as on No. 9.</p>
               <table rows="2" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">11.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>Al6–P34</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a</hi>. ANS-ETN, ex <name type="pname">Sandeman</name> Sale, <name type="pname">Sotheby</name>, June 1911, 113.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 8.60</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> L., ex Bunbury Sale, <name type="pname">Sotheby</name>, June 1896, 727; ex O'Hagan Sale, <name type="pname">Sotheby</name>, May 1908, 308.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 8.57</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <pb n="14"/>
               <p>12. STATER. (<name type="pname">Müller</name>No. 638). Similar to No. 2.</p>
               <p>Similar to No. 11, but without monogram.</p>
               <table rows="1" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">12.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A17–P35</cell>
                     <cell>L.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 8.57</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>13. TETRADRACHM. <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q122248">Heracles</name> head with slight differences from foregoing issues.</p>
               <p>Similar to No. 3, but youthful figure has small die-break beneath out-stretched arms.</p>
               <table rows="5" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">13.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A18–P36</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a.</hi> ANS-Storrs.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.23</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> ANS-ETN. (Pl. III)</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.14</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">c.</hi> ANS-ETN.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.01</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">13.2</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A19–P36</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a.</hi>
                        <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_cairo">Cairo</name>. <name type="pname">Dattari</name>.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> ANS-ETN.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.01</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>14. TETRADRACHM. (<name type="pname">Müller</name> No. 637). Similar to No. 13.</p>
               <p>Similar to No. 13.</p>
               <table rows="11" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">14.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A20–P37</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a.</hi> Cat. <name type="pname">H. Weber</name>, No. 2096.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.17</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b.</hi>
                        <name type="pname">O. Davidson</name>.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.90</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">14.2</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A21–P38</cell>
                     <cell>L. (Possibly = A 19)</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.73</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">14.3</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A22–P39</cell>
                     <cell>ANS-ETN, ex <name type="pname">Egger XL</name>, May 1912, 635.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.18</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">14.4</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P40</cell>
                     <cell>ANS-ETN (small segment removed).</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.57</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">14.5</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P41</cell>
                     <cell>Formerly Sir <name type="pname">R. Storrs</name> Collection.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">14.4</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P40</cell>
                     <cell>ANS-ETN (<name type="pname">Haynes' Babylon Hoard</name>.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.57</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">14.5</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P41</cell>
                     <cell>Formerly Sir <name type="pname">R. Storrs</name> Collection.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">14.6</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P42</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a.</hi>ANS-ETN (<name type="pname">Haynes' Babylon Hoard</name>).</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.51</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> B.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">c</hi>. A. (<name type="pname">Epidauuss Hoard</name>, <hi rend="italic">Eph. Arch.,</hi> 1903.) Pl. VII, 2.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.75</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">14.7</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A23–P42</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a.</hi> ANS-ET IN (<name type="place">Demanhur Hoard</name>).</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.14</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b</hi>. P.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>15. TETRADRACHM. (Mülller No. 567). Die of No. 14.7.</p>
               <p>In 1. field, a barley ear. Differences in form of throne.</p>
               <table rows="3" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">15.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A23–P43</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a.</hi> ANS-ETN.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.23</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> ANS-ETN.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.22</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">c.</hi> ANS-ETN.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.90</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>16. TETRADRACHM. Die of Nos. 14.7 and 15.</p>
               <p>In I. field, a goat s head to 1. Eagle is facing.</p>
               <table rows="4" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">16.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A23–P44</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a.</hi> ANS-ETN.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.16</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> B. (Prokesch-Östen, Num. <hi rend="italic">Zeit.</hi> Vol. 1, 1869, p. 37, No. 71.)</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">c.</hi> B.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">d.</hi> ANS-ETN.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.07</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e1671" type="section">
               <pb n="15"/>
               <head>GROUP I.</head>
               <p>17. TETRADRACHM. (Müller No. 409). Head of young <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q122248">Heracles</name> to r. wearing lion's skin. Circle of dots.</p>
               <p>BAΣIΛEΩΣ in exergue and AΛEΞANΔPOY on r. <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q34201">Zeus</name> enthroned to 1., resting 1. hand on sceptre and holding eagle in outstretched r. In 1. field, star. Beneath throne, <graphic url="NS6_sym2.jpg"/>. Back of throne visible. Cf. also Pl. XIII, A.</p>
               <table rows="5" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">17.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A24–P45</cell>
                     <cell>P.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">17.2</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A25–P46</cell>
                     <cell>ANS-ETN.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.57</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">17.3</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A26–P47</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <name type="pname">Mrs. Edward T. Newel</name>.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.57</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">17.4</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A27–P48</cell>
                     <cell>Petsalis Coll.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">17.5</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P49</cell>
                     <cell>ANS-Storrs.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.39</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>18. TETRADRACHM. Similar to No. 17.</p>
               <p>Similar to No. 17; below star in 1. field, monogram, <graphic url="NS6_sym3.jpg"/>. Beneath throne <graphic url="NS6_sym4.jpg"/> or <graphic url="NS6_sym5.jpg"/>.</p>
               <table rows="3" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">18.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A28–P50</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <name type="pname">A. Saroglos</name>.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">18.2</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P51</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a.</hi> ANIS-ETN.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.08</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> ANS-Storrs.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.08</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>19. TETRADRACHM. Similar to No. 17.</p>
               <p>In 1. field, wreath enclosing dove. Between struts of throne, Δ and cornucopiae. The feet of <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q34201">Zeus</name> rest on tiny footstool.</p>
               <table rows="2" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">19.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A29–P52</cell>
                     <cell>B.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>20. TETRADRACHM. Similar to No. 17.</p>
               <p>In 1. field, wreath. Beneath throne, Δ.</p>
               <table rows="3" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">20.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A30–P53</cell>
                     <cell>P.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">20.2</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A31–P53</cell>
                     <cell>Gotha.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">20.3</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A32–P54</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <name type="pname">A. Saroglos</name>.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>21. TETRADRACHM. Similar to No. 17.</p>
               <p>Similar to No. 20, but without BAΣΛEΩΣ in exergue.</p>
               <table rows="2" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">21.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A33–P55</cell>
                     <cell>ANS-ETN.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.13</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">21.2</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P56</cell>
                     <cell>ANS-Storrs.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.09</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>22. TETRADRACHM. (Müller No. 1348). Similar to No. 17.</p>
               <p>In 1. field, <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q165023">Nike</name> r., extending laurel wreath. Above struts of throne <graphic url="NS6_sym5.jpg"/>.</p>
               <table rows="12" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">22.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A34–P57</cell>
                     <cell>L.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.04</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">22.2</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P58</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a.</hi> A.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> Cop. Syll. (Maced)., 734.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.12</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">22.3</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A35–P59</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a.</hi> P.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> V.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.3S</cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb n="16"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">22.4</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A36–P58</cell>
                     <cell>ANS-ETN.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.06</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">22.5</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A37–58</cell>
                     <cell>A.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">22.6</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A38–60</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a</hi>. ANS-ETN.</cell>
                     <cell>16.90</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b</hi>.ANS-ETN.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.67</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">22.7</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P61</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a.</hi>
                        <name type="pname">A. Saroglos</name>.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b</hi>. B.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">22.8</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A39–P62</cell>
                     <cell>B.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>23. TETRADRACHM. Similar to No. 17.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q165023">Nike</name> as on No. 22. Beneath throne NO.</p>
               <table rows="10" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">23.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A40–P63</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a.</hi> P.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> ANS-ETN.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.66</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">c.</hi> Spink, 1921-2.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">23.2</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A41–P64</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a.</hi>
                        <name type="pname">A. Saroglos</name>.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>b. ANS-ETN.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.78</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">c</hi>. <name type="pname">F. Mus. Arch</name>.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">23.3</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P65</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a</hi>. ANS-ETN, ex GDAM.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.16</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> B.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">23.4</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A42–P66</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a.</hi> B.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> A. (Epidaurus Hoard.)</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.68</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>24. TETRADRACHM. (<name type="pname">Müller</name> No. 864). Similar to No. 17.</p>
               <p>In 1. field, chimaera r. Beneath throne, NO.</p>
               <table rows="14" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">24.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A42–P67</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a.</hi> ANS-ETN.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.86</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> ANS.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.10</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">24.2</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P68</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a.</hi>
                        <name type="pname">A. Saroglos</name>.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> M.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.37</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">c.</hi>
                        <name type="pname">Sofia</name>.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.75</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">24.3</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A41–P67</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <name type="pname">B.Y. Berry</name> Coll.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">24.4</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P68</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a.</hi> ANS-ETN.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.01</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> P. De Luynes, INo. 1646.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.91</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">24.5</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P69</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a.</hi> A.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> ANS-ETN (<name type="pname">Armenak Hoard</name>).</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.07</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">24.6</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P70</cell>
                     <cell>ANS-ETN, ex GDAM.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.81</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">24.7</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P71</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a.</hi> B.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> B.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">24.8</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P72</cell>
                     <cell>L.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.92</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>25. TETRADRACHM. (<name type="pname">Müller</name> No. 865). Similar to No. 17.</p>
               <p>Chimaera as in No. 24. Beneath throne, <graphic url="NS6_sym6.jpg"/>.</p>
               <table rows="9" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">25.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A41–P73</cell>
                     <cell>ANS-Sotorrs.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.82</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">25.2</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P74</cell>
                     <cell>B.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">25.3</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P75</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a.</hi> ANS-ETN.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.99</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> B.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">25.4</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P76</cell>
                     <cell>Cop. Syll. (Maced.), 730.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.16</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">25.5</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A43–P77</cell>
                     <cell>A. Soaroglos.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">25.6</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P78</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a.</hi> ANS-ETN.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.93</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> A.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">25.7</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P79</cell>
                     <cell>ANS-ETN. (Possibly = P74.)</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.07</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>26. TETRADRACHM. (<name type="pname">Müller</name> No. 875). Similar to No. 17.</p>
               <p>In 1. field, Elpis 1. Beneath throne, NO.</p>
               <pb n="17"/>
               <table rows="15" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">26.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A44–P80</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <name type="pname">C. McClean</name>, 3442.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.97</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">26.2</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A45–P81</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <name type="pname">Egger XL</name>, May 1912, 650.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.78</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">26.3</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P80</cell>
                     <cell>A. (Sparta Hoard.)</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.25</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">26.4</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A46–P82</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a.</hi> B.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> Boston. Warren 655.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.14</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">26.5</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A47–P83</cell>
                     <cell>ANS-ETN.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.09</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">26.6</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A48–P84</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <name type="pname">Mrs. Kdward T. Newell</name>.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">26.7</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A49–P85</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <name type="pname">A. Saroglos</name>.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">26.8</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P86</cell>
                     <cell>B.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">26.9</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A50–P87</cell>
                     <cell>ANS-ETN, ex GDAM.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.12</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">26.10</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A51–P82</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a</hi>. M</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b</hi>. ANS. (Chisel-marked.)</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.98</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">26.11</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A52–P88</cell>
                     <cell>L.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.13</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">26.12</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A53–P89</cell>
                     <cell>ANS-ETN ( = Bunbury Sale, <name type="pname">Sotheby</name>, June 1896, 765 = O'Hagan Sale, <name type="pname">Sotheby</name>, May 1908, 313).</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.14</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">26.13</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A54–P90</cell>
                     <cell>ANS-ETN (<name type="pname">Armenak Hoard</name>).</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.05</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>27. TETRADRACHM. Similar to No. 17.</p>
               <p>In l. field, <name type="pname">Heracles r.</name>, leaning on club. Beneath throne, <graphic url="NS6_sym7.jpg"/> I.</p>
               <table rows="2" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">27.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A47–P91</cell>
                     <cell>L. <hi rend="italic">Num. Chron.,</hi> 1900, Pl. XIII, 6 = <name type="pname">Sotheby</name> 1900 (Late CoII.), 208.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">27.2</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A55–P92</cell>
                     <cell>ANS-ETN = Bunbury Sale, <name type="pname">Sotheby</name>, June 1896, 766 (2). (Cf. <hi rend="italic">Num. Chroti.,</hi> 1883, p. 7).</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.12</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e2568" type="section">
               <head>GROUP III</head>
               <p>28. TETRADRACHM. Similar to No. 17.</p>
               <p>In 1. field, aphlaston; beneath throne, NO.</p>
               <table rows="5" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">28.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A56–P93</cell>
                     <cell>ANS-ETN.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.77</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">28.2</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A57–P94</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a.</hi>
                        <name type="pname">V. Hollschek</name>.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.69</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> Milan.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">28.3</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P95</cell>
                     <cell>B.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">28.4</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P96</cell>
                     <cell>ANS-ETN (<name type="pname">Armenak Hoard</name>).</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.11</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>29. TETRADRACHM. Similar to No. 17.</p>
               <p>As on No. 28. Beneath throne, ΔO.</p>
               <table rows="8" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">29.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A57–P97</cell>
                     <cell>ANS-ETN (<name type="pname">Armenak Hoard</name>).</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.12</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">29.2</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P98</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a.</hi>
                        <name type="pname">A. Saroglos</name> 222.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> M.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">29.3</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P99</cell>
                     <cell>L.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.02</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">29.4</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A58–P100</cell>
                     <cell>M.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">29.5</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A59–P101</cell>
                     <cell>ANS-ETN (<name type="pname">Armenak Hoard</name>).</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.13</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">29.6</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P102</cell>
                     <cell>B.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">29.7</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A60–Pl03</cell>
                     <cell>B.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>30. TETRADRACHM. (<name type="pname">Müller</name> Nos. 889 and 890). Similar to No. 17.</p>
               <p>As on No. 28. Beneath throne, ΔE. Except on Nos. 30.1, 30.2, 30.8 and 30.9, there are small Nikes on back of throne. BA∑IΔEΩ∑ in exergue, except on P111–112.</p>
               <pb n="18"/>
               <table rows="10" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">30.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A57–P104</cell>
                     <cell>B. (No Nikes.)</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">30.2</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P105</cell>
                     <cell>Cop. Syll. (Maced. 732). (No Nikes.)</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.81</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">30.3</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A61–P106</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a.</hi> AND-ETN (<name type="pname">Armenak Hoard</name>).</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.10</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> B.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">30.4</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A62–P107</cell>
                     <cell>A.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">30.5</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P108</cell>
                     <cell>B.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">30.6</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P109</cell>
                     <cell>ANS-ETN (Serbian Hoard).</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.93</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">30.7</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A61–P110</cell>
                     <cell>ANS-Storrs.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.59</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">30.8</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A63–P111</cell>
                     <cell>ANS-ETN (<name type="pname">Armenak Hoard</name>). (No Nikes.)</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.17</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">30.9</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P112</cell>
                     <cell>M. (No Nikes.)</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.88</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>31. TETRADRACHM. (<name type="pname">Müller</name> No. 888). Similar to No. 17.</p>
               <p>As on No. 28. Beneath throne, HP or <graphic url="NS6_sym6.jpg"/>. BA∑IΔEΩ∑ in exergue.</p>
               <table rows="4" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">31.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A63–P113</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a.</hi> B.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> Leningrad, Hermitage.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">31.2</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P114</cell>
                     <cell>ANS-ETN.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.97</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">31.3</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A64–P115</cell>
                     <cell>M.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.12</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>32. TETRADRACHM. (<name type="pname">Müller</name> No. 892). Similar to No. 17.</p>
               <p>In 1. field, amphora. Beneath throne, ΔE.</p>
               <table rows="4" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">32.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A61–P116</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a.</hi> Leningrad, Hermitage.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> V.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.73</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">32.2</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P117</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a.</hi> ANS-ETN.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.12</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b.</hi>
                        <name type="pname">Sofia</name>.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 15.80</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>33. TETRADRACHM. Similar to No. 17.</p>
               <p>In 1. field, horse's head 1.</p>
               <table rows="1" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">33.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A65–Pll8</cell>
                     <cell>ANS-ETN.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.38</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>34. TETRADRACHM. (<name type="pname">Müller</name> No. 891). Similar to No. 17.</p>
               <p>Horse's head as on No. 33. Beneath throne, ΔE.</p>
               <table rows="10" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">34.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A65–P119</cell>
                     <cell>ANS-Storrs.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.59</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">34.2</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P120</cell>
                     <cell>ANS-ETN, ex GDAM.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.05</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">34.3</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P121</cell>
                     <cell>M.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.13</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">34.4</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A66–P119</cell>
                     <cell>ANS-ETN.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.90</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">34.5</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P122</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a.</hi> Leningrad, Hermitage.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> L.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.98</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">34.6</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P120</cell>
                     <cell>A. (Epidaurus Hoard, <hi rend="italic">Eph. Arch.,</hi> 1903, Pl. VII, 6.)</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.63</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">34.7</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A67–P119</cell>
                     <cell>Empedocles Coll.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">34.8</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P123</cell>
                     <cell>B.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">34.9</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A68–P122</cell>
                     <cell>B.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>35. TETRADRACHM. (<name type="pname">Müller</name> No. 877). Similar to No. 17.</p>
               <p>In 1. field, cornucopiae. Beneath throne NO.</p>
               <table rows="20" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">35.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A65-Pl24</cell>
                     <cell>Formerly Sir <name type="pname">R. Storrs</name> Coll.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">35.2</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A66–P125</cell>
                     <cell>B.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">35.3</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P126</cell>
                     <cell>A.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">35.4</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A68–P127</cell>
                     <cell>ANS-ETYN.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.04</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">35.5</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P128</cell>
                     <cell>B. (No Nikes on throne.)</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.04</cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb n="19"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">35.6</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A69–P129</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a.</hi> Leningrad, Hermitage.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> ALS-ETN (<name type="pname">Armenak Hoard</name>).</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.20</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">35.7</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A70– P130</cell>
                     <cell>P.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">35.8</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P131</cell>
                     <cell>ANS-Storrs.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.73</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">35.9</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A71–Pl32</cell>
                     <cell>Yakountchikov Coll.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.10</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">35.10</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P129</cell>
                     <cell>ANS-ETN.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.97</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">35.11</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P133</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <name type="pname">A. Saroglos</name> Coll.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">35.12</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P134</cell>
                     <cell>M.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.50</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">35.13</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A72-135</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a.</hi>
                        <name type="pname">C. McClean</name> Coll., Pl. 127, 11</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.07</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> B.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">35.14</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A73–P136</cell>
                     <cell>A. (Kpidaurus Hoard.)</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.99</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">35.15</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A74–P137</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <name type="pname">V. Hollschek</name> Coll.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.62</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">35.16</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P138</cell>
                     <cell>ANS-ETN, ex GDAM.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.02</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">35.17</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P139</cell>
                     <cell>ANS-ETN.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.12</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">35.18</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A75–P140</cell>
                     <cell>ANS-ETN.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.12</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e3272" type="section">
               <head>GROUP IV.</head>
               <p>36. TETRADRACHM. (<name type="pname">Müller</name> No. 876). Similar to No. 17.</p>
               <p>In 1. held, Demeter (?) with cornucopiae in 1. and patera in r. Beneath throne, EXE or EX.</p>
               <table rows="6" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">36.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A73–P141</cell>
                     <cell>ANS-ETN.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.04</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">36.2</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P142</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a</hi>. B.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b.</hi>
                        <name type="pname">F. Mus. Arch</name>.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">c.</hi> Cop. Syll. (Maced.), 731.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.54</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">36.3</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P143</cell>
                     <cell>ANS-ETN.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.93</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">36.4</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A71–P144</cell>
                     <cell>M.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.01</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>37. TETRADRACHM. (<name type="pname">Müller</name> No. 883). Similar to No. 17.</p>
               <p>In 1. field, <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q37122">Athena</name> with shield and spear, facing. Beneath throne, OΛ in wreath.</p>
               <table rows="4" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">37.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A76–Pl45</cell>
                     <cell>Boston.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">37.2</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P146</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a</hi>. M.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.75</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b</hi>. L.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.04</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">37.3</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A77–P147</cell>
                     <cell>V.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.29</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>38. TETRADRACHM. Similar to No. 17.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q37122">Athena</name> as on No. 37. Beneath throne, OΛY.</p>
               <table rows="2" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">38.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A78–P148</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a</hi>. B.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> Petsalis</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>39. TETRADRACHM. Similar to No. 17.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q37122">Athena</name> as on No. 38, but holds <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q165023">Nike</name> flying 1. in r. Beneath throne, OΛY.</p>
               <table rows="1" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">39.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A78–P149</cell>
                     <cell>ANS-ETN.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.02</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>40. TETRADRACHM. (<name type="pname">Müller</name> No. 878). Similar to No. 17.</p>
               <p>In 1. field, <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q37122">Athena</name> advances 1. with raised spear. Beneath throne, EY.</p>
               <table rows="10" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">40.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A79–P150</cell>
                     <cell>ANS-ETN.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.87</cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb n="20"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">40.2</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P151</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a</hi>. A. (Epidaurus Hoard, <hi rend="italic">Eph. Arch.,</hi> 1903, Pl. VII, 7.)</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.83</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> L.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.02</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">c.</hi> M.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.70</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">40.3</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P152</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a.</hi> L.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> M.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.78</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">c</hi>. Cop. Syll. (Maced.), 735.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.78</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">40.4</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A80–P152</cell>
                     <cell>Commerce. (Svoronos, Tά Noµίσµατα . . . Πτoλεµαίων, Pl. I, 20.)</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">40.5</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A81–P 153</cell>
                     <cell>B.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">40.6</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A82–P154</cell>
                     <cell>ANS-ETN (<name type="place">Olympia Hoard</name>, 69).</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.82</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>41. TETRADRACHM. Similar to No. 17.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q37122">Athena</name> as on No. 40. No letters beneath throne.</p>
               <table rows="3" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">41.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A83–P155</cell>
                     <cell>Leningrad, Hermitage.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">41.2</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P156</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a.</hi> B.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> ANS-ETN (<name type="place">Olympia Hoard</name>, 68).</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.76</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>42. TETRADRACHM Similar to No. 17.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q37122">Athena</name> as on No. 40. Beneath throne, F.</p>
               <table rows="1" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">42.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A84–P157</cell>
                     <cell>ANS-ETN (<name type="place">Olympia Hoard</name>, 72).</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.76</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>43. TETRADRACHM. (<name type="pname">Müller</name> No. 874). Similar to No. 17.</p>
               <p>In 1. field, youth r. with arms raised, holding fillet. Beneath throne, NO. No Nikes on back of throne.</p>
               <table rows="3" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">43.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A85–P158</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a</hi>. ANS-ETN.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.11</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b.</hi>
                        <name type="pname">A. Saroglos</name> Coll.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">43.2</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A86–P159</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <name type="pname">C. Leake</name> (Kings, p. 5, 15). Perhaps an electrotype.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.60</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>44. TETRADRACHM. Similar to No. 17.</p>
               <p>Similar to No. 43, but in 1. field, youth faces 1. Beneath throne, <graphic url="NS6_sym8.jpg"/>.</p>
               <table rows="1" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">44.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A87–P160</cell>
                     <cell>B.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>45. TETRADRACHM. Similar to No. 17.</p>
               <p>Youth as on No. 44. Beneath throne, bird r. above <graphic url="NS6_sym9.jpg"/>. Nikes on back of throne. No inscription in exergue.</p>
               <table rows="5" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">45.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A88–P161</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a.</hi> ANS-ETN.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.06</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b</hi>. B.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">45.2</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P162</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a</hi>. B. (Beneath throne, <graphic url="NS6_sym10.jpg"/>.)</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> A.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">45.3</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P163</cell>
                     <cell>A.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>46. TETRADRACHM. (<name type="pname">Müller</name> No. 868). Identical with No. 45, but die worn.</p>
               <p>Similar to No. 45. No bird beneath throne.</p>
               <table rows="4" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">46.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A88–P164</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a.</hi> ANS-ETN.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.60</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> L.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.80</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">c.</hi> L.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.65</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">d</hi>. B.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <pb n="21"/>
               <p>47. TETRADRACHM. (<name type="pname">Müller</name> No. 871). Die of No. 45; much worn.</p>
               <p>Similar to No. 46. Beneath throne, <graphic url="NS6_sym11.jpg"/>.</p>
               <table rows="3" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">47.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A88–P165</cell>
                     <cell>ANS-ETN.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.16</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">47.2</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P166</cell>
                     <cell>a<hi rend="italic">.</hi> L.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.72</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b</hi>. B.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>48. TETRADRACHM. Die of Nos. 45–47.</p>
               <p>Similar to No. 46 but with a crescent in 1. field behind youth.</p>
               <table rows="1" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">48.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A88–P167</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <name type="pname">D. M. Robinson</name> Coll.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 15.82</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>49. TETRADRACHM. (<name type="pname">Müller</name> No. 866). Similar to No. 17.</p>
               <p>Similar to No. 46. Beneath throne, <graphic url="NS6_sym12.jpg"/>.</p>
               <table rows="2" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">49.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A89–P168</cell>
                     <cell>L. (<hi rend="italic">Coins of the Ancients</hi>, Pl. 31.)</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.04</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">49.2</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P168</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <name type="pname">A. Saroglos</name> Coll. Die P168 with addition of Σ to 1. of youth.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>50. TETRADRACHM. (<name type="pname">Müller</name> No. 867). Die of No. 49, but worn.</p>
               <p>Similar to 49.2, but beneath throne, <graphic url="NS6_sym13.jpg"/>.</p>
               <table rows="2" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">50.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A89–P169</cell>
                     <cell>Formerly Sir <name type="pname">R. Storrs</name> Coll.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">50.2</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P170</cell>
                     <cell>ANS-ETN.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.01</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>51. TETRADRACHM. Head of Her-acles of broad style, differing from preceding</p>
               <p>In 1. field, youth with fillet; bird flying to 1. above head of youth. Beneath throne, <graphic url="NS6_sym14.jpg"/>.</p>
               <table rows="2" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">51.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A90–P171</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a</hi>. Cop. Syll. (Maced.), 733.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.68</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> ANS.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.95</cell>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>52. TETRADRACHM. Die of No. 51.</p>
               <p>Youth and bird as on No. 51. Beneath throne, <graphic url="NS6_sym15.jpg"/>.</p>
               <table rows="1" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">52.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A90–P172</cell>
                     <cell>ANS.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.10</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>53. TETRADRACHM. Similar to No. 51.</p>
               <p>Youth and bird as on No. 51. Beneath throne, <graphic url="NS6_sym16.jpg"/>E or <graphic url="NS6_sym8.jpg"/>.</p>
               <table rows="3" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">53.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A91–P173</cell>
                     <cell>ANS.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.91</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">53.2</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A92 P174</cell>
                     <cell>ANS-Storrs.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.73</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">53.3</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A90–P175</cell>
                     <cell>Commerce (bird erased?).</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>54. TETRADRACHM. Similar to No. 51.</p>
               <p>Youth similar to No. 51, but bird is smaller. Beneath throne, <graphic url="NS6_sym13.jpg"/>.</p>
               <table rows="3" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">54.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A93–P176</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a.</hi> ANS-ETN, ex Waldeck Coll.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.93</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> L.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">c.</hi> B.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>55. TETRADRACHM. (<name type="pname">Müller</name> No. 869). Similar to No. 51.</p>
               <p>In 1. field, youth with fillet to 1.; wreath above head of youth. Beneath throne, <graphic url="NS6_sym13.jpg"/>.</p>
               <table rows="4" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">55.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A93–P177</cell>
                     <cell>A.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">55.2</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P178</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a</hi>. B.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> ANS-ETN.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.76</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">55.3</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P179</cell>
                     <cell>P.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <pb n="22"/>
               <p>56. TETRADRACHM. (<name type="pname">Müller</name> No. 873). Similar to No. 17.</p>
               <p>In 1. field youth with fillet 1. Beneath throne, <graphic url="NS6_sym17.jpg"/>.</p>
               <table rows="2" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">56.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A94–P180</cell>
                     <cell>B.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">56.2</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P181</cell>
                     <cell>ANS.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 15.92</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>57. TETRADRACHM. Die of No. 56.</p>
               <p>In 1. field, youth with doubled fillet 1. Beneath throne, <graphic url="NS6_sym18.jpg"/>. Similar to foregoing but larger in scale. Legs of throne as in Nos. 55 and 56.</p>
               <table rows="2" cols="3">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">57.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A94–P182</cell>
                     <cell>B.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>58. TETRADRACHM. (<name type="pname">Müller</name> No. 885). Similar to No. 17.</p>
               <p>Similar. In 1. field, trident 1. Beneath throne, <graphic url="NS6_sym19.jpg"/>. The Nikes are larger than in previous occurrences. Pearl-border on P183.</p>
               <table rows="9" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">58.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A95–P183</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a.</hi> A.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> C. <name type="pname">McClean Coll</name>., Pl. 130, 1.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.80</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">c.</hi> L. (<hi rend="italic">Coins of the Ancients</hi>, Pl. 31.)</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.85</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">d</hi>. ANS-ETN.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.73</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">e.</hi> Jameson Coll., 989.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.63</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">f</hi>. <name type="pname">Egger XL</name>, May 1912, 651 = Hess Sale, March 1906, 297.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.23</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">g</hi>. <name type="pname">Naville I</name>, 1921 (Pozzi), 930.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.85</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">h.</hi> Riechmann XXX, Dec. 1924, 453.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.49</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">58.2</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P184</cell>
                     <cell>B.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>59. TETRADRACHM. (<name type="pname">Müller</name> No. 881). Similar to No. 17.</p>
               <p>In 1. field, <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q37122">Athena</name> to 1., with shield and spear on which tiny owl is perched. Beneath throne, ΔE. Throne similar to P184.</p>
               <table rows="11" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">59.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A96–P185</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a</hi>. A.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> ANS-ETN.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.95</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">c.</hi>
                        <name type="pname">C. McClean</name> Coll., Pl. 127, 12.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.03</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">d.</hi> L.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.48</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">e.</hi> B.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">f.</hi> B.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">59.2</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P186</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a.</hi> ANS-ETN, = <name type="pname">Sotheby</name> July, 1909 (Hazlitt), 57.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.12</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> ANS, ex <name type="pname">Hirsch XXVI</name>, 1910, 156.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.00</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">c.</hi>
                        <name type="pname">Sotheby</name> Sale, May 1900, 207.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">d.</hi> Basel IV, Oct. 1935, 633.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.92</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">e.</hi> P. De Luynes Coll., 1651.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.00</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>60. TETRADRACHM. (<name type="pname">Müller</name> No. 882). Similar to No. 17.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q37122">Athena</name> as on No. 59 but figure smaller in scale. Beneath throne, <graphic url="NS6_sym16.jpg"/>E.</p>
               <table rows="15" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">60.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A96–P187</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a</hi>. A.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b.</hi>
                        <name type="pname">C. McClean</name> Coll., Pl. 128.1.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.92</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">c</hi>. L.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.07</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">d.</hi> B.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">60.2</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P188</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a</hi>. ANS-ETN.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.13</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b.</hi>
                        <name type="pname">C. Leake</name> Suppl. (Syll., IV, 3, 2139).</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.05</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">c.</hi>
                        <name type="pname">C. Leake</name> Addenda (Syll., IV, 3, 2138).</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.12</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">d</hi>. B.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <pb n="23"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">60.3</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P189</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a</hi>. A.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> A.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">c.</hi> L.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.87</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">60.4</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P190</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <name type="pname">A. Saroglos</name> Coll.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">60.5</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A97–P191</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a</hi>. ANS-ETN.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.92</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b</hi>. B.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">60.6</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A98–P192</cell>
                     <cell>B.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>61. TETRADRACHM. Similar to No. 17.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q37122">Athena</name> as on No. 60. Beneath throne. OΛ.</p>
               <table rows="2" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">61.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A99–P193</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a</hi>. Rome. Vatican Coll.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b</hi>. <name type="pname">B.Y. Berry</name> Coll.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>62. TETRADRACHM. Similar to No. 17.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q37122">Athena</name> similar to No. 60 but with round shield covering upper part of body. Beneath throne, AE.</p>
               <table rows="1" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">62.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A100–P194</cell>
                     <cell>ANS-ETN, ex GDAM (cf. <name type="pname">Hirsch XXXIV</name>, 1914, 295).</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.80</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>63. TETRADRACHM. (<name type="pname">Müller</name> No. 893). Stylized head of <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q122248">Heracles</name> in high relief.</p>
               <p>In 1. field, mounted Dioscuroi to 1. Beneath throne, AΛE. Nikes disproportionately large, the one to 1. exceeding its companion.</p>
               <table rows="4" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">63.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A101–P195</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a.</hi> A.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> ANS-ETN.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.81</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">c</hi>. B.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">d.</hi> 33 specimens in Patras Hoard (<hi rend="italic">Num. Chron.</hi> 1853, p. 33).</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>64. TETRADRACHM. Similar to No. 17.</p>
               <p>In 1. field, trident pointing upward. Beneath throne, ΔA. Difference in throne.</p>
               <table rows="2" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">64.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A102–P196</cell>
                     <cell>L.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 17.17</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">64.2</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P197</cell>
                     <cell>ANS-ETN.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.53</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>65. TETRADRACHM. Similar to No. 17.</p>
               <p>Trident as on No. 64. Beneath throne, <graphic url="NS6_sym16.jpg"/>E.</p>
               <table rows="1" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">65.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A103–P198</cell>
                     <cell>B.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>66. TETRADRACHM. Similar to No. 17.</p>
               <p>Same die as No. 65 with Λ to r. of trident.</p>
               <table rows="1" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">66.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A104–P198</cell>
                     <cell>Brussels (de <name type="pname">Hirsch</name>).</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.90</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>67. TETRADRACHM. (<name type="pname">Müller</name> No. 896). Similar to No. 17.</p>
               <p>In 1. field, fulmen. Beneath throne ΦI. Differences in scale of figure of <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q34201">Zeus</name>.</p>
               <table rows="7" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">67.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A105–P199</cell>
                     <cell>L.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.83</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">67.2</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P200</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <name type="pname">O. Davidson</name> Coll.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">67.3</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P201</cell>
                     <cell>a. ANS-ETN.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.78</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> A.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">c</hi>. B.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">67.4</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P202</cell>
                     <cell>ANS.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.92</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">67.5</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P203</cell>
                     <cell>B.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <pb n="24"/>
               <p>68. TETRADRACHM. (<name type="pname">Müller</name> No. 895). Similar to No. 17.</p>
               <p>Fulmen as on No. 67. Beneath throne <graphic url="NS6_sym20.jpg"/>. In exergue <graphic url="NS6_sym1.jpg"/>
               </p>
               <table rows="2" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">68.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A105–P204</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a</hi>. L.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.98</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> B.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>69. TETRADRACHM. Notably different die.</p>
               <p>Similar to No. 67 but Nikes well-defined, and with traces of a possible monogram in exergue. <graphic url="NS6_sym16.jpg"/> added to reverse of 69.2.</p>
               <table rows="2" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">69.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A106–P205</cell>
                     <cell>B.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">69.2</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>P205</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <name type="pname">Turin</name>.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.85</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>70. TETRADRACHM. (<name type="pname">Müller</name> 894). Similar to No. 17.</p>
               <p>Same die as No. 68 with exergual letters changed to <graphic url="NS6_sym21.jpg"/>.</p>
               <table rows="3" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="bold">70.1</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>A106–P204</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">a</hi>. ANS-ETN.</cell>
                     <cell>gr. 16.95</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">b.</hi> A.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">c.</hi> B.</cell>
                     <cell/>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d1e4843" type="chapter">
            <pb n="25"/>
            <head>NOTES TO THE CATALOGUE</head>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e4847" type="section">
               <head>GROUP I.</head>
               <p>Symbols: Youth, Rudder, Fulmen, Barley-ear, Goat's head.</p>
               <p>The lower limit for the dating of this group is fixed by the occurrence of nearly all of its silver components in the <name type="place">Demanhur Hoard</name>., the date for the burial of which is 318 B. C.<ref target="#CH3-n1a">1</ref> In 1921, in his discussion of the <name type="place">Kyparissia Hoard</name>,<ref target="#CH3-n2a">2</ref>
                  <name type="pname">Mr. Newell</name> stated that "about 330 B. C.—and certainly by 325 B. C.—a large issue of staters and tetradrachms bearing <name type="pname" corresp="#nomisma_alexander_iii">Alexander</name> types was instituted at <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_sicyon">Sicyon</name>." No specimens of these tetradrachms occur in the <name type="place">Kyparissia Hoard</name> buried in 327 B. C. The interval covered by the group is therefore from between 330 and 325 B. C. to before 318 B. C.</p>
               <p>The only gold assigned to the <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_sicyon">Sicyon</name> mint by <name type="pname">Mr. Newell</name>, if we except the coinage of <name type="pname">Demetrius Poliorcetes</name>,<ref target="#CH3-n3a">3</ref> belongs to this period. The preponderance of distaters is not without significance; other, and probably contemporary, issues of this rather exceptional denomination are found at Amphipolis.</p>
               <p>The youthful figure which occupies the space usually given to the magistrate's monogram or the initial letters of the name of the city issuing the coinage, has been accepted since <name type="pname">Müller's</name> day as indicating <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_sicyon">Sicyon</name>.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="pname">Müller's</name> assignment is supported in an extended note published by <name type="pname" corresp="#viaf_74638710">Ernest Babelon</name> in the <hi rend="italic">Revue Numismatique</hi> for 1904 (p. 117). The figure is there associated with the youth holding a fillet (Nos. 43.1–57.1, Pl. XIV–XV) although the fact that more than half a century separates the appearance of these symbols is not realized. <name type="pname">M. Babelon</name> believes that the attitude of the youth with a fillet signifies a scene of divination through observation of the flight of birds. <name type="pname">Mr. Newell</name> noted what he believed a connection between Nos. 13.1 and 51–54 because of the presence of the bird which is to be seen on the later issue, but the <hi rend="italic">fleur-de-coin</hi> specimen which was acquired by The American Numismaicc Society with the Sir <name type="pname" corresp="#viaf_65453680">Ronald Storrs</name> Collection shows clearly that on 13.1 this is not a bird but a die-break.</p>
               <p>The tiny figure in the gold and silver of the first issue is very boyish, almost cherubic, while the youth holding the fillet is nearer the age of an ephebe. There is considerable variation in the position taken by the figure—note 3.1 as compared with 3.2, 4.2 and especially with 12.1 and 14.2.</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="pname">Mr. Newell's</name> arrangement is easy to follow. The gold coins provide the key. The initial issue with the suppliant alone, precedes the issue with the suppliant and rudder. The magistrates' initials A and <graphic url="NS6_sym1.jpg"/> accompanied by a fulmen as symbol (Pl. II) appear on a large group of di-staters with a single stater issue and no accompanying issue of silver, a most interesting phenomenon whose interpretation invites
<pb n="26"/>
speculation. Cannot the mint of <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_sicyon">Sicyon</name> have been supplying some of the "sinews of the Lamian War?</p>
               <p>Beginning with No. 9.1, there is reversion to the symbol of the original issue (this time with a slight change of attitude) but now with <graphic url="NS6_sym22.jpg"/>, the magistrate of the intervening issue. The symbol on the silver parallels that on the gold coinage with amazing closeness. The die-mulings make the sequence indicated practically inescapable. No magistrate's initials appear on the silver. One would hardly venture assigning Nos. 15.1 and 16.1 to <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_sicyon">Sicyon</name> were it not for the muling of the obverse die with 14.7. The facing eagle on the reverse of No. 16.1 is very unusual, but so is the goat's head symbol. The barley-ear occurs as a symbol at other mints—Amphipolis, Alexandria, and Miletus, for example.</p>
               <p>In <name type="pname">Mr. Newell's</name> manuscript notes there is a marked gap between this first series and the one which follows. We are told that Ptolemy "freed" <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_sicyon">Sicyon</name> of its <name type="place">Macedonian</name> garrison in 308 B. C. (Polybius xx, 11–118th <name type="place">Olympiad</name>). After the death of Antipater in 319, Polyperchon and his son <name type="pname" corresp="#nomisma_alexander_iii">Alexander</name> were in control in the Peloponnesus, and it was the widow of <name type="pname" corresp="#nomisma_alexander_iii">Alexander</name>, Cratesipolus, who surrendered <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_sicyon">Sicyon</name> to Ptolemy (308). Neither Polyperchon nor his son has a coinage attributed to him. There seems no good reason why <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_sicyon">Sicyon</name> may not have been striking autonomous coins in this interval previous to its control by Ptolemy. Duting the period of Ptolemy's occupation, coins are believed to have been struck by him at Corinth;<ref target="#CH3-n1b">1</ref> another Ptolemy mint at near-by <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_sicyon">Sicyon</name> would have been superfluous.</p>
               <note place="end" xml:id="CH3-n1a">
                  <seg type="note-symbol">1</seg>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">
                        <name type="place">Demanhur</name>,</hi> p. 153.</p>
               </note>
               <note place="end" xml:id="CH3-n2a">
                  <seg type="note-symbol">2</seg>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">
                        <name type="pname" corresp="#nomisma_alexander_iii">Alexander</name> Hoards</hi> — <hi rend="italic">Introduction and <name type="place">Kyparissia Hoard</name>
                     </hi> (Num. Notes &amp; Monogr. No. 3), p. 14.</p>
               </note>
               <note place="end" xml:id="CH3-n3a">
                  <seg type="note-symbol">3</seg>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Demetrius</hi>, p. 144.</p>
               </note>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e5006" type="section">
               <head>GROUP II</head>
               <p>Symbols: Star, Wreath, <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q165023">Nike</name>, Chimaera, Elpis, <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q122248">Heracles</name>.</p>
               <p>We have noted that there was probably no coinage at <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_sicyon">Sicyon</name> during the occupancy of Ptolemy I, 308–303 B. C. In his tentative identification of a brief coinage at <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_sicyon">Sicyon</name> by <name type="pname">Demetrius</name> after he had regained possession in 290 B. C, <name type="pname">Mr. Newell</name> implies that <name type="pname" corresp="#nomisma_alexander_iii">Alexander</name>-type tetradrachms were struck there by him between 303 and 301 B. C.<ref target="#CH3-n2b">2</ref> This procedure would have been in keeping with the practice of both <name type="pname">Antigonus</name> and <name type="pname">Demetrius</name>, and we may accordingly look for support for the identification of the initial issues of the group (those having the star and wreath for symbols) as having appeared between 303 and 301 B. C.</p>
               <p>The occurrence of BAΣIΛEΩΣ in the exergue of all the issues with the star for symbol and for all but two of those with the wreath symbol shows that they must have been struck after the use of this title by the successors of <name type="pname" corresp="#nomisma_alexander_iii">Alexander</name> had become general. There may be significance in its abandonment. Cannot this have been an indication and a consequence of the reverses incident to Ipsus? Both Polybius and Plutarch tell of the removal and renaming of the city by <name type="pname">Demetrius</name> after its "freeing" from Ptolemy. The star symbol occurs on the issues of <name type="pname">Demetrius</name>
                  <pb n="27"/>
struck at Ephesus at this time<ref target="#CH3-n1c">1</ref> and the wreath is another symbol in which it would not be unreasonable to see a reference to benefits received by <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_sicyon">Sicyon</name> from <name type="pname">Demetrius</name> in connection with its transfer to a more easily defensible situation. Further, the number of dies with the kingly reference would cover a period which would approximate the duration of the control of <name type="pname">Demetrius</name>. Additional support comes from an inscription found in the Athenian Agora in 1935 published by <name type="pname">E. Schweigert</name> in <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="place">Hesperia</name>
                  </hi> in 1939 (p. 35), from which <name type="pname">Dr. Ferguson</name> has deduced<ref target="#CH3-n2c">2</ref> that the alliance treaty between <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_athens">Athens</name> and <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_sicyon">Sicyon</name> which it records must be dated "late in 301." The mention in the decree of the Athenians of τòγ δῆµoγ Σικωγίωγ prohibits an earlier date. Since there must have been a gap following the ousting of the <name type="place">Macedonian</name> garrison, it would seem to have come during the use of the wreath as symbol, with Nos. 19 and 21 to be explained as due to the exigencies of the situation.</p>
               <div3 xml:id="d1e5115" type="subsection">
                  <head>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">Wreath</hi> (Nos. 19–21; Pl. IV).</head>
                  <p>The first of these coins is remarkable for the dove within the wreath in the left field — a peculiarly and distinctively <name type="place">Sicyonian</name> symbol. It is coupled with a second symbol—cornucopiae—beneath the seat of the throne, where this second symbol is accompanied by the tiny letter Δ. This letter recurs on five other dies bearing this symbol, three of which bear BAΣIΛEΩΣ in the exergue. In none of these pieces with the wreath does the delta enclose omicron as in the preceding coins with the star as symbol.</p>
               </div3>
               <div3 xml:id="d1e5125" type="subsection">
                  <head>
                     <name type="pname">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Nike</hi>
                     </name> (Nos. 22–23; Pl. V).</head>
                  <p>The figure of <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q165023">Nike</name> bearing a wreath used as a symbol is intriguing and suggestive of similar uses elsewher, e. g., Tarsus. A relationship to the seated <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q34201">Zeus</name> may be intended, whereas, in contrast, the figures of Elpis (Pl. VII) and the boy of Plate I face away from him. With the exception of a single coin, the style is excellent.</p>
                  <p>There are nine obverse and ten reverse dies. It is unusual that reverse die P58 is muled with three obverse dies. Two of the obverse dies carry over to the chimaera issue.</p>
               </div3>
               <div3 xml:id="d1e5141" type="subsection">
                  <head>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">Chimaera</hi> (Nos. 24–25; Pl. VI).</head>
                  <p>The coins of the group bearing this symbol are connected with the <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q165023">Nike</name> group by the continued use of the obverse dies Nos. 41 and 42 as well as by the carrying over of the magistracy of NO. One obverse die is used with no less than twelve reverses.</p>
                  <p>There may be significance in that the chimaera, the city's badge, is shown facing toward <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q34201">Zeus</name>, just as did the <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q165023">Nike</name> figure. Such a use of the civic emblem is common at a later date with the spread-flan tetradrachms of <name type="pname">Müller</name>s Class VI. Its employment as early as this is exceptional.</p>
                  <p>The use of the chimaera symbol lasted for the life of less than three obverse
<pb n="28"/>
dies—two of these dies were used with the preceding <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q165023">Nike</name> symbol. This seems to imply that the symbols changed annually and that die No. A41, starting in one year had been used well into the succeeding year. It might explain the civic and local rather than personal or magisterial nature of the symbols of <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_sicyon">Sicyon</name>.</p>
                  <note place="end" xml:id="CH3-n1c">
                     <seg type="note-symbol">6</seg>
                     <p>
                        <name type="pname">
                           <hi rend="italic">Demetrius</hi>
                        </name>, p. 64 ff.</p>
                  </note>
                  <note place="end" xml:id="CH3-n2c">
                     <seg type="note-symbol">7</seg>
                     <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">
                           <name type="place">
                              <hi rend="italic">Hesperia</hi>
                           </name>
                        </hi>, Vol. XVII (1948), p. 126, note 39.</p>
                  </note>
               </div3>
               <div3 xml:id="d1e5189" type="subsection">
                  <head>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">Elpis</hi> (No. 26; Pl. VII).</head>
                  <p>The figure of Elpis, the symbol for this group, is one of the daintiest to be found anywhere, and the die-cutter of No. 26.9 must have been a gifted artist, for not only is the seated <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q34201">Zeus</name> beautifully modelled but this excellence extends to the obverse die as well—an excellence which does not mark the obverses of the entire group. The enlargement (Plate XVIII) shows how strongly a sculptural prototype is suggested. The proportion of obverse to reverse dies is greater than in the preceding group—probably an indication that additional mulings are to be expected as further hoards come to light. The use of die No. A47 (No. 26.5) with the <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q122248">Heracles</name> die (No. 27.1) is noteworthy.</p>
               </div3>
               <div3 xml:id="d1e5202" type="subsection">
                  <head>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">
                        <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q122248">Heracles</name>
                     </hi> (No. 27; Pl. VIII)</head>
                  <p>Up to the presen, there are but two specimens of the type with the resting <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q122248">Heracles</name> for symbol, and these are from two pairs of dies, although one obverse die is also muled with a reverse having Elpis as its symbol (No. 26.5). But the contrast in the style of these two obverses is startling, although Wroth in describing the British Museum specimen at the time of its acquisition<ref target="#CH3-n1d">1</ref> says that No. 27.1 is 'almost identical' with No. 27.2. He further states that "the Herakles symbol, as Bunbury has already noted<ref target="#CH3-n2d">2</ref> closely resembles the well-known Farnese Hercules in the Naples Museum. This statue is a product of the Neo-Attic school and is signed by <name type="pname">Glykon</name>, the Athenian, a sculptor who probably flourished towards the end of the first century B. C. The motive of the statue has been usually traced to a Resting <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q122248">Heracles</name> by <name type="pname" corresp="#viaf_297421082">Lysippus</name>, but for the general treatment, and especially for the exaggeration of the muscular forms, <name type="pname">Glykon</name>, and not <name type="pname" corresp="#viaf_297421082">Lysippus</name>, must be held responsible." Pausanias mentions having seen a bronze <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q122248">Heracles</name> by <name type="pname" corresp="#viaf_297421082">Lysippus</name> at <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_sicyon">Sicyon</name>.</p>
                  <p>This is the first use of the initial three letters of the magistrate's name if we except the monogram of Nos. 18.1 and 18.2.</p>
               </div3>
               <note place="end" xml:id="CH3-n1b">
                  <seg type="note-symbol">4</seg>
                  <p>Cf. <name type="pname">Ravel, O</name>. "Corinthian Hoard from Chiliomodi," in <hi rend="italic">Trans, of the International Numismatic Congress</hi> (<name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_london">London</name>, 1938), p. 104.</p>
               </note>
               <note place="end" xml:id="CH3-n2b">
                  <seg type="note-symbol">5</seg>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">
                        <name type="pname">Demetrius</name>,</hi> p. 146.</p>
               </note>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e5246" type="section">
               <head>GROUP III</head>
               <p>Symbols: Aphlaston, Amphora, Horse's head, Cornucopiae.</p>
               <div3 xml:id="d1e5251" type="subsection">
                  <head>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">Aphlaston</hi> (Nos. 28–31; Pls. VIII and IX).</head>
                  <p>For a very informative and helpful explanation of the significance of the aphlaston used as a symbol or as part of the type, see Agnes Baldwin Brett, "The</p>
                  <pb n="29"/>
                  <p>Aphlaston, Symbol of Naval Victory or Supremacy on Greek and Roman Coins" in <hi rend="italic">Trans, of the International Numismatic Congress</hi> (<name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_london">London</name>, 1938), pp. 23 ff. It is not uncommon as a symbol elsewhere on the <name type="pname" corresp="#nomisma_alexander_iii">Alexander</name> coinage, nor is it easy to distinguish the <name type="place">Sicyonian</name> form from others. One of these is attributed by <name type="pname">Mr. Newell</name> to an uncertain mint of Northern Greece. Its significance as indicating a naval victory makes its association with <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_sicyon">Sicyon</name> hard to understand unless it has some reference to the return of the victorious <name type="pname">Demetrius Poliorcetes</name>. This is a possibility since we have several of these tetradrachms occurring in the <name type="pname">Armenak Hoard</name> dated by <name type="pname">Mr. Newell</name> as having been buried c. 280. The regal coins of <name type="pname">Demetrius</name> believed to have been struck by him at <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_sicyon">Sicyon</name> are dated by <name type="pname">Mr. Newell</name> c. 290 B. C. <hi rend="italic">(<name type="pname">Demetrius</name>,</hi> p. 145). The initial absence and subsequent replacement of BAΣIΛEΩΣ in the exergue would fit in with such a supposition, since this usage would reasonably follow the regaining of the control of the <name type="place">Sicyonians</name> by <name type="pname">Demetrius</name>.</p>
                  <p>The workmanship stops short of being fine. Note the apparently beardesss <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q34201">Zeus</name> of No. 30.5. There are interesting variations in the form of the aphlaston. Anvil die A57 is muled with eight reverses by three magistrates (NO, ΔE, and ΔO) and A61 connects the aphlaston with the amphora group (No. 32).</p>
                  <note place="end" xml:id="CH3-n1d">
                     <seg type="note-symbol">1</seg>
                     <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">Num. Chron,</hi> 1900, p. 278.</p>
                  </note>
                  <note place="end" xml:id="CH3-n2d">
                     <seg type="note-symbol">2</seg>
                     <p>
                        <hi rend="italic">Num. Chron,</hi> 1883, pp. 7 f. No. 27.2 is the Bunbury specimen.</p>
                  </note>
               </div3>
               <div3 xml:id="d1e5330" type="subsection">
                  <head>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">Amphora</hi> (No. 32; Pl. X).</head>
                  <p>But two reverse dies with the amphora for symbol are recorded. In <name type="pname">Mr. Newell's</name> arrangement, owing to an overlapping of his serial numbers, they follow the horse-head group but because of the sharing of their single obverse die with an obverse die of the aphlaston series (Nos. 30.3, 30.7) they have been shifted to their present position.<ref target="#CH3-n1e">1</ref> Other occurrences of the amphora as a symbol on <name type="pname" corresp="#nomisma_alexander_iii">Alexander</name> types are found at Chios, Myrina, Temnos, Sardes, Pella and at more than one uncertain mint. The magistrate ΔE has his initials on three successive groups. The workmanship on the dies is of continued excellence.</p>
               </div3>
               <div3 xml:id="d1e5346" type="subsection">
                  <head>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">Horse's Head</hi> (Nos. 33–34; Pl. X).</head>
                  <p>Mulings make this series seem more extensive than it really is, for of the four obverse dies three carry over into the cornucopiae issues following. There is but a single magistrate, ΔE, although his initials do not occur on No. 33.1. Six reverse dies are combined with the four anvil dies. BAΣIΛEΩΣ occurs in the exergue throughout. The horse-head symbol also occurs at Magnesia.</p>
               </div3>
               <div3 xml:id="d1e5353" type="subsection">
                  <head>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">Cornucopiae</hi> (No. 35; Pls. XI–XI).</head>
                  <p>Although three obverse dies carry over from the preceding series, the magistrate NO is the only one found with the cornucopiae group. This name has occurred previously—with symbols <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q165023">Nike</name>, chimaera, Elpis and aphlaston, although not as sole magistrate except in the Elpis group. The number of the dies and the use of
<pb n="30"/>
A74, with its disfiguring break, point to a stepped-up coinage and possibly to more than a single year's duration for the use of the cornucopiae as symbol. There is a steady deterioration noticeable in the obverse dies, but this is not apparent for the reverses. BAΣIΛEΩΣ is in its customary exergual position.</p>
                  <p>There is, however, in this series the beginning of a convention which is distinctive—the treatment of the throne, if the seat of <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q34201">Zeus</name> can be so called. On Pls. I and III, this seat takes the form of a stool or square bench. Although the head of <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q34201">Zeus</name> is usually in profile or almost so, the upper portion of his body is shown facing, to accommodate the holding of his sceptre, while his legs are turned so that they are on the side rather than the front of the seat.</p>
                  <p>A notable change had taken place at <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_sicyon">Sicyon</name> by the time the coins on Plate IV had been struck—i. e., about 303. The lower portion of the throne had by that time become more substantial and a back had been provided, increasing the die-cutter's difficulties. Frequently the part played by the back in the composition is minimized, either by making it of slighter thickness than the legs or by the merest indication of the top of the left upright beyond the right shoulder of <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q34201">Zeus</name>. Sometimes the back is omitted altogether (Nos. 17.3 and 22.7). A cross-piece which connects the two uprights is likewise given summary treatment in many dies, while a similar cross-piece near the top, which is structurally necessary, is sometimes visible behind the shoulder of the god. A problem in perspective results. The designer, as we have seen, solved this by presenting the upper part of the figure as supported by the back, although the head and legs are shown in profile. The treatment of these details as well as those of the eagle and sceptre in the other mints using the types of <name type="pname" corresp="#nomisma_alexander_iii">Alexander</name> provide more variety than is generally realized.</p>
                  <p>That variety, however, finds a new expression in the tiny figures of <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q165023">Nike</name> which appear on the tips of the uprights of the throne-back. Later, they become very prominent and it is by working back from the later occurrences that one discovers they were introduced during the life of this group. A number of these little figures will be found among the enlargements of Plate XVIII, but a powerful glass will reward the examination of their occurrences from this point onward. Compare the use of similar tiny Nikes on the stylis held by <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q165023">Nike</name> on the gold staters of <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_sidon">Sidon</name>
                     <ref target="#CH3-n1f">1</ref>
                  </p>
                  <note place="end" xml:id="CH3-n1e">
                     <seg type="note-symbol">1</seg>
                     <p>Judging from the wear on the obvesse die, this issue with the amphora may have preceded the aphlaston issue also.</p>
                  </note>
               </div3>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e5401" type="section">
               <head>GROUP IV</head>
               <p>Symbols: Demeter, <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q37122">Athena</name>, Youth with fillet, Dioscuroi, Trident, Fulmen.</p>
               <div3 xml:id="d1e5409" type="subsection">
                  <head>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">Demeter</hi> (No. 36; Pl. XII).</head>
                  <p>There are two obverse and four reverse dies, A71 having been used with four reverses in the preceding group and A73 with one. The magistrate EXE does not occur elsewhere in the series. The figure holds a cornucopiae and patera. No. 35.14 was in the Epidaurus Hoard, dated by <name type="pname">Mr. Newell</name> as having been buried after 285. This gives an approximate dating for these two groups.</p>
                  <pb n="31"/>
                  <p>
                     <name type="pname">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Athena</hi>
                     </name> I (Nos. 37–39; Pl. XII).</p>
                  <p>The symbol-figure which accompanies the name OΛY (or OΛ) is clearly intended to represent <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q37122">Athena</name> on Nos. 38.1 and 39.1. On Nos. 37.1 and 37.2, this figure is facing, but there is slight room for doubt that here, too, <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q37122">Athena</name> is intended. The enlargement (cf. Plate XVIII) makes the details clearer. Attention might be directed to the part played by the spear in all three variations, even in No. 39.1 where a tiny <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q165023">Nike</name> is held in the outstretched hand of the goddess. Is it not probable that the wreath encircling the magistrate's initials on Nos. 37.1–3 may indicate that he was a victor in some agonistic contest? Encircled monograms are found beneath the throne in other mints, and wreathed initials or monograms occur in the field, but wreathing a name beneath the throne may have had some additional significance. The absence of any muling with the preceding group may indicate an interval without coinage. No. 39.1 does not have the <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q165023">Nike</name> finials. In each instance, the symbol-figure is shown standing on what may be considered a pedestal or statue-basis.</p>
                  <note place="end" xml:id="CH3-n1f">
                     <seg type="note-symbol">1</seg>
                     <p>
                        <name type="pname" corresp="#numismatics_newell">E. T. Newell</name>, <hi rend="italic">The Dated <name type="pname" corresp="#nomisma_alexander_iii">Alexander</name> Coinage of <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_sidon">Sidon</name> and <name type="place">Ake</name>
                        </hi> (<name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_new_haven_connecticut">New Haven</name>, 1916), p. 25.</p>
                  </note>
               </div3>
               <div3 xml:id="d1e5460" type="subsection">
                  <head>
                     <name type="pname">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Athena</hi>
                     </name> II (Nos. 40–42; Pl. XIII).</head>
                  <p>The figure of <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q37122">Athena</name> on coins of this group is shown facing to 1. with crested helmet and threatening spear. On two pieces there is indication of a ground-line. The magistrate is EY, but his initials do not occur on Nos. 41.1 and 41.2. On No. 42.1, we have a digamma replacing EY. For the sharing of the obverse die of No. 40.6 with two radically different reverses shown on Pl. XIII, consult the discussion of the <name type="place">Olympia Hoard</name> (p. 35) from which all these pieces were obtained.</p>
               </div3>
               <div3 xml:id="d1e5474" type="subsection">
                  <head>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">Youth with Fillet</hi> (Nos. 43–57; Pls. XIV–XV).</head>
                  <p>This group, with a youth holding a fillet for its symbol is not only one of the largest but one of the most puzzling in the coinage of <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_sicyon">Sicyon</name>. Its identification with <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_sicyon">Sicyon</name> is certain because of a bronze coin with this youthful figure in the same attitude (cf. enlargement on Plate XVIII). The reverse of this bronze coin has a wreath enclosing the first two letters of the city's name.</p>
                  <p>This group may be examined from three approaches: (1) the magistrates, (2) the symbol, (3) the form of the <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q34201">Zeus</name> throne.</p>
                  <p>The magistrates are eight in number: NO, <graphic url="NS6_sym16.jpg"/>E, <graphic url="NS6_sym13.jpg"/>, <graphic url="NS6_sym14.jpg"/>, <graphic url="NS6_sym15.jpg"/>, <graphic url="NS6_sym12.jpg"/>, <graphic url="NS6_sym17.jpg"/> and <graphic url="NS6_sym18.jpg"/>. The first of these, NO, we have met previously and over an extended period. His name is found on the series with <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q165023">Nike</name> for its symbol, on the chimaera group, and on those with Elpis, the aphlaston and the cornucopiae.</p>
                  <p>In two of these (Elpis, cornucopiae), his are the only initials found so far. For the others, he shares responsibilities with one (<name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q165023">Nike</name>, chimaera) or with three others (aphlaston). The significance of this is not clear. What historical data concerning <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_sicyon">Sicyon</name> we have, records constant factional strife and NO's name on widely separated issues is possibly to be explained as a consequence of such party politics. The absence of connection between symbol and magistrate calls for note. NO has two pairs of dies. No mulings have been found. <graphic url="NS6_sym16.jpg"/>E, the second of the
<pb n="32"/>
magistrates listed, has these letters joined, with a peculiar stroke preceding the theta. There is a considerable increase in the scale of the figure of <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q34201">Zeus</name>. As with the dies of NO, BAΣIΛEΩΣ is found in the exergue of the first reverse. For the other two, and for the rest of this series and for those which follow, this title no longer occurs. <graphic url="NS6_sym16.jpg"/>E uses three pairs of dies. Any attempt to see in this a break with <name type="pname" corresp="#nomisma_antigonus_ii">Antigonus Gonatas</name> must also answer the query "Why, then, did the use of <name type="place">Macedon</name>ian types continue?" Possibly one of the tyrants mentioned by Plutarch may have been responsible for omitting BAΣIΛEΩΣ.</p>
                  <p>The monogram for HEPA . . . takes three forms, <graphic url="NS6_sym13.jpg"/>, <graphic url="NS6_sym10.jpg"/> and <graphic url="NS6_sym11.jpg"/>. We cannot be sure that it is the same as the HP and <graphic url="NS6_sym6.jpg"/> seen on the chimaera and aphlaston issues but it probably parallels the recurrence of the NO initials if this is the correct deduction. HEPA. . . employs more dies than any other of these six magistrates, at least four obverses, but no less than fourteen reverses. On three reverse dies, we find the large Σ to be discussed in connection with the next magistrate, <graphic url="NS6_sym12.jpg"/>. Die A88 is given hard usage; seven reverses are coupled with it, and A89 is used with three or four dies (No. 49.2 seems to be the same or a recutting of the reverse of 49.1, with Σ added).</p>
                  <p>No. 49.1 bears the monogram <graphic url="NS6_sym12.jpg"/> beneath the throne. No. 49.2 which has the same obverse, may be identical as to reverse also. It is encrusted so that it is difficult to be certain. But even though otherwise the same, a large Σ has been added in front of the youthful figure in the 1. field. This, as we have seen, is found on Nos. 50.1 and 50.2 but not elsewhere on the coinage. It can hardly be interpreted as other than the initial of <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_sicyon">Sicyon</name>. It seems independent of the symbol-figure.</p>
                  <p>
                     <graphic url="NS6_sym17.jpg"/> has been found on two reverse dies, which show a common obverse, and the last magistrate's name, ΔI, is found on a single die.</p>
                  <p>The symbol, a youth holding a long fillet, has been mentioned in connection with the initial issue, and the conclusion was that their only connection rests in the fact that both were struck at <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_sicyon">Sicyon</name>. The varied positions leave no doubt that the intent is to represent a figure in action, but there is no agreement as to the significance of this action. On five or six of the reverses, a bird (dove?) appears flying above the figure and like the large initial Σ, this connotes <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_sicyon">Sicyon</name>. On three others, a wreath occupies the same position. A bird also appears beneath the throne on Nos. 45.1–3. The fillet seems to be an enlarged lustration fillet and clearly shows a terminal tassel.</p>
                  <p>Such a lengthy fillet would have to be especially prepared, and such a preparation would suggest that its use was ritualistic. Since the dove was the civic badge used extensively on the <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_sicyon">Sicyon</name> coinage, it is tempting to see a connection of the youth and his fillet with the bird above, but, as we have seen, a bird also occurs beneath the throne on three reverses, obviously with no relation to the youth. The wreath might indicate that the youth officiating in this suggested ceremonial had been a victor in the games, and chosen for that reason. The enigma must be left unsolved.</p>
                  <pb n="33"/>
                  <p>The <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q165023">Nike</name> finials to the throne of <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q34201">Zeus</name> are sometimes present, sometimes lacking. Another detail deserves attention. There are 21 ±1 varieties recorded for this symbol; six of these are represented in the <name type="pname" corresp="#numismatics_newell">Newell</name> Collection and two others in the collection of Sir <name type="pname" corresp="#viaf_65453680">Ronald Storrs</name>. Many of these are of a superior state of preservation. One of the finest of <name type="pname">Mr. Newell's</name> specimens was once in the Prince Waldeck Collection (No. 54.1). It shows clearly a detail which, because its occurrence here can be fixed as before 251 B. C., may have usefulness in dating its introduction elsewhere. The enlargement (Plate XVIII) shows that the legs of the throne are carved with tiny sphinxes. On this specimen they face outward; on Nos. 55.1 and 55.2, the sphinx on the r. leg faces to 1. When a coin is worn, as is No. 52.1, it is almost impossible to be sure which way it does face. As will be seen, this "convention," for such it seems to become at other mints, lasted for but five dies at <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_sicyon">Sicyon</name>.</p>
               </div3>
               <div3 xml:id="d1e5594" type="subsection">
                  <head>
                     <name type="pname">
                        <hi rend="smallcaps">Athena</hi>
                     </name> III (Nos. 59–62; Pl. XVI).</head>
                  <p>The <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q37122">Athena</name> on this group differs from those which have preceded (Pls. XII–XIII). Here, she is trailing her spear, and on it a tiny owl is perched. Helmet and shield are clear. The figure is three-quarters facing (See Plate XVIII). Three magistrates officiate, ΔE, <graphic url="NS6_sym16.jpg"/>E and OA. The last-named we have met previously (No. 37) and there also associated with an <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q37122">Athena</name> for symbol. There is, however, the difference in scale to which allusion has been made and <name type="pname">Mr. Newell's</name> placement is supported by the huge eagle and the position of the spear. ΔE is represented by two reverses and a single obverse which is taken over by and used with four more reverses. On No. 60.1, the symbol is small and dainty and the die-workmanship is excellent, but for No. 60.6, all details including both symbol and Nikes are increased in scale and the die-cutting is decidedly inferior.</p>
                  <p>A variant <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q37122">Athena</name>, with helmet and trailing spear, but with shield shown in the full round rather than in perspective as heretofore is connected with AE as magistrate in a single pair of dies of only fair quality.</p>
               </div3>
               <div3 xml:id="d1e5618" type="subsection">
                  <head>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">Dioscuroi</hi> (No. 63; Pl. XVII).</head>
                  <p>This beautiful tetradrachm with the mounted Dioscuroi for symbol and AAE as magistrate is represented by a single pair of dies. The absence of the exergual BAΣIAEΩΣ and the size of the Nikes confirm its placement here. Thirty-three specimens are reported to have been found in the Patras Hoard (cf. later discussion of hoards) — the ones traced number only three!</p>
               </div3>
               <div3 xml:id="d1e5625" type="subsection">
                  <head>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">Trident</hi> I (No. 58; Pl. XVI).</head>
                  <p>Two reverses and a single obverse die represent the tenure of the magistracy for coining by <graphic url="NS6_sym19.jpg"/>. The symbol, an ornate trident, occurs later—with ΔA and <graphic url="NS6_sym16.jpg"/>E. On these reverse dies, the throne supports large, almost obtrusive Nikes. The <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q165023">Nike</name> at the left is slightly the larger—the companion is crowded between the head of <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q34201">Zeus</name> and the tip of the sceptre.</p>
                  <pb n="34"/>
                  <p>
                     <name type="pname">Mr. Newell's</name> placement of this type in the series is ambiguous. The treatment of the jaw of the lion-skin on the obverse (cf. with No. 59.1), and of details such as the foot-stool and the <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q165023">Nike</name> figures of the reverse have necessitated its being located before the <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q37122">Athena</name> Group.</p>
               </div3>
               <div3 xml:id="d1e5653" type="subsection">
                  <head>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">Trident</hi> II (Nos. 64–66; Pl. XVII)</head>
                  <p>The vertical trident with tips upward, seems separated in time from Nos. 58.1–2. ΔA has not served as magistrate previously—here, he has one obverse and two reverse dies. <graphic url="NS6_sym16.jpg"/>E occurs in the preceding group as well as with the youth holding a fillet. He owns to two obverse dies. Compare also the tetradrachm C on Pl. XIII, where there is very great disparity between the workmanship of obverse and reverse. This variety, like the <name type="place">Olympian Hoard</name> pieces shown on the same plate, comes from a <name type="place">Peloponnesian Hoard</name> of which only a small section was available for study. The style of the obverse die is utterly different from anything in the entire coinage of <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_sicyon">Sicyon</name>. The reverse, too, is strange — note the treatment of the hair of <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q34201">Zeus</name> and the misunderstood cutting of the throne-back. The weight is 16.56.</p>
               </div3>
               <div3 xml:id="d1e5674" type="subsection">
                  <head>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">Fulmen</hi> (Nos. 67–70; Pl. XVII).</head>
                  <p>The fulmen group, apparently the last of the issues with <name type="pname" corresp="#nomisma_alexander_iii">Alexander</name> types for <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_sicyon">Sicyon</name>, has for magistrates ΦI and AP. On No. 69.2, the letter <graphic url="NS6_sym16.jpg"/> appears to the left of the fulmen, having been added to the die used with No. 69.1. The second magistrate, AP takes over two obverse dies which had been used by his predecessor, but with them he employs but a single reverse. This reverse is doubly remarkable. The die-break which connects the brow of <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q34201">Zeus</name> with the wing of <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q165023">Nike</name> is barely visible on No. 68.1; whereas on No. 70.1 it extends from the left rim of the die to the initial stroke of the A of AAEΞANΔPOY. The exergue provides further peculiarities. The earlier state shows the letter <graphic url="NS6_sym16.jpg"/> below the cross-stroke of an alpha or possibly a lambda. On No. 70.1, we find what looks like AA, with the cross-stroke of the second A fainter than the first, so faint as to suggest that it may have been cut mistakenly and rectified by the cutting of the first letter's cross-stroke.</p>
                  <p>The only drachm for the entire coinage is reproduced on Pl. XIII from a cast. It is in the collection of the <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_athens">Athens</name> Museum. The symbol is a fulmen, closely similar to that of the tetradrachm on Pl. XVII. The monogram or letter beneath the throne is apparently encrusted, in consequence it is difficult to state whether or not it consists of more than the letter Γ which does seem clear. A <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q165023">Nike</name> to the left of the head of <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q34201">Zeus</name> is discernible. Drachms with <name type="pname">Alexander's</name> types at this period are exceedingly rare for Greece proper.</p>
               </div3>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d1e5712" type="chapter">
            <head>THE <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_sicyon">Sicyon</name> HOARDS</head>
            <p>There are four hoards which are of importance in dating the <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_sicyon">Sicyon</name>
               <name type="pname">Alexanders</name>.</p>
            <p>I. <hi rend="italic">The <name type="place">Demanhur Hoard</name>
               </hi> has already been mentioned as fixing the date of Group</p>
            <p>I. This Egyptian hoard was discovered in 1905. It received careful study by
<pb n="35"/>
               <name type="pname">Mr. Newell</name> who revised a first publication (1912) in a more detailed consideration in 1923<ref target="#CH4-n1a">1</ref> Here, it is shown that this great treasure must have been deposited in the earth in 318 B. C. Consequently, the coins in our Group I, since the latest of them were all represented in this hoard, must be dated before 318 B. C.</p>
            <p>II. <hi rend="italic">The <name type="pname">Armenak Hoard</name>,</hi> 1927 (Noe 67). This hoard, summarized in a note supplied by <name type="pname">Mr. Newell</name> in the second edition of the <hi rend="italic">Bibliography of Greek Coin Hoards</hi>
               <ref target="#CH4-n2a">2</ref> is mentioned in <hi rend="italic">Eastern <name type="place" corresp="#pleiades_45635759">Seleucid Mints</name>,</hi>
               <ref target="#CH4-n3a">3</ref> p. 23, with added data. <name type="pname">Mr. Newel's</name> date of burial, c. 280 B. C., must have received careful checking for this entry, and the large number of Lysimachus tetradrachms which it contained, none of which were posthumous issues, is a basis for this dating. This hoard contained <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_sicyon">Sicyon</name> tetradrachms with the symbols Elpis, aphlaston and cornucopiae (Nos. 26.13, 29.5, 35.6). Since these must come before c. 280 B. C., the aphlaston type and the cornucopiae may have some implication of Demetrios Poliorcetes' repossession of <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_sicyon">Sicyon</name> in 290. <name type="pname">Mr. Newell</name> assigns gold and silver issues in the name of <name type="pname">Demetrius</name> to the <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_sicyon">Sicyon</name> mint for this year.</p>
            <p>The aphlaston with its usual connotation of a naval victory has an allusion that is obvious.</p>
            <p>III. <hi rend="italic">The <name type="place">Olympia Hoard</name>
               </hi> provides more complications than helpfulness for this study. Found in 1922 and published by <name type="pname">Mr. Newell</name> in 1929, it contained along with coins of Elis, <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_athens">Athens</name>, <name type="place">Aegina</name>, <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_boeotia">Boeotia</name>, <name type="pname" corresp="#nomisma_lysimachus">Lysimachus</name> and the <name type="pname">Ptolemies I</name> and II, sixteen tetradrachms of <name type="pname" corresp="#nomisma_alexander_iii">Alexander</name> and five drachms. Among these were Nos. 40.6, 41.2 and 42.1 (Nos. 69, 68 and 72 of <name type="pname">Mr. Newell's</name> list of coins in this hoard). Of these three, 42.1 (72) was unpublished, and <name type="pname">Mr. Newell</name> comments on the lateness of the digamma beneath the throne. He also pointed out that two other tetradrachms—one (No. 70; our A on Pl. XIII), with a bee for its symbol and ΠY beneath the throne, and another (No. 71; our B on Pl. XIII), with a charioteer in a biga and <graphic url="NS6_sym23.jpg"/> beneath, and with Ξ beneath the throne, have obverse dies identical with our No. 40.6, and these he suggested may belong to another mint—possibly, Argos. Of these three coins, A alone has BAΣIΛEΩΣ in the exergue, and although No. 40.6 has the victories on the throne, neither of the other two does. The tickets for these coins bear no indication that <name type="pname">Mr. Newell</name> had reached a more definite conclusion as to their assignment after publishing this hoard. No. 73 in this same list adds further confusion. Its symbol would align it with our No. 17.1, but comparison shows that it does not belong there, for this star is seven-pointed while that of 17.1 has eight rays. Furthermore, this tetradrachm has the Nikes on the throne, and their introduction had not taken place when 17.1 was struck. <name type="pname">Mr. Newell</name> did not include this with his <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_sicyon">Sicyon</name> pieces. If his conclusion be accepted, we must also concede that tetradrachms with the <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q165023">Nike</name> finials are not necessarily all <name type="place">Sicyonian</name>. <name type="pname">Mr. Newell's</name> date, 235–225 B. C., confirms the evidence of the Patras Hoard as to the lateness of these <name type="place">Sicyonian</name> issues.</p>
            <pb n="36"/>
            <p>IV. <hi rend="italic">The Patras Hoard.</hi> This important hoard is described in 1852 in a letter from <name type="pname">Mr. C. T. Newton</name> published in the <hi rend="italic">Numismatic Chronicle</hi> in 1854. It may have been on its evidence that <name type="pname">Müller</name> correctly assigned many of the <name type="pname" corresp="#nomisma_alexander_iii">Alexander</name>-type tetradrachms to <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_sicyon">Sicyon</name> since his publication was printed in 1855. If his attribution was independent, this hoard provided valuable confirmation. <name type="pname">Mr. Newton's</name> careful description enables a fairly close identification, and a list of the varieties follows:</p>
            <table rows="17" cols="3">
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Symbol</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Numbers</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Specimens</hi>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Youth with fillet</cell>
                  <cell>46.1 or 45</cell>
                  <cell>10</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>45.2</cell>
                  <cell>1</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>47.1 (?)</cell>
                  <cell>1</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>?</cell>
                  <cell>1</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>50.1–2</cell>
                  <cell>1</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>55.1–3</cell>
                  <cell>1</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Trident (horizontal)</cell>
                  <cell>58.1–2</cell>
                  <cell>9</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>?</cell>
                  <cell>1</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Trident (points upward)</cell>
                  <cell>65.1</cell>
                  <cell>2</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q37122">Athena</name>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>59.1–2</cell>
                  <cell>21</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>60.1–6</cell>
                  <cell>22</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>?</cell>
                  <cell>1</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>40.1–6</cell>
                  <cell>1</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Dioscuroi mounted</cell>
                  <cell>63.1</cell>
                  <cell>33</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Fulmen</cell>
                  <cell>70.1 (?)</cell>
                  <cell>1</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>68.1</cell>
                  <cell>3</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>67.1–5</cell>
                  <cell>7</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>The foregoing are described as very well preserved. Among the pieces less well preserved, one with a "club" for symbol and ΦI beneath throne <hi rend="italic">might</hi> be a mistaken description for Nos. 67.1–5, although a piece listed as without ΦI makes one hesitate. Two pieces of Philip Aridaeus are probably from <name type="pname">Babylon</name>. A single piece with aphlaston and monogram is probably from the Amphipoiss mint. Other pieces may have been for Miletus,<ref target="#CH4-n1b">1</ref> Pella (?) and Amphipois.<ref target="#CH4-n2b">2</ref>
            </p>
            <p>A tetradrachm of Seleucus, struck at Ecbatana, is dated by <name type="pname">Mr. Newell</name> c. 280.</p>
            <p>In accordance with the accepted interpretation of hoards, we should expect to find the most numerous of the varieties also the latest of the issues. Hence, the <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q37122">Athena</name> group would be preceded by the issue with the Dioscuroi and that, in turn, by the youth with the fillet. And, broadly speaking, this is the way that <name type="pname">Mr. Newell</name> arranged them, for the fulmen and trident groups are probably shorter issues whose representation would therefore be less numerous.</p>
            <p>If the number of tetradrachms with the Dioscuroi symbols (No. 63) is correctly recorded,—i. e., 33 (one suspects dittography)—we have an interesting illustration of the disappearance of ancient coins, for <name type="pname">Mr. Newell</name> succeeded in locating only three specimens of this variety.</p>
            <pb n="37"/>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH4-n1a">
               <seg type="note-symbol">1</seg>
               <p>Numismatic Notes and Monographs No. 19.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH4-n2a">
               <seg type="note-symbol">2</seg>
               <p>Numismatic Notes and Monographs No. 78.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH4-n3a">
               <seg type="note-symbol">3</seg>
               <p>Numismatic Studies No. 1.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH4-n1b">
               <seg type="note-symbol">1</seg>
               <p>
                  <name type="pname">Newton's</name> I, <hi rend="italic">Nu</hi>m<hi rend="italic">. Chron.,</hi> 1854, p. 34.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH4-n2b">
               <seg type="note-symbol">2</seg>
               <p>
                  <name type="pname">Newtons</name> VI, <hi rend="italic">ibid.,</hi> p. 35.</p>
            </note>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d1e6061" type="chapter">
            <head>THE <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_sicyon">Sicyon</name> SYMBOLS</head>
            <p>Plate XVIII has been arranged to emphasize the difference between the subsidiary symbols which appear on the <name type="pname">Alexandrine</name> tetradrachms of <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_sicyon">Sicyon</name> and those of other mints striking in this period. These symbols have a closer similarity to those which appear contemporaneously on the staters of Corinth than to the symbols on other mintings of <name type="pname">Alexanders</name>.</p>
            <p>The similarity of the figure of <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q122248">Heracles</name> (No. 27) to the Farnese Hercules has already been noted. The form of many of the other symbols supports the suggestion that they too may have been derived from statues at <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_sicyon">Sicyon</name>. To enable the reader to judge more effectively, these enlargements have been brought together. There has been no attempt to assocatte these figures with known statues—this is clearly outside the limits set for this work. Discussions of the references to temples and shrines at <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_sicyon">Sicyon</name> by Pausanias, and controversies regarding the work at <name type="pname" corresp="#viaf_297421082">Lysippus</name> and of the school of sculptors located in this city, would make a sizable list. Nor has any effort been made to link any of these symbols with the tyrants whose names are given by Plutarch<ref target="#CH6-n1">1</ref> in his biography of <name type="pname">Aratus</name>.</p>
            <p>The general nature of these symbols is civic rather than personal, a condition which might be expected during control of <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_sicyon">Sicyon</name> by tyrants whose fealty to <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_macedon">Macedon</name> during the rule of <name type="pname" corresp="#nomisma_antigonus_ii">Antigonus Gonatas</name> must have flowed and ebbed with his military successes and setbacks. <name type="pname">Adherence</name> to his cause may have been induced from time to time by concession, but the balance between the absentee-overlordshp of <name type="pname">Antigonus</name> and the tolerance of the citizens must have made the lot of any of these tyrants far from happy.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d1e6116" type="chapter">
            <head>CONCLUSION</head>
            <p>Assigning a date to the final issue of <name type="pname" corresp="#nomisma_alexander_iii">Alexander</name> types at <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_sicyon">Sicyon</name> presents difficulties. From Plutarchss "Life of <name type="pname">Aratus</name>" we learn the names of four individuals prominent in the affairs of <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_sicyon">Sicyon</name> previous to its joining the <name type="place">Achaean League</name>. Two of these, Timokeides and Kleinias (the father of <name type="pname">Aratus</name>) were chosen chief magistrates under a democratic government after the murder of <name type="pname">Kleon</name>, their tyrant predecessor. During the year 264,<ref target="#CH7-n2">2</ref> the democracy was overthrown by <name type="pname">Abantidas</name> who continued as tyrant until a short time before the entrance of <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_sicyon">Sicyon</name> into the League (c. 251). It is commonly believed that <name type="pname" corresp="#nomisma_antigonus_ii">Antigonus Gonatas</name> maintained his control of <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_sicyon">Sicyon</name> and of other Greek cities in the Peloponnesus either through garrisons of <name type="place">Macedonian</name> soldiers or by subsidizing tyrants who relied on mercenaries. Professor <name type="pname">Tarn</name>, however, cites the tolerance by <name type="pname">Antigonus</name> of this brief democratic control between c. 274 and 264 as an indication "that he sought no conquests in the Peloponnesus, and was not establishing tyrants for amusement."<ref target="#CH7-n3">3</ref>
            </p>
            <pb n="38"/>
            <p>But even if <name type="pname">Antigonus</name> did acquessce in the <name type="place">Sicyonian</name> democracy, it is difficult to believe that there would have been a coinage of <name type="place">Macedonian</name> types during its brief period of control, while for the tyrants it is much easier to think that acceptance of subsidies from <name type="pname">Antigonus</name> may have involved the continuance of the customary <name type="pname" corresp="#nomisma_alexander_iii">Alexander</name> types as an oblique acknowledgment of the connection. Reasonable though such a gesture may seem, we must admit that the coinage of <name type="pname">Alexandrine</name> tetradrachms may have stopped with the establishment of the democracy, and possibly even before. The coins on the plates from No. 43 onward are fairly homogeneous and seem uninterrupted. Such details as the dropping of the Nikes from the finials of the throne-back (Cf. Pls. XIV and XV) and their subsequent replacement can hardly be given significance in this connection. The symbol youth with fillet is a distinctively local symbol and might be considered appropriate for the period of the democracy were it not that the main type is <name type="place">Macedonian</name>.</p>
            <p>
               <name type="pname">Mr. Newell</name> seems to have been convinced that the coinage of <name type="pname" corresp="#nomisma_alexander_iii">Alexander</name> types at <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_sicyon">Sicyon</name> continued until the union with the <name type="place">Achaean League.</name>
               <ref target="#CH7-n1">1</ref> If this was his considered opinion, a re-interpretation of the subsidiary symbols for this coinage would seem to be involved. We have noted that these symbols are little short of subsidiary <hi rend="italic">types</hi>. Not only do we have the youth with fillet as a type for contemporary bronze coins of the city, but the dove, which is also unmistakably <name type="place">Sicyonian</name>, occurs in a wreath (No. 19), as well as in conjunction with the youth with fillet (Nos. 51–54, Pl. XV). The aphlaston appears on the coinage as a symbol at a time which makes its connection with <name type="pname">Demetrius Poliorcetes</name> a probable rather than merely a possible one. Many of these symbols have little of a personal nature—the figures of <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q37122">Athena</name>, Demeter, <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q122248">Heracles</name>, Elpis and <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q165023">Nike</name> could hardly be personal badges. The magisterial responsibility for the coinage is indicated by monograms or initial letters. Possibly the <name type="pname">Heracles-Zeus</name> type was no longer considered <name type="place">Macedonian</name> and the original Pan-Hellencc significance may have been accepted by <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_sicyon">Sicyon</name> and other <name type="place">Peloponnesian</name> cities to an extent greater than we have realized. How shall we explain the adoption of <name type="pname" corresp="#nomisma_alexander_iii">Alexander</name> types by the Aetolian League both for their gold staters and for the obverse of the silver issue commemorating their victory over the Celts? Unless some other explanation can be found, we must conclude that the coinage of <name type="pname" corresp="#nomisma_alexander_iii">Alexander</name> types at <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_sicyon">Sicyon</name> may have stopped <hi rend="italic">before</hi> 251. This would not affect the order in the arrangement here submitted; it would compress the coinage into a shorter interval of time.</p>
            <pb n="39"/>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH6-n1">
               <seg type="note-symbol">1</seg>
               <p>Plutarch, Loeb ed., Vol. 11, p. 5.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH7-n1">
               <seg type="note-symbol">1</seg>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="place" corresp="#nomisma_olympia">Olympia</name>
                  </hi>, p. 20.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH7-n2">
               <seg type="note-symbol">2</seg>
               <p>The date given by <name type="pname">W. W. Tarn</name>, <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="pname">Antigonos Gonatas</name>
                  </hi> (<name type="place" corresp="#geonames_2640729">Oxford</name>, 1913) p. 361.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH7-n3">
               <seg type="note-symbol">3</seg>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">
                     <name type="pname">Antigonos Gonatas</name>,</hi> p. 278.</p>
            </note>
         </div1>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div1 xml:id="d1e6294" type="backma">
            <head>INDEX OF SYMBOLS</head>
            <list>
               <item>Amphora with ΔE, No. 32</item>
               <item>Aphlaston with ΔE, No. 30; with ΔO, No. 29; with HP or <graphic url="NS6_sym6.jpg"/>, No. 31; with NO, No. 28</item>
               <item>
                  <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q37122">Athena</name> 1. with ΔE, No. 59; with <graphic url="NS6_sym16.jpg"/>E, No. 60; with OΛ, No. 61; with round shield, with AE, No. 62</item>
               <item>
                  <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q37122">Athena</name>, facing, with OΛ in wreath, No. 37; with OΛY, No. 38</item>
               <item>
                  <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q37122">Athena</name> Nikephoros, with OΛY, No. 39</item>
               <item>
                  <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q37122">Athena</name> Promachos, brandishing spear, No. 41; with EY, No. 40; with F, No. 42</item>
               <item>Barley ear, No. 15</item>
               <item>Bird with youth and <graphic url="NS6_sym14.jpg"/>, No. 51; with <graphic url="NS6_sym16.jpg"/>E or <graphic url="NS6_sym8.jpg"/>, No. 53; with <graphic url="NS6_sym13.jpg"/>, Nos. 45, 54; with <graphic url="NS6_sym15.jpg"/>, No. 52</item>
               <item>Chimaera r., with <graphic url="NS6_sym6.jpg"/>, No. 25; with NO, No. 24</item>
               <item>Cornucopaee with NO, No. 35; with wreath enclosing dove and Δ, No. 19</item>
               <item>Crescent with youth and <graphic url="NS6_sym13.jpg"/>, No. 48</item>
               <item>Demeter(?) 1., with EXE or EX, No. 36</item>
               <item>Dioscuroi 1., mounted, with AΛE, No. 63</item>
               <item>Dove in wreath with Δ and cornucopiae, No. 19</item>
               <item>Elpis 1. with NO. No. 26</item>
               <item>Fulmen, vertical, with A, No. 6; with <graphic url="NS6_sym1.jpg"/>, Nos. 7, 8; with <graphic url="NS6_sym20.jpg"/> and <graphic url="NS6_sym21.jpg"/>, No. 70; with <graphic url="NS6_sym20.jpg"/> and <graphic url="NS6_sym1.jpg"/> No. 68; with Φ1, Nos. 67, 69.1; with Φ1 and <graphic url="NS6_sym16.jpg"/>, No. 69.2.</item>
               <item>Goat's head 1., No. 16</item>
               <item>
                  <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q122248">Heracles</name> r. with <graphic url="NS6_sym7.jpg"/>, No. 27</item>
               <item>Horse's head 1., No. 33; with ΔE, No. 34</item>
               <item>
                  <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q165023">Nike</name> in r. hand of <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q37122">Athena</name> with OΛY, No. 39</item>
               <item>
                  <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q165023">Nike</name> r. extending laurel wreath with <graphic url="NS6_sym5.jpg"/>, No. 22; with NO, No. 23</item>
               <item>Olive leaf with youth, suppliant, and <graphic url="NS6_sym1.jpg"/>. No. 10</item>
               <item>Rudder with youth, suppliant, Nos. 4, 5</item>
               <item>Star, eight-pointed, with <graphic url="NS6_sym5.jpg"/>, No. 17; with <graphic url="NS6_sym5.jpg"/> and <graphic url="NS6_sym3.jpg"/>, No. 18</item>
               <item>Trident 1. with <graphic url="NS6_sym19.jpg"/>, No. 58</item>
               <item>Trident, upwards, with ΛA, No. 64; with Λ and <graphic url="NS6_sym16.jpg"/>E, No. 66; with <graphic url="NS6_sym16.jpg"/>E, No. 65</item>
               <item>Wreath with Δ, Nos. 20, 21; with youth and <graphic url="NS6_sym13.jpg"/>, No. 55</item>
               <item>Wreath enclosing dove, with Δ and cornucopiae, No. 19</item>
               <item>Wreath enclosing OΛ with <name type="pname" corresp="#wikidata_Q37122">Athena</name>, facing, No. 37</item>
               <pb n="40"/>
               <item>Youth 1. with <graphic url="NS6_sym18.jpg"/>, No. 57; with <graphic url="NS6_sym17.jpg"/>, No. 56; with <graphic url="NS6_sym8.jpg"/>, No. 44; with <graphic url="NS6_sym13.jpg"/>, No. 46; with <graphic url="NS6_sym12.jpg"/>, No. 49.1; with <graphic url="NS6_sym11.jpg"/>, No. 47; with ∑ and <graphic url="NS6_sym12.jpg"/> (?), No. 49.2; with ∑ and <graphic url="NS6_sym13.jpg"/>, No. 50; with crescent and <graphic url="NS6_sym13.jpg"/>, No. 48; with wreath and <graphic url="NS6_sym13.jpg"/>, No. 55; with bird and <graphic url="NS6_sym14.jpg"/>, No. 51 ; with bird and <graphic url="NS6_sym13.jpg"/>, Nos. 45, 54; with bird and <graphic url="NS6_sym10.jpg"/>, No. 45.2; with bird and <graphic url="NS6_sym15.jpg"/>, No. 52; with bird and <graphic url="NS6_sym16.jpg"/>E or <graphic url="NS6_sym8.jpg"/>, No. 53.</item>
               <item>Youth r. with NO, No. 43</item>
               <item>Youth 1., suppliant, Nos. 1–3, 12–14</item>
               <item>Youth 1., suppliant, with rudder, Nos. 4, 5; with <graphic url="NS6_sym1.jpg"/>, Nos. 9, 11; with <graphic url="NS6_sym1.jpg"/> and olive leaf, No. 10</item>
            </list>
            <pb n="41"/>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d1e6478" type="backma">
            <head>INDEX OF LETTERS AND MONOGRAMS</head>
            <p>A No. 6</p>
            <p>AE No. 62</p>
            <p>AΛ No. 70</p>
            <p>AΛE No. 63</p>
            <p>
               <graphic url="NS6_sym1.jpg"/> No. 68</p>
            <p>
               <graphic url="NS6_sym20.jpg"/> Nos. 68, 70</p>
            <p>
               <graphic url="NS6_sym7.jpg"/> No. 27</p>
            <p>
               <graphic url="NS6_sym15.jpg"/> No. 52</p>
            <p>
               <graphic url="NS6_sym3.jpg"/> No. 18</p>
            <p>Δ Nos. 19, 20, 21</p>
            <p>ΔA No. 64</p>
            <p>ΔE Nos. 30, 32, 34, 59</p>
            <p>
               <graphic url="NS6_sym18.jpg"/> No. 57</p>
            <p>
               <graphic url="NS6_sym4.jpg"/> Nos. 18, 22</p>
            <p>
               <graphic url="NS6_sym2.jpg"/> Nos. 17, 18</p>
            <p>ΔO No. 29</p>
            <p>EY No. 40</p>
            <p>EX, EXE No. 36</p>
            <p>F No. 42</p>
            <p>HP No. 31</p>
            <p>
               <graphic url="NS6_sym6.jpg"/> Nos. 25, 31</p>
            <p>
               <graphic url="NS6_sym13.jpg"/> Nos. 45, 46, 48, 50, 54, 55</p>
            <p>
               <graphic url="NS6_sym11.jpg"/> No. 47</p>
            <p>
               <graphic url="NS6_sym10.jpg"/> No. 45.2</p>
            <p>
               <graphic url="NS6_sym16.jpg"/> No. 69.2</p>
            <p>
               <graphic url="NS6_sym8.jpg"/> Nos. 44, 53</p>
            <p>
               <graphic url="NS6_sym16.jpg"/>E Nos. 53, 60, 65, 66</p>
            <p>
               <graphic url="NS6_sym14.jpg"/> No. 51</p>
            <p>Λ No. 66</p>
            <p>
               <graphic url="NS6_sym1.jpg"/> Nos. 7, 8, 9, 10, 11</p>
            <p>
               <graphic url="NS6_sym17.jpg"/> No. 56</p>
            <p>NO Nos. 23, 24, 26, 28, 35, 43</p>
            <p>OΛ Nos. 37, 61</p>
            <p>OΛY Nos. 38, 39</p>
            <p>
               <graphic url="NS6_sym19.jpg"/> No. 58</p>
            <p>∑ Nos. 49.2, 50</p>
            <p>
               <graphic url="NS6_sym12.jpg"/> No. 49</p>
            <p>ΦI Nos. 67, 69</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d1e6580" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>PLATES</head>
            <pb/>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e6585" type="backma">
               <head>PLATE I</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-2">
                  <head>PLATE I - 1.1a</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_041a.jpg"/>
                  <p>1.1a</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-3">
                  <head>PLATE I - 1.1b</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_041b.jpg"/>
                  <p>1.1b</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-4">
                  <head>PLATE I - 2.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_041c.jpg"/>
                  <p>2.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-5">
                  <head>PLATE I - 3.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_041d.jpg"/>
                  <p>3.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-6">
                  <head>PLATE I - 3.2</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_041e.jpg"/>
                  <p>3.2</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-7">
                  <head>PLATE I - 3.3</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_041f.jpg"/>
                  <p>3.3</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-8">
                  <head>PLATE I - 3.4</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_041g.jpg"/>
                  <p>3.4</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-9">
                  <head>PLATE I - 3.5</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_041h.jpg"/>
                  <p>3.5</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-10">
                  <head>PLATE I - 3.6</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_041i.jpg"/>
                  <p>3.6</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-11">
                  <head>PLATE I - 3.7</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_041j.jpg"/>
                  <p>3.7</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-12">
                  <head>PLATE I - 4.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_041k.jpg"/>
                  <p>4.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-13">
                  <head>PLATE I - 3.8</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_041l.jpg"/>
                  <p>3.8</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-14">
                  <head>PLATE I - 4.2</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_041m.jpg"/>
                  <p>4.2</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-15">
                  <head>PLATE I - 5.1a</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_041n.jpg"/>
                  <p>5.1a</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-16">
                  <head>PLATE I - 5.1b</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_041o.jpg"/>
                  <p>5.1b</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-17">
                  <graphic url="NS6_041p.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e6681" type="backma">
               <pb/>
               <head>PLATE II</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-18">
                  <head>PLATE II - 6.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_042a.jpg"/>
                  <p>6.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-19">
                  <head>PLATE II - 7.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_042b.jpg"/>
                  <p>7.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-20">
                  <head>PLATE II - 7.2</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_042c.jpg"/>
                  <p>7.2</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-21">
                  <head>PLATE II - 7.3</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_042d.jpg"/>
                  <p>7.3</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-22">
                  <head>PLATE II - 7.4</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_042e.jpg"/>
                  <p>7.4</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-23">
                  <head>PLATE II - 7.5</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_042f.jpg"/>
                  <p>7.5</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-24">
                  <head>PLATE II - 7.6</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_042g.jpg"/>
                  <p>7.6</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-25">
                  <head>PLATE II - 7.7</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_042h.jpg"/>
                  <p>7.7</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-26">
                  <head>PLATE II - 7.8</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_042i.jpg"/>
                  <p>7.8</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-27">
                  <head>PLATE II - 7.9</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_042j.jpg"/>
                  <p>7.9</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-28">
                  <head>PLATE II - 7.10</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_042k.jpg"/>
                  <p>7.10</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-29">
                  <head>PLATE II - 7.11</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_042l.jpg"/>
                  <p>7.11</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-30">
                  <head>PLATE II - 7.12</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_042m.jpg"/>
                  <p>7.12</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-31">
                  <head>PLATE II - 7.13</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_042n.jpg"/>
                  <p>7.13</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-32">
                  <head>PLATE II - 7.14</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_042o.jpg"/>
                  <p>7.14</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-33">
                  <head>PLATE II - 7.15</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_042p.jpg"/>
                  <p>7.15</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-34">
                  <head>PLATE II - 7.16</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_042q.jpg"/>
                  <p>7.16</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-35">
                  <head>PLATE II - 7.17</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_042r.jpg"/>
                  <p>7.17</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-36">
                  <head>PLATE II - 8.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_042s.jpg"/>
                  <p>8.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-37">
                  <head>PLATE II - 9.1a</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_042t.jpg"/>
                  <p>9.1a</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-38">
                  <head>PLATE II - 9.1b</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_042u.jpg"/>
                  <p>9.1b</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-39">
                  <head>PLATE II - 9.2</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_042v.jpg"/>
                  <p>9.2</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-40">
                  <head>PLATE II - 10.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_042w.jpg"/>
                  <p>10.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-41">
                  <head>PLATE II - 11.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_042x.jpg"/>
                  <p>11.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-42">
                  <graphic url="NS6_042y.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e6833" type="backma">
               <pb/>
               <head>PLATE III</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-43">
                  <head>PLATE III - 12.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_043a.jpg"/>
                  <p>12.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-44">
                  <head>PLATE III - 13.1a</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_043b.jpg"/>
                  <p>13.1a</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-45">
                  <head>PLATE III - 3.1b</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_043c.jpg"/>
                  <p>3.1b</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-46">
                  <head>PLATE III - 3.2</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_043d.jpg"/>
                  <p>3.2</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-47">
                  <head>PLATE III - 4.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_043e.jpg"/>
                  <p>4.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-48">
                  <head>PLATE III - 4.2</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_043f.jpg"/>
                  <p>4.2</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-49">
                  <head>PLATE III - 4.3</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_043g.jpg"/>
                  <p>4.3</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-50">
                  <head>PLATE III - 4.4</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_043h.jpg"/>
                  <p>4.4</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-51">
                  <head>PLATE III - 4.5</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_043i.jpg"/>
                  <p>4.5</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-52">
                  <head>PLATE III - 4.6</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_043j.jpg"/>
                  <p>4.6</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-53">
                  <head>PLATE III - 4.7</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_043k.jpg"/>
                  <p>4.7</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-54">
                  <head>PLATE III - 15.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_043l.jpg"/>
                  <p>15.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-55">
                  <head>PLATE III - 16.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_043m.jpg"/>
                  <p>16.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-56">
                  <graphic url="NS6_043n.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e6918" type="backma">
               <pb/>
               <head>PLATE IV</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-57">
                  <head>PLATE IV - 17.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_044a.jpg"/>
                  <p>17.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-58">
                  <head>PLATE IV - 17.2</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_044b.jpg"/>
                  <p>17.2</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-59">
                  <head>PLATE IV - 17.3</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_044c.jpg"/>
                  <p>17.3</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-60">
                  <head>PLATE IV - 17.4</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_044d.jpg"/>
                  <p>17.4</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-61">
                  <head>PLATE IV - 17.5</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_044e.jpg"/>
                  <p>17.5</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-62">
                  <head>PLATE IV - 18.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_044f.jpg"/>
                  <p>18.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-63">
                  <head>PLATE IV - 18.2</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_044g.jpg"/>
                  <p>18.2</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-64">
                  <head>PLATE IV - 19.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_044h.jpg"/>
                  <p>19.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-65">
                  <head>PLATE IV - 20.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_044i.jpg"/>
                  <p>20.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-66">
                  <head>PLATE IV - 20.2</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_044j.jpg"/>
                  <p>20.2</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-67">
                  <head>PLATE IV - 20.3</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_044k.jpg"/>
                  <p>20.3</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-68">
                  <head>PLATE IV - 21.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_044l.jpg"/>
                  <p>21.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-69">
                  <head>PLATE IV - 21.2</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_044m.jpg"/>
                  <p>21.2</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-70">
                  <graphic url="NS6_044n.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e7003" type="backma">
               <pb/>
               <head>PLATE V</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-71">
                  <head>PLATE V - 22.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_045a.jpg"/>
                  <p>22.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-72">
                  <head>PLATE V - 22.2</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_045b.jpg"/>
                  <p>22.2</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-73">
                  <head>PLATE V - 22.3</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_045c.jpg"/>
                  <p>22.3</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-74">
                  <head>PLATE V - 22.4</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_045d.jpg"/>
                  <p>22.4</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-75">
                  <head>PLATE V - 22.5</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_045e.jpg"/>
                  <p>22.5</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-76">
                  <head>PLATE V - 22.6</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_045f.jpg"/>
                  <p>22.6</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-77">
                  <head>PLATE V - 22.7</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_045g.jpg"/>
                  <p>22.7</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-78">
                  <head>PLATE V - 22.8</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_045h.jpg"/>
                  <p>22.8</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-79">
                  <head>PLATE V - 23.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_045i.jpg"/>
                  <p>23.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-80">
                  <head>PLATE V - 23.2</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_045j.jpg"/>
                  <p>23.2</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-81">
                  <head>PLATE V - 23.3</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_045k.jpg"/>
                  <p>23.3</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-82">
                  <head>PLATE V - 23.4</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_045l.jpg"/>
                  <p>23.4</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-83">
                  <graphic url="NS6_045m.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e7082" type="backma">
               <pb/>
               <head>PLATE VI</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-84">
                  <head>PLATE VI - 24.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_046a.jpg"/>
                  <p>24.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-85">
                  <head>PLATE VI - 24.2</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_046b.jpg"/>
                  <p>24.2</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-86">
                  <head>PLATE VI - 24.3</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_046c.jpg"/>
                  <p>24.3</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-87">
                  <head>PLATE VI - 24.4</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_046d.jpg"/>
                  <p>24.4</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-88">
                  <head>PLATE VI - 24.5</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_046e.jpg"/>
                  <p>24.5</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-89">
                  <head>PLATE VI - 24.6</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_046f.jpg"/>
                  <p>24.6</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-90">
                  <head>PLATE VI - 24.7</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_046g.jpg"/>
                  <p>24.7</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-91">
                  <head>PLATE VI - 24.8</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_046h.jpg"/>
                  <p>24.8</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-92">
                  <head>PLATE VI - 25.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_046i.jpg"/>
                  <p>25.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-93">
                  <head>PLATE VI - 25.2</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_046j.jpg"/>
                  <p>25.2</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-94">
                  <head>PLATE VI - 25.3</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_046k.jpg"/>
                  <p>25.3</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-95">
                  <head>PLATE VI - 25.4</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_046l.jpg"/>
                  <p>25.4</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-96">
                  <head>PLATE VI - 25.5</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_046m.jpg"/>
                  <p>25.5</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-97">
                  <head>PLATE VI - 25.6</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_046n.jpg"/>
                  <p>25.6</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-98">
                  <head>PLATE VI - 25.7</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_046o.jpg"/>
                  <p>25.7</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-99">
                  <graphic url="NS6_046p.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e7179" type="backma">
               <pb/>
               <head>PLATE VII</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-100">
                  <head>PLATE VII - 26.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_047a.jpg"/>
                  <p>26.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-101">
                  <head>PLATE VII - 26.2</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_047b.jpg"/>
                  <p>26.2</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-102">
                  <head>PLATE VII - 26.3</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_047c.jpg"/>
                  <p>26.3</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-103">
                  <head>PLATE VII - 26.4</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_047d.jpg"/>
                  <p>26.4</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-104">
                  <head>PLATE VII - 26.5</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_047e.jpg"/>
                  <p>26.5</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-105">
                  <head>PLATE VII - 26.6</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_047f.jpg"/>
                  <p>26.6</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-106">
                  <head>PLATE VII - 26.7</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_047g.jpg"/>
                  <p>26.7</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-107">
                  <head>PLATE VII - 26.8</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_047h.jpg"/>
                  <p>26.8</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-108">
                  <head>PLATE VII - 26.9</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_047i.jpg"/>
                  <p>26.9</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-109">
                  <head>PLATE VII - 26.10</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_047j.jpg"/>
                  <p>26.10</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-110">
                  <head>PLATE VII - 26.11</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_047k.jpg"/>
                  <p>26.11</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-111">
                  <head>PLATE VII - 26.12</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_047l.jpg"/>
                  <p>26.12</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-112">
                  <head>PLATE VII - 26.13</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_047m.jpg"/>
                  <p>26.13</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-113">
                  <graphic url="NS6_047n.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e7264" type="backma">
               <pb/>
               <head>PLATE VIII</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-114">
                  <head>PLATE VIII - 27.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_048a.jpg"/>
                  <p>27.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-115">
                  <head>PLATE VIII - 27.2</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_048b.jpg"/>
                  <p>27.2</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-116">
                  <head>PLATE VIII - 28.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_048c.jpg"/>
                  <p>28.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-117">
                  <head>PLATE VIII - 28.2</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_048d.jpg"/>
                  <p>28.2</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-118">
                  <head>PLATE VIII - 28.3</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_048e.jpg"/>
                  <p>28.3</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-119">
                  <head>PLATE VIII - 28.4</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_048f.jpg"/>
                  <p>28.4</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-120">
                  <head>PLATE VIII - 29.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_048g.jpg"/>
                  <p>29.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-121">
                  <head>PLATE VIII - 29.2</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_048h.jpg"/>
                  <p>29.2</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-122">
                  <head>PLATE VIII - 29.3</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_048i.jpg"/>
                  <p>29.3</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-123">
                  <head>PLATE VIII - 29.4</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_048j.jpg"/>
                  <p>29.4</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-124">
                  <graphic url="NS6_048k.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e7332" type="backma">
               <pb/>
               <head>PLATE IX</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-125">
                  <head>PLATE IX - 29.5</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_049a.jpg"/>
                  <p>29.5</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-126">
                  <head>PLATE IX - 29.6</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_049b.jpg"/>
                  <p>29.6</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-127">
                  <head>PLATE IX - 29.7</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_049c.jpg"/>
                  <p>29.7</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-128">
                  <head>PLATE IX - 30.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_049d.jpg"/>
                  <p>30.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-129">
                  <head>PLATE IX - 30.2</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_049e.jpg"/>
                  <p>30.2</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-130">
                  <head>PLATE IX - 30.3</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_049f.jpg"/>
                  <p>30.3</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-131">
                  <head>PLATE IX - 30.4</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_049g.jpg"/>
                  <p>30.4</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-132">
                  <head>PLATE IX - 30.5</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_049h.jpg"/>
                  <p>30.5</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-133">
                  <head>PLATE IX - 30.6</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_049i.jpg"/>
                  <p>30.6</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-134">
                  <head>PLATE IX - 30.7</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_049j.jpg"/>
                  <p>30.7</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-135">
                  <head>PLATE IX - 30.8</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_049k.jpg"/>
                  <p>30.8</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-136">
                  <head>PLATE IX - 30.9</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_049l.jpg"/>
                  <p>30.9</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-137">
                  <head>PLATE IX - 31.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_049m.jpg"/>
                  <p>31.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-138">
                  <head>PLATE IX - 31.2</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_049n.jpg"/>
                  <p>31.2</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-139">
                  <head>PLATE IX - 31.3</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_049o.jpg"/>
                  <p>31.3</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-140">
                  <graphic url="NS6_049p.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e7429" type="backma">
               <pb/>
               <head>PLATE X</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-141">
                  <head>PLATE X - 32.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_050a.jpg"/>
                  <p>32.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-142">
                  <head>PLATE X - 32.2</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_050b.jpg"/>
                  <p>32.2</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-143">
                  <head>PLATE X - 33.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_050c.jpg"/>
                  <p>33.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-144">
                  <head>PLATE X - 34.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_050d.jpg"/>
                  <p>34.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-145">
                  <head>PLATE X - 34.2</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_050e.jpg"/>
                  <p>34.2</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-146">
                  <head>PLATE X - 34.3</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_050f.jpg"/>
                  <p>34.3</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-147">
                  <head>PLATE X - 34.4</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_050g.jpg"/>
                  <p>34.4</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-148">
                  <head>PLATE X - 34.5</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_050h.jpg"/>
                  <p>34.5</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-149">
                  <head>PLATE X - 34.6</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_050i.jpg"/>
                  <p>34.6</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-150">
                  <head>PLATE X - 34.7</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_050j.jpg"/>
                  <p>34.7</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-151">
                  <head>PLATE X - 34.8</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_050k.jpg"/>
                  <p>34.8</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-152">
                  <head>PLATE X - 34.9</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_050l.jpg"/>
                  <p>34.9</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-153">
                  <graphic url="NS6_050m.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e7508" type="backma">
               <pb/>
               <head>PLATE XI</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-154">
                  <head>PLATE XI - 35.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_051a.jpg"/>
                  <p>35.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-155">
                  <head>PLATE XI - 35.2</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_051b.jpg"/>
                  <p>35.2</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-156">
                  <head>PLATE XI - 35.3</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_051c.jpg"/>
                  <p>35.3</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-157">
                  <head>PLATE XI - 35.4</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_051d.jpg"/>
                  <p>35.4</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-158">
                  <head>PLATE XI - 35.5</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_051e.jpg"/>
                  <p>35.5</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-159">
                  <head>PLATE XI - 35.6</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_051f.jpg"/>
                  <p>35.6</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-160">
                  <head>PLATE XI - 35.7</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_051g.jpg"/>
                  <p>35.7</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-161">
                  <head>PLATE XI - 35.8</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_051h.jpg"/>
                  <p>35.8</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-162">
                  <head>PLATE XI - 35.9</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_051i.jpg"/>
                  <p>35.9</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-163">
                  <head>PLATE XI - 35.10</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_051j.jpg"/>
                  <p>35.10</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-164">
                  <head>PLATE XI - 35.11</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_051k.jpg"/>
                  <p>35.11</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-165">
                  <head>PLATE XI - 35.12</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_051l.jpg"/>
                  <p>35.12</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-166">
                  <head>PLATE XI - 35.13</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_051m.jpg"/>
                  <p>35.13</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-167">
                  <head>PLATE XI - 35.14</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_051n.jpg"/>
                  <p>35.14</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-168">
                  <head>PLATE XI - 35.15</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_051o.jpg"/>
                  <p>35.15</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-169">
                  <graphic url="NS6_051p.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e7605" type="backma">
               <pb/>
               <head>PLATE XII</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-170">
                  <head>PLATE XII - 35.16</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_052a.jpg"/>
                  <p>35.16</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-171">
                  <head>PLATE XII - 35.17</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_052b.jpg"/>
                  <p>35.17</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-172">
                  <head>PLATE XII - 35.18</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_052c.jpg"/>
                  <p>35.18</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-173">
                  <head>PLATE XII - 36.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_052d.jpg"/>
                  <p>36.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-174">
                  <head>PLATE XII - 36.2</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_052e.jpg"/>
                  <p>36.2</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-175">
                  <head>PLATE XII - 36.3</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_052f.jpg"/>
                  <p>36.3</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-176">
                  <head>PLATE XII - 36.4</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_052g.jpg"/>
                  <p>36.4</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-177">
                  <head>PLATE XII - 37.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_052h.jpg"/>
                  <p>37.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-178">
                  <head>PLATE XII - 37.2</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_052i.jpg"/>
                  <p>37.2</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-179">
                  <head>PLATE XII - 37.3</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_052j.jpg"/>
                  <p>37.3</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-180">
                  <head>PLATE XII - 38.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_052k.jpg"/>
                  <p>38.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-181">
                  <head>PLATE XII - 39.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_052l.jpg"/>
                  <p>39.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-182">
                  <graphic url="NS6_052m.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <pb/>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e7685" type="backma">
               <head>PLATE XIII</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-183">
                  <head>PLATE XIII - 40.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_053a.jpg"/>
                  <p>40.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-184">
                  <head>PLATE XIII - 40.2</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_053b.jpg"/>
                  <p>40.2</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-185">
                  <head>PLATE XIII - 40.3</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_053c.jpg"/>
                  <p>40.3</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-186">
                  <head>PLATE XIII - 40.4</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_053d.jpg"/>
                  <p>40.4</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-187">
                  <head>PLATE XIII - 40.5</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_053e.jpg"/>
                  <p>40.5</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-188">
                  <head>PLATE XIII - 40.6</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_053f.jpg"/>
                  <p>40.6</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-189">
                  <head>PLATE XIII - 41.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_053g.jpg"/>
                  <p>41.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-190">
                  <head>PLATE XIII - 41.2</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_053h.jpg"/>
                  <p>41.2</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-191">
                  <head>PLATE XIII - 42.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_053i.jpg"/>
                  <p>42.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-192">
                  <graphic url="NS6_053j.jpg"/>
                  <p>A</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-193">
                  <graphic url="NS6_053k.jpg"/>
                  <p>C</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-194">
                  <graphic url="NS6_053l.jpg"/>
                  <p>B</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-195">
                  <graphic url="NS6_053m.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e7757" type="backma">
               <pb/>
               <head>PLATE XIV</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-196">
                  <head>PLATE XIV - 43.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_054a.jpg"/>
                  <p>43.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-197">
                  <head>PLATE XIV - 43.2</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_054b.jpg"/>
                  <p>43.2</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-198">
                  <head>PLATE XIV - 44.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_054c.jpg"/>
                  <p>44.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-199">
                  <head>PLATE XIV - 45.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_054d.jpg"/>
                  <p>45.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-200">
                  <head>PLATE XIV - 45.2</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_054e.jpg"/>
                  <p>45.2</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-201">
                  <head>PLATE XIV - 45.3</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_054f.jpg"/>
                  <p>45.3</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-202">
                  <head>PLATE XIV - 46.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_054g.jpg"/>
                  <p>46.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-203">
                  <head>PLATE XIV - 47.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_054h.jpg"/>
                  <p>47.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-204">
                  <head>PLATE XIV - 47.2</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_054i.jpg"/>
                  <p>47.2</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-205">
                  <head>PLATE XIV - 48.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_054j.jpg"/>
                  <p>48.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-206">
                  <head>PLATE XIV - 49.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_054k.jpg"/>
                  <p>49.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-207">
                  <head>PLATE XIV - 49.2</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_054l.jpg"/>
                  <p>49.2</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-208">
                  <head>PLATE XIV - 50.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_054m.jpg"/>
                  <p>50.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-209">
                  <graphic url="NS6_054n.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e7842" type="backma">
               <pb/>
               <head>PLATE XV</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-210">
                  <head>PLATE XV - 50.2</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_055a.jpg"/>
                  <p>50.2</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-211">
                  <head>PLATE XV - 51.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_055b.jpg"/>
                  <p>51.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-212">
                  <head>PLATE XV - 52.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_055c.jpg"/>
                  <p>52.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-213">
                  <head>PLATE XV - 53.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_055d.jpg"/>
                  <p>53.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-214">
                  <head>PLATE XV - 53.2</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_055e.jpg"/>
                  <p>53.2</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-215">
                  <head>PLATE XV - 53.3</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_055f.jpg"/>
                  <p>53.3</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-216">
                  <head>PLATE XV - 54.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_055g.jpg"/>
                  <p>54.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-217">
                  <head>PLATE XV - 55.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_055h.jpg"/>
                  <p>55.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-218">
                  <head>PLATE XV - 55.2</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_055i.jpg"/>
                  <p>55.2</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-219">
                  <head>PLATE XV - 55.3</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_055j.jpg"/>
                  <p>55.3</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-220">
                  <head>PLATE XV - 56.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_055k.jpg"/>
                  <p>56.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-221">
                  <head>PLATE XV - 56.2</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_055l.jpg"/>
                  <p>56.2</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-222">
                  <head>PLATE XV - 57.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_055m.jpg"/>
                  <p>57.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-223">
                  <graphic url="NS6_055n.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e7927" type="backma">
               <pb/>
               <head>PLATE XVI</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-224">
                  <head>PLATE XVI - 58.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_056a.jpg"/>
                  <p>58.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-225">
                  <head>PLATE XVI - 58.2</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_056b.jpg"/>
                  <p>58.2</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-226">
                  <head>PLATE XVI - 59.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_056c.jpg"/>
                  <p>59.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-227">
                  <head>PLATE XVI - 59.2</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_056d.jpg"/>
                  <p>59.2</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-228">
                  <head>PLATE XVI - 60.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_056e.jpg"/>
                  <p>60.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-229">
                  <head>PLATE XVI - 60.2</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_056f.jpg"/>
                  <p>60.2</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-230">
                  <head>PLATE XVI - 60.3</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_056g.jpg"/>
                  <p>60.3</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-231">
                  <head>PLATE XVI - 60.4</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_056h.jpg"/>
                  <p>60.4</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-232">
                  <head>PLATE XVI - 60.5</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_056i.jpg"/>
                  <p>60.5</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-233">
                  <head>PLATE XVI - 60.6</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_056j.jpg"/>
                  <p>60.6</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-234">
                  <head>PLATE XVI - 61.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_056k.jpg"/>
                  <p>61.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-235">
                  <head>PLATE XVI - 62.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_056l.jpg"/>
                  <p>62.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-236">
                  <graphic url="NS6_056m.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e8006" type="backma">
               <pb/>
               <head>PLATE XVII</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-237">
                  <head>PLATE XVII - 63.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_057a.jpg"/>
                  <p>63.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-238">
                  <head>PLATE XVII - 64.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_057b.jpg"/>
                  <p>64.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-239">
                  <head>PLATE XVII - 64.2</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_057c.jpg"/>
                  <p>64.2</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-240">
                  <head>PLATE XVII - 65.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_057d.jpg"/>
                  <p>65.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-241">
                  <head>PLATE XVII - 66.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_057e.jpg"/>
                  <p>66.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-242">
                  <head>PLATE XVII - 67.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_057f.jpg"/>
                  <p>67.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-243">
                  <head>PLATE XVII - 67.2</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_057g.jpg"/>
                  <p>67.2</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-244">
                  <head>PLATE XVII - 67.3</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_057h.jpg"/>
                  <p>67.3</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-245">
                  <head>PLATE XVII - 67.4</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_057i.jpg"/>
                  <p>67.4</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-246">
                  <head>PLATE XVII - 68.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_057j.jpg"/>
                  <p>68.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-247">
                  <head>PLATE XVII - 67.5</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_057k.jpg"/>
                  <p>67.5</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-248">
                  <head>PLATE XVII - 69.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_057l.jpg"/>
                  <p>69.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-249">
                  <head>PLATE XVII - 69.2</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_057m.jpg"/>
                  <p>69.2</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-250">
                  <head>PLATE XVII - 70.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_057n.jpg"/>
                  <p>70.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-251">
                  <graphic url="NS6_057o.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e8097" type="backma">
               <pb/>
               <head>PLATE XVIII</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-252">
                  <head>PLATE XVIII - 1.1a</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_058a.jpg"/>
                  <p>1.1a</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-253">
                  <head>PLATE XVIII - 13.1a</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_058b.jpg"/>
                  <p>13.1a</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-254">
                  <head>PLATE XVIII - 14.6</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_058c.jpg"/>
                  <p>14.6</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-255">
                  <head>PLATE XVIII - 22.6</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_058d.jpg"/>
                  <p>22.6</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-256">
                  <head>PLATE XVIII - 23.3</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_058e.jpg"/>
                  <p>23.3</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-257">
                  <head>PLATE XVIII - 26.9</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_058f.jpg"/>
                  <p>26.9</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-258">
                  <head>PLATE XVIII - 27.2</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_058g.jpg"/>
                  <p>27.2</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-259">
                  <head>PLATE XVIII - 42.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_058h.jpg"/>
                  <p>42.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-260">
                  <head>PLATE XVIII - 36.4</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_058i.jpg"/>
                  <p>36.4</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-261">
                  <head>PLATE XVIII - 40.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_058j.jpg"/>
                  <p>40.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-262">
                  <head>PLATE XVIII - 40.3</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_058k.jpg"/>
                  <p>40.3</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-263">
                  <head>PLATE XVIII - 60.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_058l.jpg"/>
                  <p>60.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-264">
                  <head>PLATE XVIII - 39.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_058m.jpg"/>
                  <p>39.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-265">
                  <head>PLATE XVIII - 43.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_058n.jpg"/>
                  <p>43.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-266">
                  <head>PLATE XVIII - 46.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_058o.jpg"/>
                  <p>46.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-267">
                  <head>PLATE XVIII - 50.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_058p.jpg"/>
                  <p>50.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-268">
                  <head>PLATE XVIII - 54.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_058q.jpg"/>
                  <p>54.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-269">
                  <head>PLATE XVIII - 55.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_058r.jpg"/>
                  <p>55.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-270">
                  <head>PLATE XVIII - 60.5</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_058s.jpg"/>
                  <p>60.5</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-271">
                  <graphic url="NS6_058t.jpg"/>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-272">
                  <head>PLATE XVIII - 62.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_058u.jpg"/>
                  <p>62.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-273">
                  <head>PLATE XVIII - 35.18</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_058v.jpg"/>
                  <p>35.18</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-274">
                  <head>PLATE XVIII - 63.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_058w.jpg"/>
                  <p>63.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-275">
                  <head>PLATE XVIII - 40.3</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_058x.jpg"/>
                  <p>40.3</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-276">
                  <head>PLATE XVIII - 36.4</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_058y.jpg"/>
                  <p>36.4</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-277">
                  <head>PLATE XVIII - 60.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_058z.jpg"/>
                  <p>60.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-278">
                  <head>PLATE XVIII - 63.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_058aa.jpg"/>
                  <p>63.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-279">
                  <head>PLATE XVIII - 54.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_058ab.jpg"/>
                  <p>54.1</p>
               </figure>
               <figure xml:id="fig-280">
                  <head>PLATE XVIII - 58.1</head>
                  <graphic url="NS6_058ac.jpg"/>
                  <p>58.1</p>
               </figure>
            </div2>
         </div1>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
