<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd"
     xml:id="nnan30114">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Attambelos I of Characene</title>
            <author>
               <name>Hill, George Francis, Sir, 1867-1948</name>
               <idno type="URI">http://viaf.org/viaf/68994178</idno>
            </author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>TEI P5 XML markup in conformance with the TEI DTD</resp>
               <name>AEL Data</name>
            </respStmt>
            <funder>Open access edition funded by the National Endowment for the Humanities/Andrew W. Mellon Foundation Humanities Open Book Program.</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <name>American Numismatic Society</name>
               <idno type="URI">http://numismatics.org/authority/american_numismatic_society</idno>
            </publisher>
            <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
            <date>1922</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">This work is made available under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International license</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Numismatic Notes and Monographs</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">14</biblScope>
            <idno type="URI">http://numismatics.org/library/195778</idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>Donum</title>
               <idno type="URI">http://numismatics.org/library/30114</idno>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <title>Worldcat</title>
               <idno type="URI">http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/248598112</idno>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <title>Worldcat Works</title>
               <idno type="URI">http://worldcat.org/entity/work/id/25335780</idno>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://nomisma.org/">
               <term ref="http://nomisma.org/id/greek_numismatics">Greek Numismatics</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2018-04-02">Ran TEI file through XSLT process, detailed in the Mellon EBook migration Google Document.</change>
         <change when="2018-04-02">Included normalized entity labels and URIs from
				previous OpenRefine process.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div1 xml:id="d380e30" type="cover">
            <pb/>
            <figure xml:id="fig-001">
               <graphic url="NNM21_001.jpg"/>
            </figure>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d380e34" type="frontma">
            <pb/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="bold">PUBLICATIONS</hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="hang">
               <hi rend="bold">The American Journal of Numismatics, 1866–1920.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Monthly, May, 1866—April, 1870.</p>
            <p>Quarterly, July, 1870—October, 1912.</p>
            <p>Annually, 1913–1920.</p>
            <p rend="hang">With many plates, illustrations, maps and tables. Less than a dozen complete sets of the Journal remain on hand. Prices on application. Those wishing to fill broken sets can secure most of the needed volumes separately. An index to the first 50 volumes has been issued as a part of Volume 51. It may also be purchased as a reprint for $3.00.</p>
            <p rend="hang">The American Numismatic Society. Catalogue of the International Exhibition of Contemporary Medals. March, 1910. New and revised edition. <placeName>New York</placeName>. 1911. xxxvi, 412 pages, 512 illustrations. $10.00.</p>
            <p rend="hang">The American Numismatic Society. Exhibition of United States and Colonial Coins. 1914. vii, 134 pages, 40 plates. $1.00.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d380e57" type="frontma">
            <pb/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="bold">NUMISMATIC NOTES AND MONOGRAPHS</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">editor: sydney p. noe</hi>
            </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d380e65" type="dedication">
            <pb/>
            <p>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">Numismatic Notes and Monographs</hi> is devoted to essays and treatises on subjects relating to coins, paper money, medals and decorations, and is uniform with Hispanic Notes and Monographs published by the Hispanic Society of <placeName>America</placeName>, and with Indian Notes and Monographs issued by the Museum of the American Indian—Heye Foundation.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d380e74" type="colophon">
            <pb/>
            <p>COPYRIGHT 1922 BY THE AMERICAN NUMISMATIC SOCIETY</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">Press of Patterson &amp; White Co., Philadelphia</hi>
            </p>
         </div1>
         <titlePage>
            <pb/>
            <docTitle>
               <titlePart type="main">ATTAMBELOS I OF CHARACENE</titlePart>
            </docTitle>
            <byline>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">By</hi> GEORGE F. HILL, M.A.
</byline>
            <figure xml:id="fig-002">
               <graphic url="NNM14_006.jpg"/>
            </figure>
            <docImprint>
               <publisher>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">the american numismatic society</hi>
               </publisher>
               <pubPlace>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">broadway at</hi> 156<hi rend="smallcaps">th street</hi>
               </pubPlace>
               <pubPlace>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">new york</hi>
               </pubPlace>
               <date>1922</date>
            </docImprint>
         </titlePage>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div1 xml:id="d380e108" type="chapter">
            <pb n="1"/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="bold">ATTAMBELOS I OF CHARACENE</hi>
            </head>
            <byline>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">by G. F. Hill.</hi>
            </byline>
            <p>The five tetradrachms of this king, which were published in the recently issued volume of the British Museum Catalogue,<ref target="#CH1-n1">
                  <hi rend="sup">1</hi>
               </ref> formed part of a hoard. Of this hoard 50 pieces in all were secured by Col. <persName>H. B. McCormick, D.S.O.</persName> Whether the hoard ever contained any more than these I am unable to state. It was reported to have been fetched across the border from Susa to Amara, where it was bought; but there may be no more truth in that statement than in another, to wit: that the coins had been buried in a bronze pot which, when examined by experts, proved to be of Arab workmanship and perhaps a thousand years later than the coins. That the coins had been in contact with copper is, however, undoubtedly true, for the forty-five coins which were brought to me by Col.
<pb n="2"/>
               <persName>McCormick</persName> were so thickly coated with a copper deposit that their real composition—a not very pure silver<ref target="#CH1-n2">
                  <hi rend="sup">2</hi>
               </ref>—could hardly be surmised. They have all since been cleaned—nearly all with complete success; two, however, had considerable patches of deep-seated decay, which in the cleaning disappeared altogether, leaving large cavities on the obverses.</p>
            <p>Of the 45 new coins shown by Colonel McCormick, one has been kept by himself, and 22 by the British Museum. In the following list, an asterisk is placed against the weight of the specimens retained by the Museum. I proceed to give a complete list of all the coins known to me of this king—51 in all, including the Berlin specimen, or 52, if, as seems probable, the bronze coin at Paris is of him and not of the second Attambelos.</p>
            <p>All the coins are of the general description already given in the Museum Catalogue, as follows:</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">Obv.</hi> Head of King r., diademed, bearded, hair in curls; border of dots.</p>
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> Herakles seated l., with club which rests on his r. knee. On r. downwards and on l. downwards, inscription (rarely preserved in full) ΒΑΣӀΛΕΩΣ ΑΤΤΑΜΒΗΛ&#x7f;<graphic url="NNM14_009.jpg"/> on r., ΣΩΤΗΡ&#x7f;Σ ΚΑӀ Ε<graphic url="NNM14_009.jpg"/>ΕΡΓΕΤ&#x7f;<graphic url="NNM14_009.jpg"/> on l. Above r. arm, monogram; in exergue, date (too often mutilated).</p>
            <p>They fall into three groups, according as they have</p>
            <list type="alpha">
               <item n="(A)">a monogram on obverse in front of the head, and on the reverse a monogram or letter under the arm, as well as the monogram above it.</item>
               <item n="(B)">no monogram on obverse, but a letter under the arm as well as the monogram above it.</item>
               <item n="(C)">no monogram on obverse, and on the reverse no letter under the arm, but only the monogram above it.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Contrary to the usual rule in the development of coins, the equipment of monograms and letters becomes less complicated as time goes on; the chronological order of the groups is the same as that given above.</p>
            <div2 xml:id="d380e164" type="section">
               <pb n="4"/>
               <head>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">Series</hi> A.</head>
               <p>On the obverse, monogram <graphic url="NNM14_010a.jpg"/> in front of head.</p>
               <p>1–5. On the reverse, <graphic url="NNM14_010b.jpg"/> above arm, <graphic url="NNM14_010c.jpg"/> below; date, when legible ΖΞΣ (267). Weights, 15.09 grammes, 14.78 gr.*, 13,41 gr., 12.97 gr.* <hi rend="italic">(Pl. I)</hi>, 12.82 gr.</p>
               <p>6. On the reverse, obscure monogram<ref target="#CH1-n3">
                     <hi rend="sup">3</hi>
                  </ref> above arm, Ο below date НΞΣ (268). Wt. 11.24 gr.* <hi rend="italic">(Pl. I).</hi>
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d380e191" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">Series</hi> B.</head>
               <p>No monogram on obverse; on reverse, above arm <graphic url="NNM14_010d.jpg"/> (No. 7) or <graphic url="NNM14_010e.jpg"/> (Nos. 8–13); below, a letter.</p>
               <p>7. Letter under arm obliterated. Date, θΞΣ (269). Wt. 10.50 gr.* (B.M C. p. 291, No. 1).</p>
               <p>8. Letter under arm, Ζ. Date, <graphic url="NNM14_010f.jpg"/>ΞΣ Wt. 14.47 gr.</p>
               <p>9. Letter under arm, Ζ. Date illegible. Wt. 13.37 gr.*</p>
               <p>10. Letter under arm, Ρ. Date illegible. <hi rend="italic">Same obv. die as No. 9.</hi> Wt. 14.02 gr.* <hi rend="italic">(Pl. I)</hi>.</p>
               <p>11. Similar to No. 10, but from differ-
<pb n="5"/>
ent dies. Date, &#x7f;(?)Σ (270). Double struck on rev. Wt. 11.88 gr.</p>
               <p>12. Letter X (?) under arm. Date, <graphic url="NNM14_011a.jpg"/>Σ (270). Wt. 13.15 gr*.</p>
               <p>13. Letter X under arm. Date off the flan. Wt. 10.74 gr.* (B.M.C. p. 292, No. 5).</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d380e228" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">Series</hi> C.</head>
               <p>No monogram on obverse; on reverse, monogram <graphic url="NNM14_011b.jpg"/> above arm.</p>
               <p>14, 15. Date, Β&#x7f;Σ (272). Wts. 13.68 gr.* (B.M.C. p. 291, No. 3) and 13.72 gr.*</p>
               <p>16, 17. Date, Γ&#x7f;Σ (273). <hi rend="italic">Both from same obv. die as No. 15</hi>. Wts. 10.69 gr.* and (?) (the latter retained by Col. McCormick).</p>
               <p>18, 19. Date, Γ&#x7f;Σ. <hi rend="italic">Both from same obv. die.</hi> Wts. 13.46 gr.* <hi rend="italic">(Pl. II)</hi> and 10.37 gr.</p>
               <p>20. Date, Γ&#x7f;Σ or ΓΠΣ(283). Wt.? (Berlin; Waddington, <hi rend="italic">Mélanges</hi> Pl. VI. 7, where the date is taken to be ΓΠΣ). The bottoms of the letters of the date are off the flan or not struck up, judging from a cast which I owe to Dr. Regling.</p>
               <pb n="6"/>
               <p>21. Date, Ε&#x7f;Σ(275). Wt. 12.53 gr.*</p>
               <p>22. Date, Ε(?)&#x7f;Σ. Wt. 9.95 gr.*</p>
               <p>23. Date, <graphic url="NNM14_012a.jpg"/>Σ(276). <hi rend="italic">Same obv. die as No. 22.</hi> Wt. 12.43 gr.*</p>
               <p>24. Date, <graphic url="NNM14_012b.jpg"/>[&#x7f;]Σ. Different dies. Wt. 11.22 gr.</p>
               <p>25, 26. Date, <graphic url="NNM14_012c.jpg"/>Σ (277). <hi rend="italic">Both from same obv. die.</hi> Wts. 15.07 gr.* <hi rend="italic">(Pl. II),</hi> 12.09 gr.*</p>
               <p>27, 28. Date, Н&#x7f;Σ (278). <hi rend="italic">From the same pair of dies.</hi> Wts. 14.13 gr.* <hi rend="italic">(Pl. II),</hi> 11.54 gr.</p>
               <p>29. Date, Н&#x7f;Σ. <hi rend="italic">Different dies.</hi> Wt. 13.98 gr.</p>
               <p>30. Date, <graphic url="NNM14_012d.jpg"/>&#x7f;Σ (279). Wt. 13.54 gr.* (B.M.C. p. 291, No. 2).</p>
               <p>31. Date, <graphic url="NNM14_012e.jpg"/>Σ. Wt. 12.13 gr.*</p>
               <p>32. Date, Γ&#x7f;Σ. Wt. 12.15 gr.* (B.M.C. p 292, No. 4). I cannot explain the very puzzling digit sign. In some lights there seems to be a middle horizontal. If the right vertical were continued downwards and a bottom horizontal supplied, we should have a square theta, such as is used in the name of the next king, Thionesios. The loss of the
<pb n="7"/>
missing parts would be accounted for by a slight depression in the surface which occupies their place. Judging by the style of the obverse, the coin belongs to about this period of the reign. The weak point of this explanation is that a round theta seems to be used on Nos. 30 and 31.</p>
               <p>33. Date, <graphic url="NNM14_013a.jpg"/>&#x7f;Σ. Wt. 11.20 gr.*</p>
               <p>34. Date quite illegible. <hi rend="italic">Same obv. die as No. 33.</hi> Wt. 11.50 gr.</p>
               <p>35,36. Date, <graphic url="NNM14_013b.jpg"/>&#x7f;Σ or <graphic url="NNM14_013c.jpg"/>ΠΣ. <hi rend="italic">From same obv. die.</hi> Wts. 12.97 gr.*, 12.18 gr. (a large cavity on obverse of the latter).</p>
               <p>37–40. Date, <graphic url="NNM14_013d.jpg"/>&#x7f;Σ or <graphic url="NNM14_013e.jpg"/>ΠΣ. Wts. 12.14 gr., 11.96 gr., 11.94 gr., 10.04 gr.</p>
               <p>41. Date, ΓΠΣ(283). Wt. 12.42 gr.* (large cavity on obverse).</p>
               <p>42. Date, ΔΠΣ (284). Wt. 12.30 gr.* <hi rend="italic">(Pl. III).</hi>
               </p>
               <p>43. Date, <graphic url="NNM14_013f.jpg"/>ΣΣ. <hi rend="italic">Same obv. die as No. 42;</hi> therefore the first letter of the date is probably Γ, Δ or Ε.</p>
               <p>44, 45. Date illegible. <hi rend="italic">Both from same obv. die.</hi> Wts. 13.20 gr.*, 12.72 gr.</p>
               <p>46, 47. Date illegible. <hi rend="italic">Both from</hi>
                  <pb n="8"/>
                  <hi rend="italic">same pair of dies.</hi> Weights 11.66 grammes, 10.11 grammes.*</p>
               <p>48–51. Date illegible. Wts. 14.05 gr., 11.63 gr., 11.31 gr., 9.93 gr.</p>
               <p>52. The bronze coin with Nike as reverse type (Waddington, <hi rend="italic">Mélanges,</hi> p. 89, No. 6, here <hi rend="italic">Pl. III)</hi> seems to me, judging from a cast, to be of this Attambelos rather than of the second.</p>
               <p>The first point to be noted is that if the date on the coins of Thionesios I were really ΓΟΣ, as it has always been read, he would be an intruder in the middle of the reign of Attambelos I. But, as Mr. Robinson has observed to me, the omicron on these coins is always square, and the middle sign is therefore presumably a koppa. His suggestion is completely confirmed by <persName>M. Babelon</persName> who, having re-examined the coins, kindly informs me that the beginning of the tail of the koppa is discernible on the two out of the three specimens on which the date is legible at all. (See <hi rend="italic">Pl. III, A</hi>.) We thus have the dates 267 to 284 (46/5–29/8 B.C.) fixed in the chronology
<pb n="9"/>
of Attambelos I and 293 (20/19 B.C.) in that of Thionesios I.<ref target="#CH1-n4">
                     <hi rend="sup">4</hi>
                  </ref> There thus still remains a gap of nine years to be supplied between the dates established for the two kings; and, further, since it is uncertain whether the latest date of Tiraios II is 261 or 264, there may be a year or two to add on at the beginning of the reign of Attambelos.</p>
               <p>The next king known in succession to Thionesios I is Attambelos II. His portrait is easily distinguishable from that of Attambelos I by the treatment of the hair; both are in long locks, but those of the first king are frizzed, whereas on the head of the second they hang more or less lankly. A good specimen is figured in <hi rend="italic">Pl. III, B.</hi> This is the piece the date on which <persName>M. Babelon</persName>
                  <ref target="#CH1-n5">
                     <hi rend="sup">5</hi>
                  </ref> has read ΕΠΣ. Since this would make Thionesios I an intruder in his reign, the reading would seem to require revision. The coin is slightly double struck, and on the cast I seem to see that the hundreds figure may have been a Τ of which only the right-hand portion of the horizontal
<pb n="10"/>
and the upper portion of the vertical remain legible. It bears the same monogram as coins dated ΓӀΤ(?),ςӀΤ and ΙӀΤ<ref target="#CH1-n6">
                     <hi rend="sup">6</hi>
                  </ref> and resembles them also in the style of its lettering. The earliest date otherwise read on coins of this king is Ε<graphic url="NNM14_016.jpg"/>Σ (Berlin).<ref target="#CH1-n7">
                     <hi rend="sup">7</hi>
                  </ref> Taking this, then, as the first fixed point in his reign, we have a gap of 12 years between him and Thionesios I.</p>
               <p>It is unlikely that these gaps will be filled by the discovery of other kings, because, as I have remarked elsewhere, the series we now know squares with the numbers given by a passage of Pseudo-Lucian which caused some difficulty before the discovery of Attambelos I.</p>
               <p>I am unable to offer any certain explanation of the monograms and letters which distinguish these coins. But it seems probable that those on the reverses represent officials in charge of the mint, for they are used continuously for a shorter or longer period of years, and do not recur after an interval, as they might if they represented place names. The
<pb n="11"/>
monogram on the obverse of Series A is possibly meant for the king's own name, like the somewhat similar countermark, which is found on coins of Attambelos III and Thionesios III.<ref target="#CH1-n8">
                     <hi rend="sup">8</hi>
                  </ref> The letters under the arm cannot represent months, since they run to X.</p>
               <p>The weights, it will be observed, are excessively irregular. This may partly be due to the cleaning of the coins; although nothing has been deliberately removed, chemical changes in alloy may have affected the weights of some of the pieces.</p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div1 xml:id="d380e421" type="backma">
            <pb n="12"/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="bold">NOTES</hi>
            </head>
            <note xml:id="CH1-n1" place="end">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">1</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Arabia</hi> &amp;c., pp. 291–2. In the course of these notes I have made a few tacit corrections in my previous descriptions of these coins.</p>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="CH1-n2" place="end">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">2</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>But easily distinguishable from the metal of the succeeding kings, which is very base.</p>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="CH1-n3" place="end">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">3</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>All that is clear is a loop resembling the lower part of a B.</p>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="CH1-n4" place="end">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">4</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>Assuming the use of the Seleucid era, and not that of <persName>Alexander</persName>; a point on which Col. Allotte de la Fuÿe will have something to say.</p>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="CH1-n5" place="end">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">5</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Mélanges numismatiques</hi> iii (1900) p. 230.</p>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="CH1-n6" place="end">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">6</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>B.M.C. p. 293. Nos. 1–3. I note here that No. 5 of this king has the same monogram as his earlier coins of <graphic url="NNM14_018a.jpg"/>Σ. Ε<graphic url="NNM14_018b.jpg"/>Σ and Τ, and should therefore have been placed before No. 1, although its date is illegible.</p>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="CH1-n7" place="end">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">7</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>There is also one at Paris with <graphic url="NNM14_018c.jpg"/>Σ.</p>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="CH1-n8" place="end">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">8</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>B.M.C. <hi rend="italic">Arabia,</hi> p. cciii.</p>
            </note>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d380e490" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="bold">ATTAMBELOS I</hi>
            </head>
            <div2 xml:id="d380e495" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">Plate I</hi>
               </head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-003">
                  <graphic url="NNM14_019.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d380e501" type="section">
               <pb/>
               <head>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">Plate II</hi>
               </head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-004">
                  <graphic url="NNM14_020.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d380e508" type="section">
               <pb/>
               <head>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">Plate III</hi>
               </head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-005">
                  <graphic url="NNM14_021.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d380e515" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="bold">PUBLICATIONS</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item rend="hang">
                  <persName>Agnes Baldwin</persName>. The Electrum Coinage of Lampsakos. 1914. 36 pages. 2 plates. $1.00.</item>
               <item rend="hang">
                  <persName>Edward T. Newell</persName>. The Seleucid Mint of <placeName>Antioch</placeName>, 1918. 137 pages. 13 plates. $5.00.</item>
               <item rend="hang">
                  <persName>Edward T. Newell</persName>. Tarsos under <persName>Alexander</persName>. 1919. 47 pages. 8 plates. $2.50.</item>
               <item rend="hang">
                  <persName>Edward T. Newell</persName>. Some Rare or Unpublished Greek Coins. 12 pages. 2 plates. $1.00.</item>
               <item rend="hang">
                  <persName>Edgar H. Adams</persName>. Private Gold Coinage of California. 5 Vols. (Unbound). $3.50.</item>
               <item rend="hang">
                  <persName>Edgar H. Adams</persName> and <persName>William H. Woodin</persName>. <placeName>United States Pattern</placeName>, Trial and Experimental Pieces .... issued by the U. S. Mint from 1792 up to the present time. 1913. 204 pages. Illus. Cloth, $3.00.</item>
            </list>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d380e557" type="backma">
            <head>
               <hi rend="bold">
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">Numismatic Notes and Monographs</hi>
               </hi>
            </head>
            <list type="numbered">
               <item n="1.">
                  <persName>Sydney P. Noe</persName>. Coin Hoards, 1921. 47 pages. 6 plates. 50c.</item>
               <item n="2.">
                  <persName>Edward T. Newell</persName>. Octobols of Histiæa. 1921. 25 pages. 2 plates. 50c.</item>
               <item n="3.">
                  <persName>Edward T. Newell</persName>. <persName>Alexander</persName> Hoards—Introduction and Kyparissia Hoard. 1921. 21 pages. 2 plates. 50c.</item>
               <pb/>
               <item n="4.">
                  <persName>Howland Wood</persName>. The Mexican Revolutionary Coinage, 1913–1916. 1921. 44 pages. 26 plates. $2.00.</item>
               <item n="5.">
                  <persName>Leonidas Westervelt</persName>. The Jenny Lind Medals and Tokens. 1921. 25 pages. 9 plates. 50c.</item>
               <item n="6.">
                  <persName>Agnes Baldwin</persName>. Five Roman Gold Medallions. 1921. 103 pages. 8 plates. $1.50.</item>
               <item n="7.">
                  <persName>Sydney P. Noe</persName>. Medallic Work of A. A. Weinman. 1921. 31 pages. 17 plates. $1.00.</item>
               <item n="8.">
                  <persName>Gilbert S. Perez</persName>. The Mint of the Philippine <placeName>Islands</placeName>. 1921. 8 pages. 4 plates. 50c.</item>
               <item n="9.">
                  <persName>David Eugene Smith, LL.D</persName>. Computing Jetons. 1921. 70 pages. 25 plates. $1.50.</item>
               <item n="10.">
                  <persName>Edward T. Newell</persName>. The First Seleucid Coinage of Tyre. 1921. 40 pages. 8 plates. $1.00.</item>
               <item n="11.">
                  <persName>Harrold E. Gillingham</persName>. French Orders and Decorations. 1922. 110 pages. 35 plates. $2.00.</item>
               <item n="12.">
                  <persName>Howland Wood</persName>. Gold Dollars of 1858. 1922. 7 pages. 2 plates. 50c.</item>
               <item n="13.">
                  <persName>R. B. Whitehead</persName>. Pre-Mohammedan Coinage of Northwestern <placeName>India</placeName>. 1922. 56 pages. 15 plates. $2.00.</item>
            </list>
         </div1>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
