<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd"
     xml:id="nnan53903">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>first Seleucid coinage of Tyre</title>
            <author>
               <name>Newell, Edward Theodore, 1886-1941</name>
               <idno type="URI">http://numismatics.org/authority/newell</idno>
            </author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>TEI P5 XML markup in conformance with the TEI DTD</resp>
               <name>AEL Data</name>
            </respStmt>
            <funder>The Andrew W. Mellon Foundation</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <name>American Numismatic Society</name>
               <idno type="URI">http://numismatics.org/authority/american_numismatic_society</idno>
            </publisher>
            <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
            <date>1921</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">This work is made available under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International license</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Numismatic Notes and Monographs</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">10</biblScope>
            <idno type="URI">http://numismatics.org/library/195778</idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>Donum</title>
               <idno type="URI">http://numismatics.org/library/53903</idno>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <title>Worldcat</title>
               <idno type="URI">http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/944918862</idno>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <title>Worldcat Works</title>
               <idno type="URI">http://worldcat.org/entity/work/id/30153963</idno>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://nomisma.org/">
               <term ref="http://nomisma.org/id/greek_numismatics">Greek Numismatics</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <particDesc>
            <listPerson>
               <person xml:id="nomisma_alexander_iii">
                  <persName>Alexander III of Macedon</persName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/alexander_iii</idno>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="nomisma_c_alli_bala_rrc">
                  <persName>C. Allius Bala</persName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/c_alli_bala_rrc</idno>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="nomisma_antiochus_iii">
                  <persName>Antiochus III the Great</persName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/antiochus_iii</idno>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="nomisma_antiochus_i">
                  <persName>Antiochus I Soter</persName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/antiochus_i</idno>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="nomisma_antiochus_hierax">
                  <persName>Antiochus Hierax</persName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/antiochus_hierax</idno>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="nomisma_antiochus_iv">
                  <persName>Antiochus IV Epiphanes</persName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/antiochus_iv</idno>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="nomisma_seleucus_iv">
                  <persName>Seleucus IV</persName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/seleucus_iv</idno>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="nomisma_seleucus_i">
                  <persName>Seleucus I</persName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/seleucus_i</idno>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="nomisma_demetrius_i">
                  <persName>Demetrius I Poliorcetes</persName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/demetrius_i</idno>
               </person>
            </listPerson>
         </particDesc>
         <settingDesc>
            <listPlace>
               <place xml:id="nomisma_egypt">
                  <placeName>Egypt</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/egypt</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="nomisma_paris">
                  <placeName>Paris</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/paris</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="nomisma_greek_asia">
                  <placeName>Asia</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/greek_asia</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="nomisma_babylonia">
                  <placeName>Babylonia</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/babylonia</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="nomisma_cilicia">
                  <placeName>Cilicia</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/cilicia</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="nomisma_syria">
                  <placeName>Syria</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/syria</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="nomisma_athens">
                  <placeName>Athens</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/athens</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="nomisma_phoenicia">
                  <placeName>Phoenicia</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/phoenicia</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="nomisma_sidon">
                  <placeName>Sidon</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/sidon</idno>
               </place>
            </listPlace>
         </settingDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2018-04-02">Ran TEI file through XSLT process, detailed in the Mellon EBook migration Google Document.</change>
         <change when="2018-04-02">Included normalized entity labels and URIs from
				previous OpenRefine process.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div1 xml:id="d95e30" type="cover">
            <pb/>
            <figure xml:id="fig-1">
               <graphic url="NNM10_001.jpg"/>
            </figure>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d95e34" type="frontma">
            <pb/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="bold">PUBLICATIONS</hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="hang">
               <hi rend="bold">The American Journal of Numismatics, 1866–1920.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Monthly, May, 1866—April, 1870.</p>
            <p>Quarterly, July, 1870—October, 1912.</p>
            <p>Annually, 1913–1920.</p>
            <p rend="hang">With many plates, illustrations, maps and tables. Less than a dozen complete sets of the Journal remain on hand. Prices on application. Those wishing to fill broken sets can secure most of the needed volumes separately. An index to the first 50 volumes has been issued as a part of Volume 51. It may also be purchased as a reprint for $3.00.</p>
            <p rend="hang">The American Numismatic Society. Catalogue of the International Exhibition of Contemporary Medals. March, 1910. New and revised edition. <name type="place">New York</name>. 1911. xxxvi, 412 pages, 512 illustrations. $10.00.</p>
            <p rend="hang">The American Numismatic Society. Exhibition of <name type="place">United States</name> and Colonial Coins. 1914. vii, 134 pages, 40 plates. $1.00.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d95e60" type="frontma">
            <pb/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="bold">NUMISMATIC</hi>
            </head>
            <p>NOTES AND MONOGRAPHS</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d95e67" type="dedication">
            <pb/>
            <p>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">Numismatic Notes and Monographs</hi> is devoted to essays and treatises on subjects relating to coins, paper money, medals and decorations, and is uniform with Hispanic Notes and Monographs published by the Hispanic Society of <name type="place">America</name>, and with <name type="place">Indian</name> Notes and Monographs issued by the Museum of the American Indian-Heye Foundation.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d95e79" type="copyright">
            <pb/>
            <p>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">copyright 1921 by</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">the american numismatic society</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">Press of The <name type="pname">John C. Powers</name> Company, Inc.</hi>, <name type="place">N. Y</name>.</p>
         </div1>
         <titlePage>
            <pb/>
            <docTitle>
               <titlePart type="main">THE FIRST SELEUCID COINAGE OF TYRE</titlePart>
            </docTitle>
            <byline>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">By Edward T. Newell</hi>
            </byline>
            <figure xml:id="fig-2">
               <graphic url="NNM10_006.jpg"/>
            </figure>
            <docImprint>
               <publisher>The American Numismatic Society</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Broadway at 156th Street</pubPlace>
               <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
               <date>1921</date>
            </docImprint>
         </titlePage>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div1 xml:id="d95e117" type="chapter">
            <pb n="1"/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="bold">THE FIRST SELEUCID COINAGE OF TYRE</hi>
            </head>
            <byline>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">By Edward T. Newell</hi>
            </byline>
            <p>In the city of Tyre was located one of the most active mints of the Seleucid kings. Their well known tetradrachms of <orgName type="ethnic">Phœnician</orgName> weight, bearing the eagle type associated with the usual symbol of the Tyrian mint (the club combined with the letters ΤϒΡ), are among the commonest coins of the entire Seleucid series. It is, however, a matter of considerable surprise when we contemplate the fact that the striking of these particular coins only commenced with the reign of <persName corresp="#nomisma_alexander_iii">Alexander</persName> I <persName corresp="#nomisma_c_alli_bala_rrc">Bala</persName> (150–145 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c</hi>.), although the flourishing city of Tyre had already been subject to the Syrian monarchs for over fifty years.</p>
            <p>Under the previous dominion of the Ptolemaic kings of <placeName corresp="#nomisma_egypt">Egypt</placeName> the city had constituted one of their principal mints—
<pb n="2"/>
indeed the most prolific and continuously active one along the entire Phœnician coast.<ref target="#CH1-n1">
                  <hi rend="sup">1</hi>
               </ref> It is difficult to believe, therefore, that Tyre really ceased for a time to coin silver, when in 201 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c</hi>. <persName corresp="#nomisma_antiochus_iii">Antiochus III</persName> entered its gates and the city became the centre of his <orgName type="ethnic">Phœnician</orgName> dominions. The commercial importance of Tyre, its great strategic value, and its past numismatic history all point to the necessary conclusion that its silver coinage could hardly have stopped when it passed from Lagid to Seleucid rule.</p>
            <p>It is true that a few copper coins have already been attributed to Tyre for the period preceding the reign of <persName>Alexander Bala</persName>. In addition, one tetradrachm bearing the portrait of <persName corresp="#nomisma_antiochus_iii">Antiochus III</persName> has also been assigned to this mint by <persName>Dr. J. Rouvier</persName> (No. 1824 in his Numismatique des Villes de la Phénicie, <hi rend="italic">Jour. Int. Num.</hi>, Vol. 6, 1904). This latter piece, however, because of its style and fabric, probably never emanated from the Tyrian mint.<ref target="#CH1-n2">
                  <hi rend="sup">2</hi>
               </ref> We are, therefore, reduced to the above mentioned rather paltry copper coinage as the sole
<pb n="3"/>
representatives for over fifty years of the wealthy city of Tyre and a great Seleucid fortress.</p>
            <p>Induced by this somewhat surprising state of affairs to institute a careful search through the various catalogues of important public collections and also such private collections as were accessible to him, the writer was soon rewarded by finding a comparatively large and remarkably homogeneous group of tetradrachms and drachms whose attribution to Tyre now appears certain. With these the disturbing and, in fact, impossible gap in the Tyrian silver coinage, which extended from the capture of the city by <persName corresp="#nomisma_antiochus_iii">Antiochus III</persName> in 201 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c.</hi> to the inauguration of the well known series of "eagle" tetradrachms of Phœnician weight in 150 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c</hi>. (the first year of Alexander I's reign), is now completely and apparently satisfactorily filled. As the following catalogue shows, every Seleucid sovereign who reigned during the fifty years in question is represented by an adequate silver coinage, in addition to a plentiful series of bronze coins.</p>
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>The writer is here desirous of expressing his deep sense of gratitude to the Rev. Edgar Rogers for his great kindness in allowing him to publish certain rare and apparently unpublished varieties (Nos. 51 and 53). The writer is also very grateful to <persName>Dr. Rogers</persName>, <persName>M. Jameson</persName>, and the authorities of the British Museum and <placeName corresp="#nomisma_paris">Paris</placeName> collections for their kindness and trouble in sending him casts of certain important pieces needed for this article.</p>
            <div2 xml:id="d95e207" type="section">
               <head>ANTIOCHUS III, 223–187 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c</hi>.</head>
               <div3 xml:id="d95e213" type="subsectioin">
                  <head>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">Series I, Circa 201–196 b.c</hi>.</head>
                  <p>1 <hi rend="smallcaps">Tetradrachm</hi>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Obv.</hi> Head to right adorned with diadem with fluttering ends: The features of <persName corresp="#nomisma_antiochus_iii">Antiochus III</persName> are rather fleshy, his nose is comparatively short.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> ΒΑΣΙΛΕΩΣ onright. ANTIOXOϒ on left. Apollo, completely naked, seated to left on omphalos. He holds arrow in outstretched right hand and rests left on a bow of the "composit" type. On r., outside inscription, <graphic url="NNM10_010a.jpg"/> On l., outside inscription, <graphic url="NNM10_010b.jpg"/>
                  </p>
                  <p>Newell Coll. <hi rend="bold">Plate I</hi>.</p>
                  <pb n="5"/>
                  <p>2 <hi rend="smallcaps">Tetradrachm</hi>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Obv.</hi> From the same die as the preceding coin.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> Similar, but the shaft of Apollo's bow forms a simple curve.</p>
                  <p>Newell Coll. <hi rend="bold">Plate I</hi>. Another in commerce, gr. 17.23.</p>
                  <p>3 <hi rend="smallcaps">Chalkous</hi>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Obv.</hi> Similar head to right, at times in a circle of dots.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. ΒΑΣΙΛΕΩΣ above. ΑΝΤΙΟΞΟϒ below. Prow of galley, adorned with dolphin, to l., in circle of dots.</p>
                  <p>Newell Coll. Two specimens, gr. 6.65 and 5.36. <hi rend="bold">Plate I</hi>.</p>
                  <p>4 <hi rend="smallcaps">Chalkous</hi>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Obv.</hi> Similar.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> Similar, but above prow is to be seen the date PIE (= 198–197 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c</hi>.).</p>
                  <p>
                     <placeName corresp="#nomisma_paris">Paris</placeName>, No. 450 (gr. 4.40) Pl. xi, 5; No. 451 gr. 4.90.</p>
                  <p>5 <hi rend="smallcaps">Dilepton</hi>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Obv.</hi> Similar.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> ΒΑΣΙΛΕΩΣ on right. ANTIOXOϒ on left. Palm tree, the whole surrounded by a circle of dots.</p>
                  <p>Newell Coll. gr. 2.76. <hi rend="bold">Plate I</hi>.</p>
                  <pb n="6"/>
                  <p>While conforming in a general way to the types and style of the tetradrachms which the writer has elsewhere<ref target="#CH1-n3">
                        <hi rend="sup">3</hi>
                     </ref> shown must be assigned to Antioch, our two coins, Nos. 1 and 2, nevertheless differ markedly in many minor details. This fact at once suggests the possibility that we have here to do with the issues of another mint. On the other hand, the technique of the diecutting and the fabric of the coins themselves point to a mint whose location could not have been at any very great distance from Antioch, that is to say, as far away as <placeName corresp="#nomisma_greek_asia">Asia</placeName> Minor or <placeName corresp="#nomisma_babylonia">Babylonia</placeName>. We must, therefore, look nearer home—perhaps in <placeName corresp="#nomisma_cilicia">Cilicia</placeName>, <placeName corresp="#nomisma_syria">Syria</placeName>, or along the <orgName type="ethnic">Phœnician</orgName> coast.</p>
                  <p>Again the features of <persName corresp="#nomisma_antiochus_i">Antiochus</persName> on these coins show that he is no longer a young man. The coins must certainly be later than Nos. 7 to 12 on <hi rend="bold">Plate I</hi> of the writer's "The Seleucid Mint of Antioch," where the features are still very youthful. On the other hand, our head does not exhibit the sunken cheeks and sharper profile of Nos. 25 to 30 on <hi rend="bold">Plate II</hi> of the same work.
<pb n="7"/>
In other words, our coins evidently fall somewhere between these two groups and so are to be considered as nearly contemporaneous with Series II of the Antiochene mint which is assigned to about 206–200 B.c. A comparison of the portraiture confirms this in a general way.</p>
                  <p>A glance at our Plate I shows unmistakably the close connection that must exist between the bronze coins (Nos. 3 and 5) there displayed and our two tetradrachms. There is a striking similarity between the portraits which all these coins bear, and a still greater similarity in the style of their die-cutting. So evident is this, that the most conservative of numismatists will probably admit the strong chance that all these coins were perhaps actually issued from one and the same mint. Now the technique displayed by the bronze coins, the flans upon which they were struck and, above all, their types are characteristically, even certainly, <orgName type="ethnic">Phœnician</orgName>. Hence, at least, the tentative assignment of Nos. 1–5 to some important <orgName type="ethnic">Phœnician</orgName> city can hardly be seriously
<pb n="8"/>
disputed. Furthermore, it should be pointed out that the conclusions arrived at above as to the approximate date of their first appearance coincides with the historical fact that <persName corresp="#nomisma_antiochus_iii">Antiochus III</persName> finally secured possession of the <orgName type="ethnic">Phœnician</orgName> coast in the spring of 201 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c</hi>. The actual date borne by No. 4 is probably the terminus of this particular issue. The definite assignment to Tyre, as proposed in this article, of our tetradrachms rests largely upon the attribution of Series II and III.</p>
                  <p>The bronze coins described above have been given, following <persName>M. Babelon</persName> and <persName>Dr. J. Rouvier</persName>, the convenient terms of Chalkous and Dilepton to facilitate a quick distinction between the two denominations used. To determine upon what really are the denominations found in Greek copper coins is a knotty problem, and requires a longer period of research and study before it is placed upon a definite and acceptable basis. The terms are here used only for convenience sake and in deference to <persName>M. Babelon</persName>'s well-known authority.<ref target="#CH1-n4">
                        <hi rend="sup">4</hi>
                     </ref>
                  </p>
               </div3>
               <div3 xml:id="d95e389" type="subsectioin">
                  <pb n="9"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">Series II, Circa 196 b.c</hi>.</head>
                  <p>6 <hi rend="smallcaps">Tetradrachm</hi>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Obv.</hi> Diademed head as on preceding tetradrachms but with longer nose and features less fleshy. The diadem ends henceforth hang down straight instead of fluttering.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> Inscription and type as on Nos. 1 and 2. Apollo is entirely nude as before, but the omphalos is here draped with his himation. His bow is again of the simple type. On l. outside inscription, <graphic url="NNM10_015a.jpg"/> On r., outside inscription, <graphic url="NNM10_015b.jpg"/>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <placeName corresp="#nomisma_paris">Paris</placeName>, No. 336, <hi rend="bold">Plate II</hi>; <placeName corresp="#nomisma_athens">Athens</placeName>, <hi rend="italic">Jour. Int. Num.</hi> Vol. VI, 1903, Pl. vii, 2.</p>
                  <p>7 <hi rend="smallcaps">Tetradrachm</hi>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Obv.</hi> From the same obverse die as was used for the preceding coins.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> Similar. On l., outside inscription, <graphic url="NNM10_015a.jpg"/> On r., outside inscription, <graphic url="NNM10_015c.jpg"/> Newell Coll. <hi rend="bold">Plate II</hi>.</p>
                  <p>8 <hi rend="smallcaps">Tetradrachm</hi>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Obv.</hi> Similar but of higher relief and better style. For the first time a circle of dots surrounds the head.</p>
                  <pb n="10"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> Similar, but the omphalos (as on Nos. 1 and 2), is no longer draped. The bow is of simple style. On l., outside inscription, <graphic url="NNM10_016a.jpg"/> On r., outside inscription, <graphic url="NNM10_016b.jpg"/> In exergue, Bull rushing to l.</p>
                  <p>
                     <placeName corresp="#nomisma_paris">Paris</placeName>, No. 337. <hi rend="bold">Plate II</hi>.</p>
                  <p>Nos. 6 and 7 of this series are united not only by the monogram <graphic url="NNM10_016c.jpg"/> found on both, but especially by the fact that their obverses were struck from the same die. No. 6 bears also the monogram <graphic url="NNM10_016b.jpg"/> which we have seen occurred on our two first tetradrachms Nos. 1 and 2. Therefore, in spite of the minor differences in style and details of design between the two groups, it is probable that they were all struck in one and the same mint. This inference is definitely proved by No. 8 which in style and details of the obverse design is closest to Nos. 6 and 7, but in the style of its reverse is closest to Nos. 1 and 2. Further more, it bears the same two monograms <graphic url="NNM10_016a.jpg"/> and <graphic url="NNM10_016b.jpg"/> found on the tetradrachms of Series I, and so must certainly have been struck at their mint. The infuriated bull which
<pb n="11"/>
is to be seen in the exergue of this coin is probably only a magistrate's symbol.</p>
               </div3>
               <div3 xml:id="d95e482" type="subsectioin">
                  <head>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">Series III, circa 196–188 b.c</hi>.</head>
                  <p>9 <hi rend="smallcaps">Tetradrachm</hi>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Obv.</hi> Diademed head of <persName corresp="#nomisma_antiochus_iii">Antiochus III</persName> to r. surrounded by a circle of dots. The portrait on this and the following coins is somewhat idealized, the features are thinner and sharper, the nose long and pointed. The diadem ends hang down stiffly. The breaks which appear later on this die do not show here.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> On r. ΒΑΣΙΛΕΩΣ; on l., ΑΝΤΙΟXOϒ. Apollo, naked but for his right thigh which is draped, is seated to l. on omphalos, the top of which is also draped. In style and details, this reverse approaches closest to those of Nos. 6 and 7. On l., outside inscription, <graphic url="NNM10_017a.jpg"/> on r., outside inscription, <graphic url="NNM10_017b.jpg"/>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <placeName corresp="#nomisma_paris">Paris</placeName>, No. 291 (erroneously attributed to <persName corresp="#nomisma_antiochus_hierax">Antiochus Hierax</persName>) Pl. viii, fig. 6, here <hi rend="bold">Plate III</hi>. A much finer specimen from the same obverse and reverse dies is shown on Pl. xxii, No. 581, Hirsch Sale, XXXII. 1912.</p>
                  <p>10 <hi rend="smallcaps">Tetradrachm</hi>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Obv.</hi> From the same obverse die. Die
<pb n="12"/>
breaks are here commencing to show at the back of the head.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. As above, but only Apollo's right thigh is draped. On l., outside inscription, <graphic url="NNM10_018a.jpg"/> On r., outside inscription, <graphic url="NNM10_018b.jpg"/>
                     <hi rend="italic">In exergue. Bow in Quiver.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Pozzi Sale, Apr. 4, 1921, Pl. lxxxvi, No. 2948, <hi rend="bold">Plate III</hi>.</p>
                  <p>11 <hi rend="smallcaps">Tetradrachm</hi>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Obv</hi>. From the same die as the preceding, but with the die breaks still more evident.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> Similar to preceding, but with Apollo entirely nude. On l., outside inscription, <graphic url="NNM10_018c.jpg"/> and Lighted Torch. On r., outside inscription, <graphic url="NNM10_018a.jpg"/> In exergue, <hi rend="italic">Club.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <placeName>London</placeName>, No. 7, <hi rend="bold">Plate III</hi>; Newell Coll.; <placeName corresp="#nomisma_paris">Paris</placeName>, No. 290 (erroneously attributed to <persName corresp="#nomisma_antiochus_hierax">Antiochus Hierax</persName>); Pozzi Sale, Apr. 4, 1921, Pl. lxxxvi, No. 2949.</p>
                  <p>12 <hi rend="smallcaps">Tetradrachm</hi>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Obv.</hi> From the same obverse die as was used for the preceding coin.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> Similar. On l., outside inscription, <graphic url="NNM10_018c.jpg"/> On r., outside inscription, <graphic url="NNM10_018a.jpg"/>
                  </p>
                  <p>Newell Coll. <hi rend="bold">Plate IV</hi>. A similar coin, but with the obverse from another die, was sold by Mme. Serrure in her sale of Nov. 18, 1911, No. 76, Pl. iii.</p>
                  <pb n="13"/>
                  <p>13 <hi rend="smallcaps">Drachm</hi>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Obv</hi>, Diademed head similar to preceding.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> Similar type and inscription. On l., outside inscription, <graphic url="NNM10_019a.jpg"/> On r., outside inscription, <graphic url="NNM10_019b.jpg"/> Newell Coll. <hi rend="bold">Plate V</hi>; Pozzi Sale, Apr. 4, 1921, Pl. lxxxvi, No. 2956.</p>
                  <p>14 <hi rend="smallcaps">Tetradrachm</hi>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Obv.</hi> From the same die as Nos. 9–12.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> Similar to preceding. On left, outside inscription, <graphic url="NNM10_019a.jpg"/> On r., outside inscription, <graphic url="NNM10_019b.jpg"/> In exergue, <hi rend="italic">Club.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Rev. Edgar Rogers. <hi rend="bold">Plate IV</hi>.</p>
                  <p>15 <hi rend="smallcaps">Tetradrachm</hi>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Obv.</hi> From the same die as the preceding. This die is now showing very bad breaks and dimmed outlines due to long continued use.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> Similar to preceding. On l., out side inscription, <graphic url="NNM10_019a.jpg"/> above <hi rend="italic">Club.</hi> On r., outside inscription, <graphic url="NNM10_019b.jpg"/> Newell Coll. <hi rend="bold">Plate IV</hi>; another in commerce.</p>
                  <p>16 <hi rend="smallcaps">Chalkous</hi>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Obv.</hi> Diademed head with sharp features as on preceding coins. Circle of dots around.</p>
                  <pb n="14"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> ΒΑΣΙΛΕΩΣ above. ΑNTIOXOϒ below. Stem of galley (not prow as described by <persName>M. Babelon</persName>). In field the date PIZ (= 196–195 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c</hi>.)</p>
                  <p>
                     <placeName corresp="#nomisma_paris">Paris</placeName>, No. 452. gr. 7.75. Pl. xi, 6.</p>
                  <p>17 <hi rend="smallcaps">Chalkous</hi>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Obv</hi>. Similar.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> Similar but date is ΡΙΘ (= 194–193 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c</hi>.).</p>
                  <p>Newell Coll. gr. 7.20. <hi rend="bold">Plate V</hi>.</p>
                  <p>18 <hi rend="smallcaps">Chalkous</hi>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Obv.</hi> Similar.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> Similar but date is PK (= 193192 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c</hi>.).</p>
                  <p>Newell Coll. gr. 9.32.</p>
                  <p>19 <hi rend="smallcaps">Chalkous</hi>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Obv.</hi> Similar.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> Similar but date is ΡΚΔ (= 189188 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c</hi>.).</p>
                  <p>
                     <placeName>London</placeName>, No. 33.</p>
                  <p>20 <hi rend="smallcaps">Dilepton</hi>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Obv.</hi> Similar, features thinner and sharper than on No. 5.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> ΒΑΣΙΛΕΩΣ on r. ΑNTIOXOϒ on l. Palm tree. The whole in circle of dots.</p>
                  <pb n="15"/>
                  <p>Newell Coll. 4 specimens, gr. 3.27, 2.35, 2.24, 2.05 <hi rend="bold">Plate V</hi>; <placeName corresp="#nomisma_paris">Paris</placeName>, Nos. 577–578, gr. 2.00 and 3.15 (erroneously assigned to <persName corresp="#nomisma_antiochus_iv">Antiochus IV</persName>); <persName>Dr. Rouvier</persName>, No. 1823; <placeName>London</placeName>, No. 48, Pl. ix, 8.</p>
                  <p>We need not here delay over the attribution of the bronze coins Nos. 16–20 to Tyre, an attribution that is certain and recognized by all recent authorities. The dates PIZ to ΡΚΔ which appear on the larger of the two denominations show their issue to have taken place between the years 196 and 189 B.c. The small bronze pieces, Nos. 5 and 20, with the type of the palm tree, are the beginning of a long line of similar pieces whose attribution to Tyre is certain and has so been recognized by <persName>Dr. J. Rouvier</persName> as well as by <persName>M. Babelon</persName>.</p>
                  <p>Nos. 9, 10, 11, 12, 14 and 15, form a remarkably homogeneous group. All the known specimens, with but a single exception (an example of No. 12) are struck from one and the same obverse die. A glance at these coins, as reproduced on Plates III and IV, shows clearly the advancing wear, breaks, and general deterioration of the particular die in question, due to its long continued service. Especially
<pb n="16"/>
to be noted is the fact that this group of coins throughout displays a monogram already used for the issues of Series I and II, namely <graphic url="NNM10_022a.jpg"/>, thus conclusively proving that these coins must all be the issues of a single mint. Finally, the tetradrachms of Series III are important as now, for the first time in Seleucid numismatics, appears the Club—the customary attribute of Tyrian Heracles and the usual symbol of the mint of Tyre. The two symbols, Lighted Torch and Quiver, occurring on our coins only intermittently, are evidently but the symbols of magistrates responsible for the coinage and so, unlike the Club, do not occur again on later issues.</p>
               </div3>
               <div3 xml:id="d95e794" type="subsectioin">
                  <head>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">Series IV, circa</hi> 188–187 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c</hi>.</head>
                  <p>21 <hi rend="smallcaps">Tetradrachm</hi>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Obv.</hi> Diademed head of <persName corresp="#nomisma_antiochus_iii">Antiochus III</persName> to r.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> ΒΑΣΙΛΕΩΣ on r. ΑNTIOXOϒ on l. Apollo seated to l. on omphalos, holding arrow in right hand and resting left on bow. On l., outside inscription ΣΑ and <hi rend="italic">Club.</hi> On r., outside inscription, <graphic url="NNM10_022b.jpg"/>
                  </p>
                  <p>Coll, of <persName>Dr. E. P. Robinson</persName>. <hi rend="bold">Plate V</hi>.</p>
                  <pb n="17"/>
                  <p>The single known tetradrachm of Series IV was probably struck but a short time previous to the death of <persName corresp="#nomisma_antiochus_iii">Antiochus III</persName>. This follows from the fact that not only the symbol but also both monograms are found on the immediately succeeding issue of <persName corresp="#nomisma_seleucus_iv">Seleucus IV</persName>. Thus is finally crystallized the general type and character of the silver issues of Seleucid Tyre until the time when the entire system was changed by <persName>Alexander I Bala</persName>.</p>
                  <p>The style of No. 21 is identical with that of the immediately preceding tetradrachms of Series III. Like them, it bears the mint symbol <hi rend="italic">Club,</hi> and the monogram <graphic url="NNM10_023.jpg"/> which has been found to occur on Nos. 9 to 15 inclusive. Further proof of the identity of the mint is hardly necessary. A new magistrate, signing his initials ΣΑ immediately above the club, appears now for the first time, but we will have further occasion to record his signature on the succeeding issues of <persName corresp="#nomisma_seleucus_iv">Seleucus IV</persName> and <persName corresp="#nomisma_antiochus_iv">Antiochus IV</persName>.</p>
               </div3>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d95e855" type="sectioin">
               <pb n="18"/>
               <head>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">
                     <persName corresp="#nomisma_seleucus_iv">Seleucus IV</persName>, 187–175 b.c</hi>.</head>
               <p>22 <hi rend="smallcaps">Tetradrachm</hi>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Obv.</hi> Diademed head of <persName corresp="#nomisma_seleucus_iv">Seleucus IV</persName> to r. Circle of dots.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. ΒΑΣΙΛΕΩΣ on r. ΣΕΛΕϒΚΟϒ on l. Apollo seated to r. as on previous issues, holding arrow in outstretched right hand and resting left on bow. On l., outside inscription, <hi rend="italic">Club</hi> and ΣΑ. On r., outside inscription, <graphic url="NNM10_024a.jpg"/> (or <graphic url="NNM10_024b.jpg"/>).</p>
               <p>Rev. Edgar Rogers Coll. <hi rend="bold">Plate VI</hi>.</p>
               <p>23 <hi rend="smallcaps">Tetradrachm</hi>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Obv.</hi> Similar.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Similar. On l., outside inscription, <hi rend="italic">Club</hi> and ΣΑ. On r., outside inscription, <graphic url="NNM10_024c.jpg"/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Num. Chron.,</hi> 1883. Pl. vi, No. 3; Rev. Edgar Rogers, <hi rend="bold">Plate VI</hi> (the club is missing on this specimen).</p>
               <p>24 <hi rend="smallcaps">Chalkous</hi>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Obv</hi>. Similar diademed head of <persName corresp="#nomisma_seleucus_iv">Seleucus IV</persName> to r. Circle of pearls.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. ΒΑΣΙΛΕΩΣ above. ΣΕΛΕϒΚΟϒ below. Stem of galley as on the later bronze issues of <persName corresp="#nomisma_antiochus_iii">Antiochus III</persName>. In
<pb n="19"/>
field, the date ΕΛΡ (= 178–177 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c</hi>.).</p>
               <p>
                  <placeName>Glasgow</placeName>, Hunterian Coll., No. 11 (gr. 7.55), Pl. lxvi, 5.</p>
               <p>25 <hi rend="smallcaps">Chalkous</hi>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Obv.</hi> Similar.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> Similar, but date is SΛΡ (= 177–176 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c</hi>.).</p>
               <p>
                  <placeName corresp="#nomisma_paris">Paris</placeName>, No. 509 (gr. 7.10), No. 510 (gr. 6.80).</p>
               <p>26 <hi rend="smallcaps">Chalkous</hi>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Obv,</hi> Similar.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev,</hi> Similar, but date is ΡΛΗ (=176–175 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c</hi>.).</p>
               <p>
                  <placeName corresp="#nomisma_paris">Paris</placeName>, No. 512 (gr. 7.20), Pl. xi, 20; <placeName>Glasgow</placeName>, Hunterian Coll. No. 12 (gr. 6.84); Newell Coll., (gr. 6.95) <hi rend="bold">Plate VI</hi>.</p>
               <p>27 <hi rend="smallcaps">Chalkous</hi>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Obv.</hi> Similar.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> Similar, but date is ΡΛΗ (= 175–174 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c</hi>.).</p>
               <p>Newell Coll., gr. 6.30.</p>
               <p>28 <hi rend="smallcaps">Dilepton</hi>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Obv.</hi> Similar.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. ΒΑΣΙΛΕΩΣ on r. ΣΕΛΕϒΚΟϒ on l. Palm tree, the whole in circle of dots.</p>
               <p>Newell Coll. (gr. 2.00) <hi rend="bold">Plate VI</hi>.</p>
               <pb n="20"/>
               <p>The two tetradrachms described above, bearing the name and portrait of <persName corresp="#nomisma_seleucus_iv">Seleucus IV</persName>, follow closely the type and style of his father's last issue in Tyre. Each coin, furthermore, displays in the left field, outside the inscription, the magistrate's initials ΣΑ and beneath them the mint-mark Club—thus exactly reproducing the above mentioned piece of <persName corresp="#nomisma_antiochus_iii">Antiochus III</persName> (No. 21). Finally, in the right field of our coins are to be seen either <graphic url="NNM10_026a.jpg"/> (No. 22) or <graphic url="NNM10_026b.jpg"/> (No. 23), both monograms occurring frequently on preceding coinages. There can be no possible question, therefore, but that we here possess issues for the same mint whose activities we have studied for the preceding reign.</p>
               <p>The bronze coins, Nos. 24–28, likewise carry on the issues of <persName corresp="#nomisma_antiochus_iii">Antiochus III</persName> for Tyre. We see the same types used for the two denominations struck, excepting only that the portrait and name of <persName corresp="#nomisma_seleucus_iv">Seleucus IV</persName> have now been substituted for those of his father <persName corresp="#nomisma_antiochus_iii">Antiochusthe Great</persName>. Similarly, it is only the larger of the two denominations that bear dates, in this case ΕΛΡ
<pb n="21"/>
to ΡΛΗ inclusive. This latter date PΛH (year 138 Aer. Sel. = after September 30th of 175 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c</hi>.) is interesting as its existence on the coinage of <persName corresp="#nomisma_seleucus_iv">Seleucus IV</persName> has been questioned more than once. First published by Sestini (<hi rend="italic">Lett. Num.</hi> Vol. VIII, p. 110) where, however, the coin has been wrongly described, the portrait of <persName corresp="#nomisma_seleucus_i">Seleucus</persName> being called a bust of Dionysus and the ship's stern a prow—it has been republished by Mionnet although he questions it in the following terms: <hi rend="italic">"Si cette date a été bien lue</hi>, elle <hi rend="italic">donne un grand prix à cette médaille qui prolonge le règne de <persName corresp="#nomisma_seleucus_iv">Seleucus IV</persName> d'une année ou de quelques mois</hi>, puisque <hi rend="italic">c'est en l'an</hi> 138 <hi rend="italic">de l'ère des Séleucides qu' <persName corresp="#nomisma_antiochus_iv">Antiochus IV</persName> est monté sur le trône."</hi> Furthermore, Cavedoni (<hi rend="italic">Rev. Num.</hi> 1856, p. 377) has attempted to reject the date PΛH, while Clinton in his <hi rend="italic">Fasti Hellenici</hi> does not even mention it under the reign of <persName corresp="#nomisma_seleucus_iv">Seleucus IV</persName>. On these apparently sufficient grounds <persName>M. Babelon</persName>, too, in his <hi rend="italic">"Les Rois de Syrie</hi>, d'<hi rend="italic">Arm' nie et de Commagène</hi>," p. xci, discards the date in question from among the coins of <persName corresp="#nomisma_seleucus_i">Seleucus</persName>. On the other hand,
<pb n="22"/>
the coin in the author's collection (No. 27) is unquestionably an issue of <persName corresp="#nomisma_seleucus_iv">Seleucus IV</persName> as it bears a typical portrait of that king, while the name ΣΕΛΕϒΚΟϒ is plainly visible. The types correct the description of the coin given by Sestini and prove the piece to belong to the issues of the mint now under discussion. The date ΡΛΗ, in its usual position immediately above the stern, is quite legible, and, in particular, the final letter H—the crux of the whole matter—chances to be clearest of all. The coin is not reproduced on our plate as the character of the patina with which it is covered is such that, while the date is quite legible to the naked eye, it has been found impossible to secure a plaster cast of sufficient clearness to make reproduction on the plates worth while.</p>
               <p>The presence of the date ΡΛΗ on a coin of <persName corresp="#nomisma_seleucus_iv">Seleucus IV</persName> is proved by the specimen in the author's collection. Can we explain this appearance in the face of the general scepticism among scholars recorded above? I think the true explanation lies in the circumstances immediately follow+
<pb n="23"/>
ing the assassination of <persName corresp="#nomisma_seleucus_iv">Seleucus IV</persName> by his minister Heliodorus. This latter event appears in all probability to have occurred in the summer of 175 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c</hi>., as the chronologists give <persName corresp="#nomisma_seleucus_i">Seleucus</persName> twelve years of reign. Now there followed several months of doubt and uncertainty regarding the succession to the Seleucid throne. Heliodorus as regent probably proclaimed <persName corresp="#nomisma_antiochus_i">Antiochus</persName>, infant son of the murdered king, and carried on the rule in his name. On the other hand, <persName corresp="#nomisma_antiochus_i">Antiochus</persName>, the brother of <persName corresp="#nomisma_seleucus_iv">Seleucus IV</persName>, being at <placeName corresp="#nomisma_athens">Athens</placeName> when the news of the assassination reached him, immediately proclaimed his own candidacy to the throne. He sailed for <placeName corresp="#nomisma_greek_asia">Asia</placeName> Minor and with the assistance of Eumenes, king of Pergamum, finally overcame Heliodorus and secured the dominions of his brother These events must have covered many months to allow sufficient time for the news to reach <placeName corresp="#nomisma_athens">Athens</placeName>, for <persName corresp="#nomisma_antiochus_i">Antiochus</persName> to arrive in <placeName corresp="#nomisma_greek_asia">Asia</placeName> Minor, for Eumenes to collect his forces, for the subsequent advance into <placeName corresp="#nomisma_syria">Syria</placeName> and for the eventual overthrow of Heliodorus. It might well be, therefore,
<pb n="24"/>
that the Seleucid year 138—which we now know for certain saw the striking of bronze coins with the names of both <persName corresp="#nomisma_seleucus_iv">Seleucus IV</persName> (No. 27) and <persName corresp="#nomisma_antiochus_iv">Antiochus IV</persName> (No. 33)—was already several months old before <persName corresp="#nomisma_antiochus_i">Antiochus</persName> finally found himself completely master of the situation. In the meanwhile things must have been somewhat uncertain. And as small change was needed in Tyre, the authorities there decided to continue the bronze coinage with the old types but bearing the correct date PΛH. Such a procedure neither faction could really take amiss. So soon as <persName corresp="#nomisma_antiochus_i">Antiochus</persName> was definitely established in Syria, Tyre hastened to change the old types for the new ones on her coinages.</p>
               <p>It is, of course, possible that the assassination of <persName corresp="#nomisma_seleucus_i">Seleucus</persName> did not actually take place until after the commencement of the year 138 <hi rend="italic">A er. Sel</hi>. (that is after September or October 175 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c</hi>.)—we do not know the exact date of this occurrence. Such dated cuneiform tablets as have been published<ref target="#CH1-n5">
                     <hi rend="sup">5</hi>
                  </ref> do not help us much in this regard. The latest one dated in the reign
<pb n="25"/>
of <persName corresp="#nomisma_seleucus_iv">Seleucus IV</persName> bears the date 135 <hi rend="italic">A er. Sel</hi>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">. (= 177–176 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c</hi>.)</hi>, while the first one of <persName corresp="#nomisma_antiochus_iv">Antiochus IV</persName> was dated on the 22nd day of Iyyar of the year 138. This corresponds to May 174 B.C., as in <orgName type="ethnic">Babylonian</orgName> records the Seleucid Era appears to have been computed from the first of Nisan (April) of 312 B.C.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d95e1209" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">
                     <persName corresp="#nomisma_antiochus_iv">Antiochus IV</persName>
                  </hi>, 175–164 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c</hi>.</head>
               <div3 xml:id="d95e1218" type="subsection">
                  <head>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">Series I</hi>.</head>
                  <p>29 <hi rend="smallcaps">Tetradrachm</hi>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Obv.</hi> Diademed head of <persName corresp="#nomisma_antiochus_iv">Antiochus IV</persName> to r. Around, fillet (?) border.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> ΒΑΣΙΛΕΩΣ on r. ΑΝΤΙΟΧΟϒ on l. Apollo seated to l. on omphalos, holds arrow in outstretched right hand and rests left on bow. On l., outside inscription, ΣΑ over <hi rend="italic">Club.</hi> On r., outside inscription, <graphic url="NNM10_031.jpg"/>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <placeName corresp="#nomisma_paris">Paris</placeName>, No. 518. <hi rend="bold">Plate VII</hi>.</p>
                  <p>30 <hi rend="smallcaps">Drachm</hi>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Obv.</hi> Similar.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Similar.</p>
                  <p>
                     <placeName corresp="#nomisma_athens">Athens</placeName>. <hi rend="bold">Plate VII</hi>.</p>
                  <p>31 <hi rend="smallcaps">Drachm</hi>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Obv.</hi> Similar.</p>
                  <pb n="26"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> Similar, but Club is in exergue and ΣΑ is missing.</p>
                  <p>
                     <placeName>Glasgow</placeName> (Hunterian Coll. No. 6).</p>
                  <p>32 <hi rend="smallcaps">Drachm</hi>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Obv.</hi> Similar.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> Similar, but Club only on l.</p>
                  <p>
                     <placeName>Glasgow</placeName> (Hunterian Coll. No. 7.)</p>
                  <p>33 <hi rend="smallcaps">Chalkous</hi>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Obv.</hi> Similar. Circle of dots.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> ΒΑΣΙΛΕΩΣ above. ΑΝΤΙΟΧΟϒ below. Stern of galley above which is date L ΡΛΗ (= 175–174 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c</hi>.).</p>
                  <p>
                     <placeName corresp="#nomisma_paris">Paris</placeName>, No. 672 (gr. 7.20), Pl. xiv, fig. 19; Rouvier Coll., No. 1840, where type is wrongly described as <hi rend="italic">prow.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>34 <hi rend="smallcaps">Chalkous</hi>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Obv.</hi> Similar.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> Similar, but date is ΛΘΛΠ (= 174–173 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c</hi>.).</p>
                  <p>
                     <placeName corresp="#nomisma_paris">Paris</placeName>, No. 673 (gr. 5.45).</p>
                  <p>35 <hi rend="smallcaps">Dilepton</hi>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Obv.</hi> Similar.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> ΒΑΣΙΛΕΩΣ on r. ΑNTIOXOϒ on l. Palm tree.</p>
                  <p>Rouvier Coll., No. 1845.</p>
               </div3>
               <div3 xml:id="d95e1364" type="subsection">
                  <pb n="27"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">Series II</hi>.</head>
                  <p>36 <hi rend="smallcaps">Tetradrachm</hi>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Obv.</hi> Diademed head of <persName corresp="#nomisma_antiochus_iv">Antiochus IV</persName> to r. Fillet border around.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> ΒΑΣΙΛΕΩΣ on r. ΑNTIOXOϒ on l. Apollo, as on No. 29, seated to l. On l., outside inscription, <graphic url="NNM10_033a.jpg"/>
                     <hi rend="italic">over Club.</hi> On r., outside inscription, <graphic url="NNM10_033b.jpg"/>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <persName>R. Jameson</persName> Coll., No. 1696. <hi rend="bold">Plate VII</hi>.</p>
                  <p>37 <hi rend="smallcaps">Tetradrachm</hi>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Obv.</hi> Similar.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> Similar. On l., outside inscription, <graphic url="NNM10_033c.jpg"/> over <hi rend="italic">Wing,</hi> On r., outside inscription, <graphic url="NNM10_033d.jpg"/>
                     <hi rend="italic">Club</hi> in exergue.</p>
                  <p>
                     <placeName>Glasgow</placeName> (Hunterian Coll., No. 5), Pl. lxvi, 10.</p>
                  <p>38. <hi rend="smallcaps">Chalkous</hi>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Obv.</hi> Diademed head of <persName corresp="#nomisma_antiochus_iv">Antiochus IV</persName> to r. Behind ΔΜΡ (= 169–168 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c</hi>.). <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> ΒΑΣΙΛΕΩΣ ΑNTIOXOϒ TϒΡΙΩΝ in three lines above stern of galley.</p>
                  <p>
                     <graphic url="NNM10_033e.jpg"/> in two lines beneath.</p>
                  <p>Newell (gr. 7.33); Rouvier Coll. No. 1842, Pl. xviii, 25; <placeName>London</placeName>, No. 55; <placeName corresp="#nomisma_paris">Paris</placeName>, Nos. 674 (Pl. xiv. fig. 20) to 677 (gr. 7.50, 7.75, 8.50, 7.65).</p>
                  <pb n="28"/>
                  <p>39 <hi rend="smallcaps">Chalkous</hi>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Obv.</hi> Similar, but date is EMP (= 168–167 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c</hi>.).</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> Similar.</p>
                  <p>
                     <placeName corresp="#nomisma_paris">Paris</placeName>, No. 678 (gr. 6.35).</p>
                  <p>40 <hi rend="smallcaps">Chalkous</hi>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Obv.</hi> Similar, but the head is also radiate and there is no date.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> Similar inscriptions, but type represents prow of a galley.</p>
                  <p>
                     <placeName corresp="#nomisma_paris">Paris</placeName>, Nos. 679–681 (gr. 6.10, 7.70, 6.85); Rouvier Coll. No. 1844.</p>
                  <p>Rouvier describes these coins as showing a prow instead of the stern of a galley, and cites the pieces in the <placeName corresp="#nomisma_paris">Paris</placeName> Collection. <persName>M. Babelon</persName>, however, makes no note of the change in type.</p>
                  <p>In the 138th year of the Seleucid Era, the brilliant but erratic <persName corresp="#nomisma_antiochus_iv">Antiochus IV</persName>, surnamed Epiphanes, finally became established as ruler of the empire. This we learn definitely from the dated bronze coins struck in Tyre (Nos. 27 and 33), which in that year substituted his name and portrait for those of <persName corresp="#nomisma_seleucus_i">Seleucus</persName> his predecessor.</p>
                  <p>With regard to the Tyrian silver issues of <persName corresp="#nomisma_antiochus_i">Antiochus</persName>, we should note that the first
<pb n="29"/>
series continues exactly the style and appearance of the <persName corresp="#nomisma_seleucus_i">Seleucus</persName>' coinage for this mint. The two magistrates ΣΑ and <graphic url="NNM10_035.jpg"/> again sign their initials on the coinage, thus making it certain that we have here the issues of a single mint.</p>
                  <p>The break which occurs in the Tyrian bronze coinage (no issues known between ΘΛΡ and ΔΜΡ) appears to extend to the silver coinage as well. An interval of some years duration must have elapsed between the appearance of Nos. 29 and 36. Though they are evidently the issues of one mint—they both display the club symbol, which by now we have come to recognize as characteristic of our series, and the same magistrate's monogram <graphic url="NNM10_035.jpg"/>—there is a noticeable difference in style. In this respect the earlier coin is nearest to its immediate predecessors under <persName corresp="#nomisma_seleucus_iv">Seleucus IV</persName>. Its style is fine, its relief is still rather high, its flan is small and the surface of its reverse is somewhat concave.</p>
                  <p>On the other hand, Nos. 36 and 37 are more closely allied with the succeeding silver issues under <persName>Antiochus V</persName> and
<pb n="30"/>
                     <persName corresp="#nomisma_demetrius_i">Demetrius I</persName>. Like them, Nos. 36 and 37 are of lower relief and more spread fabric. On No. 37, for the first time, an additional symbol—a wing—appears in the field, and is henceforth always present until the reform instituted in the Tyrian coinage in the first year of <persName>Alexander I Bala</persName>.</p>
               </div3>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d95e1540" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">Antiochus V</hi>, 164–162 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c</hi>.</head>
               <p>On the sudden death of <persName corresp="#nomisma_antiochus_i">Antiochus</persName>
                  <persName corresp="#nomisma_antiochus_iv">Epiphanes</persName>, his young son, also named <persName corresp="#nomisma_antiochus_i">Antiochus</persName>, succeeded him for a short and troubled reign of two years. None-the-less, both silver and bronze coins were issued in his name at Tyre, as the following pieces bear witness.</p>
               <p>41 <hi rend="smallcaps">Tetradrachm</hi>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Obv.</hi> Diademed head of <persName>Antiochus V</persName> to r. Fillet border.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> ΒΑΣΙΛΕΩΣ on r. ΑNTIOXOϒ on l. ΕϒΠΑΤΟΡΟΣ in exergue. Apollo seated to l. as on No. 36. On l., outside inscription, <graphic url="NNM10_036a.jpg"/> above <hi rend="italic">Wing.</hi> On r., outside inscription, <graphic url="NNM10_036b.jpg"/> above <hi rend="italic">Club.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <placeName>London</placeName>, No. 1. <hi rend="bold">Plate VII</hi>.</p>
               <p>42 <hi rend="smallcaps">Dilepton</hi>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Obv.</hi> Similar. Border of dots.</p>
               <pb n="31"/>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> ΒΑΣΙΛΕΩΣ on r. ΑNTIOXOϒ on l. Palm tree.</p>
               <p>Rouvier Coll., No. 1846. Pl. xviii, 23.</p>
               <p>43 <hi rend="smallcaps">Dilepton</hi>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Obv.</hi> Similar.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> Similar, but in field N—P (= 163–162 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c</hi>.).</p>
               <p>Cat. Walcher de Molthein No. 2947, Pl. xxvi; Newell Coll. (gr. 2.43).</p>
               <p>Rouvier Coll., No. 1847. <hi rend="bold">Plate VII</hi>.</p>
               <p>In style and appearance these coins are exactly similar to the last issues under <persName corresp="#nomisma_antiochus_iv">Antiochus IV</persName>. On the tetradrachm we may notice the monograms of the two magistrates who had previously signed No. 37. Our coin also displays the <hi rend="italic">Club</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Wing</hi> symbols. For the first time in our mint there now appears on the silver coinage the official appellation—in this case E<hi rend="italic">ύπἀτωρ</hi>—of the ruling king, a custom which had already become prevalent in the central mint of Antioch under <persName corresp="#nomisma_antiochus_iv">Antiochus IV</persName> (see the author's "The Seleucid Mint of Antioch," <hi rend="italic">Amer. Jour. of Num.,</hi> Vol. LI).</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d95e1651" type="section">
               <pb n="32"/>
               <head>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">
                     <persName corresp="#nomisma_demetrius_i">Demetrius I</persName>, 162–151 b.c</hi>.</head>
               <p>44 <hi rend="smallcaps">Tetradrachm</hi>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Obv.</hi> Diademed head of <persName corresp="#nomisma_demetrius_i">Demetrius I</persName>. to r., the whole surrounded by a laurel wreath.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> ΒΑΣΙΛΕΩΣ on r. ΔΗΜΗΤΡΙΟϒ on l. Tyche enthroned to l., holds short sceptre in r. hand and cornucopiæ in l. On l., outside inscription, <graphic url="NNM10_038a.jpg"/> over <hi rend="italic">Club.</hi> On r., outside inscription, <graphic url="NNM10_038b.jpg"/>
                  <hi rend="italic">over Wing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <placeName>London</placeName>, No. 35; Warren Coll., No. 1301. Pl. xxx; <placeName corresp="#nomisma_paris">Paris</placeName> (recent acquisition), monogram here is <graphic url="NNM10_038c.jpg"/>
                  <hi rend="bold">Plate VIII</hi>.</p>
               <p>45 <hi rend="smallcaps">Tetradrachm</hi>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Obv.</hi> Similar.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> Similar. On l., outside inscription, <graphic url="NNM10_038d.jpg"/> over <hi rend="italic">Wing.</hi> On r., outside inscription, <graphic url="NNM10_038b.jpg"/> In exergue, <hi rend="italic">Club.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <placeName corresp="#nomisma_paris">Paris</placeName>, No. 714, <hi rend="bold">Plate VIII</hi>; <placeName>Glasgow</placeName> (Hunterian Coll., No. 7).</p>
               <p>46 <hi rend="smallcaps">Drachm</hi>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Obv.</hi> Similar but head is surrounded with a dotted border instead of the laurel wreath.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> Similar. On l., outside inscrip-
<pb n="33"/>
tion, <graphic url="NNM10_039a.jpg"/> over <hi rend="italic">Wing,</hi> On r., outside inscription, <graphic url="NNM10_039b.jpg"/> In exergue, <hi rend="italic">Club.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Egger, XLV, Pl. xix, 680; Rev. Edgar Rogers Coll., <hi rend="bold">Plate VIII</hi>; Petrowicz Coll. (Z.f.N. Vol. XXIX, 1912, Pl. iv, 17).</p>
               <p>47 <hi rend="smallcaps">Chalkous</hi>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Obv.</hi> Diademed head of <persName corresp="#nomisma_demetrius_i">Demetrius</persName> to r. Border of dots.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> ΒΑΣΙΛΕΩΣ ΔΗΜΗΤΡΙΟϒ ΛΔΝΠ (= 159–158 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c</hi>.) in three lines above stern of galley. ΤϒΡΙΩΝ and <graphic url="NNM10_039c.jpg"/> beneath.</p>
               <p>
                  <placeName>London</placeName>, Nos. 43 and 44; <placeName corresp="#nomisma_paris">Paris</placeName>, No. 770 (gr. 8.10) and No. 771 (gr. 6.05) Pl. xvii, fig. 2; Rouvier Coll., No. 1850; Newell Coll. (gr. 7.24).</p>
               <p>48 <hi rend="smallcaps">Hemichalkous</hi>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Obv.</hi> Similar.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> ΒΑΣΙΛΕΩΣ ΔΗΜΗΤΡΙΟϒ ΤϒΡΙΩΝ in three lines above prow to l. ΛΔΝΡ (= 159–158 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c</hi>.) and <graphic url="NNM10_039d.jpg"/> in exergue.</p>
               <p>Rouvier Coll., No. 1848, Pl. xviii, 27; Rev. Edgar Rogers Coll.</p>
               <p>49 <hi rend="smallcaps">Hemichalkous</hi>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Obv.</hi> Similar.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> ΒΑΣΙΛΕΩΣ ΔΗΜΗΤΡΙϒ LΔΝΡ in three lines above prow to l. ΤϒΡΙΩΝ and <graphic url="NNM10_039e.jpg"/> in exergue.</p>
               <pb n="34"/>
               <p>Rouvier Coll., No. 1849, Pl. xviii, 26; Rev. Edgar ogers Coll. <hi rend="bold">Plate VIII</hi>.</p>
               <p>50 <hi rend="smallcaps">Chalkous</hi>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Obv.</hi> Similar.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> Similar to No. 47 except that date is LHNP (= 155–154 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c</hi>.).</p>
               <p>Newell Coll (gr. 7.30, 6.25); <placeName corresp="#nomisma_paris">Paris</placeName>, Nos. 772 to 774 (gr. 6.10, 7.70, 6.50); <placeName>London</placeName>, Nos. 45 and 46; Rouvier Coll., No. 1851; Rev. Edgar Rogers Coll.</p>
               <p>51 <hi rend="smallcaps">Hemichalkous</hi>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Obv</hi>. Similar.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> Like No. 49 but dated HNP.</p>
               <p>Rev. Edgar Rogers Coll.</p>
               <p>52 <hi rend="smallcaps">Chalkous</hi>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Obv.</hi> Similar.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> Similar to No. 50, except that the date is ΘΝΡ (= 154–153 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c</hi>.).</p>
               <p>Newell Coll. (gr. 6.55); <placeName corresp="#nomisma_paris">Paris</placeName>, Nos. 775, 776 (gr. 7.10, 6.55); <placeName>London</placeName>, Nos. 47 and 48; Rouvier Coll., No. 1852; Rev. Edgar Rogers Coll.</p>
               <p>53 <hi rend="smallcaps">Hemichalkous</hi>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Obv.</hi> Similar.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> Similar to No. 51, except that date is ΘΝΡ.</p>
               <p>Rev. Edgar Rogers Coll.</p>
               <p>54 <hi rend="smallcaps">Dilepton</hi>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Obv.</hi> Similar.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> ΒΑΣΙΛΕΩΣ on r. ΔΗΜΗΤΡΙΟϒ
<pb n="35"/>
on l. Palm tree. Date is ΞΡ (= 153–152 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c</hi>.).</p>
               <p>
                  <placeName corresp="#nomisma_paris">Paris</placeName>, No. 779 (gr. 2.45), Pl. xvii. fig. 3: Newell Coll. (gr. 2.08, 2.20, 1.80, 1.90). <hi rend="bold">Plate VIII</hi>.</p>
               <p>55 <hi rend="smallcaps">Dilepton</hi>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Obv.</hi> Similar.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Rev.</hi> Similar, except that date reads ΛΑ–ΞΡ (= 152–151 <hi rend="smallcaps">b.c</hi>.).</p>
               <p>Schroeder Coll., Beyrout.</p>
               <p>
                  <persName corresp="#nomisma_demetrius_i">Demetrius</persName>' Tyrian coins, both in silver and bronze, continue all the features first introduced during the latter portion of <persName corresp="#nomisma_antiochus_i">Antiochus</persName> Epiphanes' reign and continued in the coinage of his young son <persName>Antiochus V</persName>. The issues of <persName corresp="#nomisma_demetrius_i">Demetrius</persName> are still supervised by the magistrate <graphic url="NNM10_041.jpg"/> and the tetradrachms and drachms all bear the symbols <hi rend="italic">Club</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Wing.</hi> The coinage continues at intervals throughout the twelve years reign of <persName corresp="#nomisma_demetrius_i">Demetrius</persName> until the 161st of the Seleucid era. In that year his rival, <persName corresp="#nomisma_alexander_iii">Alexander</persName> I, surnamed Bala, first secured a good foothold in <placeName corresp="#nomisma_phoenicia">Phœnicia</placeName>. The following year the latter finally succeeded in completely overthrowing <persName corresp="#nomisma_demetrius_i">Demetrius</persName>, who perished in a pitched battle fought not far from Antioch.</p>
               <pb n="36"/>
               <p>It was in that very same year, namely 162 of the Seleucid Era, that <persName corresp="#nomisma_alexander_iii">Alexander</persName> first introduced the Ptolemaic system of coinage into the Seleucid series. These new tetradrachms and didrachms are of <orgName type="ethnic">Phœnician</orgName> weight, they display the portrait of the ruler on the obverse, his name and the Ptolemaic eagle on the reverse. They were first struck in large quantities at the mints of Tyre, <placeName corresp="#nomisma_sidon">Sidon</placeName> and Berytus. The monograms or symbols of these cities are conspicuously placed in the reverse field. Tyre is designated by a Club and monogram, <placeName corresp="#nomisma_sidon">Sidon</placeName> by ΣΙ and an Acrostolium, Berytus by a Trident.</p>
               <p>* * * * *</p>
               <p>In the preceding pages has been described a group of silver tetradrachms and occasional drachms which together form an unusually homogeneous series. With the exception of a few varieties at the very commencement, every one of these silver coins displays a club as symbol, in addition to varying monograms and other symbols. The club, therefore, is the characteristic symbol of this series as a whole, and we
<pb n="37"/>
have every reason for recognizing in it the symbol of the mint which once issued this group of coins. To judge by the portrait of <persName corresp="#nomisma_antiochus_iii">Antiochus III</persName>, under whom this issue commenced, its first appearance must be assigned to about the middle of that monarch's reign. It finally came to an end with the accession of <persName>Alexander Bala</persName>, who substituted his well-known <orgName type="ethnic">Phœnician</orgName> tetradrachms with their accompanying smaller denominations. No coins similar to those described in the preceding pages have so far been published or exist in any collection to which the writer has had access, which bear any other portrait than those of the five kings immediately preceding <persName>Alexander Bala</persName>.</p>
               <p>In the introduction attention was called to the surprising fact that scholars have not yet been successful in assigning any Seleucid silver issues to the wealthy seaport of Tyre, from the time it was finally captured by <persName corresp="#nomisma_antiochus_iii">Antiochus III</persName> to the death of <persName corresp="#nomisma_demetrius_i">Demetrius I</persName>. And yet, throughout these fifty odd years, <placeName corresp="#nomisma_phoenicia">Phœnicia</placeName> had formed a vastly important province of the Syrian
<pb n="38"/>
Empire under the more or less prosperous reigns of <persName corresp="#nomisma_antiochus_iii">Antiochus III</persName>, <persName corresp="#nomisma_seleucus_iv">Seleucus IV</persName>, <persName corresp="#nomisma_antiochus_iv">Antiochus IV</persName>, <persName>Antiochus V</persName> and <persName corresp="#nomisma_demetrius_i">Demetrius I</persName>. That Tyre really possessed an active mint throughout this very period we are certain because of the large series of named and dated bronze coins whose attribution is absolutely beyond question. Now, as shown above, there has come to light a strikingly homogeneous series of tetradrachms and accompanying drachms which bear the names and portraits of every one of the five missing kings. The series commences abruptly with the tetradrachms of <persName corresp="#nomisma_antiochus_iii">Antiochus III</persName> and ends as abruptly with those of <persName corresp="#nomisma_demetrius_i">Demetrius I</persName>. The latter, however, should be compared with the succeeding <orgName type="ethnic">Phœnician</orgName> tetradrachms of <persName>Alexander Bala</persName>, those of Tyrian mintage, which they closely resemble in style and technique. The surmise that one and all were struck in Tyre is definitely confirmed by the practically invariable presence of the club, a symbol which for over four hundred years was continuously employed to indicate the Tyrian mint. Moreover, the
<pb n="39"/>
portraits on the accompanying bronze coins, whose attribution to Tyre is certain, closely resemble in character and workmanship those found on the silver denominations.</p>
               <p>Thus that unexplainable gap in the Tyrian silver mintage, the only real gap that existed in its issues from the time when the mint was reopened under Antigonus after its closing by <persName corresp="#nomisma_alexander_iii">Alexander the Great</persName>, until the final silver issues under the Roman emperors Trajan and Caracalla, is now apparently closed. Incidentally, one more group of the great Seleucid series can be placed on one side as now assignable, with every appearance of finality, to its original mint—in this case, Tyre.</p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div1 xml:id="d95e2067" type="backma">
            <pb n="40"/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="bold">NOTES</hi>
            </head>
            <note xml:id="CH1-n1" place="end">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">1</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>Compare its issues with those of <name type="place">Sidon</name>, <name type="place">Gaza</name>, <name type="place">Ptolemais</name>, or <name type="place">Joppa</name> in Svoronos' "Τά Νομίσματα τού Κράτους τών ΙΙτολeμαίων."</p>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="CH1-n2" place="end">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">2</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>In a recent letter to the writer, the Rev. Edgar Rogers, well known for 'his studies of the Seleucid series, made this same observation based upon previous and entirely independent research.</p>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="CH1-n3" place="end">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">3</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>"The Seleucid Mint of Antioch," <hi rend="italic">Amer. Jour. Num.</hi> Vol. LI, 1917.</p>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="CH1-n4" place="end">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">4</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>Rois de Syrie, etc.</p>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="CH1-n5" place="end">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">5</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>
                  <name type="pname">A. T. Clay</name>: Legal Documents from Erech, <name type="place">N. Y.</name>, 1913, Introd., p. 14.</p>
            </note>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d95e2122" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">Plate</hi> I</head>
            <figure xml:id="fig-3">
               <graphic url="NNM10_047.jpg"/>
               <p>
                  <name type="pname">Antiochus III</name>
               </p>
               <p>Series I</p>
            </figure>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d95e2135" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">Plate</hi> II</head>
            <figure xml:id="fig-4">
               <graphic url="NNM10_048.jpg"/>
               <p>
                  <name type="pname">Antiochus III</name>
               </p>
               <p>Series II</p>
            </figure>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d95e2148" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">Plate</hi> III</head>
            <figure xml:id="fig-5">
               <graphic url="NNM10_049.jpg"/>
               <p>
                  <name type="pname">Antiochus III</name>
               </p>
               <p>Series III</p>
            </figure>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d95e2161" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">Plate</hi> IV</head>
            <figure xml:id="fig-6">
               <graphic url="NNM10_050.jpg"/>
               <p>
                  <name type="pname">Antiochus III</name>
               </p>
               <p>Series III</p>
            </figure>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d95e2174" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">Plate</hi> V</head>
            <figure xml:id="fig-7">
               <graphic url="NNM10_051.jpg"/>
               <p>
                  <name type="pname">Antiochus III</name>
               </p>
               <p>Series III (Nos. 13–20)</p>
               <p>Series IV (No. 21)</p>
            </figure>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d95e2189" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">Plate</hi> VI</head>
            <figure xml:id="fig-8">
               <graphic url="NNM10_052.jpg"/>
               <p>
                  <name type="pname">Seleucus IV</name>
               </p>
            </figure>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d95e2200" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">Plate</hi> VII</head>
            <figure xml:id="fig-9">
               <graphic url="NNM10_053.jpg"/>
               <p>
                  <name type="pname">Antiochus IV</name> (Nos. 29–36)</p>
               <p>
                  <name type="pname">Antiochus V</name> (Nos. 41–43)</p>
            </figure>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d95e2216" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">Plate</hi> VIII</head>
            <figure xml:id="fig-10">
               <graphic url="NNM10_054.jpg"/>
               <p>
                  <name type="pname">Demetrius I</name>
               </p>
            </figure>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d95e2227" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="bold">PUBLICATIONS</hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="hang">
               <name type="pname">Ernest Babelon</name>. Les Médailles Historiques du Règne de Napoleon le Grand, Empereur et Roi. <name type="place">Paris</name>. 1912. Folio, lx, 430 pages printed in three tones, a special border for every page. Illustrating two hundred unpublished drawings of Napoleonic medals, …. by Chaudet and Lemot for …. the <name type="place">French</name> Institute. $20.00.</p>
            <p rend="hang">
               <name type="pname">Agnes Baldwin</name>. The Electrum Coinage of Lampsakos. 1914. 36 pages. 2 plates. $1.00.</p>
            <p rend="hang">
               <name type="pname">Edward T. Newell</name>. The Seleucid Mint of Antioch. 1918. 137 pages. 13 plates. $5.00.</p>
            <p rend="hang">
               <name type="pname">Edward T. Newell</name>. Tarsos under <name type="pname">Alexander</name>. 1919. 47 pages. 8 plates. $2.50.</p>
            <p rend="hang">
               <name type="pname">Edward T. Newell</name>. Some Rare or Unpublished Greek Coins. 12 pages. 2 plates. $1.00.</p>
            <p rend="hang">
               <name type="pname">Edgar H. Adams.</name> Private Gold Coinage of <name type="place">California</name>. 5 Vols. (Unbound). $3.50.</p>
            <p rend="hang">
               <name type="pname">Edgar H. Adams</name> and William <name type="pname">H. Woodin</name>. <name type="place">United States</name> Pattern, Trial and Experimental Pieces …. issued by the <name type="place">U. S.</name> Mint from 1792 up to the present time. 1913. 204 pages. Illus. Cloth, $3.00.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d95e2281" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="bold">
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">Numismatic Notes and Monographs</hi>
               </hi>
            </head>
            <list type="numbered">
               <item n="1.">
                  <name type="pname">Sydney P. Noe</name>. Coin Hoards. 1921. 47 pages. 6 plates.50¢</item>
               <item n="2.">
                  <name type="pname">Edward T. Newell</name>. Octobols of Histiæa. 1921. 25 pages. 2 plates. 50<hi rend="italic">¢</hi>.</item>
               <item n="3.">
                  <name type="pname">Edward T. Newell</name>. <name type="pname">Alexander Hoards—</name> Introduction and <name type="pname">Kyparissia Hoard</name>. 1921. 21 pages. 2 plates. 50<hi rend="italic">¢</hi>.</item>
               <item n="4.">
                  <name type="pname">Howland Wood.</name> The <name type="place">Mexican</name> Revolutionary Coinage 1913–1916. 1921. 44 pages. 26 plates. $2.00.</item>
               <item n="5.">
                  <name type="pname">Leonidas</name> Westervelt. The Jenny Lind Medals and Tokens. 1921. 25 pages. 9 plates. 50¢.</item>
               <item n="6.">
                  <name type="pname">Agnes Baldwin</name>. Five Roman Gold Medallions. 1921. 103 pages. 8 plates. $1.50.</item>
               <item n="7.">
                  <name type="pname">Sydney P. Noe</name>. Medallic Work of <name type="pname">A. A. Weinman</name>. 1921. 31 pages. 17 plates. $1.00.</item>
               <item n="8.">
                  <name type="pname">Gilbert.S. Perez</name>. The Mint of the <name type="place">Philippine</name> Islands. 1921. 8 pages. 4 plates. 50¢.</item>
               <item n="9.">
                  <name type="pname">David Eugene Smith</name>, LL.D. Computing Jetons. 1921. 70 pages. 25 plates. $1.50.</item>
               <item n="10.">
                  <name type="pname">Edward T. Newell</name>. The First Seleucid Coinage of Tyre. 40 pages. 8 plates. $1.00.</item>
            </list>
         </div1>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
