<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd"
     xml:id="nnan117997">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>triumviral portrait gold of the quattuorviri monetales of 42 B. C</title>
            <author>
               <name>Buttrey, Theodore V.</name>
               <idno type="URI">http://viaf.org/viaf/44312470</idno>
            </author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>TEI P5 XML markup in conformance with the TEI DTD</resp>
               <name>AEL Data</name>
            </respStmt>
            <funder>The Andrew W. Mellon Foundation</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <name>American Numismatic Society</name>
               <idno type="URI">http://numismatics.org/authority/american_numismatic_society</idno>
            </publisher>
            <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
            <date>1956</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">This work is made available under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial
                  4.0 International license</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Numismatic Notes and Monographs</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">137</biblScope>
            <idno type="URI">http://numismatics.org/library/195778</idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>Donum</title>
               <idno type="URI">http://numismatics.org/library/117997</idno>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <title>Worldcat</title>
               <idno type="URI">http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/465503552</idno>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <title>Worldcat Works</title>
               <idno type="URI">http://worldcat.org/entity/work/id/4992031</idno>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://nomisma.org/">
               <term ref="http://nomisma.org/id/roman_numismatics">Roman Numismatics</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <particDesc>
            <listPerson>
               <person xml:id="nomisma_p_clodivs_m_f_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">
                  <persName>P. Clodius</persName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/p_clodivs_m_f_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc</idno>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="nomisma_petillivs_capitolinvs_rrc">
                  <persName>Petillius Capitolinus</persName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/petillivs_capitolinvs_rrc</idno>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="nomisma_m_lepidvs_rrc">
                  <persName>M. Aemilius Lepidus</persName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/m_lepidvs_rrc</idno>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="nomisma_l_mvssidivs_t_f_longvs_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">
                  <persName>L. Mussidius Longus</persName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/l_mvssidivs_t_f_longvs_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc</idno>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="nomisma_l_livineivs_regvlvs_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">
                  <persName>L. Livineius Regulus</persName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/l_livineivs_regvlvs_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc</idno>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="nomisma_mark_antony">
                  <persName>Mark Antony</persName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/mark_antony</idno>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="nomisma_julius_caesar">
                  <persName>Julius Caesar</persName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/julius_caesar</idno>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="nomisma_octavian">
                  <persName>Octavian</persName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/octavian</idno>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="nomisma_pompey">
                  <persName>Pompey</persName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/pompey</idno>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="nomisma_l_flaminivs_chilo_iiii_vir_rrc">
                  <persName>L. Flaminius Chilo</persName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/l_flaminivs_chilo_iiii_vir_rrc</idno>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="nomisma_augustus">
                  <persName>Augustus</persName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/augustus</idno>
               </person>
            </listPerson>
         </particDesc>
         <settingDesc>
            <listPlace>
               <place xml:id="nomisma_rome">
                  <placeName>Rome</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/rome</idno>
               </place>
            </listPlace>
         </settingDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2018-04-02">Ran TEI file through XSLT process, detailed in the Mellon EBook migration Google Document.</change>
         <change when="2018-04-02">Included normalized entity labels and URIs from previous OpenRefine process.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div1 xml:id="d52e30" type="cover">
            <pb/>
            <figure xml:id="fig-1">
               <graphic url="NNM137_01.jpg"/>
            </figure>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d52e34" type="frontma">
            <pb/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="bold">THE AMERICAN NUMISMATIC SOCIETY</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">Founded 1858 · Incorporated 1865</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">Broadway Between 155th &amp; 156th Streets</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">
                  <placeName>New York</placeName>
               </hi> 32, N. Y.</p>
            <p rend="hang">
               <hi rend="italic">PURPOSES:</hi> The Society was founded for the collection and preservation of coins and medals and for the investigation of
               their history and other subjects connected therewith.</p>
            <p rend="hang">
               <hi rend="italic">MEMBERSHIP:</hi> Applications for membership are welcomed from all interested in numismatics. Inquiries regarding membership
               should be addressed to the Secretary of the Society.</p>
            <p rend="hang">
               <hi rend="italic">DUES:</hi> The annual dues for an Associate Membership are $7.50. Issues of the <hi rend="italic">Notes and Monographs, Museum,
                  Notes, Hispanic Numismatic Series,</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Numismatic Literature</hi> are distributed to all members.</p>
            <p rend="hang">
               <hi rend="italic">PUBLICATIONS:</hi> The <hi rend="italic">Numismatic Notes and Monographs</hi> consist of separately issued papers, each on a
               single topic, of which two to four numbers appear each year. <hi rend="italic">The American Numismatic Society Museum Notes</hi> is a
               publication, irregular in appearance, consisting of brief notes and papers, principally on items in the Society's collections. <hi rend="italic">Numismatic Literature</hi> is a quarterly listing current numismatic publications with abstracts of their content. <hi rend="italic">Numismatic Studies</hi> is a series which accommodates works of full book length. The <hi rend="italic">Hispanic Numismatic Series,</hi>
               published in cooperation with the Hispanic Society of America, consists of publications devoted to the coinage of the Iberian Peninsula, and is
               based on the collections of the Hispanic Society.</p>
            <p rend="hang">
               <hi rend="italic">MUSEUM:</hi> The Society maintains a museum located in uptown Manhattan, <placeName>New York</placeName> City, which houses
               its offices, collections and library. Collections embrace coins of all periods from their inception to modern times, medals and decorations.
               Selections from its cabinets are on display in an exhibition. The library, consisting of about 17,000 volumes, covers all branches of
               numismatics.</p>
            <p>The Museum is open to Members and the public on Tuesdays, Wednesdays, Thursdays, Fridays and Saturdays. It is closed on Sundays and Mondays and
               the following holidays: New Year's Day, Lincoln's Birthday, Washington's Birthday, Memorial Day, Independence Day, Election Day, Thanksgiving Day
               and Christmas Day. The hours of the Library are from 9 <hi rend="smallcaps">a.m.</hi> to 5 <hi rend="smallcaps">p.m.</hi> The public exhibition
               is open from 2 to 5 <hi rend="smallcaps">p.m.</hi>
            </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d52e104" type="frontma">
            <pb/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="bold">NUMISMATIC NOTES AND MONOGRAPHS</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">Number</hi> 137</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d52e113" type="dedication">
            <pb/>
            <p>NUMISMATIC NOTES AND MONOGRAPHS is devoted to essays and treatises on subjects relating to coins, paper money, medals and decorations.</p>
            <list>
               <head>PUBLICATION COMMITTEE</head>
               <item>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">
                     <persName>A. Carson Simpson</persName>
                  </hi>, <hi rend="italic">Chairman</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">
                     <persName>Alfred R. Bellinger</persName>
                  </hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">
                     <persName>Thomas O. Mabbott</persName>
                  </hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">
                     <persName>Theodor E. Mommsen</persName>
                  </hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>EDITORIAL STAFF</head>
               <item>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">
                     <persName>Sawyer McA. Mosser</persName>
                  </hi>, <hi rend="italic">Editor</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">
                     <persName>Howard L. Adelson</persName>
                  </hi>, <hi rend="italic">Associate Editor</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d52e156" type="colophon">
            <pb/>
            <p>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">all rights reserved by the american numismatic society</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">printed in <placeName>germany</placeName>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">at <persName>J. J. augustin</persName> • <placeName>glückstadt</placeName>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <pb/>
         </div1>
         <titlePage>
            <pb/>
            <docTitle>
               <titlePart type="main">The Triumviral Portrait Gold of the <hi rend="italic">Quattuorviri Monetales</hi> of 42 B.C.</titlePart>
            </docTitle>
            <byline> BY THEODORE V. BUTTREY, JR. </byline>
            <figure xml:id="fig-2">
               <graphic url="NNM137_07.jpg"/>
            </figure>
            <docImprint>
               <publisher>THE AMERICAN NUMISMATIC SOCIETY</publisher>
               <pubPlace>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">Broadway at 156th Street</hi>
               </pubPlace>
               <pubPlace>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">New York</hi>
               </pubPlace>
               <date>1956</date>
            </docImprint>
         </titlePage>
         <div1 xml:id="d52e198" type="contents">
            <pb n="v"/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="bold">CONTENTS</hi>
            </head>
            <table rows="8" cols="2">
               <row>
                  <cell>PREFACE</cell>
                  <cell rend="right">vii</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>I.</cell>
                  <cell rend="right">1</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>II.</cell>
                  <cell rend="right">14</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>III.</cell>
                  <cell rend="right">22</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>IV.</cell>
                  <cell rend="right">32</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>DESCRIPTION OF OBVERSE DIES</cell>
                  <cell rend="right">45</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>DESCRIPTION OF REVERSE DIES</cell>
                  <cell rend="right">54</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>CATALOGUE</cell>
                  <cell rend="right">63</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d52e244" type="frontma">
            <pb n="vii"/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="bold">PREFACE</hi>
            </head>
            <p>The difficulties inherent in establishing the chronology of the moneyers of the Roman Republic are only too well known. It is hardly necessary to
               present an account of the work done over the last century, or to remark that at many points certainty seems as far removed as ever. Only three
               years ago we saw that Broughton at any rate felt that whatever work had been done on the problem had achieved results only conjectural at best.
               For he excluded the moneyers from his annual arrangement of magistrates and relegated the lot to an appendix in the second volume, listing them
                  alphabetically.<ref target="#CH1-n1">
                  <hi rend="sup">1</hi>
               </ref> Pink has constructed a scheme covering the entire period, but his publication wants the essential argumentation which could establish his
               results as permanent.<ref target="#CH1-n2">
                  <hi rend="sup">2</hi>
               </ref> In fact, they are already being challenged.<ref target="#CH1-n3">
                  <hi rend="sup">3</hi>
               </ref> Any work, then, which can cast the smallest light on the problem—granted that there be light rather than the generation of more heat—ought
               to be of some value.</p>
            <p>Yet, although the problem be justly attacked, one may question whether the fine detail given below is really necessary to the presentation of the
               solution. The answer is twofold. First, obviously the problem could be stated, the method briefly described, and the solution revealed. But in no
               way would the final position be any stronger than the author's word. Without the solid foundation of proof pre- <pb n="viii"/> sented, the
               solution would become, for the reader, simply one more amid the dozens of conjectures. One may witness the attacks—justifiable attacks—on both
               Pink and Sydenham,<ref target="#CH1-n4">
                  <hi rend="sup">4</hi>
               </ref> both of whom might have been able to make a stronger case for a given attribution if space had been available for the publication of their
               reasoning. The method of this monograph will be to arrive at a solution scientifically, insofar as that is possible; thus the facts determined by
               the method and leading to the solution should be presented fully.</p>
            <p>Second, regardless of the problem at hand, the method itself, may it be suggested, is worthy of consideration. The description of die links as a
               guide to chronology is well known. Many authors have arranged a given mass of coin in sequence by means of the study of the dies used in common
               by two or more pieces.<ref target="#CH1-n5">
                  <hi rend="sup">5</hi>
               </ref> Generally, the number of coins is so great that the individual piece is granted no especial study. Nor need it be. If one proves that,
               say, obverse X is struck only to reverses 4 and 5, it will matter little, in establishing the chronology, if we have a hundred examples of X/4
               and only three of X/5. Similarly, it matters little to prove that the sequence can be X/4, X/5, X/4 <hi rend="italic">bis,</hi> X/5 <hi rend="italic">bis.</hi> For while some importance may reside herein, the one necessary fact is established: that obverse X was used after
               reverses 1, 2, and 3 were consumed, and before 6, 7, or 8 were conceived. <pb n="ix"/> Whatever the significance of the hundred examples of X/4
                  <hi rend="italic">versus</hi> the three of X/5, the chronological sequence remains the same.</p>
            <p>For this reason very little work has been done with the individual piece, with the arrangement <hi rend="italic">inter se</hi> of the hundred
               pieces struck from the dies X/4. In that context the results would be almost without value. And the examples of this approach which spring to
               mind are to be found not in the study of ancient coins, but in that of early American.<ref target="#CH1-n6">
                  <hi rend="sup">6</hi>
               </ref> Such fineness in detail may be considered unnecessary; in the problem to be discussed in this paper it is essential. For if it can be
               shown that the sequence X/4, X/5, X/6 is valid, while X/4, X/5, X/4, X/6 is not, the entire result of the paper is altered. For the number 4 or 5
               or 6 will represent here not simply another reverse die, but the reverse die of another moneyer.</p>
            <p>It is essential then that each coin to be considered below be minutely examined. And if the method be seen to have any usefulness, it must then
               be applied more widely to the problem of the arrangement of the Roman moneyers. To be sure, in the latest series the moneyers rarely share a die;
               but the earliest silver—anonymous, or bearing a monogram or symbol, — can ultimately be conquered only thus. If the dies of the period can be
               collected and examined, eventually they must yield the solution for which we have been searching so long. Alföldi, preferring an examination of
               style rather than of die links, has already suggested the same approach.<ref target="#CH1-n7">
                  <hi rend="sup">7</hi>
               </ref> One can hardly conceive how many thousands of coins would have to be examined. Yet if anything is accomplished in this manner, the results
               will stand, permanently, against theory and conjecture. Similarly, the results of this paper are, at <pb n="x"/> least in part, permanent. They
               have been suggested before; they have never before been proved.</p>
            <p>This monograph could not have been written without the generous help of those who permitted me to examine the collections in their charge, and
               who responded freely to my requests for casts or photographs: <persName>Dr. Jean Babelon</persName> (<placeName>Paris</placeName>), <persName>Dr. H. Bloesch</persName> (Winterthur), <persName>Dr. Guido Bruck</persName> (<placeName>Vienna</placeName>), Mr. <persName>R. A. G. Carson</persName> (<placeName>London</placeName>), <persName>Dr. Ernst Holzer</persName> (<placeName>Graz</placeName>), <persName>Dr. A. Kerényi</persName> (<placeName>Budapest</placeName>), <persName>Dr. F. Linnenger</persName> (St.
               Florian), <persName>Dr. Luigi</persName>
               <persName>Michelini-Tocci</persName> (<placeName>Vatican</placeName>), <persName>Dr. Franco Panvini-Rosati</persName> (<placeName>Rome</placeName>), <persName>Miss Anne Robertson</persName> (<placeName>Glasgow</placeName>), <persName>Dr. Attilio
                  Stazio</persName> (<placeName>Naples</placeName>), <persName>Dr. A. N. Zadoks-Jitta</persName> (<placeName>the Hague</placeName>), and
               the staff of the American Numismatic Society generally.</p>
            <p>I owe my thanks, finally, to the United States government from whom I received a Fulbright grant for study in <placeName>Italy</placeName>,
               1953–4, by virtue of which I was able to visit the Italian as well as the <placeName>British</placeName> Museums.</p>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n1">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">1</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>
                  <persName>T. R. S. Broughton</persName>, <hi rend="italic">The Magistrates of the Roman Republic,</hi>
                  <placeName>New York</placeName>, 1951–2.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n2">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">2</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>Karl Pink, <hi rend="italic">The</hi>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">triumviri monetales</hi>
                  <hi rend="italic">and the Structure of the Coinage of the Roman Republic</hi> (Numismatic Studies no. 7), <placeName>New York</placeName>,
                  1952.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n3">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">3</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>Cf., e.g., the reviews by Alföldi (<hi rend="italic">Gnomon</hi> XXVI [1954] 381–91) and Hersh (<hi rend="italic">Numismatic Chronicle</hi>
                  series 6 XII [1952] 145–51).</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n4">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">4</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>
                  <persName>E. A. Sydenham</persName>, <hi rend="italic">The Coinage of the Roman Republic</hi>, <placeName>London</placeName>, 1952
                  (hereafter "Sydenham").</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n5">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">5</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>E.g., <persName>E. T. Newell</persName>, <hi rend="italic">Reattribution of certain Tetradrachms of <persName>Alexander the
                        Great</persName>
                  </hi>, <placeName>New York</placeName>, 1912. Most recently, Lucien Naville, <hi rend="italic">Les Monnaies d'Or de la Cyrénaique</hi>,
                     <placeName>Geneva</placeName>, 1951; <persName>D. M. Robinson</persName>, <hi rend="italic">A Hoard of Silver Coins from
                     Carytus</hi> (Numismatic Notes and Monographs no. 124), <placeName>New York</placeName>, 1952; <persName>Doris Raymond</persName>,
                     <hi rend="italic">Macedonian Regal Coinage to 413 B.C.</hi> (NNM no. 126), <placeName>New York</placeName>, 1953. <persName>R.
                     I. Nesmith</persName>, in <hi rend="italic">The Coinage of the First Mint of the Americas at <placeName>Mexico</placeName> City</hi> (NNM
                  no. 131), <placeName>New York</placeName>, 1955, established a chronology in his material not through the dies directly, but by a minute
                  study of the punches used to manufacture the dies. I owe a great deal to the method which he conceived.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n6">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">6</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>E.g., S. S. Crosby, <hi rend="italic">The Early Coins of America,</hi> Boston, 1875; W. H. Sheldon, <hi rend="italic">Early American Cents,
                     1793–1814,</hi>
                  <placeName>New York</placeName>, 1949.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n7">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">7</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>Review of Pink, p. 383.</p>
            </note>
         </div1>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div1 xml:id="d52e518" type="chapter" n="I">
            <pb n="1"/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="bold">I</hi>
            </head>
            <p>That the four moneyers who issued the coins figuring in this study should be considered the members of one college has never been proved up to
               this time. The possibility that Publius <persName corresp="#nomisma_p_clodivs_m_f_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">Clodius</persName>, Lucius Livineius
               Regulus, Lucius Mussidius Longus,<ref target="#CH1-n8">
                  <hi rend="sup">8</hi>
               </ref> and Caius Vibius Varus were colleagues was explored years ago; Mommsen assumed them to form a college which he dated to the year 38
                  B.C.<ref target="#CH1-n9">
                  <hi rend="sup">9</hi>
               </ref> Later, however, in publishing the <ref target="http://numismatics.org/chrr/id/VIG">Vigatto hoard</ref>, he suggested that Regulus and
               Mussidius be dated to the college of 43, having as colleagues P. Accoleius Lariscolus<ref target="#CH1-n10">
                  <hi rend="sup">10</hi>
               </ref> and <persName corresp="#nomisma_petillivs_capitolinvs_rrc">Petillius</persName> Capitolinus.<ref target="#CH1-n11">
                  <hi rend="sup">11</hi>
               </ref> The main argument for the rearrangement was the want of any coin of <persName corresp="#nomisma_p_clodivs_m_f_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">Clodius</persName> or Varus bearing the portrait of <persName corresp="#nomisma_m_lepidvs_rrc">Lepidus</persName>, while both Mussidius and
               Regulus were known to have struck with his head, indicating a production of coin in the early days of the Triumvirate.<ref target="#CH1-n12">
                  <hi rend="sup">12</hi>
               </ref> An example of the missing <persName corresp="#nomisma_p_clodivs_m_f_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">Clodius</persName>
               <pb n="2"/> piece with head of <persName corresp="#nomisma_m_lepidvs_rrc">Lepidus</persName> was found three years later, in the <ref target="http://numismatics.org/chrr/id/CAI">Cajazzo hoard</ref>.<ref target="#CH1-n13">
                  <hi rend="sup">13</hi>
               </ref> Von Duhn concluded that <persName corresp="#nomisma_p_clodivs_m_f_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">Clodius</persName> must have been colleague to
               Mussidius and Regulus, accepting and confirming von Sallet's arrangement of the year before, which had grouped the three "and a fourth" together
               and dated them to 43 B.C.<ref target="#CH1-n14">
                  <hi rend="sup">14</hi>
               </ref> Von Duhn postulated the fourth to have been Caius Vibius Varus. Friedländer added, that which von Duhn had not known, that the Cajazzo
               hoard had contained as well the only known specimen of a portrait of <persName corresp="#nomisma_m_lepidvs_rrc">Lepidus</persName> struck by
                  Varus.<ref target="#CH1-n15">
                  <hi rend="sup">15</hi>
               </ref> The series were thereby complete: each moneyer struck for each <hi rend="italic">triumvir</hi>.</p>
            <p>Babelon followed von Duhn in accepting the four moneyers as one college, assigning them to 43–2 B.C.<ref target="#CH1-n16">
                  <hi rend="sup">16</hi>
               </ref> Bahrfeldt had already drawn the connection,<ref target="#CH1-n17">
                  <hi rend="sup">17</hi>
               </ref> and Mommsen had reverted <pb n="3"/> to his original opinion.<ref target="#CH1-n18">
                  <hi rend="sup">18</hi>
               </ref> But in <placeName>England</placeName> the effect of Count de Salis' historical and stylistic inquiries was to disregard the evidence of
               the Cajazzo find and the conclusions of the German scholars. Thus Grueber continued in the old opinion, separating the moneyers into two groups
               and dating them relatively late, Mussidius and Regulus to 39 B.C., <persName corresp="#nomisma_p_clodivs_m_f_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">Clodius</persName> and Varus to 38.<ref target="#CH1-n19">
                  <hi rend="sup">19</hi>
               </ref> De Salis too had seen that the portrait of <persName corresp="#nomisma_m_lepidvs_rrc">Lepidus</persName> was unknown on the coins of
                  <persName corresp="#nomisma_p_clodivs_m_f_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">Clodius</persName> and Varus, concluding that their coinage must have been later
               than that of Mussidius and Regulus. Yet Grueber, writing thirty-three years after the discovery of the Cajazzo hoard, could say, "The addition of
               these gold coins to the series does not, however, affect the general classification."<ref target="#CH1-n20">
                  <hi rend="sup">20</hi>
               </ref> He apparently justifies his division by his own chronological arrangement of the hoard material<ref target="#CH1-n21">
                  <hi rend="sup">21</hi>
               </ref>—itself a dangerous pit-fall —as well as the style or fabric of the coins. "There is certainly a remarkable resemblance in the character of
               the types and the issues of the gold and silver coins of all four moneyers, but those of <persName corresp="#nomisma_l_mvssidivs_t_f_longvs_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">L. Mussidius Longus</persName> and <persName corresp="#nomisma_l_livineivs_regvlvs_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">L. Livineius Regulus</persName> have certain characteristics not found in the money
               of P. <persName corresp="#nomisma_p_clodivs_m_f_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">Clodius</persName> and C. Vibius Varus, and <hi rend="italic">vice
                  versa</hi>."<ref target="#CH1-n22">
                  <hi rend="sup">22</hi>
               </ref>
            </p>
            <p>Cesano followed Grueber in his dating, arguing that the reverse type of the gold struck for <persName corresp="#nomisma_mark_antony">Antony</persName> by <persName corresp="#nomisma_p_clodivs_m_f_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">Clodius</persName>—the figure of "Pantheus"—could only
               refer "alla sottomissione ed al dominio pacifico dell' Oriente per opera di Antonio stesso," a work which must date to 39 and 38, if not
                  later.<ref target="#CH1-n23">
                  <hi rend="sup">23</hi>
               </ref>
            </p>
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>In 1923, Bahrfeldt was able to refer to the coins of the four moneyers as "Die Münzen des durch die Funde von Cajazzo und Pieve-Quinta nunmehr
               ganz gesicherten Viermänner-Kollegiums."<ref target="#CH1-n24">
                  <hi rend="sup">24</hi>
               </ref> Pink too assigned all four men to the college of 42 B.C.<ref target="#CH1-n25">
                  <hi rend="sup">25</hi>
               </ref> Yet again, the second and most recent English catalogue disperses the moneyers so as to date Mussidius and Regulus to 42 B.C., <persName corresp="#nomisma_p_clodivs_m_f_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">Clodius</persName> to 41, and Varus still later to 39.<ref target="#CH1-n26">
                  <hi rend="sup">26</hi>
               </ref> Sydenham's catalogue includes relatively little discussion of the reasons behind an attribution; no argument is presented to sustain this
               division and dating. Mattingly, in a note on Sydenham's arrangement, restates the other view: "C. Vibius Varus makes a fourth moneyer with
               Longus, Regulus, and <persName corresp="#nomisma_p_clodivs_m_f_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">Clodius</persName> in 43 to 42 B.C."<ref target="#CH1-n27">
                  <hi rend="sup">27</hi>
               </ref> Finally, UlrichBansa has assigned to 42 B.C. a college composed of Longus, Regulus, P. <persName corresp="#nomisma_p_clodivs_m_f_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">Clodius</persName> Vestalis (<hi rend="italic">sic</hi>—P. <persName corresp="#nomisma_p_clodivs_m_f_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">Clodius</persName> or C. <persName corresp="#nomisma_p_clodivs_m_f_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">Clodius</persName> Vestalis?), and L. Flaminius Chilo.<ref target="#CH1-n28">
                  <hi rend="sup">28</hi>
               </ref>
            </p>
            <p>The point, it appears, remains to be proved one way or the other. It is evident that current opinion has tended toward two positions: 1) The four
               moneyers are to be dated together, as one college; 2) The college did not exist but the issues of the four are very alike. Even so with respect
               to the date of the moneyers: whether they formed a college or no, it is generally agreed that they struck either around 43/2 or about 39/8.
               Neither of the two familiar means of approach has succeeded in establishing the solution, although either <pb n="5"/> might have suggested it.
               Grueber's reliance on non-numismatic evidence as a means of identifying, and thus dating, the moneyers breaks down here on his own admission. For
               three of the four officials are altogether unknown; for Regulus alone can he so much as hazard a guess.<ref target="#CH1-n29">
                  <hi rend="sup">29</hi>
               </ref> On the other hand, Pink's arrangement of the four as one college is at least partly fallacious, as will be elaborated below, and stands
               ultimately only as long as his entire structure stands.</p>
            <p>This study could marshal and examine the evidence, review the opinions of the past, and assert itself in support of one or the other. But no
               final solution would have been attained; the problem would still remain, to be attacked again and again. It would seem preferable, rather, to
               begin at the beginning, to attempt to approach the problem from an entirely new point of view, to invoke evidence never before considered, and to
               attempt to reach an answer without recourse to either the historical or the <hi rend="italic">Aufbau</hi> method. Each of these will be invoked
               in its turn, but the method of this investigation is to be the study of the coins themselves. Considering them simply as metallic evidence of
               things past, we shall inquire whether they can reveal to us anything pertaining to the function of the moneyer or the pattern of the coinage
               which we do not already know.</p>
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>The coins to be considered represent only a fraction of the total output of their respective moneyers. All struck silver of private types.<ref target="#CH1-n30">
                  <hi rend="sup">30</hi>
               </ref> In addition, <persName corresp="#nomisma_p_clodivs_m_f_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">Clodius</persName>, Mussidius, and Regulus issued portrait
               denarii of <persName corresp="#nomisma_julius_caesar">Caesar</persName> (as had the moneyers of 44, and Gracchus and Vitulus in 43); <persName corresp="#nomisma_p_clodivs_m_f_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">Clodius</persName>, Regulus, and Varus struck denarii portraying <persName corresp="#nomisma_octavian">Octavian</persName>; while <persName corresp="#nomisma_mark_antony">Antony</persName> was similarly honored on
               silver of <persName corresp="#nomisma_p_clodivs_m_f_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">Clodius</persName> and Varus. The purpose of these issues needs not be
               discussed here;<ref target="#CH1-n31">
                  <hi rend="sup">31</hi>
               </ref> the omission of <persName corresp="#nomisma_m_lepidvs_rrc">Lepidus</persName>, less than a year after he had assumed the office of <hi rend="italic">triumvir r.p.c.,</hi> shows clearly enough the real significance of his position.</p>
            <p>The private types of each moneyer were peculiarly his own. The portrait coinage must then be the closest connection between the officials. But
               the series are not complete; Mussidius apparently struck no portrait of <persName corresp="#nomisma_octavian">Octavian</persName> or <persName corresp="#nomisma_mark_antony">Antony</persName> in silver. And while an argument based generally on style can be drawn to some fineness it
               involves a subjective criticism which may not be accepted everywhere. The comparison of these portraits by style will be considered incidentally
               below, but the argument is not strong enough to carry off the victory in the principle struggle: did these moneyers, or any two or three of them,
               pertain to the same college?</p>
            <p>The story of the coinage in gold is much the same. Each moneyer struck private types; indeed all but Regulus struck two.<ref target="#CH1-n32">
                  <hi rend="sup">32</hi>
               </ref> Each moneyer also struck for the members of the Triumvirate, and in this case the evidence is complete: <pb n="7"/> portraits of each <hi rend="italic">triumvir</hi> are known for each series. Therefore these gold series, five in all, are to form the subject of this study, and
               they may properly be presented at this point.<ref target="#CH1-n33">
                  <hi rend="sup">33</hi>
               </ref>
            </p>
            <table rows="9" cols="2">
               <row>
                  <cell>I. 38.<ref target="#CH1-n34">
                        <hi rend="sup">34</hi>
                     </ref> M.LEPIDVS.III.VIR. R.P.C</cell>
                  <cell>C.VEIBIVS / VAARVS<ref target="#CH1-n35">
                        <hi rend="sup">35</hi>
                     </ref>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Head of <persName corresp="#nomisma_m_lepidvs_rrc">Lepidus</persName>, l.</cell>
                  <cell>Two clasped hands.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Dotted border.</cell>
                  <cell>Dotted border.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>39. M.ANTONIVS.III.VIR. R.P.C</cell>
                  <cell>as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Head of <persName corresp="#nomisma_mark_antony">Antony</persName>, r.</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Dotted border.</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>40. C.CAESAR.III.VIR.R.P.C</cell>
                  <cell>as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Head of <persName corresp="#nomisma_octavian">Octavian</persName>, r.</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Dotted border.</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>The reverse type is clearly symbolic of Concordia: the reconciliation of the <hi rend="italic">triumviri</hi> in particular, in general the
               renewed political stability of the state, more hoped for than actual. There may be here an attempt to recall the occurrence of the type on the
               denarii of Albinus and C. Vibius Pansa, and later on the quinarii of L. Aemilius Buca, under <persName corresp="#nomisma_julius_caesar">Caesar.</persName> Mussidius also struck denarii of the type of clasped hands and caduceus, with the head of Concordia on the obverse.<ref target="#CH1-n36">
                  <hi rend="sup">36</hi>
               </ref>
            </p>
            <pb n="8"/>
            <table rows="9" cols="2">
               <row>
                  <cell>II. 41. M.LEPIDVS.III.VIR.R.P.C</cell>
                  <cell>L.MVSSIDIVS / LONGVS</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Head of <persName corresp="#nomisma_m_lepidvs_rrc">Lepidus</persName>, l.</cell>
                  <cell>Cornucopia with fillet.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Dotted border.</cell>
                  <cell>Dotted border.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>42. M.ANTONIVS.III.VIR.R.P.C</cell>
                  <cell>as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Head of <persName corresp="#nomisma_mark_antony">Antony</persName>, r.</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Dotted border.</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>43. C.CAESAR.III.VIR.R.P.C</cell>
                  <cell>as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Head of <persName corresp="#nomisma_octavian">Octavian</persName>, r.</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Dotted border.</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>The cornucopia is symbolic of the stability and fecundity to be expected under the new régime.<ref target="#CH1-n37">
                  <hi rend="sup">37</hi>
               </ref>
            </p>
            <table rows="3" cols="2">
               <row>
                  <cell>III. 44. M.LEPIDVS.III.VIR.R.P.C or M.LEPIDVS.III.VIR.R.P.C.</cell>
                  <cell>P.CLODIVS. M/F/IIII. VIR.A.P.F</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Head of <persName corresp="#nomisma_m_lepidvs_rrc">Lepidus</persName>, l.</cell>
                  <cell>Felicitas<ref target="#CH1-n38">
                        <hi rend="sup">38</hi>
                     </ref> standing r., holding sceptre in r. hand, cornucopia in l. At her feet, an object.<ref target="#CH1-n39">
                        <hi rend="sup">39</hi>
                     </ref>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Dotted border.</cell>
                  <cell>Dotted border.</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <pb n="9"/>
            <table rows="6" cols="2">
               <row>
                  <cell>45. M.ANTONIVS.III.VIR. R.P.C</cell>
                  <cell>P.CLODIVS.M.F / IIII. VIR. A.P.F</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell> Head of <persName corresp="#nomisma_mark_antony">Antony</persName>, r.</cell>
                  <cell>Male figure<ref target="#CH1-n40">
                        <hi rend="sup">40</hi>
                     </ref> standing l., winged and radiate, holding caduceus in l. hand, cornucopia in r., quiver and bow across back, r. foot resting on
                     globe. At his feet, r., shield, l., an eagle upon a rectangular or rhomboid object.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Dotted border.</cell>
                  <cell>Dotted border.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>46. C.CAESAR.III.VIR.R.P.C</cell>
                  <cell>P.CLODIVS / M.F.IIII. / VIR.A.P.F., or P.CLO-DIVS.M.F.IIII.VIR.A.P.F</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Head of <persName corresp="#nomisma_octavian">Octavian</persName>, r.</cell>
                  <cell>Venus sitting l. on <hi rend="italic">cippus,</hi> holding dove in r. hand, embracing Cupid with l.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Dotted border.</cell>
                  <cell>Dotted border.</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>The significance of the reverse types of this series will be understood only when the figure on the coin of <persName corresp="#nomisma_mark_antony">Antony</persName> is finally explained. Perhaps we are to take together Felicitas- Genius/Aion-Venus (of whom
               Concordia is a derivative)<ref target="#CH1-n41">
                  <hi rend="sup">41</hi>
               </ref> as <pb n="10"/> symbolic of both the stability and the fecundity of the new age, the new era of hope.</p>
            <table rows="6" cols="2">
               <row>
                  <cell>IV. 47. M.LEPIDVS.III.VIR.R.P.C</cell>
                  <cell>L.REGVLVS / IIII.VIR. A.P.F</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Head of <persName corresp="#nomisma_m_lepidvs_rrc">Lepidus</persName>, r.</cell>
                  <cell>The Vestal Virgin Aemilia<ref target="#CH1-n42">
                        <hi rend="sup">42</hi>
                     </ref> standing 1., holding <hi rend="italic">simpulum</hi> in r. hand, sceptre in l.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Dotted border.</cell>
                  <cell>Dotted border.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>48. M.ANTONIVS / III.VIR. R.P.C. or M.ANTONIVS.III.VIR.R.P.C or M.ANTONIVS.III.VIR.R.P.C.</cell>
                  <cell>L.REGVLVS / IIII.VIR. A.P.F</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Head of <persName corresp="#nomisma_mark_antony">Antony</persName>, r.</cell>
                  <cell>Hercules<ref target="#CH1-n43">
                        <hi rend="sup">43</hi>
                     </ref> seated facing on a rock, holding sceptre in r. hand, in l. sword (or parazonium?). At his l. leans a shield with Gorgon's
                     head.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Dotted border.</cell>
                  <cell>Dotted border.</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <pb n="11"/>
            <table rows="3" cols="2">
               <row>
                  <cell>49. C.CAESAR / III.VIR.R.P.C or C.CAESAR / III.VIR.R.P.C.</cell>
                  <cell>L.REGVLVS / IIII.VIR. A.P.F</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Head of <persName corresp="#nomisma_octavian">Octavian</persName>, r.</cell>
                  <cell>Aeneas advancing r., bearing Anchises.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Dotted border.</cell>
                  <cell>Dotted border.</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>The reverse types of Regulus associate each <hi rend="italic">triumvir</hi> with his forebears. Only Antony's coin bears the image of the god,
               but Venus is implied on the <persName corresp="#nomisma_octavian">Octavian</persName> piece, as is Mars on that of <persName corresp="#nomisma_m_lepidvs_rrc">Lepidus.</persName> The conceit is not original—Sulla's association with Venus, <persName corresp="#nomisma_pompey">Pompey's</persName> with Neptune, Caesar's with Venus all preceded—but the implications are clear: the <hi rend="italic">triumviri</hi> claimed justly the power of office, for the very gods had conspired to endow Rome with their services. Not only
               was a new age at hand, symbolized by the reverse types of the other moneyers, but the Fortune of the city was to be assured by divinity as it
               were made flesh.</p>
            <table rows="9" cols="2">
               <row>
                  <cell>V. 50. M.LEPIDVS.III.VIR.R.P.C</cell>
                  <cell>L.MVSSIDIVS.T.F.LON- GVS.IIII.VIR.A.P.F.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Head of <persName corresp="#nomisma_m_lepidvs_rrc">Lepidus</persName>, l.</cell>
                  <cell>Mars standing r., holding spear in r. hand, parazonium in l., his l. foot resting on shield.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Dotted border.</cell>
                  <cell>Dotted border.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>51. M.ANTONIVS.III.VIR.R.P.C</cell>
                  <cell>as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Head of <persName corresp="#nomisma_mark_antony">Antony</persName>, r.</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Dotted border.</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>52. C.CAESAR.III.VIR.R.P.C</cell>
                  <cell>as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Head of <persName corresp="#nomisma_octavian">Octavian</persName>, r.</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Dotted border.</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>The reverse type is that of Mars disarmed, signaling the cessation of war. Perhaps the Roman actually accepted the symbol, in the hope that the
               proscriptions had ended once for all the divisions in the state. But one is reminded of the types of Hilaritas, Securitas, and Concordia, so
               common in <pb n="12"/> the third century A.D., occuring most often precisely at those times when they meant the least.</p>
            <p>The obverse legend is constant for the <hi rend="italic">triumvir,</hi> the only varieties consisting in punctuation and spacing. All are read
               inward, and all begin at the lower left save for those of dies O.III and O.IV<ref target="#CH1-n44">
                  <hi rend="sup">44</hi>
               </ref> which begin upper right. The reverse legends begin at various points and are all read across or inward, except for those of dies C.Aa,
               C.Ba, and R.Bo which are read outward. It is to be noted that the reverse legends vary: Varus never includes IIII. VIR. A.P.F, <persName corresp="#nomisma_p_clodivs_m_f_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">Clodius</persName> and Regulus always do, Mussidius does in the one series but not in the
               other. The position of the dies usually approximates ↑↑ or ↑↓ — rarely ↑← or ↑→ — but the dies were not fixed.</p>
            <p>Granted that all the coins described above portray all the <hi rend="italic">triumviri,</hi> one may yet inquire what justification can be
               offered for the joint consideration of several series of coin struck by moneyers who may very well not have been colleagues. The answer is that,
               in the first place, the obverse types, the portraits, are not common in series; a series of coin portraying each of the <hi rend="italic">triumviri</hi> is known in only one other instance. We have a group of aurei, certainly not struck at Rome and attributed by Grueber and
               Sydenham to Gaul, which falls into two parts.<ref target="#CH1-n45">
                  <hi rend="sup">45</hi>
               </ref> The first consists of those coins bearing the portrait of <persName corresp="#nomisma_mark_antony">Antony</persName> on one face and
                  <persName corresp="#nomisma_m_lepidvs_rrc">Lepidus</persName> on the other, the second, of <persName corresp="#nomisma_mark_antony">Antony</persName> on one face and <persName corresp="#nomisma_octavian">Octavian</persName> on the other. The aurei are quite rare—no denarii
               of these types are known—and no other series can be found which portrays all the <hi rend="italic">triumviri.</hi> Returning to our gold, it
               seems inherently unlikely that several moneyers at random, over a period of years, should have hit on the idea of striking these types in series.
               They much more reasonably must have struck together.</p>
            <pb n="13"/>
            <p>Nor need we rely on a conjectural, or even a stylistic comparison, for a closer connection than type or style has been discovered between the
               series. The <hi rend="italic">terminus</hi> from which we depart was suggested thirty years ago by Bahrfeldt. In assembling and arranging the
               material for us to use, Bahrfeldt discovered a coincidence of cardinal importance: these moneyers, in their gold coinage for the <hi rend="italic">triumviri,</hi> in some cases made use of the same obverse portrait dies. "Die für <persName corresp="#nomisma_m_lepidvs_rrc">Lepidus</persName> von Varus und Longus geprägten Goldstücke n. 38, 41 u. a. sind von stempelgleicher Hs., also müssen sie in derselben
               Münzstätte und auch zu derselben Zeit geschlagen worden sein!"<ref target="#CH1-n46">
                  <hi rend="sup">46</hi>
               </ref> "Für jeden der drei Machthaber wurde ge- sondert geprägt, dabei wenden Vibius und Mussidius für alle drei dieselben Rs.-Darstellungen an,
               während <persName corresp="#nomisma_p_clodivs_m_f_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">Clodius</persName> und Livineius wechseln. Die vielfach vorkommenden
               Stempel- gleichheiten beweisen, daß alle diese Münzen gleichzeitig und in einer und derselben Münzstätte, nämlich in Rom, aus- geprägt worden
                  sind."<ref target="#CH1-n47">
                  <hi rend="sup">47</hi>
               </ref> Sydenham apparently knew nothing of this die coincidence, for it would seem to invalidate his dating altogether. Yet one might argue, and
               it would be impossible at this point to disprove, that a number of dies might have been left over at the mint, to be used in some later year by
               another moneyer. That is, although it be very likely that the sharing of one die by two moneyers indicates that they struck in the same college,
               yet the coincidence is of itself no certain proof. Some further evidence would be welcomed.</p>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n8">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">8</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>The <hi rend="italic">nomen</hi> Mussidius will be used throughout, so that in the designation of the dies there can be no confusion between
                  those of L(ongus) and those portraying L(epidus).</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n9">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">9</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Th. Mommsen, Geschichte des Römischen Münzwesens</hi>, <placeName>Berlin</placeName>, 1860; p. 653.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n10">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">10</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>For P. Accoleius and L. Ariscolus as two distinct moneyers see Alföldi, review of Pink, p. 388.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n11">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">11</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>"Römische Denarschätze. IV: Der Denarschatz von Vigatto." In <hi rend="italic">Zeitschrift für Numismatik,</hi> II (1875) 66–8.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n12">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">12</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>The point is put clearly by Borghesi <hi rend="italic">(Œuvres Complètes,</hi>
                  <placeName>Paris</placeName>, 1862–4; II, p. 77): "Mussidio unì quel tipo alla testa di ciascuno dei triumviri [he refers to the reverse type
                  of Mars standing—see below], mentre da Clodio fu preterito Lepido, Golziana essendo la medaglia non mai veduta da alcuno, che dicevasi portare
                  il suo ritratto. E la ragione procederà dal tempo, nel quale da ognuno di loro fu amministrata la zecca: onde sul principio del triumvirato,
                  quando la potenza di Lepido era eguale a quella dei suoi colleghi, osservasi onorato del pari dai monetieri Livineio e Mussidio; ma scaduto
                  dopo di riputazione, e quasi relegato nell' Africa, fu poi negletto tanto dal nostro Clodio quanto da Vibio Varo." Yet von Sallet was not
                  disturbed ("Die Münzen Caesars mit seinem Bildniss." In <hi rend="italic">ZfN,</hi> IV [1877] 137): "Wir keine Münze des <persName corresp="#nomisma_m_lepidvs_rrc">Lepidus</persName> vom Monetar <persName corresp="#nomisma_p_clodivs_m_f_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">Clodius</persName> besitzen, während die beiden andern genannten Quattuorvirn des Jahres 711, Mussidius Longus und Livineius Regulus für
                  alle drei Triumvirn, Antonius, <persName corresp="#nomisma_octavian">Octavian</persName>, <persName corresp="#nomisma_m_lepidvs_rrc">Lepidus</persName> Goldstücke prägten; indeß ist bei der enormen Seltenheit aller dieser Goldstücke und besonders der Goldmünzen des
                     <persName corresp="#nomisma_m_lepidvs_rrc">Lepidus</persName> immer noch möglich, daß es auch einige wenige Stücke vom Monetar <persName corresp="#nomisma_p_clodivs_m_f_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">Clodius</persName> mit <persName>Lepidus'</persName> Bild gab und daß wir sie
                  vielleicht noch finden. Es ist eine bekannte Sache, daß bisher unbekannte Goldstücke jener Zeit auch jetzt noch zu Tage kommen: ich erinnere
                  nur an das Berliner Unicum mit dem Kopfe des Antyllus, das im zweiten Band dieser Zeitschrift publiciert worden ist."</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n13">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">13</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>
                  <persName>F. von Duhn</persName>, "Münzfund bei Cajazzo." In <hi rend="italic">ZfN</hi> V (1878) 236.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n14">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">14</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>Loc. cit.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n15">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">15</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>
                  <persName>J. Friedländer</persName>, "Zum Münzfund von Cajazzo." In <hi rend="italic">ZfN</hi> V (1878) 242.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n16">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">16</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>
                  <persName>E. Babelon</persName>, <hi rend="italic">Description Historique et Chronologique des Monnaies de la République Romaine,</hi>
                  <placeName>Paris</placeName>, 1885; p. 167. "M. W. Caland place leurs fonctions en 712 (42 av. J.-C.): ils sont en effet restés en charge
                  pendant cette année, mais ils ont commencé à battre monnaie dès l'année précédente." Cf. W. Caland, <hi rend="italic">De Nummis M. Antonii III
                     viri</hi>, Leyden 1883; ρρ. 29–39.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n17">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">17</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>Max Bahrfeldt, "Der Denarschatz von Pieve-Quinta." In <hi rend="italic">ZfN</hi> X (1883) 18.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n18">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">18</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>Th. Mommsen, "Der Denar des Q. Salvidienus und die Schätze von Peccioli und Metz." In <hi rend="italic">ZfN</hi> XI (1884) 73–4, 79.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n19">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">19</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>H. A. Grueber, <hi rend="italic">Coins of the Roman Republic in the</hi>
                  <placeName>British</placeName>
                  <hi rend="italic">Museum,</hi>
                  <placeName>London</placeName>, 1910; I, pp. 573–88 (hereafter "Grueber"). De Salis assigned no more than two active moneyers to each of the
                  years 43 through 37.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n20">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">20</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>I, P. 555.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n21">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">21</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>I, p. cxiv; III, pp. 28–9.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n22">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">22</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>I, p. 583.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n23">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">23</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>Lorenzina Cesano, "Contributo allo studio delle monete antiche dimezzate," in <hi rend="italic">Rivista Italiana di Numismatica</hi> XXVIII
                  (1915) 22–4.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n24">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">24</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">Die Römische Goldmünzenprägung während der Republik und unter <persName corresp="#nomisma_augustus">Augustus</persName>
                  </hi>, Haale, 1923; p. 50 (hereafter "Bahrfeldt").</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n25">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">25</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>P. 43.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n26">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">26</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>Sydenham, pp. 180–6. One will remark how the distinction of a century ago—the association of Mussidius and Regulus, <hi rend="italic">versus</hi>
                  <persName corresp="#nomisma_p_clodivs_m_f_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">Clodius</persName> and Varus— has lingered on, curiously, long after the reason
                  for it, the dearth of portraits of <persName corresp="#nomisma_m_lepidvs_rrc">Lepidus</persName>, was no longer valid.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n27">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">27</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>H. Mattingly, in Sydenham, p. 223.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n28">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">28</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>O. Ulrich-Bansa, "Introduzione alla Numismatica Romana (parte II)," <hi rend="italic">Rivista Italiana di Numismatica</hi> LVI (1954) 60.
                  Sydenham too assigns Chilo to 42 B.C. (p. 180).</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n29">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">29</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>I, p. 573.: "Of the moneyer Lucius Mussidus Longus, the son of T. Mussidius Longus, we know nothing but what we learn from his coins."</p>
               <p>P. 583. "Of Publius <persName corresp="#nomisma_p_clodivs_m_f_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">Clodius</persName>, son of Marcus <persName corresp="#nomisma_p_clodivs_m_f_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">Clodius</persName>, we have no certain information beyond that he was one of a
                  quattuorvirate of the mint."</p>
               <p>P. 587. "Caius Vibius Varus is also only known from his coins."</p>
               <p>P. 578–9. "Lucius Livineius Regulus, like his colleague L. Mussidius Longus, is not known to us from history, and our information about him is
                  derived only from his coins, which tell us that he was the son of Lucius Livineius Regulus, the praetor, who, with his brother Marcus, was a
                  friend of Cicero, and who appears to have served under <persName corresp="#nomisma_julius_caesar">Caesar</persName> in the African war, B.C.
                  46 (Hirtius, <hi rend="italic">Bell</hi>. <hi rend="italic">Afr.,</hi> 89)." Münzer, in PW XXV, cols. 808–9, takes the moneyer himself to have
                  been the Livineius Regulus mentioned in Hirtius. So too Broughton, II, p. 581: "Praefect Hadrumentum 46." But there is no evidence whatever
                  for either identification.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n30">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">30</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>For the coins in general of the four moneyers, see Grueber, I, pp. 573–90.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n31">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">31</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>On the problem of coin portraiture immediately following the death of <persName corresp="#nomisma_julius_caesar">Caesar</persName>, see A.
                  Alföldi, "Porträtkunst und Politik in 43 v. Chr." In <hi rend="italic">Netherlands Y ear-Book for History of Art</hi> V (1954) 160–3.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n32">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">32</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>Bahrfeldt, nos. 30–7. The first type of <persName corresp="#nomisma_p_clodivs_m_f_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">Clodius</persName>, no. 30, with head of
                  Apollo, is no longer to be thought unique. At least two other examples are known: 1. R. Ratto sale (Morcom-Hands), Lucerne, Feb. 8, 1928; no.
                  1016; 2. Glendining sale (V. J. E. Ryan), <placeName>London</placeName>, Feb. 20, 1951; no. 1562 = Ciani sale, <placeName>Paris</placeName>,
                  May 6–7, 1955; no. 248.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n33">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">33</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>A catalogue of the known specimens of each type will be found on p. 63.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n34">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">34</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>To simplify reference, the numbers assigned by Bahrfeldt have been retained throughout, and the types are generally referred to in the order
                  which he used.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n35">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">35</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>This reverse type appears to have been entirely unknown, with any of the three portraits, before the discovery of the Cajazzo hoard in 1878.
                  Although von Duhn and Friedländer (opp. citt.) list but three examples of number 40, it is probable that the fourth stems from that find as
                  well. Considering the rarity of all the five series here to be discussed, an extraordinary number and variety occurred in the Cajazzo hoard.
                  Von Duhn and Friedländer certify: no. 38 (1 example), 39 (3), 40 (3), 41 (1), 42 (1), 43 (3). 44 (1). 45 (1). 47 (1), 48 (2), 49 (1), 52
                  (1).</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n36">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">36</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>Albinus and Pansa: Grueber, I, nos. 3964–5, 3987–8; Buca: I, no. 4162; Mussidius: I, no. 4236.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n37">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">37</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>For the cornucopia as symbol of the Fortune of <persName corresp="#nomisma_octavian">Octavian</persName>, see A. Blanchet, "Monnaies de
                  Lugdunum (<hi rend="italic">Copia</hi>).<hi rend="italic">"</hi> In <hi rend="italic">Revue Numismatique</hi> series 5 X (1947/8) 121–2.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n38">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">38</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>"Concordia"—Grueber, I, p. 584; "Concordia (?)"—Sydenham, p. 184; "Weibliche Gestalt"—Bahrfeldt, p. 57. Felicitas seems not to have been
                  previously suggested. The figure does not carry the caduceus as we might expect, but the omission is not unparalleled: cf., e.g., the sesterce
                  of Titus in Mattingly, <hi rend="italic">Coins of the Roman Empire in the British Museum</hi>, <placeName>London</placeName>, 1923—, II, nos.
                  156–160. Conversely, the caduceus is sometimes associated with Concordia: cf. the denarius of Mussidius, n. 36 <hi rend="italic">supra.</hi>
                  Felicitas has an especial meaning for <persName corresp="#nomisma_m_lepidvs_rrc">Lepidus</persName>, for <persName corresp="#nomisma_julius_caesar">Caesar</persName> removed the remains of the Curia Hostilia, burnt in 52 B.C., and proposed a temple to
                  Felicitas on the site of the old senate-house. But his death supervened, and the temple was completed in 44 B.C. by <persName corresp="#nomisma_m_lepidvs_rrc">Lepidus</persName> (Dio xliv.5.2).</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n39">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">39</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>"Owl?"—Grueber, loc. cit.; "Owl"—Sydenham; "Undeutlicher Gegenstand. (Tropaeon?)"—Bahrfeldt. The object remains obscure; <persName>Dr.
                     Laurence</persName> Richardson suggests to me that it might be a wineskin lying on its side, complementing the cornucopia.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n40">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">40</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>"Genius"—Grueber, I, p. 582; and Sydenham, p. 184; "Pantheus"— Bahrfeldt, p. 58. The significance of the iconography has been the subject of
                  some discussion, in part stemming from the attribution of the piece to 38 B.C. or later, a date which permits an interpretation involving
                     <persName>Antony's</persName> role in Eastern affairs. For the literature up to 1923 see Bahrfeldt, p. 58, to whose list one might add
                  Cavedoni, review of Cohen's <hi rend="italic">Médailies Consulaires,</hi> in <hi rend="italic">RN</hi> new series X (1857) 349; and Borghesi,
                  II, pp. 72, 77–81. Alföldi, "Der neue Weltherrscher der IV. Ekloge Vergils," in <hi rend="italic">Hermes</hi> LXV (1930) 369–84, interprets
                  the figure as Aion, that is, the <hi rend="italic">saeculum frugiferum.</hi>
               </p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n41">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">41</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>L. <persName>Preller</persName>, <hi rend="italic">Römische Mythologie,</hi>
                  <placeName>Berlin</placeName>, 1883 (3rd edition, by <persName>H. Jordan</persName>), II, p. 260. That these three deities were associated on
                  one festival day appears to be more than a coincidence, given the coin types. CIL I<hi rend="sup">2</hi>, p. 331 reproduces the calendar for
                  October 9th: <hi rend="italic">VII ID. OCT.</hi> – C. <hi rend="italic">Genio public(o), faustae Felicitati, Vener [i) victr(ici) in
                     Capitol(io).</hi> (The phrase <hi rend="italic">in Capitolio</hi> need not mean "on the Capitol," nor need it apply here to anyone other
                  than Venus. Mommsen interprets the inscription correctly, loc. cit.; but cf. <persName>S. B. Platner</persName>, <hi rend="italic">Topographical Dictionary of Ancient Rome</hi>, <placeName>London</placeName>, 1929 (revised, <persName>T. Ashby</persName>), pp. 206, 207,
                  247, 555.) Felicitas was appropriate to <persName corresp="#nomisma_m_lepidvs_rrc">Lepidus</persName> as we have seen, Venus to <persName corresp="#nomisma_octavian">Octavian.</persName> (The Venus of the coin is Venus Genetrix; but Genetrix and Victrix were often not
                  distinguished: cf. <persName>Preller</persName>, op. cit., I, 443; II, 356–7.) Yet if there be here a reference to the Triumvirate, what could
                  be the significance of the ninth of October? The date of the meeting near Bononia is not known, but it appears to have fallen at the end of
                  the month or early in November.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n42">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">42</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>The identification was fixed by Borghesi, I, pp. 329–32. Cf. Plutarch, <hi rend="italic">Romulus</hi>, II. 3.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n43">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">43</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>"Mars"—Bahrfeldt, p. 59. But the lion's skin can be seen hanging down in the space between the rock and Hercules' legs. Grueber (I, p. 578)
                  and Sydenham (p. 182) prefer Anton as the identification, which can hardly be attacked although it seems unnecessarily subtle. Although the
                  sceptre and shield seem strange for Heracles, there appear to be no representations of Anton to establish his iconography. Cf. Plutarch,
                     <persName corresp="#nomisma_mark_antony">Antony</persName>, iv. 1, xxxvi. 4, lx. 3.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n44">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">44</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>For the scheme of die identification, see below note 48.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n45">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">45</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>Grueber, II, nos. 46–7; Sydenham nos. 1161–2.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n46">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">46</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>P. 50.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n47">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">47</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>P. 55.</p>
            </note>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d52e1657" type="chapter" n="II">
            <pb n="14"/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="bold">II</hi>
            </head>
            <p>Once the study of die linkage is undertaken as a method of chronological arrangement, one must pass beyond the stated coincidences. To ascertain
               not only which coins shared a given die, but the order in which they struck, would be a long step toward the solution of the problem. Although no
               one of the moneyers would be dated to any given year, their relative order might be established. For this reason an exacting study of the dies
               was undertaken. All the coins attributed in the Catalogue to <placeName>New York</placeName>, <placeName>London</placeName>, <placeName corresp="#nomisma_rome">Rome</placeName>, the <placeName>Vatican</placeName>, and <placeName>Naples</placeName> were studied in the original
               specimen. Casts were obtained of those in <placeName>Glasgow</placeName>, <placeName>the Hague</placeName>, <placeName>Paris</placeName>,
                  <placeName>St. Florian</placeName>, <placeName>Vienna</placeName>, and <placeName>Budapest</placeName>, as well as nos. 41.6, 44.1 and .2,
               47.11 and .12, and 48.7 and .14. The remaining specimens, about one quarter, were studied through photographs. Each coin was examined in the most
               minute detail. The progression of faults and breaks of each die was charted to reveal the chronological sequence of the coins struck from that
               die. The study was not always successful: in some cases the coins could be separated only into groups, not classified individually. In a few
               cases, particularly with respect to reverse dies, no separation was possible. But usually some distinctions could be drawn.</p>
            <p>When each die had been individually considered, the reverse dies were studied together. Something of the mint organization might be revealed by
               their sequence. Clearly, reverse dies could not have been traded about between the moneyers, for they were the signature dies; they could not
               indicate ties between the officials. But they might indicate how each official worked. Several dies offer us no information, either in not
               exhibiting progressive damage—e.g. <pb n="15"/>
               <persName>M.Ec</persName>
               <ref target="#CH1-n48">
                  <hi rend="sup">48</hi>
               </ref>—or in being paired with only one die, itself not found elsewhere—e.g. R.Bo—or in occurring on but a single example—e.g. A.VII. These dies
               will not be discussed below, save for the reverse dies of Varus, <hi rend="italic">exempli gratia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The reverse dies of C. Vibius Varus are of no assistance. The coins are too rare at present—we have only eight examples of this series for the
                  <hi rend="italic">triumviri</hi> together—and the die arrangement is indecisive. Die V.A was employed with one portrait die of <persName corresp="#nomisma_m_lepidvs_rrc">Lepidus</persName> and one of <persName corresp="#nomisma_octavian">Octavian.</persName> In either
               combination the breaks of V.A are the same, when the area in which they occur is not off the flan altogether. Die V.B occurs only with one
               portrait die of <persName corresp="#nomisma_mark_antony">Antony.</persName> Only one stage in the life of the die can be assumed for the three
               examples which we possess.</p>
            <p>The reverse dies of L. Mussidius Longus with cornucopia as type are more revealing. The known examples of reverse M.Ac show clearly that obverse
               O.II was struck with this reverse before obverse A.II. Moreover, die M.Bc began, insofar as our examples can indicate, with obverse A.III as
               mate, followed by O.II. The damage suffered by the reverse under the hammer marks the progression clearly. The latest pieces are struck with L.IV
               and, again, A.III. Similarly in <pb n="16"/> the case of reverse die M.Cc, the occurrences of obverses L.V and O.I intertwine in time.</p>
            <p>The second series of Mussidius, nos. 50–2, with Mars as the reverse type, offers a similar variation in the pairing of obverse dies. The gold
               struck to both M.Am and M.Bm may present examples of the random selection of obverse dies, as did those of M.Bc and M.Cc above. Until it is
               possible to divide the coins into smaller groups their exact sequence cannot be established. Certainly the pieces struck from die M.Bm appear to
               have been struck first to the portrait of <persName corresp="#nomisma_m_lepidvs_rrc">Lepidus</persName>, then to that of <persName corresp="#nomisma_mark_antony">Antony</persName>, and finally to the head of <persName corresp="#nomisma_octavian">Octavian.</persName> A
               further point of importance is to be noted: the sequence indicates that obverse portrait A.I, in some cases at least, was used before A.II, an
               element to be considered below in establishing the overall sequence of obverse dies. The evidence of reverse die M.Am exactly contradicts that of
               M.Bm; the sequence of obverse portraits begins with <persName corresp="#nomisma_octavian">Octavian</persName>, continues with <persName corresp="#nomisma_mark_antony">Antony</persName>, and ends with <persName corresp="#nomisma_m_lepidvs_rrc">Lepidus.</persName>
            </p>
            <p>The reverse dies of Publius <persName corresp="#nomisma_p_clodivs_m_f_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">Clodius</persName> add little to the study up to this
               point. None of them occurs with the portrait of more than one <hi rend="italic">triumvir,</hi> for the reverse type was cut with reference to the
               obverse die. Even within these limits only one sequence can be demonstrated. Die C.Al, of which we know only two impressions, was used with, at
               least, two <persName corresp="#nomisma_m_lepidvs_rrc">Lepidus</persName> portrait dies. In this case die L.I was employed before L.II. The two
               reverse dies cut for <persName corresp="#nomisma_mark_antony">Antony</persName>, as well as the two for <persName corresp="#nomisma_octavian">Octavian</persName>, occur each with only one obverse die.<ref target="#CH1-n49">
                  <hi rend="sup">49</hi>
               </ref>
            </p>
            <pb n="17"/>
            <p>Finally, the reverse dies of L. Livineius Regulus. Again, only one of the seven dies is known in combination with more than one portrait die.<ref target="#CH1-n50">
                  <hi rend="sup">50</hi>
               </ref> Reverse R.Ca occurs with three, <persName corresp="#nomisma_mark_antony">Antony</persName> portraits A.IV, A.V, and A.VI. Clearly A.VI was
               the latest to be paired with R.Ca, in two cases at least. Whether the point can be made in the third case, for no. 48.5, is not clear, nor is the
               relative dating of dies A.IV and A.V yet established.</p>
            <p>Thus far only the production of the individual moneyer has been presented; no connections between the officials have been established. These
               connections will present themselves with the consideration of the portrait dies of the <hi rend="italic">triumviri.</hi> The five series of gold
               consumed in all, as far as we know, seven portrait dies of <persName corresp="#nomisma_m_lepidvs_rrc">Lepidus</persName>, seven of <persName corresp="#nomisma_mark_antony">Antony</persName>, and four of <persName corresp="#nomisma_octavian">Octavian.</persName> Of the total of
               eighteen, five were used by more than one moneyer:</p>
            <table rows="5" cols="2">
               <row>
                  <cell>L.IV:</cell>
                  <cell>38.1 (Varus)—41.1, .2, .7 (Mussidius/cornucopia)</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>A.I:</cell>
                  <cell>45.1–.5, .7–9 (<persName corresp="#nomisma_p_clodivs_m_f_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">Clodius</persName>) —51.1, .3–7, .9 (Mussidius/Mars)</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>A.II:</cell>
                  <cell>39.1–.3 (Varus)—42.4, .7, .9 (Mussidius/cornucopia)—51.10, .11 (Mussidius/Mars)</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>O.I:</cell>
                  <cell>43.2, .3, .8 (Mussidius/cornucopia)—46.1, .2 (<persName corresp="#nomisma_p_clodivs_m_f_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">Clodius</persName>)</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>O.II:</cell>
                  <cell>40.1–.4 (Varus)—43.1, .4–.7, .9–.10 (Mussidius/cornucopia)—52.1–7, .10–.13 (Mussidius/Mars).</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>Bahrfeldt himself compared a part of the coins which he <pb n="18"/> listed, so that he was able to account for about half of the above
               links.</p>
            <p>Portrait die L.III is found only in the Mussidius series with Mars reverse. Four examples are known, with which appear three reverse dies. The
               order of the moneyer's signature dies may here be traced from the obverse damage: M.Am was the first to be used, M.Cm the second, and M.Bm the
               last. If this order can be shown to be consistent, this evidence may in its turn determine the order of other portraits struck to one or more of
               these reverses.</p>
            <p>The fourth portrait dies of <persName corresp="#nomisma_m_lepidvs_rrc">Lepidus</persName> occurs with but two reverse dies, V.A and M.Bc. The
               correct order of each moneyer's signature dies will be considered below; that is not to be found here. There is no doubt, however, that in this
               case at any rate Varus used the portrait die before Mussidius. After Varus had struck the one example which we possess, the die broke between the
               forehead of <persName corresp="#nomisma_m_lepidvs_rrc">Lepidus</persName> and the legend, and that break is to be seen on the three examples
               struck by Mussidius. Immediately Grueber's chronology is wrong, for he had dated Varus to the year after Mussidius' term of office. Similarly,
               Sydenham's dating, Mussidius to 42, Varus to 39, cannot be accepted.</p>
            <p>Die L.V occurs with two Mussidius reverses of the cornucopia type, M.Cc and M.Ec. The obverse damage makes clear that the two dies were used in
               that order. The coins struck from L.VI are relatively common, but the reverse die is the same in all cases, R.Al.</p>
            <p>The portrait dies of <persName corresp="#nomisma_mark_antony">Antony</persName> are equally helpful. Die A.I occurs in two series, those of
                  <persName corresp="#nomisma_p_clodivs_m_f_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">Clodius</persName> and Mussidius with Mars as reverse type. Two reverse dies of
                  <persName corresp="#nomisma_p_clodivs_m_f_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">Clodius</persName> were paired to the portrait. Unfortunately, only the
                  <placeName>British</placeName> Museum example of the first pairing, A.I and C.Aa, can easily be read; the only other piece known is
               illustrated in Riccio's catalogue, whose electrotype impressions are too crude for more than simple recognition. The one legible example was
               clearly <pb n="19"/> struck before the remaining <persName corresp="#nomisma_mark_antony">Antony</persName> pieces produced by <persName corresp="#nomisma_p_clodivs_m_f_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">Clodius</persName>, which bear reverse die C.Ba. The latter form a group which cannot
               easily be broken down into smaller segments.</p>
            <p>All the examples of A.I with a reverse die of <persName corresp="#nomisma_p_clodivs_m_f_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">Clodius</persName> preceded those
               with the signature of Mussidius. On the coins which we have the line of demarcation is very clear: on all the examples signed by <persName corresp="#nomisma_p_clodivs_m_f_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">Clodius</persName> the area enclosed by the upper parts of the letters NIV, on the obverse
               die, is totally corrupt. All save no. 45.7 have a clean break from the upper curve of the final C to the dotted edge. In the later series the
               first massive break has been repaired. Some traces remain, but two new breaks are now to be seen between TO and ON. The area about the end of the
               inscription has also been reworked to remove the break observed there: note that on the nos. 45 the dotted edge contains four dots from
               immediately above the vertical of P to above the upper tip of C. When this area was reworked the dotted edge was cut anew, so that five dots
               appear in the place of four on all the examples struck by Mussidius from this die.</p>
            <p>Antony's portrait A.I was paired by Mussidius with three reverse dies, M.Am, M.Bm, and M.Cm. Again, as in the case of the reverses of L.III, M.Am
               is earlier than M.Bm. The position of M.Cm is not clear, for the die was apparently used concurrently with M.Bm.</p>
            <p>The above evidence demonstrates that a second of Grueber's datings must be rejected, for Mussidius is assigned to 39 B.C. in his catalogue,
                  <persName corresp="#nomisma_p_clodivs_m_f_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">Clodius</persName> to 38. In accordance with the destruction of die A.I,
                  <persName corresp="#nomisma_p_clodivs_m_f_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">Clodius</persName> must have struck his series of gold honoring the <hi rend="italic">triumviri r.p.c.</hi> before the production of the Mussidius series with Mars reverse. So too Sydenham's arrangement is in
               error; it is not possible to agree that Mussidius struck in 42, <persName corresp="#nomisma_p_clodivs_m_f_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">Clodius</persName>
               in 41.</p>
            <p>Die A.II is found in three of the five series, the Mussidius series with Mars reverse, the Varus coinage, and the Mussidius series with
               cornucopia reverse. Only one reverse die is <pb n="20"/> found in combination with A.II from each series. The evidence confirms that which is
               presented above under L.IV, that Varus can no longer be dated later than Mussidius.</p>
            <p>Die A.III is found only in the Mussidius series with cornucopia reverse. It appears with three reverse dies, M.Bc, M.Dc, and M.Ec, in that order.
               The latest examples, nos. 42.2 and .6, are again struck from a pairing of A.III and M.Bc. This is one of only two cases in the five series of the
               recurrence of a reverse die; the other lies in the combination of A.I and M.Bm.</p>
            <p>Obverse die A.IV is known in eight impressions, six of them with Regulus' reverse R.Ba. The latest of the eight, no. 48.9, bears reverse R.Ca,
               thus establishing the relation of those two signature dies. The reverse of no. 48.14, die R.Aa, is otherwise unknown. It clearly preceded some of
               the examples of R.Ba, and probably should be taken as the earliest reverse of its type.</p>
            <p>Die A.V is found on only one coin; from its reverse die, R.Ca, it was determined above that it preceded at least two examples of A.VI. Portrait
               die A.VI occurs only with reverse R.Ca, the consideration of which demonstrated that this obverse must have followed A.IV.</p>
            <p>Of the four portrait dies of <persName corresp="#nomisma_octavian">Octavian</persName>, O.I is shared by two moneyers, <persName corresp="#nomisma_p_clodivs_m_f_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">Clodius</persName> and Mussidius in the cornucopia series. Only two coins are known of
                  <persName>Clodius'</persName> production for <persName corresp="#nomisma_octavian">Octavian</persName>, each with its distinctive reverse die.
               The reverse dies, of course, occur nowhere else, and the condition of the obverse in each case is not sufficiently distinctive to allow an
               opinion as to the priority of the striking. Both coins fall before the pieces struck by Mussidius from this obverse. In this group only one
               pairing occurs, with reverse M.Cc.</p>
            <p>Die O.II is found in three series, first with the Mussidius reverse bearing Mars as the type, latterly with a die of Varus and both Mussidius
               types. This large second group can be no further reduced—die O.II was unusually sturdy—but the <pb n="21"/> overall pattern follows that set
               above in the consideration of portrait A.II: some of the coins struck to Mussidius' Mars type are earlier than both the Varus pieces and the
               Mussidius cornucopia specimens. Whether or not one wishes to date all the Mussidius Mars reverses before the remaining types, that arrangement
               obtains in at least a number of cases, and we have found no evidence to contradict it.</p>
            <p>With respect to the reverse dies paired with obverse O.II, the three earliest specimens occur with M.Am, while the coins of this series in the
               second group are all found with M.Bm. The evidence of L.III and A.I above, that this was the order of consumption of the two reverse dies, is
               here confirmed. The Varus reverse is the same in all cases, V.A. The usage of the cornucopia dies of Mussidius, M.Ac and M.Bc, cannot be
               disentangled at this point.</p>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n48">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">48</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>The reader will wish to consult the two tables below, pp.45 and 54, for the linkage and the chronology of each obverse and reverse die. It
                  must be observed that the die designations are, for the moment, completely arbitrary. The obverse dies are identified by the initial of the
                     <hi rend="italic">triumvir</hi> and a Roman numeral: e.g., the four portraits of <persName corresp="#nomisma_octavian">Octavian</persName>
                  are given as O.I through O.IV. The reverse dies are identified by the initial of the moneyer —V(arus), M(ussidius), C(lodius), and
                  R(egulus)—and a capital letter. Thus, Varus' two reverse dies are V.A and V.B. Since two series were struck by Mussidius, a third, minuscule
                  letter distinguishes between them: M.Cc is the third die of Mussidius in the cornucopia series, M.Am, the first in the series with Mars
                  reverse. Both <persName corresp="#nomisma_p_clodivs_m_f_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">Clodius</persName> and Regulus used especial reverses to suit the
                  individual <hi rend="italic">triumvir</hi>: R.Bo designates Regulus' second die for <persName corresp="#nomisma_octavian">Octavian</persName>,
                  R.Ca, his third die for <persName corresp="#nomisma_mark_antony">Antony</persName>, C.Al, <persName>Clodius'</persName> first die for
                     <persName corresp="#nomisma_m_lepidvs_rrc">Lepidus.</persName> The designations "first die" or "third die" are arbitrary and have as yet no
                  bearing on the chronological arrangement of the dies.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n49">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">49</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>The paucity of this series of <persName corresp="#nomisma_p_clodivs_m_f_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">Clodius</persName>' gold is the more to be
                  regretted in that the reverses cut for <persName corresp="#nomisma_octavian">Octavian</persName> are of the finest workmanship. Die C.Ao is an
                  example of the best in Roman die engraving of the period. The technique is impeccable: the relief is high, the figures finely proportioned.
                  And, more important, the concept is impeccable. The type is designed to adorn a circular field, it is not cut at random. The curve of Cupid's
                  wing and Venus' head exactly parallels the border of dots. The artist has emphasized the primary importance of the harmony of type, legend and
                  border by breaking the legend at an unexpected point, the better to fit it into the whole. (Cf. the reverse of the Concordia-Cloacina denarius
                  of Mussidius [Grueber, I, nos. 4242-7]: the type is overpowered by the legend. Cf. also reverse die R.Bo: the legend is artifically forced
                  about the figures so as to deny the circular nature of the field.) Unfortunately, the single coin known from die C.Ao is badly battered and
                  holed as well.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n50">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">50</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>Actually, reverse R.A1 is found not only with all the examples of <persName>Lepidus'</persName> portrait L.VI, but with the single impression
                  of L.VII (no. 47<hi rend="italic">bis</hi>) which I omit from this discussion. See the note to that number in the Catalogue.</p>
            </note>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d52e1974" type="chapter" n="III">
            <pb n="22"/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="bold">III</hi>
            </head>
            <p>The material in the foregoing chapter having been assembled, it now becomes possible to render an assessment of it, in the hope that some
               conclusions of fact can be reached which will surpass the suppositions of earlier years. Let us begin with the sequence of the signature dies of
               each moneyer as established by the corruption of the obverse dies.</p>
            <p>Varus' two reverse dies are never paired with the same portrait, so that no sequence can be established. But three lines can be traced in the
               Mussidius series with cornucopia reverse. First, obverse die A.III established that reverse M.Bc was followed first by M.Dc, then by M.Ec. M.Bc
               appears a second time after M.Ec. Second, reverse M.Ec was also preceded at some point by die M.Cc, as obverse L.V proves. M.Cc, however, must
               follow M.Bc, for the latter is not found paired with L.V as are both M.Cc and M.Ec. Third, reverse M.Ac is one of the earliest of the series, for
               it is paired to O.II even as is M.Bc. There the order of the two reverse dies cannot be determined. But since M.Bc precedes M.Dc and M.Ec, then
               M.Ac must precede them as well. But M.Bc, M.Dc, and M.Ec are all struck to obverse A.III, while M.Ac was paired with A.II. Therefore M.Ac
               precedes the lot. The final stemma of the cornucopia dies then should be: 1. M.Ac; 2. M.Bc; 3. M.Cc—M.Dc; 4. M.Ec; 5. M.Ac <hi rend="italic">bis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is not to imply that M.Cc and M.Dc were necessarily used concurrently. That the dies tend to fall into a one by one sequence opposes such a
               conclusion. But it is hardly safe to attempt to reduce the stemma any further. This sequence, established by the examination of the portraits, is
               confirmed by the style of the reverse types. For the two earliest cornucopiae are delicate and graceful, while the lower tips curve <pb n="23"/>
               back to the left and terminate no farther to the right than the axial line of the whole. The cornucopiae of M.Cc and M.Ec have deviated from this
               standard: the body is rather larger than need be, and the whole is thrown off balance in that the tip curves much too far to the right. The dumpy
               and graceless cornucopia of M.Dc is even worse.<ref target="#CH1-n51">
                  <hi rend="sup">51</hi>
               </ref>
            </p>
            <p>One conclusion to be drawn from this evidence is, that the striking was not organized from the obverse portrait. That is, we might have assumed
               that any authority claimed by a moneyer was but nominal. We know that the <hi rend="italic">aerarium</hi> must have been primary in the thoughts
               of the <hi rend="italic">triumviri</hi>—even thus <persName corresp="#nomisma_julius_caesar">Caesar</persName> had seized it as one of his first
               acts on entering Rome<ref target="#CH1-n52">
                  <hi rend="sup">52</hi>
               </ref>—and that the power of coinage now depended directly from them, rather than from the senate and the magistrates. One indication of such
               authority would have been the production of coin according to the portrait die; as long as Antony's image was to be seen, any moneyer could have
               signed his name on the reverse. A group of <persName corresp="#nomisma_mark_antony">Antony</persName> gold would be struck with whatever reverse
               dies, in any order or at random, followed by an issue of <persName corresp="#nomisma_m_lepidvs_rrc">Lepidus</persName> coins or <persName corresp="#nomisma_octavian">Octavian</persName> pieces.</p>
            <p>But the evidence of the cornucopia dies is that the case was just the opposite. A chronological arrangement of the coins struck from dies M.Ac,
               M.Bc, and M.Cc has been erected. But the corresponding obverse dies seem almost to have <pb n="24"/> been used at random. Why would a worker
               strike with O.I, for example, put it aside in favor of L.V, and then take it up a second time? That such a sequence was followed is the testimony
               of reverse die M.Cc. Perhaps the worker drew an obverse die at random as he began each day's work. Or perhaps there was consciously an attempt to
               balance the number of coins struck with the portrait of each <hi rend="italic">triumvir.</hi> But in any case, the reverse die, the moneyer's
               signature die, was the limiting element, not the portrait. Ultimately monetary control must have ascended to the <hi rend="italic">triumviri</hi>
               themselves; no order of coinage would change that. But in the mint itself, in the process of striking, the moneyer must still have filled a
               position of some responsibility, for the coins of each are struck first to his signature. That the position of the moneyer did not change under
                  <persName corresp="#nomisma_julius_caesar">Caesar</persName>
               <ref target="#CH1-n53">
                  <hi rend="sup">53</hi>
               </ref> or under the <hi rend="italic">triumviri</hi> ought to be sufficient to show that the responsibilities of the office were not
               initiative.</p>
            <p>The reverse dies of <persName corresp="#nomisma_p_clodivs_m_f_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">Clodius</persName> vary in type with the <hi rend="italic">triumvir,</hi> so that a stemma ought to be established for each. But only one reverse is known to have been struck to the portrait of
                  <persName corresp="#nomisma_m_lepidvs_rrc">Lepidus</persName>, while the two dies cut for <persName corresp="#nomisma_octavian">Octavian</persName> cannot be ordered chronologically by the damage done to obverse O.I. In the case of the dies cut for <persName corresp="#nomisma_mark_antony">Antony</persName> the results are clearer. The breaks in A.I show that C.Aa was earlier than C.Ba; had either
               been paired with any other obverse the evidence might have been more profitable.</p>
            <p>The reverse dies of Regulus, as those of <persName corresp="#nomisma_p_clodivs_m_f_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">Clodius</persName>, were designed for the
               individual <hi rend="italic">triumvir,</hi> so that again their significance is limited. Only one reverse is known for the <persName corresp="#nomisma_m_lepidvs_rrc">Lepidus</persName> gold, which itself knows but one portrait, save for the curious bronze, no. 47 <hi rend="italic">bis.</hi> The reverse of that piece is in no con- <pb n="25"/> dition to allow a comparison with the reverses of the gold coins.
               Two reverse dies occur for the <persName corresp="#nomisma_octavian">Octavian</persName> coinage; again, each is struck with its own obverse
               which is not found elsewhere. The <persName corresp="#nomisma_mark_antony">Antony</persName> coinage offers more variety. Portrait die A.IV
               indicates that three of the four reverses fall into the stemma: 1. R.Aa; 2. R.Ba; 3. R.Ca. The fourth reverse die, R.Da, occurs only once, on no.
               48.10, with an obverse impression which is itself unique.</p>
            <p>Finally, the reverse dies of Mussidius with Mars as type fall into a clear pattern. Obverse L.III establishes the order M.Am, M.Cm, M.Bm. The
               precedence of M.Am over M.Bm is confirmed by both portrait dies A.I and O.II. But in the former case the position of M.Cm is not secondary but
               tertiary. From the evidence of the obverse breaks it appears that the stemma must have been: 1. M.Am; 2. M.Bm; 3. M.Cm; 4. M.Bm <hi rend="italic">bis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When the reverse dies have been ordered, to the extent that is possible, the sequence of the portrait dies becomes considerably clearer. Since
               Mussidius' cornucopia dies M.Ac and M.Bc are the earliest of that series, it must follow that <persName corresp="#nomisma_octavian">Octavian</persName> portrait O.II, paired with each of the two reverses, preceded in use—again, in this series—obverse O.I, which occurs only
               with M.Cc. Similarly, portrait L.IV, struck only with M.Bc, was utilized before die L.V, which was paired with reverses M.Cc and M.Ec. Finally,
               since M.Ac preceded M.Dc and M.Ec, the portraits of <persName corresp="#nomisma_mark_antony">Antony</persName> to which they were struck must
               share that order: A.II is earlier than A.III.</p>
            <p>The two coins of <persName corresp="#nomisma_m_lepidvs_rrc">Lepidus</persName> struck by <persName corresp="#nomisma_p_clodivs_m_f_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">Clodius</persName> bear two differing portrait dies. The damage done to the reverse die,
               C.Al, establishes that obverse L.I preceded L.II. The coins of <persName corresp="#nomisma_p_clodivs_m_f_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">Clodius</persName>
               produced for <persName corresp="#nomisma_mark_antony">Antony</persName> are all struck to the same obverse die, as are those of <persName corresp="#nomisma_octavian">Octavian.</persName>
            </p>
            <pb n="26"/>
            <p>The only group of Regulus' coinage which permits examination are the pieces struck for <persName corresp="#nomisma_mark_antony">Antony.</persName> Both reverses R.Aa and R.Ba are paired with obverse die A.IV, so that it preceded the other two found with R.Ca, dies A.V
               and A.VI. Although all three comprise the earlier group of gold under R.Ca, the later coins were struck from A.VI. Now one would expect that a
               portrait die would not recur. That die was in higher relief than the reverse, the more difficult to cut, and probably the lower and better
               protected of the two dies when in striking position —there are more of the reverse dies, for one thing. Each obverse surely was used until
               nothing more could be done with it: the niggardlyness of the moneyer or the indolence of the engraver is illustrated by the repair of obverse
               A.I, as well as the lamentable state of the dies on the latest examples struck from L.V and, again, A.I. If these considerations be correct, the
               first group of coins listed under R.Ca should be broken up so that A.IV precedes, A.VI follows, and the stemma is: 1. A.IV; 2. A.V; 3. A.VI.</p>
            <p>Finally, the Mars series of Mussidius establishes that Antony's portrait die A.I preceded A.II. To be sure, M.Bm occurs twice in the stemma, but
               its own breaks indicate that A.II was the later die in use.</p>
            <p>It has been shown that when each moneyer produced his gold, no effort was made to strike to the portraits in any order. Thus, reverse die M.Bc
               was paired with obverse A.III, then with O.II, and finally with L.IV and A.III again. The only limitation seems to have been that the same three
               portrait dies were employed as long as each was usable. It should, then, be possible to trace the order of each moneyer's production in the
               college or colleges by the obverse dies, whether their dies were thrown together in a jumble, or whether each official had completed his coinage
               before the next began. Again the evidence is not always complete, for not every coin could be classified individually, but it is never
               contradictory.</p>
            <pb n="27"/>
            <p>The chronology of obverse dies determined above by reverse breaks is exactly confirmed as one traces the dies passing among the moneyers. All
               three portraits used by Varus—let us begin with Bahrfeldt's order—were used by Mussidius, two of them in both of his series. Bahrfeldt himself
               noted the one break which proved no. 38.1 to have been struck before nos. 41.1–.2, .7, break no. 3 under <persName corresp="#nomisma_m_lepidvs_rrc">Lepidus</persName> portrait L.IV below.<ref target="#CH1-n54">
                  <hi rend="sup">54</hi>
               </ref> Thus some, at any rate, of the cornucopia series struck for <persName corresp="#nomisma_m_lepidvs_rrc">Lepidus</persName> were proved
               later than the <hi rend="italic">unicum</hi> of Varus. The other examples of no. 41 were struck from obverse L.V. But it has been shown above
               that the stemma of Mussidius' cornucopia dies proves L.IV to have been used before L.V. Therefore all the Mussidius cornucopia coins struck for
                  <persName corresp="#nomisma_m_lepidvs_rrc">Lepidus</persName> are later than the Varus piece.</p>
            <p>Even this step does not prove the independence of Mussidius' coinage; one must consider the coinage by Varus and Mussidius for <persName corresp="#nomisma_mark_antony">Antony</persName> and <persName corresp="#nomisma_octavian">Octavian.</persName> In fact, obverse A.II tells
               exactly the same tale: all three examples produced by Varus are earlier than the pieces from the same die in the cornucopia series of Mussidius.
               Again, the other coins of <persName corresp="#nomisma_mark_antony">Antony</persName> in this series were struck with portrait die A.III, which by
               virtue of the stemma of cornucopia dies established above must have been in use after A.II. Portrait O.II cannot help us. Most of the coins
               struck from this obverse cannot be distinguished <hi rend="italic">inter se;</hi> those of Varus are at any rate not shown to be later than the
               Mussidius pieces of cornucopia reverse.</p>
            <p>Two of Varus' obverse dies, A.II and O.II, are also to be found in the Mussidius series with Mars' reverse. Portrait O.II is here a bit more
               helpful, for in spite of the difficulty in <pb n="28"/> distributing the coins it is clear that these Mussidius pieces were produced earlier than
               the Varus coins from the same die. The portrait of <persName corresp="#nomisma_mark_antony">Antony</persName>, A.II, makes the same point as
               definitively.</p>
            <p>Thus the results of the treatment of portraits LIV, A.II, and O.II are rather unexpected. Mussidius' cornucopia series as a whole followed the
               coins struck by Varus, as Bahrfeldt noted for one case. But Bahrfeldt implies, by the manner in which his material is arranged, that the Mars
               series of Mussidius was later still. The contrary is true: not only do the latter pieces precede the cornucopia series, they precede as well the
               coinage of Varus.</p>
            <p>
               <persName corresp="#nomisma_p_clodivs_m_f_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">Clodius</persName> struck with four obverse portraits. Two of them are shared, A.I
               with Mussidius in the Mars series, O.I with the same moneyer in the cornucopia series. In either case the <persName corresp="#nomisma_p_clodivs_m_f_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">Clodius</persName> pieces are found to be the earlier. But since the Mars series is the
               earliest of the three discussed above, the <persName corresp="#nomisma_p_clodivs_m_f_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">Clodius</persName> coinage must precede
               them all. Portrait die O.I is noted to be the only obverse die which reappears after its substitution by another, for between its two appearances
               occurs obverse O.II under Varus and in both series of Mussidius.</p>
            <p>The stemma of obverse dies as employed by these three moneyers is then established, and the order in which the four series were produced is
               absolutely certain:</p>
            <table rows="8" cols="4">
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell rend="center">
                     <persName corresp="#nomisma_m_lepidvs_rrc">Lepidus</persName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell rend="center">
                     <persName corresp="#nomisma_mark_antony">Antony</persName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell rend="center">
                     <persName corresp="#nomisma_octavian">Octavian</persName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>1. <persName corresp="#nomisma_p_clodivs_m_f_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">Clodius</persName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell rend="right">I</cell>
                  <cell rend="right">I</cell>
                  <cell rend="right">I</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell rend="right">II</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>2. Mussidius/Mars</cell>
                  <cell rend="right">III</cell>
                  <cell rend="right">I</cell>
                  <cell rend="right">II</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell rend="right">II</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>3. Varus</cell>
                  <cell rend="right">IV</cell>
                  <cell rend="right">II</cell>
                  <cell rend="right">II</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>4. Mussidius/cornucopia</cell>
                  <cell rend="right">IV</cell>
                  <cell rend="right">II</cell>
                  <cell rend="right">II</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell rend="right">V</cell>
                  <cell rend="right">III</cell>
                  <cell rend="right">I</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <pb n="29"/>
            <p>Having arrived at this point, one may be concerned to note that Regulus is omitted from the stemma. A chronology of obverse dies ought to be
               constructed for his coins even as for those of the other three moneyers. The two <persName corresp="#nomisma_m_lepidvs_rrc">Lepidus</persName>
               portraits cannot be separated in time, for that which appears only on the bronze is paired to a reverse impression too badly preserved for study.
               Of the four <persName corresp="#nomisma_mark_antony">Antony</persName> portraits, three were ordered above in the consideration of reverse R.Ca.
               The fourth, A.VII, is known in but one example, paired with a reverse itself unique, so that it must fall outside the scheme. Finally, each of
               the two portraits of <persName corresp="#nomisma_octavian">Octavian</persName> is struck to a single reverse, which permits no argument of
               priority. The stemma of the obverse dies used by Regulus is, then:</p>
            <table rows="5" cols="3">
               <row>
                  <cell rend="center">
                     <persName corresp="#nomisma_m_lepidvs_rrc">Lepidus</persName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell rend="center">
                     <persName corresp="#nomisma_mark_antony">Antony</persName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell rend="center">
                     <persName corresp="#nomisma_octavian">Octavian</persName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>VI</cell>
                  <cell>1. IV</cell>
                  <cell>III</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>VII</cell>
                  <cell>2. V</cell>
                  <cell>IV</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>3. VI</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell cols="2">plus VII at some point.</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>The curious fact is that Regulus shares no portrait die with any of the other three moneyers. Apparently Bahrfeldt missed the point, for he
               implies that the interchange of dies was general.<ref target="#CH1-n55">
                  <hi rend="sup">55</hi>
               </ref> Actually there is not a single case of die correspondence. One may argue that the material is weak—as assuredly it is—or that the
               dichotomy is merely coincidental. But the gap is even wider: save only for one case even Regulus' die engravers differ.</p>
            <p>The first two of the three portraits of <persName corresp="#nomisma_mark_antony">Antony</persName> used by <persName corresp="#nomisma_p_clodivs_m_f_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">Clodius</persName>, Mussidius, and Varus are both clearly the work of one hand and indeed
               are almost identical. The third die chronologically, A.III, bears rather a better portrait. The relief is higher, the eye is more nearly in
               profile than before, the forward edge of the nose is cut rather than simply <pb n="30"/> traced. The portrait of A.III seems to be by the same
               hand as those of A.I and A.II, but the concept is more plastic, the hand more confident. The portrait of A.III should then be compared with that
               of O.II: both heads are spherical, while the treatment of hair, eye, and ear indicate the same engraver.</p>
            <p>The five <persName corresp="#nomisma_m_lepidvs_rrc">Lepidus</persName> dies in the stemma can be broken down by style into three groups. Those
               used by <persName corresp="#nomisma_p_clodivs_m_f_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">Clodius</persName>, L.I and L.II, were cut by one hand. The head is rather
               long for its height, the treatment of the hair at the back of the head is linear, the neck and chin are separated by a deep cut. Dies L.III and
               L.IV are the work of a second artist. The head is rather square, the treatment of the hair is plastic, the chin and neck are molded together. Die
               L.III is the more successful in the profile view of the eye. Finally, the portrait of obverse die L.V is small, in high relief, representing a
               round head with a deep Scopaic wrinkle in the forehead. The three hands can equally be distinguished by the cut of the lower edge of the bust:
               the first engraver cuts two small indentations upward but overall the line is almost straight; the second engraver emphasizes the second
               indentation so that the lower right point of the bust curves downward; the third abandons the indentations for a single dramatic swoop
               upward.</p>
            <p>None of the above dies—that is, all of the stemma save O.I —was cut by any engraver who cut a portrait for Regulus. Three artists worked under
               Regulus in this series. The first cut the two <persName corresp="#nomisma_m_lepidvs_rrc">Lepidus</persName>, the two <persName corresp="#nomisma_octavian">Octavian</persName>, and the best of the four <persName corresp="#nomisma_mark_antony">Antony</persName>
               portraits, A.IV. The sensitive portraits are by far the finest of all the obverse dies. One may object that the head of <persName corresp="#nomisma_m_lepidvs_rrc">Lepidus</persName> is much too young for a man approaching his fiftieth year. But the heads are cut with
               delicacy and feeling, the hair is handled with care to preserve its plasticity, the eye is always correctly cut for the profile. All are in
               comparatively high relief. No better portrait of <persName corresp="#nomisma_m_lepidvs_rrc">Lepidus</persName>
               <pb n="31"/> exists; that of <persName corresp="#nomisma_octavian">Octavian</persName> was surpassed only after Actium when the concept of his
               portrait had changed entirely;<ref target="#CH1-n56">
                  <hi rend="sup">56</hi>
               </ref> that of <persName corresp="#nomisma_mark_antony">Antony</persName> is challenged only by the head of the unique aureus of <persName corresp="#nomisma_mark_antony">Antony</persName> and Octavia in the <placeName>Berlin</placeName> collection.<ref target="#CH1-n57">
                  <hi rend="sup">57</hi>
               </ref>
            </p>
            <p>Two other hands are seen in the portraits of <persName corresp="#nomisma_mark_antony">Antony</persName> produced for Regulus. Die A.VI is rather
               well cut technically, but the quality of the portrait is less than that of A.IV. The back of the head is somewhat misshapen, and the bust below
               is out of balance; for the right point is so lightly cut as to fade away, while the left is distinctly presented. Still, the lower part of the
               bust is reminiscent in style of the fine portraits mentioned above: perhaps we have here a product of the same engraver on an off-day. The third
               (or second?) hand cut two monstrous portraits of <persName corresp="#nomisma_mark_antony">Antony</persName>, dies A.V and A.VII. The head is
               small and round, the eye too large and incorrectly cut for the profile view, the nose large and awkward. The relief of the whole is low.</p>
            <p>A complete dichotomy between Regulus' dies and those of the other three moneyers is averted at just one point. For although Regulus never strikes
               with a die used by any of the other moneyers, the artist who created his fine portraits also cut obverse die O.I. The latter is more finely cut
               and more realistic in effect than its companion die, O.II; indeed the portraits of O.I and O.IV are almost identical. Thus, although the stemma
               of obverse dies excludes the coins of Regulus, the identification of a common engraver, as well as the historical considerations presented below,
               permit us to continue to inquire whether Regulus might not have been the colleague of <persName corresp="#nomisma_p_clodivs_m_f_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">Clodius</persName>, Mussidius, and Varus.</p>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n51">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">51</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>Prof. Alföldi has already attested the deterioration in portrait engraving which confirms his chronology of the coins of 44 B.C. <hi rend="italic">(Studien über Caesars Monarchie,</hi> Lund, 1953).</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n52">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">52</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>Dio xli.17.1–2, <hi rend="italic">inter alia.</hi> In the days of private armies, the role of commander was too heavy a burden financially for
                  any private citizen. Thus <persName corresp="#nomisma_octavian">Octavian</persName>, having occupied Rome in 43, had to distribute 2500
                  denarii per man to his eight legions, a total of some four hundred million sesterces. Each soldier received the equivalent of 805 grammes of
                  gold, a considerable amount of money even today. This was probably the occasion of the gold coinage of Ti. Sempronius Gracchus and Q. Voconius
                  Vitulus (see Alföldi, "Porträtkunst," pp. 164–6).</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n53">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">53</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>
                  <persName corresp="#nomisma_julius_caesar">Caesar</persName>, we are told, made use of <hi rend="italic">peculiares servos</hi> in the mint
                  (Suetonius, <hi rend="italic">Divus Julius</hi> lxxvi.3) in addition to having enlarged the college from three to four (cf. ibid, xli.i).
                  Undoubtedly the <hi rend="italic">servi</hi> were to keep an eye on the moneyers, but legally they had no significance.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n54">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">54</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>"Stempelgleich: … n. 41. u. 2 und Exemplar Montagu, sowie hiermit die Hs. vom Goldstücke des C. Veibius Vaarus oben n. 38. Eine auf letzterem
                  vorhandene kleine Stempelverletzung erscheint auf den Mussidius- Goldstücken vergrößert, also sind diese später geprägt, als das des Vibius!"
                  (p. 56).</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n55">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">55</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>See above, p. 13.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n56">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">56</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>The later head is a young, idealized portrait. Cf. e.g., Bahrfeldt nos. 104 to 9. The problem of the change in Augustan portraiture is treated
                  by Josef Liegle, "Die Münzprägung <persName>Octavians</persName> nach dem Siege von Actium und die augusteische Kunst," in <hi rend="italic">Jahrbuch des Deutschen Archäologischen Instituts</hi> LVI (1941) 91–119.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n57">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">57</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>Bahrfeldt no. 88.</p>
            </note>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d52e2431" type="chapter" n="IV">
            <pb n="32"/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="bold">IV</hi>
            </head>
            <p>It has been indicated above that the fact that a die link exists between two moneyers does not limit them to the same college.<ref target="#CH1-n58">
                  <hi rend="sup">58</hi>
               </ref> Even when the investigation of the die faults is successful, only a relative chronology is the result. To prove that moneyer A used die X
               before moneyer B still does not date the two men to the same year. A may have struck a day or a decade before B. Ultimately, the only way to
               prove the point is somehow to show that A struck both before and after B. They must have coined in some manner so as to overlap. Only then are
               they assuredly and beyond any question colleagues.</p>
            <p>The evidence now is clear that each of the series of gold under discussion is self-contained, each was struck individually. But fortunately for
               us, Mussidius rested from his labors and permitted Varus to coin in the interval between the two series with Mars and with the cornucopia as
               reverse types. Varus and Mussidius, then, are proved to have been colleagues. Neither Grueber nor Sydenham can be followed in this question any
               longer. The coins themselves have solved the problem once for all.</p>
            <p>
               <persName corresp="#nomisma_p_clodivs_m_f_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">Clodius</persName> is not yet assuredly a colleague of the other two. His series of
               gold preceded theirs; that is proved. Theoretically, however, he might have coined a year or two earlier. The answer to this cavil is the
               consideration of the date of the college to which Varus and Mussidius pertained.</p>
            <p>The <hi rend="italic">terminus post quem</hi> for the production of the gold under discussion is obviously the date of the Lex Titia, <pb n="33"/> November 27, 43 B.C. Before that date the Triumvirate had no legal existence, so that the obverse legend would be impossible. The <hi rend="italic">terminus ante quem</hi> is the battle of Naulochus and the defeat of Sextus <persName corresp="#nomisma_pompey">Pompey</persName> in September, 36. For after the victory <persName corresp="#nomisma_m_lepidvs_rrc">Lepidus</persName> committed himself to
               the delusion that his second-rate status as primate of Africa, fobbed off on him after Philippi and at Brundisium in 40, could be ameliorated
               only by open defiance of <persName corresp="#nomisma_octavian">Octavian.</persName> But Caesar's heir invoked once again the dramatic flair which
               recalled his father, <persName corresp="#nomisma_m_lepidvs_rrc">Lepidus</persName> cowered and begged forgiveness, and the Triumvirate became for
               all practical purposes a Duumvirate.</p>
            <p>But the latest date for our gold can be set back still further. The Triumvirate had lasted, legally, for five years, 42 through 38 B.C. When the
               term of office had expired no one dared challenge in law the position which the <hi rend="italic">triumviri</hi> had taken by force. But
               legalistics prevailed, and all unnecessarily the Triumvirate was renewed, at Tarentum in 37 B.C., as of the first of January of that year.<ref target="#CH1-n59">
                  <hi rend="sup">59</hi>
               </ref> After this date each <hi rend="italic">triumvir</hi> was theoretically <hi rend="italic">triumvir iter r.p.c.,</hi> a nicety observed by
                  <persName corresp="#nomisma_octavian">Octavian</persName> in his titulary on the coins.<ref target="#CH1-n60">
                  <hi rend="sup">60</hi>
               </ref> The omission of the iteration dates the moneyers' gold back to 38 B.C. at the latest, the date forwarded by Grueber as the year of office
               of Varus and <persName>Clodius.</persName>
            </p>
            <p>The gold of our four moneyers was struck somewhere between 43 and 38 B.C., inclusive; reason induces us to inquire why the gold was struck at
               all. Each of the moneyers struck gold with a type or types of his own choosing. The Varus aureus with head of Apollo<ref target="#CH1-n61">
                  <hi rend="sup">61</hi>
               </ref> on the obverse and standing <pb n="34"/> Venus on the reverse is the commonest of all Republican gold, save only that struck for <persName corresp="#nomisma_julius_caesar">Caesar</persName> by Hirtius. This duality, the private types and the portrait coinage of the <hi rend="italic">triumviri,</hi> makes clear that it was not incumbent on the officials simply to laud their city's leaders. Even when the <hi rend="italic">triumviri</hi> were to be honored the moneyers' enthusiasm was not boundless.</p>
            <p>The fact that these gold series are unique in conception, the fact that <persName corresp="#nomisma_m_lepidvs_rrc">Lepidus</persName> never again
               appears on a coin struck at Rome,<ref target="#CH1-n62">
                  <hi rend="sup">62</hi>
               </ref> the fact that <persName corresp="#nomisma_mark_antony">Antony</persName> and <persName corresp="#nomisma_octavian">Octavian</persName>
               never again appear at Rome on the same coin or joined in series,<ref target="#CH1-n63">
                  <hi rend="sup">63</hi>
               </ref> the fact that the moneyers manage to produce gold of types having no direct reference to the <hi rend="italic">triumviri —</hi>all lead
               one to conclude that some special impetus must have motivated the production of these rich and varied aurei. That impetus is most obviously, of
               course, the very inauguration of the Triumvirate. The newest office of the state, nearest to king, is celebrated by the king's own metal—the
               types are not <pb n="35"/> found in silver. The triumviral portrait gold of <persName corresp="#nomisma_p_clodivs_m_f_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">Clodius</persName>, Mussidius, Varus, and Regulus is to be understood as commemorative of a new beginning for Rome.</p>
            <p>Bahrfeldt had assumed as much, although the manner in which he dated the pieces cannot be accepted. "Die Münzen … scheiden sich ohne weiteres in
               zwei durch ihr Gepräge wesentlich von einander abweichenden Gruppen. Die Gepräge der ersten folgen in ihrer Verschiedenartigkeit ganz dem
               hergebrachten republikanischen Brauche, während auf denen der zweiten Gruppe die Porträts und Namen der drei Machthaber <persName corresp="#nomisma_m_lepidvs_rrc">M. Lepidus</persName>, <persName corresp="#nomisma_mark_antony">M. Antonius</persName> und <persName corresp="#nomisma_julius_caesar">C. Caesar</persName> mit ihrem Titel III.VIR.R.P.C erscheinen. Daraus folgt unzweifelhaft, daß der Abschluß
               der Triumvirats in die Amtstätigkeit des Kollegiums fiel und daß die Münzen der ersten Gruppe vor dem 27/11 711/43 geprägt worden sind, die der
               zweiten aber danach. … Die Gepräge der zweiten Gruppe sind sehr zahlreich. … Ich glaube daher annehmen zu können, daB alle diese Münzen sich
               nicht auf den kurzen Zeitraum vom 27/11 711/43 bis zum Ende des Jahres zu- sammendrängen lassen, sondern daß ihre Prägung auch noch in das Jahr
               712/42 hinübergreift, die Amtstätigkeit dieses Kollegiums also von mehr als einjähriger Dauer gewesen sein wird…"<ref target="#CH1-n64">
                  <hi rend="sup">64</hi>
               </ref>
            </p>
            <p>Bahrfeldt assumes a difficulty where none exists. For he believes that the private types must have been struck before the triumviral portraits.
               The assumption implies that had the Triumvirate been created on the first of January, instead of the twenty-seventh of November of 43, that the
               moneyers of that year would have expended all their energy in producing public types while abjuring the private. But the suggestion is
               gratuitous; P. Accoleius, <persName corresp="#nomisma_petillivs_capitolinvs_rrc">Petillius</persName> Capitolinus, and Marcellinus<ref target="#CH1-n65">
                  <hi rend="sup">65</hi>
               </ref> all struck after the formation of the <pb n="36"/> Triumvirate with no public types at all.<ref target="#CH1-n66">
                  <hi rend="sup">66</hi>
               </ref> Bahrfeldt would also have to explain why, if the moneyers were so zealous in portraying the <hi rend="italic">triumviri</hi> on their
               gold, they were so haphazard in their silver.<ref target="#CH1-n67">
                  <hi rend="sup">67</hi>
               </ref>
            </p>
            <p>Second, Bahrfeldt skirts danger by suggesting hopefully that the college of 43 might have continued in office in 42.<ref target="#CH1-n68">
                  <hi rend="sup">68</hi>
               </ref> For less than thirty-five days remained in the year after the promulgation of the Lex Titia. A great series of dies had to be cut—we know
               eighteen obverse and twenty-two reverse to have been used—and presumably golden flans had to be manufactured. Yet again the difficulty is removed
               by denying it. We know of no reason why the office might have been prorogued, and if Varus and Mussidius struck only in 42 <pb n="37"/> they
               would have had a full year for the production of all the coins which they wished to strike.<ref target="#CH1-n69">
                  <hi rend="sup">69</hi>
               </ref>
            </p>
            <p>Nor is it then difficult to fill the college of 43. The key is the discovery that the denarius of L. Servius Rufus bears not the portrait of the
               tribune, Servius Sulpicius Rufus,<ref target="#CH1-n70">
                  <hi rend="sup">70</hi>
               </ref> but that of Marcus Junius Brutus the tyrranicide.<ref target="#CH1-n71">
                  <hi rend="sup">71</hi>
               </ref> Obviously political support of this nature would have been meaningful in the course of only two years, 44 and 43 B.C. The college of 44
               has already been established: M. Mettius, L. Aemilius Buca, P. Sepullius Macer, and C. Cossutius Maridianus.<ref target="#CH1-n72">
                  <hi rend="sup">72</hi>
               </ref> The portrait of Brutus and the coinage of Servius Rufus in general, therefore, can be dated only to 43. His colleagues are assigned on the
               basis of style. Sydenham dated M. Arrius Secondus and C. Numonius Vaala to that year,<ref target="#CH1-n73">
                  <hi rend="sup">73</hi>
               </ref> and undoubtedly C. <persName corresp="#nomisma_p_clodivs_m_f_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">Clodius</persName> is to be included as the fourth
                  moneyer.<ref target="#CH1-n74">
                  <hi rend="sup">74</hi>
               </ref> The coins celebrating the formation of the second Triumvirate were struck after the beginning of the following year, when there was
               sufficient time for the preparation of dies and flans. There is then no point to, and indeed no possibility of, predating <persName corresp="#nomisma_p_clodivs_m_f_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">Clodius</persName> to Varus and Mussidius, <pb n="38"/> and the three can be taken as
               members of one and the same college, striking in 42 B.C.<ref target="#CH1-n75">
                  <hi rend="sup">75</hi>
               </ref>
            </p>
            <p>Regulus, finally, can be dated no earlier than 42, while there is every reason, as stated above, not to separate him from the other three to be
               assigned to a later year. The problem rather is, when in 42 did he strike with relation to his colleagues. The lack of any die connection with
               the coins of <persName corresp="#nomisma_p_clodivs_m_f_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">Clodius</persName>, Mussidius, and Varus would indicate that those
               three all struck before or after Regulus. His best dies, as we have seen, were cut by the engraver who produced die O.I, the earliest portrait of
                  <persName corresp="#nomisma_octavian">Octavian</persName> of the stemma above. But there are indications that the same engraver cut additional
               dies for the moneyers. The portraits of <persName corresp="#nomisma_mark_antony">Antony</persName> and <persName corresp="#nomisma_octavian">Octavian</persName> on the denarii of Varus are very close to those under discussion.<ref target="#CH1-n76">
                  <hi rend="sup">76</hi>
               </ref> The head is larger, although the relief is no larger, nor is the detail as fine; but the dies were being cut for a series of silver, not
               for commemorative gold, and presumably a number were produced more quickly. The entire concept of the portraits is the same, the hair of the
               heads of <persName corresp="#nomisma_octavian">Octavian</persName>
               <pb n="39"/> at any rate is cut always in the same manner on both gold and silver, Antony's wrinkled brow and the eyes and ears of both are
               identical.</p>
            <p>Thus, that the engraver of Regulus' fine dies cut obverse O.I as well cannot date the issue of Regulus' gold. There is, however, a second
               indication of the possibility that Regulus' coins were the earliest of these series. It has been suggested that the moneyers of any given college
               were not equal in rank, but that one held the primacy.<ref target="#CH1-n77">
                  <hi rend="sup">77</hi>
               </ref> Thus the denarius of <persName corresp="#nomisma_l_flaminivs_chilo_iiii_vir_rrc">L. Flaminius</persName> Chilo with obverse legend
                  III.VIR.PRI.FL,<ref target="#CH1-n78">
                  <hi rend="sup">78</hi>
               </ref> that is, <hi rend="italic">quattuorvir primus flavit.<ref target="#CH1-n79">
                     <hi rend="sup">79</hi>
                  </ref>
               </hi> Grueber understood by <hi rend="italic">primus</hi> that Chilo "acted as the superintendent-in-chief of the issue for the year."<ref target="#CH1-n80">
                  <hi rend="sup">80</hi>
               </ref> But the word is to be taken as well in a temporal sense: Chilo, the superintendent to be sure, was the first of his college to strike
                  coin.<ref target="#CH1-n81">
                  <hi rend="sup">81</hi>
               </ref> Now of the moneyers of 42 Regulus alone lays claim to any office beyond that of <hi rend="italic">triumvir a.p.f</hi>.<ref target="#CH1-n82">
                  <hi rend="sup">82</hi>
               </ref> He struck in great number a series of denarii, bearing on the obverse the head of his father, <pb n="40"/> L. Livineius Regulus, praetor
               in an unknown year,<ref target="#CH1-n83">
                  <hi rend="sup">83</hi>
               </ref> and reading L.REGVLVS.PR, REGVLVS.PR, or anepigraphic. One of the reverse types paired with these obverses pictures a curule chair with a
               fascis at either side and bears the legend REGVLVS.F / PRAEF.VR.<ref target="#CH1-n84">
                  <hi rend="sup">84</hi>
               </ref> The relation of a praefect of the city to the coinage is not clear; we know there to have been men of that office earlier in change of the
               production of gold.<ref target="#CH1-n85">
                  <hi rend="sup">85</hi>
               </ref>
            </p>
            <p>The enlargement of the college of moneyers from three to four under <persName corresp="#nomisma_julius_caesar">Caesar</persName> was one part of
               a considerable reorganization of the state <ref target="#CH1-n86">
                  <hi rend="sup">86</hi>
               </ref> One may well wonder why the efficient conduct of an office is projected in increasing, rather than decreasing, the number of responsible
               officials. The answer probably is to be, in this case at any rate, that the fourth man was Caesar's man, a compliment to the <hi rend="italic">peculiares servi.</hi> Again the interest in the <hi rend="italic">aerarium</hi> noted previously, and the use of the praefect in the
               financial service of both <persName corresp="#nomisma_julius_caesar">Caesar</persName> and <persName corresp="#nomisma_augustus">Augustus</persName>, bear the point out. There was to be a sure understanding and a tight control of those offices which created, <pb n="41"/> as it were, one of the means of power. When <persName corresp="#nomisma_julius_caesar">Caesar</persName> was dead, the fourth moneyer
               continued to strike into the first years of the Triumvirate; but when <persName corresp="#nomisma_augustus">Augustus'</persName> control was
               unchallenged and no especial overseer necessary, the moneyers reappeared, in 20–19 B.C., as a board of three.<ref target="#CH1-n87">
                  <hi rend="sup">87</hi>
               </ref> The indication by Regulus, then, that he was PRAEF.VR may not be as innocent as Grueber's interpretation of it: that he was <hi rend="italic">praefectus urbi feriarum Latinarum causa,</hi> a relatively minor office.<ref target="#CH1-n88">
                  <hi rend="sup">88</hi>
               </ref> Regulus, I suggest, was praefect of the city whose duties included the control of the coinage. Not until a consul was absent from the city
               did a praefect come into his full administrative powers; <persName corresp="#nomisma_m_lepidvs_rrc">Lepidus</persName>, if not
                  <persName>Plancus</persName>, seems to have remained in the city for the course of the year 42 B.C.<ref target="#CH1-n89">
                  <hi rend="sup">89</hi>
               </ref> Until such an occasion arose, Regulus had another matter to attend: he became one of the moneyers.</p>
            <p>The legend PRAEF.VR occurs on only one part of Regulus' silver coinage. This, however, does not contradict the <pb n="42"/> argument, but rather
               strengthens it: as far as the striking of coin was concerned, Regulus was a moneyer. Even on the PRAEF.VR silver we do not meet, as we might have
               expected, an indication of a special issue.<ref target="#CH1-n90">
                  <hi rend="sup">90</hi>
               </ref> He probably issued first the PRAEF.VR denarii, signifying his position, and then the gold and silver which appear to be the output of an
               ordinary moneyer. It has been commonly assumed that the PRAEF.VR silver must be later than the rest, on the grounds that once the title had been
               assumed it would never have been put by.<ref target="#CH1-n91">
                  <hi rend="sup">91</hi>
               </ref> Thus arose Grueber's interpretation of the title as a temporary honor which supervened in the course of the year. Yet the PRAEF.VR coin
               is, aside from the legend, an ordinary issue, celebrating nothing save the fact that Regulus was PRAEF.VR. But if we conceive that Regulus was
               not a moneyer who happened to become praefect, but the reverse—a praefect assigned to the mint— the problem is settled at once. The PRAEF.VR
               denarii were in a sense commemorative, an announcement of the position held by Regulus. Once the point was made he continued to strike simply as
               one of four moneyers. Compare the case of Flaminius Chilo who proclaimed that he <hi rend="italic">primus flavit.</hi> Yet only one of his two
               series bears that inscription; had we only his portrait coins of <persName corresp="#nomisma_julius_caesar">Caesar</persName> we would never have
               known of the distinction.</p>
            <p>The relative position of Regulus and Mussidius has already been considered by Alföldi in an examination of the style of the portrait of <persName corresp="#nomisma_julius_caesar">Caesar.</persName>
               <ref target="#CH1-n92">
                  <hi rend="sup">92</hi>
               </ref> Here too Mussidius is seen <pb n="43"/> to be the later, for the portrait is both smaller and cruder than that of the coins of Regulus.
               But the <persName corresp="#nomisma_julius_caesar">Caesar</persName> portrait of Regulus is in turn smaller than that of Flaminius Chilo, who
               struck during the last half of 43 B.C. Thus Regulus serves as a link between the college of 43 B.C. and his colleagues of 42.</p>
            <p>Accepting Regulus as the fourth moneyer, one returns to Pink to consider why he divides the coinage of 42 B.C. into "regular" and "special"
                  issues.<ref target="#CH1-n93">
                  <hi rend="sup">93</hi>
               </ref> The denarius of Regulus with PRAEF.VR suffers the fate of being classified "special," without any reason having been admitted to justify
               the distinction. But more disturbing, three of our five series of gold are also "special": those of Regulus and <persName corresp="#nomisma_p_clodivs_m_f_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">Clodius</persName>, and the one Mussidius series with Mars reverse. Now the speciality of
               these issues is supposed to consist in the origin of the metal. The bullion was normally <hi rend="italic">aurum privatum,</hi> purchased on the
               open market. <hi rend="italic">Aurum publicum</hi> (i.e., from the <hi rend="italic">aerarium Saturni)</hi> was to be struck only in an
               emergency, when the metal was not otherwise available.<ref target="#CH1-n94">
                  <hi rend="sup">94</hi>
               </ref> But the suggestion that the moneyer himself supplied the metal used in the mint (<hi rend="italic">aurum privatum)</hi> is backed by no
               evidence, although it has been asserted before Pink.<ref target="#CH1-n95">
                  <hi rend="sup">95</hi>
               </ref> Similarly, the contrast between "public" and "private" bullion is not supported by any Roman source. Actually the only basis for the
               division between these five gold series is the title in the reverse legend, IIII.VIR.A.P.F. And the title remains just a title: these men are <hi rend="italic">quattuorviri</hi> (what else could they be as moneyers?) who strike public gold (what other gold could they strike?).<ref target="#CH1-n96">
                  <hi rend="sup">96</hi>
               </ref>
            </p>
            <pb n="44"/>
            <p>Alfoldi is undoubtedly correct in rejecting the whole concept.<ref target="#CH1-n97">
                  <hi rend="sup">97</hi>
               </ref> Every issue was special, insofar as it depended from a <hi rend="italic">senatus consultum</hi> or a vote of the people. All the moneyers
               bore the title whether or not they engraved it on their coins. It was, after all, just that much more to be cut on die after die. If Mussidius
               can honor the <hi rend="italic">triumviri</hi> with a complete series which bears the title, and contrive to produce a second series which always
               omits it; if Varus can refuse to use it while <persName corresp="#nomisma_p_clodivs_m_f_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">Clodius</persName> and Regulus
               include it; and if the series bearing the title <hi rend="italic">precede</hi> those omitting it: then we must reexamine the criteria for the
               division between "special" and "ordinary" issues.</p>
            <p>To conclude, the college of 42 B.C. can now be more clearly conceived. <persName corresp="#nomisma_p_clodivs_m_f_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">Clodius</persName>, Varus, and Mussidius are proved to have been colleagues. Regulus was undoubtedly the fourth, as one would conclude from
               the type of the gold, the style of the portrait engraving, and the brief historical considerations above presented. The order of the production
               of the gold series is again clear in the case of the three moneyers, while the investigation of Regulus' status in the college makes it probable
               that he was <hi rend="italic">primus.</hi> We cannot construct the order of production of all the series of gold and silver of 42 B.C.; that will
               never be possible. But the gold struck in honor of the second Triumvirate is now arranged: Regulus, <persName corresp="#nomisma_p_clodivs_m_f_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">Clodius</persName>, Mussidius/Mars, Varus, Mussidius/cornucopia.</p>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n58">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">58</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>A good deal of the hybrid coinage of the Empire was produced from dies which ought to have been cancelled but which were retained in working
                  condition at the mint.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n59">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">59</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>For the date of the second term of office see the discussion in Bahr- feldt, pp. 102–3, 106; and T. Rice Holmes, <hi rend="italic">Architect
                     of the Roman Empire,</hi> Oxford, 1928; I, pp. 231–245.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n60">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">60</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>E.g., Bahrfeldt no. 103: IMP.CAESAR.DIVI.F.III.VIR.ITER.R.P.C. The coins of <persName corresp="#nomisma_mark_antony">Antony</persName> do not
                  bear the iteration.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n61">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">61</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>Not "Venus"—Bahrfeldt, p. 53. Cf. the Apollo head on the gold of <persName corresp="#nomisma_p_clodivs_m_f_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">Clodius</persName>, Bahrfeldt no. 30.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n62">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">62</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>Only two other series are known which bear his portrait: the presumably Gallic gold (see above p. 12); and an issue of gold and silver
                  attributed to Africa (Grueber, II, nos. 29–31) or Gaul (Sydenham no. 1323), with the portrait of <persName corresp="#nomisma_m_lepidvs_rrc">Lepidus</persName> on one face, that of <persName corresp="#nomisma_octavian">Octavian</persName> on the other. The provenance of the
                  coins is uncertain but they must be provincial. (One might add the bronze coin of Ephesus, bearing on the obverse the portraits of all three
                     <hi rend="italic">triumviri,</hi> on the reverse an image of the Ephesian Diana.)</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n63">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">63</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>Again, the Gallic gold discussed above bears their portraits. Otherwise the two appear together, after the formation of the Triumvirate, on:
                  1. aurei struck in Gaul (Grueber, II, no. 59); 2. aurei and denarii struck in the East by Barbatius, Nerva, and Gellius (II, nos. 98–110); 3.
                  aurei and denarii similar to the last but signed by no official (II, nos. 120–7); the tressis in the bronze coinage called of "the fleet
                  praefects," Bibulus, Atratinus, and Capito, struck in Greece or the East (II, pp. 511 and 515, and no. 154) (<hi rend="italic">pace</hi>
                  Grant, <hi rend="italic">From Imperium to Auctoritas,</hi> Cambridge, 1946, pp. 43ff., who would attribute them to Tarentum). One might
                  include 5. aurei with obverse legend ANTONIVS.IMP, reverse legend CAESAR.IMP, dated to 39 by Grueber (II, no. 90) and Sydenham (no. 1327). The
                  legend opposes so late a date, and Bahrfeldt (p. 47) argues cogently for 43 on the basis of the composition of the <ref target="http://numismatics.org/chrr/id/BOR">Borzano hoard</ref>.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n64">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">64</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>P. 50.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n65">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">65</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>But see Alföldi reviewing Pink, p. 388, who would attribute the denarius of Marcellinus to Sicily rather than Rome.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n66">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">66</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>Accoleius: Grueber, I, nos. 4211–4; Capitolinus: 1, 4217–25; Marceilinus: I, 4206–8.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n67">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">67</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>See above, p. 6. An explanation has been attempted by Gabrici, "La Monetazione di Augusto," in <hi rend="italic">
                     <persName corresp="#nomisma_augustus">Augustus</persName>, Studi in Occasione del Bimillenario Augusteo,</hi> Rome, 1938, p. 392 n. 1. He
                  is forced to date the office of Mussidius, <persName corresp="#nomisma_p_clodivs_m_f_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">Clodius</persName>, and Regulus
                  originally in 44, continuing through 43, and protruding into 42 B.C. The fourth moneyer is at first Sepullius Macer, his place being filled in
                  about February of 43 by Varus. Only thus can he justify the striking of denarii picturing <persName corresp="#nomisma_julius_caesar">Caesar</persName>, gold and silver of Republican types, silver without the portrait of <persName corresp="#nomisma_m_lepidvs_rrc">Lepidus</persName>, and finally the gold under discussion here. The dangers involved in accepting this scheme are enormous; it suffices to
                  remark that the coins of eight moneyers now attributed to 43 B.C. by Alföldi (v. n. 74 <hi rend="italic">infra</hi>) will be dated later (they
                  cannot be dated earlier) only with great difficulty. Nor can we yet understand why denarii of <persName corresp="#nomisma_mark_antony">Antony</persName> and <persName corresp="#nomisma_octavian">Octavian</persName>, but not of <persName corresp="#nomisma_m_lepidvs_rrc">Lepidus</persName>, were struck <hi rend="italic">after</hi> the formation of the triumvirate. Both Bahrfeldt and Gabrici are confuted by
                  the obvious solution: that each moneyer struck the types which pleased him and which made the proper concessions to political reality.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n68">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">68</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>A suggestion which one meets strangely often: e.g., Mattingly in Sydenham, p. 223, the latest example. We know that consular elections were
                  held in 43 B.C., albeit late in the year and under some duress from <persName corresp="#nomisma_octavian">Octavian</persName> (Dio xlvi.45.3).
                  And Dio xlvii.18.3 certainly implies that not only the new consuls, but a whole new board of magistrates took office on the first of January,
                  42.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n69">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">69</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>Cf. Pink, pp. 61–2.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n70">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">70</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>So Grueber, I, no. 4205 and pp. 566–567.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n71">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">71</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>Sydenham no. 1082; Alföldi, "Porträtkunst," pp. 160–3. Cf. the portrait of Brutus on the aureus struck in the East, Bahrfeldt no. 65.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n72">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">72</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>For the latest examinations of the college of 44, see Alföldi, <hi rend="italic">Studien</hi>;<hi rend="italic"/> C. M. Kraay, "Caesar's <hi rend="italic">Quattuorviri</hi> of 44 B.C.: the Arrangement of their Issues," in <hi rend="italic">Numismatic Chronicle</hi> series 6 XIV
                  (1954) 18–31; and UlrichBansa, op. cit., pp. 52–60.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n73">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">73</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>Nos. 1083–7.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n74">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">74</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>So too Mattingly in Sydenham, p. 223. Both the composition of the college and its date had been conceived by Mommsen, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte,</hi> p. 652; Grueber had assigned one of the four to each of the years 43–40 B.C. Alföldi now suggests that two colleges
                  struck in 43, the second taking office in August and being composed of L. Flaminius Chilo, Ti. Sempronius Gracchus, Q. Voconius Vitulus, and
                     <persName corresp="#nomisma_petillivs_capitolinvs_rrc">Petillius</persName> Capitolinus (?) ("Porträtkunst," pp. 152–6).</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n75">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">75</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>This dating will render void the opinion which sees in the "Pantheus" of the <persName corresp="#nomisma_p_clodivs_m_f_iiii_vir_a_p_f_rrc">Clodius</persName>/<persName corresp="#nomisma_mark_antony">Antony</persName> aureus a reference to the victories in the East of 39 and
                  38. Certainly the other reverses of this series, the Felicitas of the coin of <persName corresp="#nomisma_m_lepidvs_rrc">Lepidus</persName>,
                  the Venus and Cupid of <persName corresp="#nomisma_octavian">Octavian</persName>, have no especial significance in the context of the
                  victories of either <hi rend="italic">triumvir.</hi> Alföldi's interpretation of the <persName corresp="#nomisma_mark_antony">Antony</persName> reverse as Aion makes the earlier explanation unnecessary. Similarly, Pais' ingenious but unsound explication of the
                  types of Mussidius depends from accepting a date no earlier than 41 for that moneyer, and thus is to be rejected ("I Nummi di L. Mussidius
                  Longus ed il loro Significato per la Storia del Triumvirato romano," in <hi rend="italic">Rendiconti della R. Accademia Nazionale dei
                     Lincei</hi> series 5 XXXIII [1924] 15–24). Finally, the hoard evidence must in some cases be reconsidered: e.g., the <ref target="http://numismatics.org/chrr/id/PQU">Pieve-Quinta hoard</ref>,
                  which is dated by Bahrfeldt to 42 ("Der Denar- schatz," p. 18), by Grueber to 38–7 (I, p. 560), and by Sydenham to 39 (p. lvii). The date
                  depends precisely from the determination of the year in which Varus struck.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n76">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">76</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">plate</hi> 9, nos. A and B respectively, to be compared with portraits A.IV, O.I, and O.IV.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n77">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">77</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>Pink, pp. 39–40, 61.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n78">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">78</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>Grueber, I, nos. 4198–200.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n79">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">79</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>Mommsen, <hi rend="italic">Geschichte,</hi> p. 652.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n80">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">80</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>I, p. 565.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n81">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">81</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>PRI.FL, then, is only a different way of expressing what III.VIR had meant on the coins earlier. All the moneyers were <hi rend="italic">triumviri,</hi> or later <hi rend="italic">quattuorviri,</hi> but only the head of the college had used the title on his coins. (Cf.
                  Alföldi, "Studien zur Zeitfolge der Münzprägung der römischen Republik," in <hi rend="italic">Schweizerische Numismatische Rundschau</hi>
                  XXXVI [1954] 28–30, and <hi rend="italic">Studien,</hi> p. 5 n. 1.) Similarly, L. Aemilius Buca is the one moneyer of 44 B.C. to entitle
                  himself IIII.VIR (Grueber, I, no. 4162); both the style and type (the dream of Sulla) of his earliest denarii prove them to have been the
                  earliest of the year. When the portrait of <persName corresp="#nomisma_julius_caesar">Caesar</persName> was taken up, a reorganization of the
                  mint apparently took place, for in these series Mettius struck first and alone. (Cf. Alföldi, <hi rend="italic">Studien,</hi> pp. 5–6,
                  84–6).</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n82">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">82</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>Pink, p. 39: "Our previous research has shown that it is only the leading moneyer who bears the title of office." But in our college all but
                  Varus strike gold with the inscription IIII.VIR.A.P.F, so that Regulus' priority would have to be indicated otherwise. The link between the
                  old and the new forms of identifying the <hi rend="italic">primus</hi> of the mint will be found in the second college of 43 B.C. Chilo's
                  IIII.VIR.PRI.FL is balanced by Ti. Sempronius Gracchus' IIII.VIR on his aurei and denarii (Grueber, I, nos. 4313–5; Bahrfeldt no. 102).</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n83">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">83</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>Broughton, II, p. 464.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n84">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">84</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>Grueber, I, nos. 4261–2.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n85">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">85</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>A considerable number of aurei are known which were struck by L.PLANC.PR (or PRAEF).VRB during the third dictatorship of <persName corresp="#nomisma_julius_caesar">Caesar</persName>, 46–45 B.C. (Bahrfeldt nos. 20–2). Whether or not the coins were produced at the mint of
                  Rome, or at some provisional establishment, the elected moneyers had nothing to do with overseeing them. Apparently the <hi rend="italic">praefectus urbi</hi> who coined served as the precedent for the creating of the office of <hi rend="italic">praefectus aerarii
                     Saturni</hi> by <persName corresp="#nomisma_augustus">Augustus</persName> in 28 as a substitute for the quaestors who had filled that post
                  (Dio LIII.2.1; Tacitus, Annals, XIII. 28–9).</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n86">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">86</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>Suetonius <hi rend="italic">Julius</hi> 41.1, 76.3. Cf. T. Rice Holmes, <hi rend="italic">The Roman Republic</hi>, Oxford, 1923; III, pp.
                  318-25; and W. E. Heitland, <hi rend="italic">The Roman Republic</hi>, Cambridge, 1923; III, pp. 340–7, 356–62.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n87">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">87</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>Franco Panvini-Rosati, "Le Emissioni in Oro e Argento dei <hi rend="italic">Tresviri monetales</hi> di Augusto," in <hi rend="italic">Archeologia Classica</hi> III (1951) 81; Pink, pp. 44–48.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n88">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">88</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>I, pp. 579-80. The one reverse type which might refer to the games pictures two men fighting three wild beasts (Grueber, I, nos. 4271–3), but
                  never bears the legend which would indicate that Regulus was <hi rend="italic">praefectus urbi</hi> in charge of the festivities. The coin
                  reads simply, L.REGVLVS. Alföldi is surely right in regarding Regulus as praefect for the grain supply ("Studien," pp. 23–4); cf. the denarius
                  with modius and ears of grain as reverse type (Grueber, I, nos. 4269–70). Here too the legend is simply L.LIVINEIVS / REGVLVS, so that the
                  denarius with curule chair and two fasces, and the legend REGVLVS.F / PRAEF.VR, must have been meant to be commemorative.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n89">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">89</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>CIL X 6087 states that <persName>Plancus</persName> was involved in a distribution of land around Beneventum. Broughton assumed the deed to
                  date to 42: "[Plancus] began to distribute land to soldiers at Beneventum [in 42 B.C.]" (p. 357). But the inscription is Augustan and the
                  distribution is not dated; it could as well have been 41. Pink suggests (pp. 40-1) that <persName corresp="#nomisma_m_lepidvs_rrc">Lepidus</persName> was appointed <hi rend="italic">praefectus urbi</hi> not as secondary to <persName>Plancus</persName> or <persName corresp="#nomisma_m_lepidvs_rrc">Lepidus</persName>, but against <persName corresp="#nomisma_octavian">Octavian</persName>'s departure from
                  Rome. But <persName corresp="#nomisma_octavian">Octavian</persName>
                  <hi rend="italic">was</hi> out of Rome in 42, and it is curious that the praefect is nowhere referred to in any manner whatever, outside the
                  mint.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n90">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">90</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>E.g., the AD.FRV.EMV.EX.S.C of the denarius of L. Calpurnius Piso and Q. Servilius Caepio (Grueber, I, nos. 1125–8). But Pink labels the
                  Regulus piece "special," without indicating his reason (p. 43).</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n91">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">91</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>E.g., Babelon, II, p. 142. It cannot be proved that the type is either earlier or later than the other denarii of Regulus. For that reverse is
                  paired with an obverse whose legend, L.REGVLVS / PR, is not found elsewhere.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n92">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">92</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>"Porträtkunst," p. 155 and pl. IV.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n93">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">93</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>P. 43.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n94">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">94</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>P. 56–8. See too Pink's "Special Coinages under the <hi rend="italic">Triumviri Mondtales,"</hi> in <hi rend="italic">Essays in Roman Coinage
                     Presented to Harold Mattingly,</hi> Oxford, 1956, pp. 59–62.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n95">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">95</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>E.g. <persName>H. Mattingly</persName>, <hi rend="italic">Roman Coins,</hi>
                  <placeName>London</placeName>, 1928, pp. 28–9.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n96">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">96</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>Although the title appears only on the gold, it may refer to the entire coinage, to be translated "… for the striking of public money"—<hi rend="italic">argento p.f.</hi>
               </p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n97">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">97</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>Review of Pink, pp. 389–91.</p>
            </note>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d52e3284" type="chapter">
            <pb n="45"/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="bold">DESCRIPTION OF OBVERSE DIES AND NOTES ON THEIR DETERIORATION</hi>
            </head>
            <p>L.I Large bust l. Point of nose between PI. R above back of head.</p>
            <table rows="2" cols="3">
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">No.</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Reverse die</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Breaks</hi>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>44.1</cell>
                  <cell>C.Al</cell>
                  <cell>1. Break from lower lip to base of E.</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>L.II Large bust l. Point of nose at I.</p>
            <table rows="2" cols="3">
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">No.</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Reverse die</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Breaks</hi>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>44.2</cell>
                  <cell>C.Al</cell>
                  <cell>1. Two breaks <hi rend="italic">inter alia minora:</hi> from upper bar of E outward through dotted border; from dotted border to tip of
                     r. staff of V to upper curve of S.</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>L.III Large bust l. Point of nose between PI. R at back of head. Verticals of I of LEPIDVS and P of R.P.C are not parallel.</p>
            <table rows="16" cols="3">
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">No.</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Reverse die</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Breaks</hi>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>50.1</cell>
                  <cell>M.Am</cell>
                  <cell>1. Break from tip of r. leg of M toward intersection of chin and throat.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>2. Break from lower forehead upward toward point of V.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>50.3</cell>
                  <cell>M.Cm</cell>
                  <cell>1. as above but more pronounced.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>2. as above but more pronounced.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>50.2</cell>
                  <cell>M.Bm</cell>
                  <cell>1. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>2. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <pb n="46"/>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>3. Break through dotted border between EP inward to middle arm of E.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>4. Break from point of curve of D to point of V.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>5. Break from tip of vertical of R of R.P.C inward diagonally to back of head.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>50.4</cell>
                  <cell>M.Bm</cell>
                  <cell>1. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>2. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>3. as above but now beyond middle bar of E.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>4. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>5. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>6. Break from center of r. staff of V horizontally through center of S.</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>L.IV Large bust l. Point of nose between PI. R at back of head. Verticals of6 I of LEPIDVS and P of R.P.C parallel.</p>
            <table rows="12" cols="3">
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">No.</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Reverse die</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Breaks</hi>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>38.1</cell>
                  <cell>V.A</cell>
                  <cell>1. Tongue-like break below the bust, rising to the r., is regular for all examples.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>2. Bulge in center of l. leg of M.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>41.7</cell>
                  <cell>M.Bc</cell>
                  <cell>1. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>2. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>3. Two breaks: from point of I of LEPIDVS, under D, to lower forehead; from lower curve of D toward but not touching upper
                     forehead.</cell>
               </row>
               <pb n="47"/>
               <row>
                  <cell>41.1</cell>
                  <cell>M.Bc</cell>
                  <cell>1. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>2. Bulge is now a thick break to the dotted edge.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>3. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>41.2</cell>
                  <cell>M.Bc</cell>
                  <cell>1. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>2. [Off flan]</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>3. as above.</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>L.V. Small bust l. Point of nose between EP.</p>
            <table rows="13" cols="3">
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">No.</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Reverse die</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Breaks</hi>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>41.5</cell>
                  <cell>M.Cc</cell>
                  <cell>1. A number of hairline breaks are common to all examples: staff of L to base of E; curve of P to top and to center of I; lower curve of
                     D through center of l. staff of V, to tip of r. staff of V; from lower back of head diagonally l. behind neck.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>41.3</cell>
                  <cell>M.Cc</cell>
                  <cell>1. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>2. Break from top l. leg of M to dotted border.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>41.6</cell>
                  <cell>M.Cc</cell>
                  <cell>1. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>2. as above but now including break from center point of M inward.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>3. Break from hair in front to lower curve of D.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>4. Break from tip of nose to tip of lowest bar of E.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>41.4</cell>
                  <cell>M.Ec</cell>
                  <cell>1. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>2. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>3. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>4. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>5. Break from lips toward base of L.</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <pb n="48"/>
            <p>L.VI Small bust r. Point of chin between PC.</p>
            <table rows="13" cols="3">
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">No.</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Reverse die</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Breaks</hi>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>47.9</cell>
                  <cell>R.Al</cell>
                  <cell>None</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>47.1</cell>
                  <cell>R.Al</cell>
                  <cell>1. Break from base of I of LEPIDVS to back of head.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>47.2</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>47.3</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>47.5</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>47.6</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>47.7</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>47.11</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>47.12</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>47.4</cell>
                  <cell>R.Al</cell>
                  <cell>1. as above but now a large triangular fault.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>47.10</cell>
                  <cell>R.Al</cell>
                  <cell>1. Break is gone, for the die has been reworked: e.g., where earlier the head had risen sharply from the field, now the outline merges
                     with the plane. So too the bridge of the nose has disappeared, which cannot be attributed to wear.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>2. Break inward from dot after VIR.</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>L.VII Small bust r. Point of chin at P. [Known only from this bronze.]</p>
            <table rows="2" cols="3">
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">No.</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Reverse die</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Breaks</hi>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>47 <hi rend="italic">bis</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>R.Al</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>A.I<ref target="#CH1-n98">
                  <hi rend="sup">98</hi>
               </ref> Large bust r. M.AN straight.</p>
            <table rows="2" cols="3">
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">No.</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Reverse die</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Breaks</hi>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>45.7</cell>
                  <cell>C.Aa</cell>
                  <cell>1. Area from center point of I of</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <pb n="49"/>
            <table rows="22" cols="3">
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">No.</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Reverse die</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Breaks</hi>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>ANTONIVS to the letter at either side and above to the dotted edge entirely corrupt.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>45.1</cell>
                  <cell>C.Ba</cell>
                  <cell>1. as above but now including the upper area of N.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>2. Break from midpoint of curve of C, past the curve of P, to dotted edge.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>45.2</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>45.3</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>45.4</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>45.5</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>45.8</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>51.3</cell>
                  <cell>M.Am</cell>
                  <cell>1. has now been repaired. Some traces remain, but the most important break is now 3.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>2. is also repaired and the edge recut.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>3. Considerable corruption between TO and ON, not extending 1. beyond the vertical of T.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>51.1</cell>
                  <cell>M.Am</cell>
                  <cell>3. as above but extending l. beyond the vertical of T.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>51.7</cell>
                  <cell>M.Bm</cell>
                  <cell>3. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>4. Break from top of A to dotted edge.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>51.4</cell>
                  <cell>M.Bm</cell>
                  <cell>3. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>51.9</cell>
                  <cell>M.Cm</cell>
                  <cell>4. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>5. Break from lower tip of C to bust.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>51.5</cell>
                  <cell>M.Bm</cell>
                  <cell>3. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>51.6</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>4. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>5. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>6. Break toward M from intersection of back of hair and neck.</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <pb n="50"/>
            <p>A.II Large bust r. First N of ANTONIVS wider above than below: the verticals are not parallel.</p>
            <table rows="14" cols="3">
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">No.</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Reverse die</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Breaks</hi>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>51.10</cell>
                  <cell>M.Bm</cell>
                  <cell>1. Corruption at r. base of first N of ANTONIVS regular for all examples.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>51. 11</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>39.2</cell>
                  <cell>V.B</cell>
                  <cell>1. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>2. Corruption begins on upper l. side of P, hairline break toward dotted edge.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>39.3</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>39.1</cell>
                  <cell>V.B</cell>
                  <cell>1. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>2. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>3. Dot on top of curve of R of R.P.C and break beginning toward edge.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>42.4</cell>
                  <cell>M.Ac</cell>
                  <cell>1. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>2. as above but break now extends through dotted edge, and involves the dot between R.P.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>3. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>42.7</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>42.9</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>A.III<ref target="#CH1-n99">
                  <hi rend="sup">99</hi>
               </ref> Large bust r. M.AN curved.</p>
            <table rows="6" cols="3">
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">No.</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Reverse die</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Breaks</hi>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>42.3</cell>
                  <cell>M.Bc</cell>
                  <cell>None</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>42.10</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>42.5</cell>
                  <cell>M.Dc</cell>
                  <cell>1. Two hairline breaks: horizontally between AN, diagonally between NT.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>42.1</cell>
                  <cell>M.Ec</cell>
                  <cell>1. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>42.11</cell>
                  <cell>M.Dc</cell>
                  <cell>2. Hairline break from top of R of R.P.C to dotted edge.</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <pb n="51"/>
            <table rows="3" cols="3">
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">No.</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Reverse die</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Breaks</hi>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>42.2</cell>
                  <cell>M.Bc</cell>
                  <cell>1. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>42.6</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>2. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>3. Corruption at upper l. of O almost touching r. tip of bar of T.</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>A.IV Fine bust r.</p>
            <table rows="10" cols="3">
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">No.</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Reverse die</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Breaks</hi>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>48.7</cell>
                  <cell>R.Ba</cell>
                  <cell>1. Dot at back of head between TO.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>48.14</cell>
                  <cell>R.Aa</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>48.3</cell>
                  <cell>R.Ba</cell>
                  <cell>1. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>2. Small cut under nose.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>48.1</cell>
                  <cell>R.Ba</cell>
                  <cell>1. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>48.2</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>2. as above but larger.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>48.4</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>48.6</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>48.9</cell>
                  <cell>R.Ca</cell>
                  <cell>1. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>2. as above but cut connected by break to tip of nose.</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>A.V Small bust r. Point of nose between R of VIR and R of R.P.C.</p>
            <table rows="2" cols="3">
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">No.</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Reverse die</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Breaks</hi>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>48.12</cell>
                  <cell>R.Ca</cell>
                  <cell>1. Break from back of head, above lower limit of hair.</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>A.VI Gross bust r.</p>
            <table rows="6" cols="3">
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">No.</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Reverse die</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Breaks</hi>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>48.8</cell>
                  <cell>R.Ca</cell>
                  <cell>1. Two breaks: diagonally upward from lower tip of I of ANTONIVS through V to top of S and beyond toward dotted edge; from l. end of bar
                     of T upward to dotted edge.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>48.11</cell>
                  <cell>R.Ca</cell>
                  <cell>1. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <pb n="52"/>
               <row>
                  <cell>48.13</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>2. Break to M from intersection of back of neck and hair.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>–––48.5<ref target="#CH1-n100">
                        <hi rend="sup">100</hi>
                     </ref>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>R.Ca</cell>
                  <cell>1. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>2. [This area obscured by the Este counterstamp.]</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>A.VII Small bust r. Point of nose at R of VIR.</p>
            <table rows="2" cols="3">
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">No.</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Reverse die</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Breaks</hi>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>48.10</cell>
                  <cell>R.Da</cell>
                  <cell>1. Break from dotted edge to l. side of A.</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>O.I Large bust r. CAES curved.</p>
            <table rows="11" cols="3">
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">No.</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Reverse die</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Breaks</hi>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>46.1</cell>
                  <cell>C.Ao</cell>
                  <cell>1. Break from dotted edge outward above first C.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>46.2</cell>
                  <cell>C.Bo</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>43.3</cell>
                  <cell>M.Cc</cell>
                  <cell>1. as above but now extending into letter C.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>2. Break from dotted edge outward above staff of E.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>3. Two breaks from back of hair, from hair line and just above hair line.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>43.8</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>43.2</cell>
                  <cell>M.Cc</cell>
                  <cell>1. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>2. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>3. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>4. Break from back of head to r. leg of first A.</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>O.II<ref target="#CH1-n101">
                  <hi rend="sup">101</hi>
               </ref> Large bust r. CAES straight.</p>
            <table rows="3" cols="3">
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">No.</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Reverse die</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Breaks</hi>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>52.1</cell>
                  <cell>M.Am</cell>
                  <cell>None</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>52.3</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
            </table>
            <pb n="53"/>
            <table rows="15" cols="3">
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">No.</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Reverse die</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Breaks</hi>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>52.11</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>40.1</cell>
                  <cell>V.A</cell>
                  <cell>1. Short break toward edge from each of the two dots separating R.P.C.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>40.2</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>40.3</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>40.4</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>43.1</cell>
                  <cell>M.Ac</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>43.5</cell>
                  <cell>M.Bc</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>43.6</cell>
                  <cell>M.Ac</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>43.7</cell>
                  <cell>M.Bc</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>43.9</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>43.10</cell>
                  <cell>M.Ac</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>52.5</cell>
                  <cell>M.Bm</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>52.6</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>52.7</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>52.10</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>O.III Finebustr. Largeletters. Point of noseat E, of chin at A.</p>
            <table rows="6" cols="3">
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">No.</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Reverse die</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Breaks</hi>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>49.2</cell>
                  <cell>R.Bo</cell>
                  <cell>1. Considerable corruption over VIR. Top of break from I to R slopes down to r.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>49.4</cell>
                  <cell>R.Bo</cell>
                  <cell>1. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>2. Break from bottom r. tip of bust to dotted edge.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>49.1</cell>
                  <cell>R.Bo</cell>
                  <cell>1. as above but top of break from I to R now almost horizontal.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>2. as above.</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>O.IV Fine bust r. Small letters. Point of nose between ES, of chin at R.</p>
            <table rows="6" cols="3">
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">No.</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Reverse die</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Breaks</hi>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>49.3</cell>
                  <cell>R.Ao</cell>
                  <cell>1. Break from upper tip of C of R.P.C toward top of head.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>49.5</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>49.6</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>49.7</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>49.8</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
            </table>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n98">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">98</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>No. 45.9 has been omitted. For these purposes it is illegible.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n99">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">99</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>No. 42.12 has been omitted as illegible for these purposes.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n100">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">100</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>The dash indicates that the coin cannot be placed exactly in the sequence.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n101">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">101</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>It has not been possible to determine from the reproductions the condition of the die on nos. 52.2, .4, .12, and .13.</p>
            </note>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d52e4488" type="chapter">
            <pb n="54"/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="bold">DESCRIPTION OF REVERSE DIES AND NOTES ON THEIR DETERIORATION</hi>
            </head>
            <p>V.A Upper thumb under I.</p>
            <table rows="6" cols="3">
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">No.</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Reverse die</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Breaks</hi>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>38.1</cell>
                  <cell>L.IV</cell>
                  <cell>1. Two breaks: outward and upward diagonally from dotted edge to l. of first V of VAA- RVS; bulge inward from dot next above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>40.1</cell>
                  <cell>O.II</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>40.2</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>–––40.3</cell>
                  <cell>O.II</cell>
                  <cell>1. [Off flan]</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>40.4</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>V.B Upper thumb under B.</p>
            <table rows="4" cols="3">
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">No.</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Obverse die</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Breaks</hi>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>39.1</cell>
                  <cell>A.II</cell>
                  <cell>None</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>39.2</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>39.3</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>M.Ac Graceful cornucopia, tip l. IVS far from type.</p>
            <table rows="8" cols="3">
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">No.</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Obverse die</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Breaks</hi>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>43.1</cell>
                  <cell>O.II</cell>
                  <cell>1. All examples share: break from lower end of staff of first L; break connecting tops of second S and I; break connecting upper tip of
                     S of LONGVS with stem of grape-cluster.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>43.6</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>43.10</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>42.4</cell>
                  <cell>A.II</cell>
                  <cell>1. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>42.7</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>2. Two breaks; between l. fillet</cell>
               </row>
               <pb n="55"/>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>and cornucopia one mm. below their juncture; from dotted edge inward between second VS of MVSSIDIVS.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>42.9</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>M.Bc<ref target="#CH1-n102">
                  <hi rend="sup">102</hi>
               </ref> Graceful cornucopia, tip l. IVS almost touches type.</p>
            <table rows="12" cols="3">
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">No.</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Obverse die</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Breaks</hi>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>42.10</cell>
                  <cell>A.III</cell>
                  <cell>None</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>42.2</cell>
                  <cell>A.III</cell>
                  <cell>1. Tiny horizontal break connects midpoint of r. leg of V and l. curve of S of LONGVS.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>43.7</cell>
                  <cell>O.II</cell>
                  <cell>1. as above but break passes through S.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>2. Hairline break connects upper and lower portions of l. fillet, in field between fillet and cornucopia.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>43.9</cell>
                  <cell>O.II</cell>
                  <cell>1. as above but break passes into lower center of V.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>2. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>3. Break begins inward from dotted edge toward S of LONGVS, one mm. above and paralleling break 1.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>43.5</cell>
                  <cell>O.II</cell>
                  <cell>1. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>2. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>3. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>4. Break connects lower r. leg of V and lower r. curve of S, below and parallel to 1.</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <pb n="56"/>
            <table rows="7" cols="3">
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">No.</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Reverse die</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Breaks</hi>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>41.1</cell>
                  <cell>L.IV</cell>
                  <cell>1. as above but break reaches edge.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>41.7</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>42.3</cell>
                  <cell>A.III</cell>
                  <cell>2. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>3. as above but break reaches tip of S.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>4. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>42.6</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>M.Cc Gross cornucopia, tip r. Edge of cornucopia falls below IVS of MVSSIDIVS and S of LONGVS.</p>
            <table rows="10" cols="3">
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">No.</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Reverse die</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Breaks</hi>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>41.3</cell>
                  <cell>L.V</cell>
                  <cell>1. Two breaks: from base of second I to edge of cornucopia; from round fruit at r. top of cornucopia diagonally r. to dotted
                     edge.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>41.5</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>43.3</cell>
                  <cell>O.I</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>43.8</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>41.6</cell>
                  <cell>L.V</cell>
                  <cell>1. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>2. Break connects ends of three leaves protruding from end of cornucopia.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>43.2</cell>
                  <cell>O.I</cell>
                  <cell>1. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>2. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>3. Break connects upper tip of S of LONGVS to round fruit at r. top of cornucopia.</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>M.Dc Gross cornucopia, tip r. Edge of cornucopia falls below S of MVSSIDIVS and above S of LONGVS.</p>
            <table rows="3" cols="3">
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">No.</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Obverse die</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Breaks</hi>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>42.5</cell>
                  <cell>A.III</cell>
                  <cell>None</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>42.11</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
            </table>
            <pb n="57"/>
            <p>M.Ec Gross cornucopia, tip r. Edge of cornucopia falls below IVS of MVSSIDIVS and above S of LONGVS.</p>
            <table rows="3" cols="3">
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">No.</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Obverse die</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Breaks</hi>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>41.4</cell>
                  <cell>L.V</cell>
                  <cell>None</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>42.1</cell>
                  <cell>A.III</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>C.Al [Unique.]</p>
            <table rows="4" cols="3">
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">No.</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Obverse die</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Breaks</hi>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>44.1</cell>
                  <cell>L.I</cell>
                  <cell>1. Break from r. side of cornucopia under hand toward fourth I of IIII.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>44.2</cell>
                  <cell>L.II</cell>
                  <cell>1. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>2. Break inward from dot between S.M.</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>C.Aa Caduceus points to P. Bow protrudes between IIII and VIR.</p>
            <table rows="3" cols="3">
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">No.</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Reverse die</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Breaks</hi>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>45.7</cell>
                  <cell>A.I</cell>
                  <cell>1. Two breaks: from face of shield through upper part of P, past lower curve of C, to dotted edge; from lower tip of r. leg of M to
                     dotted edge.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>45.9</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>C.Ba Caduceus points between R.A.</p>
            <table rows="7" cols="3">
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">No.</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Reverse die</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Breaks</hi>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>45.1</cell>
                  <cell>A.I</cell>
                  <cell>1. A number of breaks are common to all examples: from lower curve of S to dotted edge; from lower tip of first F to dotted edge; from
                     each leg of R to dotted edge; between arms of final F.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>45.2</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>45.3</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>45.4</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>45.5</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>45.8</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
            </table>
            <pb n="58"/>
            <p>C.Ao Large group.</p>
            <table rows="2" cols="3">
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">No.</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Obverse die</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Breaks</hi>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>46.1</cell>
                  <cell>O.I</cell>
                  <cell>None</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>C.Bo Small group.</p>
            <table rows="2" cols="3">
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">No.</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Obverse die</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Breaks</hi>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>46.2</cell>
                  <cell>O.I</cell>
                  <cell>1. Break from top of O diagonally to dotted edge.</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>R.Al<ref target="#CH1-n103">
                  <hi rend="sup">103</hi>
               </ref> [Unique.]</p>
            <table rows="15" cols="3">
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">No.</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Reverse die</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Breaks</hi>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>47.9</cell>
                  <cell>L.VI</cell>
                  <cell>1. Three breaks: lower end of staff continues to dotted edge; downward from end of drapery on r.; two bulges beyond the dots above
                     L.R.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>47.11</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>47.5</cell>
                  <cell>L.VI</cell>
                  <cell>1. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>47.6</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>2. Break from upper tip of r. leg of second V toward dotted edge.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>47.7</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>47.12</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>47.1</cell>
                  <cell>L.VI</cell>
                  <cell>1. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>47.2</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>2. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>47.3</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>3. Break diagonally from body at waist to fold of drapery at r.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>47.4</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>47.10</cell>
                  <cell>L.VI</cell>
                  <cell>1. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>2. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>3. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>4. Break from corner of first L to staff.</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <pb n="59"/>
            <p>R.Aa Legend begins r. above. Elbow opposite A. IIII. VIR.A.P.F. straight.</p>
            <table rows="2" cols="3">
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">No.</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Obverse die</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Breaks</hi>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>48.14</cell>
                  <cell>A. IV</cell>
                  <cell>1. Breaks through ankle of l. leg, and from bottom of rock to dotted edge.</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>R.Ba<ref target="#CH1-n104">
                  <hi rend="sup">104</hi>
               </ref> Legend begins l. under.</p>
            <table rows="6" cols="3">
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">No.</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Reverse die</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Breaks</hi>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>48.3</cell>
                  <cell>A.IV</cell>
                  <cell>1. Two breaks: from midpoint of staff of L upward toward dotted edge; from dotted edge above R of REGVLVS outward.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>48.4</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>48.6</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>48.7</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>–––48.1</cell>
                  <cell>A.IV</cell>
                  <cell>1. [Off flan]</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>R.Ca Legend begins r. above. Elbow opposite F.</p>
            <table rows="7" cols="3">
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">No.</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Reverse die</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Breaks</hi>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>48.5</cell>
                  <cell>A.VI</cell>
                  <cell>1. Break from r. armpit to intersection of staff and drapery.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>48.9</cell>
                  <cell>A.IV</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>48.12</cell>
                  <cell>A.V</cell>
                  <cell>2. Break from midpoint of staff of F diagonally upward toward curve of P.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>48.8</cell>
                  <cell>A.VI</cell>
                  <cell>1. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>48.11</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>2. as above but touches curve of P.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>48.13</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>R.Da Legend begins r. above. Elbow opposite A. IIII. VIR.A.P.F curved.</p>
            <table rows="2" cols="3">
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">No.</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Obverse die</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Breaks</hi>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>48.10<ref target="#CH1-n105">
                        <hi rend="sup">105</hi>
                     </ref>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>A.VII</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
            </table>
            <pb n="60"/>
            <p>R.Ao Legend begins r. above.</p>
            <table rows="9" cols="3">
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">No.</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Obverse die</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Breaks</hi>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>49.7</cell>
                  <cell>O.IV</cell>
                  <cell>None</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>49.3</cell>
                  <cell>O.IV</cell>
                  <cell>1. Two breaks: from face of Anchises toward middle bar of F; from middle bar of F through upper bar to dotted edge.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>49.5</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>49.6</cell>
                  <cell>O.IV</cell>
                  <cell>1. as above but two breaks have joined.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>2. Break from midpoint of base of first L diagonally inward toward knee of <persName>Anchises.</persName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>49.8</cell>
                  <cell>O.IV</cell>
                  <cell>1. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>2. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>3. Break from lower point of G diagonally inward toward knee of Anchises.</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>R.Bo Legend begins l. above.</p>
            <table rows="8" cols="3">
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">No.</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Obverse die</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Breaks</hi>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>49.2</cell>
                  <cell>O.III</cell>
                  <cell>1. Massive fault from ground line obscures lower l. leg of Aeneas and rises to waist.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>2. Break from dotted edge inward at second I of IIII.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>49.4</cell>
                  <cell>O.III</cell>
                  <cell>1. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>2. as above but extends toward fourth I.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>49.1</cell>
                  <cell>O.III</cell>
                  <cell>1. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>2. as above but touches fourth I.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>3. Break from upper tip of A through dot to midpoint of P.</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <pb n="61"/>
            <p>M.Am<ref target="#CH1-n106">
                  <hi rend="sup">106</hi>
               </ref> Legend begins l. under.</p>
            <table rows="13" cols="3">
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">No.</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Reverse die</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Breaks</hi>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>52.1</cell>
                  <cell>O.II</cell>
                  <cell>1. Four breaks: from top of staff of first F through dotted edge; from lower tip of l. leg of MV ligature to l. end of ground line; from
                     upper r. tip of MV ligature to upper curve of S; from upper l. tip of N to dotted edge.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>51.3</cell>
                  <cell>A.I</cell>
                  <cell>1. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>52.3</cell>
                  <cell>O.II</cell>
                  <cell>2. Break from top of staff of P to dotted edge.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>52.11</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>–––52</cell>
                  <cell>O.II</cell>
                  <cell>1. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>2. [Off flan]</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>51.1</cell>
                  <cell>A.I</cell>
                  <cell>1. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>2. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>3. Break from dotted edge to upper l. tip of second V of MVSSIDIVS.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>50.1</cell>
                  <cell>L.III</cell>
                  <cell>1. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>2. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>3. as above but break continues to midpoint of I.</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>M.Bm Legend begins r. above. Spear points to first I of IIII.</p>
            <table rows="3" cols="3">
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">No.</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Reverse die</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Breaks</hi>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>50.2</cell>
                  <cell>L.III</cell>
                  <cell>1. Break from upper l. tip of N to dotted edge regular for all</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>50.4</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
            </table>
            <pb n="62"/>
            <table rows="15" cols="3">
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">No.</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Reverse die</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Breaks</hi>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>51.7</cell>
                  <cell>A.I</cell>
                  <cell>examples, when not off flan.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>2. Break from l. end of shield to lower r. leg of Mars, ending in bulge on l. side of leg.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>51.4</cell>
                  <cell>A.I</cell>
                  <cell>1. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>51.5</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>2. as above but break continues l. to spear.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>51.6</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>51.10</cell>
                  <cell>A.II</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>51.11</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>52.4</cell>
                  <cell>O.II</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>52.5</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>52.7</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>52.12</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>52.6</cell>
                  <cell>O.II</cell>
                  <cell>1. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>52.10</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>2. as above.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>3. Break from midpoint of base of second L inward toward l. leg of Mars.</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>M.Cm Legend begins r. above. Spear points to S of LONGVS.</p>
            <table rows="3" cols="3">
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">No.</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Reverse die</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Breaks</hi>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>50.3</cell>
                  <cell>L.III</cell>
                  <cell>1. Three breaks: from tip of V of LONGVS inward to ground line; from top of P to dotted edge; from tip of upper arm of final F to dotted
                     edge.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>51.9</cell>
                  <cell>A.I</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
            </table>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n102">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">102</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>The reproductions of nos. 41.2 and .12 to which I have referred are not sufficiently clear to justify their inclusion in this table.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n103">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">103</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>No. 47<hi rend="italic">bis</hi> has been omitted from consideration. See the note at that number in the Catalogue.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n104">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">104</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>No. 48.2 has been omitted, for its reproduction is illegible to me.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n105">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">105</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>The catalogue reproductions of this piece are not clear enough to permit an estimate of the damage done the die in striking.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n106">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">106</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>The reproduction of 52.13 is not sufficiently good to permit its classification.</p>
            </note>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d52e5639" type="chapter">
            <pb n="63"/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="bold">CATALOGUE<ref target="#CH1-n107">
                     <hi rend="sup">107</hi>
                  </ref>
               </hi>
            </head>
            <table rows="15" cols="5">
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">No.</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Obverse portrait</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Obv. die</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev. die</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Collection</hi>
                     <ref target="#CH1-n108">
                        <hi rend="sup">108</hi>
                     </ref>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell cols="5">
                     <hi rend="italic">C. VIBIVS VARVS</hi>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>38.1</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <persName corresp="#nomisma_m_lepidvs_rrc">Lepidus</persName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>L.IV</cell>
                  <cell>V.A</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Paris</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>39.1</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <persName corresp="#nomisma_mark_antony">Antony</persName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>A.II</cell>
                  <cell>V.B</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Paris</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.2</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>A.II</cell>
                  <cell>V.B</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Berlin</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.3</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>A.II</cell>
                  <cell>V.B</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>London</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>40.1</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <persName corresp="#nomisma_octavian">Octavian</persName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>O.II</cell>
                  <cell>V.A</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Paris</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.2</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>O.II</cell>
                  <cell>V.A</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>London</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.3</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>O.II</cell>
                  <cell>V.A</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Vatican</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.4</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>O.II</cell>
                  <cell>V.A</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Rome, Museo naz.</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell cols="5">
                     <hi rend="italic">L. MVSSIDIVS LONGVS</hi> / cornucopia</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>41.1</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <persName corresp="#nomisma_m_lepidvs_rrc">Lepidus</persName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>L.IV</cell>
                  <cell>M.Bc</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Paris</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.2</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>L.IV</cell>
                  <cell>M.Bc</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Berlin</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.3</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>L.V</cell>
                  <cell>M.Cc</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Vienna</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.4</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>L.V</cell>
                  <cell>M.Ec</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Vatican</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.5</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>L.V</cell>
                  <cell>M.Cc</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>London</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <pb n="64"/>
            <table rows="3" cols="5">
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">No.</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Obverse portrait</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Obv. die</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev. die</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Collection</hi>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.6</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>L.V</cell>
                  <cell>M.Cc</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>[.7<ref target="#CH1-n109">
                        <hi rend="sup">109</hi>
                     </ref>
                  </cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>L.IV</cell>
                  <cell>M.Bc</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>New York</placeName>
                     <ref target="#CH1-n110">
                        <hi rend="sup">110</hi>
                     </ref>
                  </cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>6. Ex Jameson coll.</p>
            <table rows="12" cols="5">
               <row>
                  <cell>42.1</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <persName corresp="#nomisma_mark_antony">Antony</persName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>A.III</cell>
                  <cell>M.Ec</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>London</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.2</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>A.III</cell>
                  <cell>M.Bc</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Paris</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.3</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>A.III</cell>
                  <cell>M.Bc</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.4</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>A.II</cell>
                  <cell>M.Ac</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.5</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>A.III</cell>
                  <cell>M.Dc</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.6</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>A.III</cell>
                  <cell>M.Bc</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Vienna</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.7</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>A.II</cell>
                  <cell>M.Ac</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.8</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Berlin</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.9</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>A.II</cell>
                  <cell>M.Ac</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Rome, Museo naz.</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.10</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>A.III</cell>
                  <cell>M.Bc</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Budapest</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>[.11</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>A.III</cell>
                  <cell>M.Dc</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>New York</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>[.12</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>A.III</cell>
                  <cell>M.Bc</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>3. Ex Jameson coll. 4. R. Ratto sale, Lucerne, Jan. 23, 1924, no. 1364.</p>
            <p>5. Formerly in <placeName>Paris</placeName>, exchanged as a duplicate. Its present habitat is not known to me. 7. Ars Classica sale XVIII,
               Lucerne, Oct. 10, 1938, no. 31. 12. M. Ratto sale, Milan, Jan. 19, 1956, no. 12.</p>
            <table rows="7" cols="5">
               <row>
                  <cell>43.1</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <persName corresp="#nomisma_octavian">Octavian</persName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>O.II</cell>
                  <cell>M.Ac</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.2</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>O.I</cell>
                  <cell>M.Cc</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Vienna</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.3</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>O.I</cell>
                  <cell>M.Cc</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Paris</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.4</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>O.II</cell>
                  <cell>M.Bc</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.5</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>O.II</cell>
                  <cell>M.Bc</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Vienna</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.6</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>O.II</cell>
                  <cell>M.Ac</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Vatican</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.7</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>O.II</cell>
                  <cell>M.Bc</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
            </table>
            <pb n="65"/>
            <table rows="4" cols="5">
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">No.</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Obverse portrait</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Obv. die</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev. die</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Collection</hi>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.8</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>O.I</cell>
                  <cell>M.Cc</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Rome, Museo naz.</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.9</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>O.II</cell>
                  <cell>M.Bc</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>London</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>[.10</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>O.II</cell>
                  <cell>M.Ac</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Rome, Museo naz.</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>1. Ex Prowe coll. 4. Formerly in <placeName>Paris</placeName>, exchanged as a duplicate. I have not seen a reproduction of this piece; the
               obverse and reverse dies are inferred from Bahrfeldt's notes on "Stempelgleichungen," p. 57. 7. R. Ratto sale, Lucerne, Jan. 23, 1924, no. 1448 =
               Leo Hamburger Auktions-Katalog No. 96, Frankfurt a. M., Oct. 25, 1932, no. 770. 10. Ex Gnecchi coll.</p>
            <table rows="3" cols="5">
               <row>
                  <cell cols="5">
                     <hi rend="italic">P. CLODIVS</hi>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>44.1</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <persName corresp="#nomisma_m_lepidvs_rrc">Lepidus</persName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>L.I</cell>
                  <cell>C.Al</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Berlin</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>[.2</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>L.II</cell>
                  <cell>C.Al</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>2. Bahrfeldt knew only the Cajazzo specimen, long thought to be unique. This second copy, struck from a different pairing of dies, has now come
               to light. A cast of it, bearing no mark of identification, is to be seen in the British Museum; in <placeName>Berlin</placeName> the collection
               of the Staatliche Museum possesses a wax impression of the coin with a note reading (apparently) "Nervegna", as <persName>Dr. Erxleben</persName>
               writes me, although the coin did not appear in the Martinetti-Nervegna sale (Sambon-Canessa), <placeName>Rome-Paris</placeName>, Nov. 18, 1907.I
               have been able to discover neither its origin nor its present location.</p>
            <table rows="9" cols="5">
               <row>
                  <cell>45.1</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <persName corresp="#nomisma_mark_antony">Antony</persName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>A.I</cell>
                  <cell>C.Ba</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Vatican</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.2</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>A.I</cell>
                  <cell>C.Ba</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Berlin</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.3</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>A.I</cell>
                  <cell>C.Ba</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Vienna</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.4</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>A.I</cell>
                  <cell>C.Ba</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Paris</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.5</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>A.I</cell>
                  <cell>C.Ba</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Hague</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.6</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.7</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>A.I</cell>
                  <cell>C.Aa</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>London</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.8</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>A.I</cell>
                  <cell>C.Ba</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Rome, Museo naz.</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>[.9</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>A.I</cell>
                  <cell>C.Aa</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>6. Formerly in <placeName>Paris</placeName>, exchanged as a duplicate. Its present whereabouts are not known to me. 9. <hi rend="italic">Catalogo
                  di Antiche Medaglie Consolari e di Famiglie Romane</hi>, <hi rend="italic">racolte da Gennaro Riccio</hi>, <placeName>Naples</placeName>,
               1855; pl. I, 4.</p>
            <table rows="2" cols="5">
               <row>
                  <cell>46.1</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <persName corresp="#nomisma_octavian">Octavian</persName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>O.I</cell>
                  <cell>C.Ao</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>London</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.2</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>O.I</cell>
                  <cell>C.Bo</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Vienna</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <pb n="66"/>
            <table rows="14" cols="5">
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">No.</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Obverse portrait</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Obv. die</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev. die</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Collection</hi>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell cols="5">
                     <hi rend="italic">L. LIVINEIVS REGVLVS</hi>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>47.1</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <persName corresp="#nomisma_m_lepidvs_rrc">Lepidus</persName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>L.VI</cell>
                  <cell>R.Al</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Paris</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.2</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>L.VI</cell>
                  <cell>R.Al</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Rome, Museo naz.</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.3</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>L.VI</cell>
                  <cell>R.Al</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Vienna</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.4</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>L.VI</cell>
                  <cell>R.Al</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.5</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>L.VI</cell>
                  <cell>R.Al</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.6</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>L.VI</cell>
                  <cell>R.Al</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>London</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.7</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>L.VI</cell>
                  <cell>R.Al</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Glasgow</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.8</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>L.VI</cell>
                  <cell>R.Al</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Berlin</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.9</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>L.VI</cell>
                  <cell>R.Al</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Vatican</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.10</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>L.VI</cell>
                  <cell>R.Al</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Hague</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>[.11</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>L.VI</cell>
                  <cell>R.Al</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>[.12</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>L.VI</cell>
                  <cell>R.Al</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>4. Ars Classica sale XVIII, Lucerne, Oct. 10, 1938, no. 28 = Glendining sale (V. J. E. Ryan coll.), <placeName>London</placeName>, Feb. 20,1951,
               no. 1581. 5. Ex Prowe coll. 8. The dies are inferred from Bahrfeldt's note, p. 59: "Sämtliche Stücke sind stempelgleich." 11. This piece is known
               to me only as an anonymous sulphur cast in the <placeName>British</placeName> Museum. It may represent the <placeName>Berlin</placeName> example.
               12. The cast of the plates has been taken from an electrotype in the <placeName>British</placeName> Museum, again of unknown provenience.</p>
            <table rows="1" cols="5">
               <row>
                  <cell>[47<hi rend="italic">bis</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <persName corresp="#nomisma_m_lepidvs_rrc">Lepidus</persName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>L.VII</cell>
                  <cell>R.Al</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Sydney</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>This strange bronze, now in the Nicholson Museum in <placeName>Sydney</placeName>, was included in the Glendining sale (Henry Platt Hall coll.),
                  <placeName>London</placeName>, July 19, 1950, no.663, and is said to have been earlier in the Museo Kircheriano in <placeName corresp="#nomisma_rome">Rome.</placeName> The coin is altogether unique; it may represent a trial strike of the gold dies. The piece is rather
               worn, and the illustration of the sales catalogue unsatisfactory; I have been unable to obtain a cast of it. But not only is the coin difficult
               to examine through its reproduction, it gives every indication of having been retooled. Thus, on the obverse, the hair of the portrait is too
               deeply cut in back. The reverse die appears to be R.Al: the position of the figure and the legend is the same. But the letters L.RE are not cut
               in the same manner as on the other examples from that die: note especially the wide loop of the R on the bronze, and the dependence of the right
               leg from the loop, not from the vertical of the letter. Similarly, the dots of the border are too widely spaced, as indeed they are too neat and
               clear for a coin wasted by wear and, apparently, corrosion. I am not alto- <pb n="67"/> gether convinced that the piece is a <hi rend="italic">bona fide</hi> product of the mint, or that, if <hi rend="italic">bona fide</hi>, its present appearance represents the piece as it was
               issued. In any case the illustration available to me is inadequate, and its consideration has been almost entirely avoided in this monograph.</p>
            <table rows="15" cols="5">
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">No.</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Obverse portrait</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Obv. die</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev. die</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Collection</hi>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>48.1</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <persName corresp="#nomisma_mark_antony">Antony</persName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>A.IV</cell>
                  <cell>R.Ba</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Vienna</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.2</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>A.IV</cell>
                  <cell>R.Ba</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.3</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>A.IV</cell>
                  <cell>R.Ba</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Naples</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.4</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>A.IV</cell>
                  <cell>R.Ba</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Vatican</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.5</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>A.VI</cell>
                  <cell>R.Ca</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <orgName>Rome, Museo Cap.</orgName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.6</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>A.IV</cell>
                  <cell>R.Ba</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>London</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.7</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>A.IV</cell>
                  <cell>R.Ba</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.8</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>A.VI</cell>
                  <cell>R.Ca</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Vienna</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.9</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>A.IV</cell>
                  <cell>R.Ca</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Paris</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.10</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>A.VII</cell>
                  <cell>R.Da</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.11</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>A.VI</cell>
                  <cell>R.Ca</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Berlin</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.12</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>A.V</cell>
                  <cell>R.Ca</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>London</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>[.13</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>A.VI</cell>
                  <cell>R.Ca</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>[.14</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>A.IV</cell>
                  <cell>R.Aa</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Holzer</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>2. Ars Classica sale XVIII, Lucerne, Oct. 10, 1938, no. 32 = Glendining sale (V. J. E. Ryan coll), <placeName>London</placeName>, Feb. 20, 1951,
               no. 1584. 5. Este stamp on obverse at lower left, between neck and legend. 7. Ex Imhoof-Blumer coll. 10. Ex Prowe coll. 13. R. Ratto sale
               (Morcom-Hands colls.), Lucerne, Feb. 8, 1928, no. 1674 = R. Ratto sale (Martini coll.), Lucerne, Feb. 24, 1930, no. 1351. The piece is
               distinguished by a large obverse gash. 14. Monnaies et Médailles sale XV, Basle, July 1, 1955, no. 704. Reverse gash at lower right.</p>
            <table rows="8" cols="5">
               <row>
                  <cell>49.1</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <persName corresp="#nomisma_octavian">Octavian</persName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>O.III</cell>
                  <cell>R.Bo</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>London</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.2</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>O.III</cell>
                  <cell>R.Bo</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Vienna</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.3</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>O.IV</cell>
                  <cell>R.Ao</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Vatican</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.4</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>O.III</cell>
                  <cell>R.Bo</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Paris</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.5</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>O.IV</cell>
                  <cell>R.Ao</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>London</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.6</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>O.IV</cell>
                  <cell>R.Ao</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Glasgow</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.7</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>O.IV</cell>
                  <cell>R.Ao</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.8</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>O.IV</cell>
                  <cell>R.Ao</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Paris</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>7. Ex Prowe coll.</p>
            <pb n="68"/>
            <table rows="17" cols="5">
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">No.</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Obverse portrait</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Obv. die</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev. die</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Collection</hi>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell cols="5">
                     <hi rend="italic">L. MVSSIDIVS LONGVS/Mars</hi>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>50.1</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <persName corresp="#nomisma_m_lepidvs_rrc">Lepidus</persName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>L.III</cell>
                  <cell>M.Am</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Vienna</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.2</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>L.III</cell>
                  <cell>M.Bm</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Paris</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.3</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>L.III</cell>
                  <cell>M.Cm</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Vienna</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.4</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>L.III</cell>
                  <cell>M.Bm</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>London</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>51.1</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <persName corresp="#nomisma_mark_antony">Antony</persName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>A.I</cell>
                  <cell>M.Am</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Paris</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.2</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>–––</cell>
                  <cell>–––</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.3</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>A.I</cell>
                  <cell>M.Am</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>St. Florian</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.4</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>A.I</cell>
                  <cell>M.Bm</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>London</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.5</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>A.I</cell>
                  <cell>M.Bm</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Vienna</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.6</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>A.I</cell>
                  <cell>M.Bm</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Rome, Museo naz.</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.7</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>A.I</cell>
                  <cell>M.Bm</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Vienna</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.8</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>–––</cell>
                  <cell>–––</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.9</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>A.I</cell>
                  <cell>M.Cm</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>[.10</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>A.II</cell>
                  <cell>M.Bm</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>[.11</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>A.II</cell>
                  <cell>M.Bm</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>2. Attributed by Bahrfeldt to <placeName>Vienna.</placeName> I am informed by <persName>Dr. Guido</persName> Bruck that the piece is not and has
               not been in the <placeName>Vienna</placeName> collection. I take the reference to be a dittography of no. 51.5 or 51.7. 8. Similarly, Bahrfeldt
               erred in reporting a second example of this type in the <placeName>Gnecchi</placeName> collection, now in the Museo nazionale in Rome. I presume
               the reference to stem from a misreading of the <persName corresp="#nomisma_octavian">Octavian</persName> piece of the same reverse type, no.
               52.10 below, which was in the <placeName>Gnecchi</placeName> collection but was not included by Bahrfeldt. 9. Glendining sale (Henry Platt Hall
               coll.), <placeName>London</placeName>, July 19, 1950, no. 664. 10. A. Sambon sale (Maddalena coll.), <placeName>Paris</placeName>, May 7, 1903,
               no. 982. 11. Naville sale X, <placeName>Geneva</placeName>, June 15, 1925, no. 1745 = Glendining sale (V. J. E. Ryan coll.),
                  <placeName>London</placeName>, Feb. 20, 1951, no. 1583.</p>
            <table rows="6" cols="5">
               <row>
                  <cell>52.1</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <persName corresp="#nomisma_octavian">Octavian</persName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>O.II</cell>
                  <cell>M.Am</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Paris</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.2</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>O.II</cell>
                  <cell>M.Am</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Glasgow</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.3</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>O.II</cell>
                  <cell>M.Am</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>London</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.4</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>O.II</cell>
                  <cell>M.Bm</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Zagreb</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.5</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>O.II</cell>
                  <cell>M.Bm</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Paris</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.6</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>O.II</cell>
                  <cell>M.Bm</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Glasgow</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <pb n="69"/>
            <table rows="8" cols="5">
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">No.</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Obverse portrait</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Obv. die</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev. die</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">Collection</hi>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <hi rend="italic">.7</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>O.II</cell>
                  <cell>M.Bm</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Vienna</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.8</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Munich</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>.9</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Milan</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>[.10</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>O.II</cell>
                  <cell>M.Bm</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Rome, Museo naz.</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>[.11</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>O.II</cell>
                  <cell>M.Am</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>New York</placeName>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>[.12</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>O.II</cell>
                  <cell>M.Bm</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>[.13</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>O.II</cell>
                  <cell>M.Am</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
            </table>
            <p>8. I am informed by <persName>Dr. Kraft</persName> that the Munich example was lost during the last war, nor is a cast or a photograph to be
               found. 9. I have not succeeded in obtaining a cast or discovering a reproduction of the piece in Milan. 12. Glendining sale (V. J. E. Ryan
               coll.), <placeName>London</placeName>, Feb. 20, 1951, no. 1629. 13. E. Bourgey sale (Vidal Quadras y Ramón coll.), <placeName>Paris</placeName>,
               Nov. 4, 1913, no. 767.</p>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n107">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">107</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>As mentioned above, the catalogue numbers are those assigned by Bahrfeldt; the numbers in brackets are additions to his listings. Bahrfeldt
                  appended to each type the history of each example of that type: place of discovery (when known), previous owners, auction sales in which the
                  coin appeared, as well as any physical peculiarities of the piece. Following his example, I have included all additional information available
                  to me, without repeating that already found in Bahrfeldt.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n108">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">108</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>I have not attempted to trace the recent history of each of the coins on the market; since almost all are illustrated somewhere the results
                  would not be commensurate with the labor involved, and one sale of Roman gold could undo them all. When the present owner is not known to me,
                  a reference to a previous collection is given.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n109">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">109</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>Bahrfeldt did not include this piece in his listing although he knew of it. But he relegated it to "Abbildungen," presumably because he lacked
                  the weight of the coin. Since weight is not considered in this monograph, I have included in the Catalogue all the examples known to me,
                  whether in the original or through casts or photographs.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n110">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">110</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>The three coins attributed to <placeName>New York</placeName>, nos. 41.7, 42.11, and 52.11, pertain to the Durkee collection in the
                  Metropolitan Museum of Art, but are to be found on deposit in the American Numismatic Society.</p>
            </note>
         </div1>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div1 xml:id="d52e7183" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="bold">PLATES</hi>
            </head>
            <div2 xml:id="d52e7188" type="section">
               <pb/>
               <head>I</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-3">
                  <graphic url="83.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d52e7194" type="section">
               <pb/>
               <head>II</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-4">
                  <graphic url="84.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d52e7200" type="section">
               <pb/>
               <head>III</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-5">
                  <graphic url="85.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d52e7206" type="section">
               <pb/>
               <head>IV</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-6">
                  <graphic url="86.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d52e7212" type="section">
               <pb/>
               <head>V</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-7">
                  <graphic url="87.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d52e7218" type="section">
               <pb/>
               <head>VI</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-8">
                  <graphic url="88.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d52e7224" type="section">
               <pb/>
               <head>VII</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-9">
                  <graphic url="89.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d52e7230" type="section">
               <pb/>
               <head>VIII</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-10">
                  <graphic url="90.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d52e7236" type="section">
               <pb/>
               <head>IX</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-11">
                  <graphic url="91.jpg"/>
               </figure>
               <pb/>
               <pb/>
            </div2>
         </div1>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
