<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd"
     xml:id="nnan67536">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Gold Dollars of 1858, with Notes of the Other Issues</title>
            <author>
               <name>Wood, Howland, 1877-1938</name>
               <idno type="URI">http://numismatics.org/authority/wood_howland</idno>
            </author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>TEI P5 XML markup in conformance with the TEI DTD</resp>
               <name>AEL Data</name>
            </respStmt>
            <funder>Open access edition funded by the National Endowment for the Humanities/Andrew W. Mellon Foundation Humanities Open Book Program.</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <name>American Numismatic Society</name>
               <idno type="URI">http://numismatics.org/authority/american_numismatic_society</idno>
            </publisher>
            <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
            <date>1922</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">This work is made available under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International license</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Numismatic Notes and Monographs</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">12</biblScope>
            <idno type="URI">http://numismatics.org/library/195778</idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>Donum</title>
               <idno type="URI">http://numismatics.org/library/67536</idno>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <title>Worldcat</title>
               <idno type="URI">http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/250507309</idno>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <title>Worldcat Works</title>
               <idno type="URI">http://worldcat.org/entity/work/id/146362939</idno>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <title>HathiTrust</title>
               <idno type="URI">https://hdl.handle.net/2027/hvd.32044011025301</idno>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <particDesc>
            <listPerson>
               <person xml:id="viaf_63957810">
                  <persName>Keck, Charles, 1875-1951</persName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://viaf.org/viaf/63957810</idno>
               </person>
            </listPerson>
         </particDesc>
         <settingDesc>
            <listPlace>
               <place xml:id="nomisma_new_york_city">
                  <placeName>New York</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/new_york_city</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="nomisma_philadelphia_pennsylvania">
                  <placeName>Philadelphia</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://www.nomisma.org/id/philadelphia_pennsylvania</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="nomisma_new_orleans">
                  <placeName>New Orleans</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/new_orleans</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="nomisma_san_francisco">
                  <placeName>San Francisco</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/san_francisco</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="geonames_4331987">
                  <placeName>Louisiana</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://www.geonames.org/4331987</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="geonames_5332921">
                  <placeName>California</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://www.geonames.org/5332921</idno>
               </place>
            </listPlace>
         </settingDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://nomisma.org/">
               <term ref="http://nomisma.org/id/united_states_numismatics">United States Numismatics</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2016-08-11">Ran TEI file through XSLT process, detailed in the Mellon EBook migration Google Document.</change>
         <change when="2016-08-31">Reprocessed: restructured TOC list into table; added HathiTrust URI; added funder</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div1 xml:id="d1e34" type="cover">
            <pb/>
            <figure xml:id="fig-1">
               <graphic url="NNM12_001.jpg"/>
            </figure>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d1e38" type="frontma">
            <pb/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="bold">PUBLICATIONS</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi rend="bold">The American Journal of Numismatics, 1866-1920.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Monthly, May, 1866-April, 1870.</p>
            <p>Quarterly, July, 1870-October, 1912.</p>
            <p>Annually, 1913-1920.</p>
            <p rend="hang">With many plates, illustrations, maps and tables. Less than a dozen complete sets of the Journal remain on hand. Prices on application. Those wishing to fill broken sets can secure most of the needed volumes separately. An index to the first 50 volumes has been issued as part of volume 51. It may also be purchased as a reprint for $3.00.</p>
            <list>
               <item rend="hang">The American Numismatic Society. Catalogue of the International Exhibition of Contemporary Medals. March, 1910. New and revised edition. <placeName corresp="#nomisma_new_york_city">New York City</placeName>. 1911. xxxvi, 412 pages, 512 illustrations. $10.00.</item>
               <item rend="hang">The American Numismatic Society. Exhibition of <placeName>United States</placeName> and Colonial Coins. 1914. vii, 134 pages, 40 plates. $1.00.</item>
            </list>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d1e65" type="frontma">
            <pb/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="bold">NUMISMATIC</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi rend="bold">NOTES &amp; MONOGRAPHS</hi>
            </p>
            <p>EDITOR: <persName>SYDNEY P. NOE</persName>
            </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d1e77" type="dedication">
            <pb/>
            <p>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">NUMISMATIC NOTES AND MONOGRAPHS</hi> is devoted to essays and treatises on subjects relating to coins, paper money, medals and decorations, and is uniform with Hispanic Notes and Monographs published by the Hispanic Society of America, and with Indian Notes and Monographs issued by the Museum of the American Indian-Heye Foundation.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d1e83" type="copyright">
            <pb/>
            <p>COPYRIGHT 1922 BY</p>
            <p>THE AMERICAN NUMISMATIC SOCIETY</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">PRESS OF THE LENT &amp; GRAFF CO., <placeName>NEW YORK</placeName>
               </hi>
            </p>
         </div1>
         <titlePage>
            <docTitle>
               <titlePart type="main">THE GOLD DOLLARS OF 1858</titlePart>
               <titlePart type="sub">WITH NOTES OF THE OTHER ISSUES</titlePart>
            </docTitle>
            <byline>BY <persName>HOWLAND WOOD</persName>
            </byline>
            <figure xml:id="fig-2">
               <graphic url="NNM12_006.jpg"/>
            </figure>
            <docImprint>
               <publisher>THE AMERICAN NUMISMATIC SOCIETY</publisher>
               <pubPlace>BROADWAY AT 156TH STREET</pubPlace>
               <pubPlace>NEW YORK</pubPlace>
               <date>1922</date>
            </docImprint>
         </titlePage>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div1 xml:id="d1e116" type="chapter">
            <pb n="1"/>
            <head>THE GOLD DOLLARS OF 1858 With Notes of the Other Issues</head>
            <byline>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">By <persName corresp="numismatics_wood_howland">Howland Wood</persName>
               </hi>
            </byline>
            <p>A number of years ago one of our old-time collectors told his son that there was a rare variety of the 1858 gold dollar with the word " <hi rend="italic">Dollar</hi> " much larger than on the ordinary specimens. While examining some <placeName>United States</placeName> proof sets at an auction sale years before, he had noticed this peculiarity, but through inappreciation of its rarity at that time he failed to get it. The son was an enthusiastic collector and though constantly on the watch for this variety was never able to locate a specimen. Other collectors have been on the lookout for this piece, but so far as known they have failed in their quest.</p>
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>The piece under consideration was for many years in the possession of <persName>Mr. J. C. Randall</persName> of <placeName corresp="#nomisma_philadelphia_pennsylvania">Philadelphia</placeName>. It was probably included in lot 472, a proof set of 1858, sold with some of his other coins by <persName>Cogan</persName> on March 29th, 1882.</p>
            <p>Whether the late <persName>Ben G. Green</persName> saw one of these coins it is impossible to prove, but in his Numismatic Reference and Check Book published in 1902 he lists under the Gold Dollars of 1858 the second one as follows: "large 1 Dollar." This statement of <persName>Mr. Green's</persName> seems to have remained unnoticed by most collectors.</p>
            <p>The American Numismatic Society has in its possession one of these gold dollars. Possibly it is the identical Randall specimen. This piece formed part of the collection of <placeName>United States</placeName> Gold and Silver Coins presented to the Society in 1908 by the late <persName>J. Pierpont Morgan</persName> and it was listed as "Rare" in the inventory of the collection. The piece differs in many respects from the regular issues as will be seen from the illustration. The letters of the legend on
                    <pb n="3"/>
                    the obverse are larger and the head is set lower in the field. The "1" on the reverse is of different shape and the word "DOLLAR" is in much higher letters. The rims around the edge are a trifle broader. It is a pattern coin in the strict sense of the word. Designed to test out the advisability of making the inscriptions more legible, it failed to do this and consequently was not adopted. One or more of these pieces may have found their way into the proof sets of that year, but none, or apparently extremely few, reached the hands of collectors of pattern coins. This particular variety is only known otherwise by a few examples struck in copper.</p>
            <p>The gold dollar came into existence in 1849 by Act of Congress on March 3rd of the same year, together with the twenty dollar gold piece, though the latter was not struck for circulation until the following year. The gold dollar was discontinued in 1889, and the Act to abolish it was passed September 26th, 1890.</p>
            <p>It is interesting to note that the first pattern for a gold dollar is dated 1836 when
                    <pb n="4"/>
               <figure xml:id="fig-3">
                  <graphic url="NNM12_004a.jpg"/>
               </figure>
                    the Gobrecht silver-dollar patterns were made in anticipation of the resumption of striking silver dollars. This first pattern for a gold piece has a liberty cap in a rayed circle, and the denomination 1 D, in a closed wreath on the reverse side.</p>
            <p>An interesting gold pattern, struck in 1849, has a square hole in the centre.</p>
            <p>In 1852 the so-called ring dollars were made by way of experiment.</p>
            <figure xml:id="fig-4">
               <graphic url="NNM12_004b.jpg"/>
            </figure>
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>
               <persName>William Barker</persName> in 1872 made a new design for all denominations of the gold and silver coinage, and specimen pieces were struck in various metals. These designs were not adopted.</p>
            <p>Of the regular gold dollars there are several minor varieties of the year 1849, differing in the size of the stars, lettering and the wreath. This style with the coronet head continued into 1854 when a new design on a larger flan appeared. This design with a feathered head-dress was struck in 1854 and 1855. In 1856 the head was made slightly larger and the head-dress changed in a few minor details. The design continued unchanged up to the cessation of the gold-dollar coinage.</p>
            <p>Gold dollars were struck at the <placeName>Philadelphia Mint</placeName> from the inception until 1889, and in the branch mints as follows:</p>
            <p>
               <placeName corresp="#nomisma_new_orleans">New Orleans</placeName>, with mint mark O, from 1849 to 1853 inclusive, and 1855.</p>
            <p>
               <placeName>Dahlonega, Ga.</placeName>, with mint mark D, from 1849 into 1861 (when the mint was closed).</p>
            <p>
               <persName>Charlotte, N. C.</persName>, with mint mark C, from 1849 to 1855 inclusive, 1857 and 1859.</p>
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>Pieces dated 1854 are unknown to collectors. The records state that only four were struck.</p>
            <p>
               <placeName corresp="#nomisma_san_francisco">San Francisco</placeName>, with mint mark S, bearing dates 1854, 1856 to 1860 inclusive, and 1870.</p>
            <p>Besides the regular issues, various commemorative gold dollars have been struck. These were authorized by Congress and have been sold at double and sometimes treble their face value to aid, for the most part, expositions.</p>
            <list>
               <item rend="hang">1903 <placeName corresp="#geonames_4331987">Louisiana</placeName> Purchase Exposition with portrait of <persName>McKinley</persName>.</item>
               <item rend="hang">1903 <placeName corresp="#geonames_4331987">Louisiana</placeName> Purchase Exposition with portrait of <persName>Jefferson</persName>.</item>
               <item rend="hang">1904 and 1905 <persName>Lewis-Clark</persName> Exposition with portrait on the obverse of <persName>Lewis</persName>; and on the other side, of <persName>Clark</persName>.</item>
               <item rend="hang">1915 Panama-Pacific Exposition with head representing Labor, by <placeName corresp="#viaf_63957810">Charles Keck</placeName>. Struck at the <placeName>San Francisco Mint</placeName>.</item>
               <item rend="hang">1916 and 1917 <persName>McKinley</persName> Birthplace Memorial; Niles, Ohio, with portrait of <persName>McKinley</persName> on one side and the Memorial building on the other.</item>
               <item rend="hang">1922 Grant Memorial Gold Dollar.</item>
            </list>
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>There are a number of gold dollars, made chiefly in <placeName corresp="#geonames_5332921">California</placeName>, but as they have no official status they are not included. For the most part they can be easily distinguished from the genuine pieces by their poor workmanship as well as by their inscriptions and designs.</p>
         </div1>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div1 xml:id="d1e265" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>GOLD DOLLARS 1858</head>
            <p>Pl. I</p>
            <figure xml:id="fig-5">
               <graphic url="NNM12_014a.jpg"/>
               <p>First Type 1849-54</p>
            </figure>
            <figure xml:id="fig-6">
               <graphic url="NNM12_014b.jpg"/>
               <p>Second Type 1854 and 1855</p>
            </figure>
            <figure xml:id="fig-7">
               <graphic url="NNM12_014c.jpg"/>
               <p>Second Variety of 1858</p>
            </figure>
            <figure xml:id="fig-8">
               <graphic url="NNM12_014d.jpg"/>
               <p>Third Type 1856-1889</p>
            </figure>
            <p>TYPES OF GOLD DOLLARS FOR CIRCULATION</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d1e289" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>GOLD DOLLARS 1858</head>
            <p>Pl. II</p>
            <figure xml:id="fig-9">
               <graphic url="NNM12_015a.jpg"/>
               <p>
                  <placeName corresp="#geonames_4331987">Louisiana</placeName> Purchase Exposition</p>
            </figure>
            <figure xml:id="fig-10">
               <graphic url="NNM12_015b.jpg"/>
               <p>
                  <persName>Lewis-Clark</persName> Exposition</p>
            </figure>
            <figure xml:id="fig-11">
               <graphic url="NNM12_015c.jpg"/>
               <p>Panama-Pacific Exposition</p>
            </figure>
            <figure xml:id="fig-12">
               <graphic url="NNM12_015d.jpg"/>
               <p>
                  <persName>McKinley</persName> Birthplace Memorial</p>
            </figure>
            <p>COMMEMORATIVE GOLD DOLLARS</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d1e319" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="bold">PUBLICATIONS</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <persName>Ernest Babelon</persName>. <foreign xml:lang="nl">Les Médailles Historiques du Règne de Napoléon le Grand, Empereur et Roi</foreign>. Paris. 1912. Folio, lx, 430 pages printed in three tones, a special border for every page. Illustrating two hundred unpublished drawings of Napoleonic medals, .... by <persName>Chaudet</persName> and <persName>Lemot</persName> for .... the French Institute. $20.00.</p>
            <list>
               <item rend="hang">
                  <persName>Anges Balwdin</persName>. The Electrum Coinage of Lampsakos. 1914. 36 pages. 2 plates. $1.00.</item>
               <item rend="hang">
                  <persName>Edward T. Newell</persName>. The Seleucid Mint of <placeName>Antioch</placeName>. 1918. 137 pages. 13 plates. $5.00.</item>
               <item rend="hang">
                  <persName>Edward T. Newell</persName>. Tarsos under <persName>Alexander</persName>. 1919. 47 pages. 8 plates. $2.50.</item>
               <item rend="hang">
                  <persName>Edward T. Newell</persName>. Some Rare or Unpublished Greek Coins. 12 pages. 2 plates. $1.00.</item>
               <item rend="hang">
                  <persName>Edgar H. Adams</persName>. Private Gold Coinage of <placeName>California</placeName>. 5 Vols. (Unbound.) $3.50.</item>
               <item rend="hang">
                  <persName>Edgar H. Adams</persName> and <persName>William H. Woodin</persName>. <placeName>United States</placeName> Pattern, Trial and Experimental Pieces .... issued by the U. S. Mint from 1792 up to the present time. 1913. 204 pages. Illus. Cloth, $3.00.</item>
            </list>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d1e377" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>NUMISMATIC NOTES AND MONOGRAPHS</head>
            <list rend="numbered">
               <item n="1">1. <persName>Sydney P. Noe</persName>. Coin Hoards. 1921 47 pp. 6 pl. 50c.</item>
               <item n="2">2. <persName>Edward T. Newell</persName>. Octobols of Histiæa. 1921. 25 pp. 2 pl. 50c.</item>
               <item n="3">3. <persName>Edward T. Newell</persName>. <persName>Alexander</persName> Hoards—Introduction and <placeName>Kyparissia</placeName> Hoard 1921. 21 pp. 2 pl. 50c.</item>
               <item n="4">4. <persName>Howland Wood</persName>. The Mexican Revolutionary Coinage, 1913-1916. 1921. 44 pp. 26 pl. $2.00.</item>
               <item n="5">5. <persName>Leonidas Westervelt</persName>. The Jenny Lind Medals and Tokens. 1921. 25 pp. 9 pl. 50c.</item>
               <item n="6">6. <persName>Anges Balwdin</persName>. Five Roman Gold Medallions. 1921. 103 pp. 8 pl. $1.50.</item>
               <item n="7">7. <persName>Sydney P. Noe</persName>. Medallic Work of <persName>A. A. Weinman</persName>. 1921. 31 pp. 17 pl. $1.00.</item>
               <item n="8">8. <persName>Gilbert S. Perez</persName>. The Mint of the <placeName>Philippine Islands</placeName>. 1921. 8 pp. 4 pl. 50c.</item>
               <item n="9">9. <persName>David Eugene Smith</persName>, LL.D. Computing Jetons. 1921. 70 pp. 25 pl. $1 50.</item>
               <item n="10">10. <persName>Edward T. Newell</persName>. The First Seleucid Coinage of Tyre. 40 pp. 8 pl. $1.00.</item>
               <item n="11">11. <persName>Harrold E. Gillingham</persName>. French Orders and Decorations, 110 pp. 35 pl. $2.00.</item>
            </list>
         </div1>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
