<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd"
     xml:id="nnan97488">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>third and fourth Dura hoard</title>
            <author>
               <name>Bellinger, Alfred R. (Alfred Raymond), 1893-1978</name>
               <idno type="URI">http://viaf.org/viaf/34584084</idno>
            </author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>TEI P5 XML markup in conformance with the TEI DTD</resp>
               <name>AEL Data</name>
            </respStmt>
            <funder>The Andrew W. Mellon Foundation</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <name>American Numismatic Society</name>
               <idno type="URI">http://numismatics.org/authority/american_numismatic_society</idno>
            </publisher>
            <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
            <date>1932</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">This work is made available under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International license</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Numismatic Notes and Monographs</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">55</biblScope>
            <idno type="URI">http://numismatics.org/library/195778</idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>Donum</title>
               <idno type="URI">http://numismatics.org/library/97488</idno>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <title>Worldcat</title>
               <idno type="URI">http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/751602539</idno>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <title>Worldcat Works</title>
               <idno type="URI">http://worldcat.org/entity/work/id/156265844</idno>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://nomisma.org/">
               <term ref="http://nomisma.org/id/greek_numismatics">Greek Numismatics</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2018-04-02">Ran TEI file through XSLT process, detailed in the Mellon EBook migration Google Document.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div1 xml:id="d413e30" type="cover">
            <pb/>
            <figure xml:id="fig-01">
               <graphic url="NNM55_001.jpg"/>
            </figure>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d413e34" type="frontma">
            <pb/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="bold">PUBLICATIONS</hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="hang">
               <hi rend="bold">The American Journal of Numismatics, 1866–1920.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Monthly, May, 1866–April, 1870.</p>
            <p>Quarterly, July, 1870–October, 1912.</p>
            <p>Annually, 1913–1920.</p>
            <p rend="hang">With many plates, illustrations, maps and tables. Less than a half-dozen complete sets of the Journal remain on hand. Price on application.</p>
            <p rend="hang">The numbers necessary to complete broken sets may in most cases be obtained. An index to the first fifty volumes has been issued as part of Volume LI. It may be purchased separately for $3.00.</p>
            <p rend="hang">The American Numismatic Society. Catalogue of the International Exhibition of Contemporary Medals. March, 1910. New and revised edition. <placeName>New York</placeName>. 1911. xxxvi, 412 pages, 512 illustrations. $10.00. Price to members, $5.00.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d413e57" type="frontma">
            <pb/>
            <head>NUMISMATIC</head>
            <p>NOTES AND MONOGRAPHS</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d413e63" type="dedication">
            <pb/>
            <p>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">Numismatic Notes and Monographs</hi> is devoted to essays and treatises on subjects relating to coins, paper money, medals and decorations, and is uniform with Hispanic Notes and Monographs published by the Hispanic Society of <placeName>America</placeName>, and with Indian Notes and Monographs issued by the Museum of the American Indian— Heye Foundation.</p>
            <list>
               <head>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">Publication Committee</hi>
               </head>
               <item>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">
                     <persName>Agnes Baldwin Brett</persName>
                  </hi>, <hi rend="italic">Chairman</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">
                     <persName>W. Gedney Beatty</persName>
                  </hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">
                     <persName>Henry Russell Drowne</persName>
                  </hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">Editorial Staff</hi>
               </head>
               <item>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">
                     <persName>Sydney Philip Noe</persName>
                  </hi>, <hi rend="italic">Editor</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">
                     <persName>Howland Wood</persName>
                  </hi>, <hi rend="italic">Associate Editor</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d413e109" type="colophon">
            <pb/>
            <p>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">Copyright, 1932, by</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">The American Numismatic Society</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">Lancaster Press, Inc.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">Lancaster, Pa.</hi>
            </p>
         </div1>
         <pb/>
         <titlePage>
            <docTitle>
               <titlePart type="main">THE THIRD AND FOURTH DURA HOARDS</titlePart>
            </docTitle>
            <byline>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">by
<persName>Alfred R. Bellinger</persName>
               </hi>
            </byline>
            <figure xml:id="fig-02">
               <graphic url="NNM55_006.jpg"/>
            </figure>
            <docImprint>
               <publisher>THE AMERICAN NUMISMATIC SOCIETY</publisher>
               <pubPlace>BROADWAY AT 156TH STREET</pubPlace>
               <pubPlace>NEW YORK</pubPlace>
               <date>1932</date>
            </docImprint>
         </titlePage>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div1 xml:id="d413e145" type="chapter">
            <pb n="1"/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="bold">THE THIRD AND FOURTH DURA HOARDS</hi>
            </head>
            <p>At the beginning of November, 1930, the excavation of <placeName>Dura-Europos</placeName> was renewed with the clearing of the Priests' House, adjoining the temples of <persName>Artemis</persName> and <persName>Atargatis</persName>, which had been partially dug the season before. In it were found two small jars containing Roman silver coins and nearby one mass of metal which also proved to be silver coins that had been buried in a bag. These last <persName>Mr. Newell</persName> has kindly undertaken to publish himself; the two other collections are dealt with in this paper.<ref target="#CH1-n1">
                  <hi rend="sup">1</hi>
               </ref> There is every reason to believe that the two jars were part of a single hoard. They were found with their mouths opposite each other, almost touching, and the limits of the series are practically the same—<persName>Nero</persName> and <persName>Diadumenianus</persName> in one case, <persName>Vitellius</persName> and <persName>Macrinus</persName> in the other. Nevertheless, for the sake of entire accuracy, they are listed separately with a summary of the combined hoard at the end. Considering their proximity, it is curious that the color of the pieces was quite different, so that
<pb n="2"/>
one could tell at a glance to which group any given coin belonged. All were covered with a thick corrosion due to the large proportion of copper in the alloy, but in the case of Hoard IV this was a much more yellowish green than in the case of Hoard III, perhaps because two bronze coins, now illegible, were in the jar with Hoard IV. As the pieces adhered to each other it was not practicable to weigh them before cleaning; the weights of the denarii after cleaning show no significant variation from the standard. Only the weights of the tetradrachms are recorded.</p>
            <p>The hoards cannot have been buried before 218 because of the presence of coins of <persName>Macrinus</persName> and his son. On the other hand, there are none of the very common coins of <persName>Elagabalus</persName> issued in 219. The general confusion of the time may have been a sufficient reason for the burial. We know of no particular crisis at <placeName>Dura</placeName>, and the contents of Hoards I and II, beginning with <persName>Caracalla</persName> and continuing without interruption to <persName>Gallienus</persName>, lead one to think that this treasure may have been due to the miserliness of a particular priest rather than to any civil peril.</p>
            <p>It is surprising and somewhat disappointing to find no denarii from the mint of <placeName>Antioch</placeName> earlier than the single coin of <persName>Pescennius Niger</persName>. That mint was certainly used by <persName>Vespasian</persName>, and occasional coins both of <persName>Trajan</persName> and <persName>Hadrian</persName> appear to have been struck there. One would expect to
<pb n="3"/>
find a few of these in a hoard so much nearer to <placeName>Antioch</placeName> than to <placeName>Rome</placeName>, but such is not the case. There is, to be sure, one barbarous piece of <persName>Antoninus Pius</persName> (III, No. 145, Pl. III) but otherwise nothing which there is any excuse for attributing to the east. With <persName>Septimius Severus</persName> and his family, however, the case is different. <placeName>Antioch</placeName> furnishes 55 of the denarii of <persName>Severus</persName>, as against <placeName>Rome</placeName>'s 37, and 4 each of <persName>Julia Domna</persName> and <persName>Caracalla</persName> come from the eastern mint. The only method of distinguishing these issues is by style and it must be confessed that, at a period when the style is never of the best, it is not always easy to make up one's mind.</p>
            <p>Perhaps the best way to begin is with a comparison of specimens clearly typical of the two mints. IV, No. 56 (Pl. XII) may be taken as an example of <placeName>Antioch</placeName>; IV, Nos. 98, 99 (Pl. XIV), of <placeName>Rome</placeName>. There are three chief distinguishing marks of the <placeName>Antioch</placeName>ene denarii: (1) the large, rough and uneven lettering, (2) the clumsy treatment of the eye, (3) the bad proportions of the standing figure, which is usually too short. In contrast with this, the Roman coins show more refinement, even the face of the standing figure being cut with considerable delicacy. These distinctions are not always so clear, but they are useful for general guidance. Plate XV shows an instructive comparison between IV, No. 111 from <placeName>Antioch</placeName> and No. 112 of the same type but
<pb n="4"/>
probably from <placeName>Rome</placeName>. Unfortunately the reverse of the latter is not well enough preserved to be satisfactory, but the Roman style of <persName>Julia Domna</persName> appears clearly on No. 116. Differences are more elusive in the case of <persName>Caracalla</persName>. IV, Nos. 147 and 150 (Pl. XVIII) show the usual features of <placeName>Rome</placeName> and <placeName>Antioch</placeName> respectively, but IV, No. 158 (Pl. XVIII) and IV, No. 159 (Pl. XIX) illustrate the difficulty of deciding in some cases. The obverse of the former is clearly inferior in the drawing of the head and certainly no more than equal in the lettering; we should incline to attribute it to the inferior mint. But with the reverses the advantage is the other way. The sprawling letters of IV, No. 159, particularly the final G's, look more like <placeName>Antioch</placeName> than <placeName>Rome</placeName>. However, since the obverse of IV, No. 158 is better than that of IV, No. 146, and the reverse of IV, No. 159 better than that of IV, No. 147, both the FELICITAS AVGG pieces are attributed to <placeName>Rome</placeName>.</p>
            <p>Since Mattingly and Sydenham's invaluable <hi rend="italic">Roman Imperial Coinage</hi> has not reached the period after <persName>Commodus</persName>, one must still rely on Cohen, with some assistance from Platnauer <hi rend="italic">The Life and Reign of the Emperor Lucius <persName>Septimius Severus</persName>
               </hi> and Mary Williams' article on <persName>Julia Domna</persName> in the American Journal of Archaeology, Vol. VI, 3 (July-September, 1902).<ref target="#CH1-n2">
                  <hi rend="sup">2</hi>
               </ref>
            </p>
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>There is only one type of <persName>Severus</persName> which requires comment. IV Nos. 105, 106 show Jupiter between infants who are generally supposed to be <persName>Caracalla</persName> and <persName>Geta</persName>. But, if <persName>Caracalla</persName> was born in 188 (Platnauer, <hi rend="italic">op. cit</hi>., pp. 50-53) and <persName>Geta</persName> in 189, the elder brother was 22, the younger 21 in 210, when IV, No. 105 was struck, and IV, No. 106 is a year later. Could they without too great absurdity, be represented as infants? Is this the mere conventional repetition of a group originating earlier, or has it a significance that has escaped us?</p>
            <p>Cohen refers to Ramus, in the catalogue of coins in the Museum of <placeName>Denmark</placeName>, a general division of the coins of <persName>Julia Domna</persName> into three classes: the earliest, inscribed IVLIA DOMNA AVG; the second, inscribed IVLIA AVGVSTA; and the third, inscribed IVLIA PIA FELIX AVG. I have assumed that the first group belongs to the earlier years of her husband's reign, 193–196. All of our pieces with IVLIA DOMNA AVG are clearly from <placeName>Antioch</placeName>, except IV, No. 112 which I consider one of the first issues of the Roman mint. The simple title IVLIA AVGVSTA I should assign to the remainder of <persName>Severus</persName>' reign. The third group, which probably continues until the time of her death may begin as early as 198. Cohen (4, pp. 137-139) gives examples of her coins struck with her husband
<pb n="6"/>
on which she appears as PIA FELIX;<ref target="#CH1-n3">
                  <hi rend="sup">3</hi>
               </ref> the reverses date them between 198 and 204. Cohen No. 69 (quoted from Rollin) a hybrid with IVLIA PIA FELIX AVG and FORT RED TRP III COS II (195) may be dismissed as spurious. <persName>Julia</persName>'s own types give no indication of date until her latter years. Our IV, No. 129 with MAT AVGG MAT SEN M PATR must be between 209, the date of Geta's elevation, and 212, the date of his death. It probably comes in the uneasy year between <persName>Septimius Severus</persName>' death and <persName>Geta</persName>'s murder.</p>
            <p>We have two denarii of <persName>Caracalla</persName> (IV, Nos. 146, 147) issued from <placeName>Antioch</placeName> in his youth, one in 197, the other in 198. These, and presumably other types not represented here, belong to the output of that mint in the early years of his father's reign. After 198 <placeName>Rome</placeName> alone seems to have been used as long as <persName>Severus</persName> lived. But there are two later pieces of <persName>Caracalla</persName> (IV, Nos. 148, 149) which appear to be from the east. On the former (Pl. XVII) the inscription MARTI PROPVGANATORI (sic) at once suggests <placeName>Antioch</placeName>, where errors in Latin inscriptions are common (Platnauer, <hi rend="italic">op. cit</hi>., p. 35); the style of the latter (Pl. XVIII) is equally indicative. Comparison of IV, No. 148 with IV, No. 165 (Pl. XIX) which has the correct reading MARTI PRO-
<pb n="7"/>
PVGNATORI will show that the differences are slight, it is true, but I believe we are justified in holding that in 211 <persName>Caracalla</persName> began again the striking of denarii at <placeName>Antioch</placeName>. It would be quite consistent with his general policy in the east. Neither hoard has any specimens of the Antoniniani which he introduced to check the depreciation of the denarius.</p>
            <p>The tridrachm of <persName>Trajan</persName> from <placeName>Caesarea</placeName> in <placeName>Cappadocia</placeName> (IV, No. 3) is unlike anything previously found at <placeName>Dura</placeName>. A few of the abundant bronzes of <placeName>Caesarea</placeName> have turned up, but no more of the silver.</p>
            <p>Before the discovery of these hoards the earliest tetradrachms found had been those of <persName>Caracalla</persName>; we now have a good piece of <persName>Marcus Aurelius</persName> and several of <persName>Septimius Severus</persName>; Hoard V, which <persName>Mr. Newell</persName> is publishing, contains still earlier tetradrachms. The coin of <placeName>Marcus Aurelius</placeName> is particularly interesting not only because it is a rare variety but because it represents the mint of <placeName>Antioch</placeName> during a period when, for some reason, its coins did not penetrate to <placeName>Dura</placeName>, or, at least, have not been found there. It rather emphasizes than explains that curious lacuna.</p>
            <p>The tetradrachms of <persName>Severus</persName> and his sons attributed to <placeName>Antioch</placeName> are of two distinct styles. There is the type of the eagle on the leg and thigh (III, No. 197, Pl. VI; IV, No. 132, Pl. XVI) together with that having stars to right and left
<pb n="8"/>
of the eagle's head (IV, No. 138, Pl. XVII; IV, No. 173, Pl. XX). On these the eagle's head is right and the wing feathers are represented by solid dots; the bend of the left wing is slightly higher and slightly sharper than that of the right. On the other hand, the pieces bearing a star between the eagle's legs (IV, No. 40, Pl. XI; IV, No. 135, Pl. XVI; IV, No. 172, Pl. XX) have the head left; the right wing is much higher than the left and the under wing coverts are represented by circles or semi-circles with a central dot. The two styles cannot, however, be the product of different mints, for there are intermediate examples. IV, No. 140 (Pl. XVII), with a star between the eagle's legs, has the wings as nearly even as on the coins with the leg and thigh, while on IV, No. 139 (too badly corroded to be illustrated) the leg and thigh are combined with the circle and dot technique for the wing coverts. The two tetradrachms of <persName>Caracalla</persName> with the thunderbolt (IV, Nos. 141, 142) are in too bad condition to furnish any ground for argument.</p>
            <p>The other mints represented have already been discussed in connection with the first two hoards.</p>
            <div2 xml:id="d413e478" type="section">
               <pb n="9"/>
               <head>HOARD III</head>
               <div3 xml:id="d413e482" type="subsection">
                  <head>NERO <hi rend="italic">DENARIVS</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">
                        <placeName>Rome</placeName> 64-68</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>1. <persName>NERO CAESAR AVGVSTVS</persName>. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. IVPPITER CVSTOS. Jupiter seated l., holding scepter and thunderbolt.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">B.M.C</hi>., I, p. 208, Nos. 74-76. Pl. 39.20.)</p>
               </div3>
               <div3 xml:id="d413e506" type="subsection">
                  <head>GALBA <hi rend="italic">DENARII</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">
                        <placeName>Rome</placeName> 68/69</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>2. IMP SER GALBA CAESAR AVG. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. DIVA AVGVSTA. Livia standing l., holding patera and scepter.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">B.M.C</hi>., I, p. 310, Nos. 8, 9. Cf. Pl. 52.3.)</p>
                  <p>3. IMP SER GALBA CAESAR AVG. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. SALVS GEN HVMANI. Female figure standing l., r. foot on globe, sacrificing out of patera over lighted altar and holding upright rudder. (<hi rend="italic">B.M.C</hi>., I, p. 315, Nos. 40, 41. Pl. 52.20.) <hi rend="italic">Plate I</hi>
                  </p>
               </div3>
               <div3 xml:id="d413e538" type="subsection">
                  <pb n="10"/>
                  <head>VITELLIVS <hi rend="italic">DENARII</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">
                        <placeName>Rome</placeName> 69</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>4. A VITELLIVS GERM IMP AVG TRP. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. LIBERTAS RESTITVTA. Libertas standing r., holding pileus and long scepter.</p>
                  <p>(.<hi rend="italic">B.M.C</hi>., I, p. 372, Nos. 31, 32. Pl. 61.8.) <hi rend="italic">Plate I</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">Lugdunum</hi> 69</p>
                  <p>5. A VITELLIVS IMP GERMAN. Head r., laur., globe beneath neck.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. VICTORIA AVGVSTI. Victory advancing l., holding shield inscribed SPQR.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">B.M.C</hi>., I, p. 393, No. 125. Pl. 62.11.)</p>
               </div3>
               <div3 xml:id="d413e577" type="subsection">
                  <head>VESPASIAN <hi rend="italic">DENARII</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">
                        <placeName>Rome</placeName>
                     </hi> 69/70</p>
                  <p>6. IMP CAESAR VESPASIAN VS AVG. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. COS ITER TR POT. Pax seated l., holding branch and caduceus. (<hi rend="italic">B.M.C</hi>., II, p. 4, Nos. 26-30. Pl. 1.9.) <hi rend="italic">Plate I</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="11"/>
                  <p>7. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. IVDAEA (in ex.). Jewess seated r. on ground, mourning; behind her trophy. (<hi rend="italic">B.M.C</hi>., II, p. 6, Nos. 35-42. Pl. 1.12.)</p>
                  <p>70/71</p>
                  <p>8, 9. IMP CAES VESP AVG PM. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. AVGVR (above) TRI POT (below). Simpulum, sprinkler, jug and lituus. (<hi rend="italic">B.M.C</hi>., II, p. 9, Nos. 50-53. Pl. 1.18.)</p>
                  <p>72/73</p>
                  <p>10. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. TRI POT (across field). Vesta seated l., holding simpulum.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">B.M.C</hi>., II, p. 10, Nos. 57-59. Pl. 1.20.) <hi rend="italic">Plate I</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>11. IMP CAES VESP AVG PM COS IIII. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. AVGVR (above) TRI POT (below). Simpulum, sprinkler, jug and lituus. (<hi rend="italic">B.M.C</hi>., II, p. 11, No. 64.)</p>
                  <p>12. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. VICTORIA AVGVSTI. Victory advancing r., holding palm and about to place wreath on trophy.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">B.M.C</hi>., II, pp. 13, 14, Nos. 75-77. Pl. 2.8,9.)</p>
                  <pb n="12"/>
                  <p>73</p>
                  <p>13, 14. IMP CAES VESP AVG CENS (beginning low r., outwardly). Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. PONTIF MAXIM. <persName>Vespasian</persName> seated r., holding branch and scepter.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">B.M.C</hi>., II, p. 19, No. 98. Pl. 3.3.) <hi rend="italic">Plate I</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>74</p>
                  <p>15. IMP CAESAR VESP AVG (beginning low r., outwardly). Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. PON MAX TRP COS V. Winged caduceus.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">B.M.C</hi>., II, p. 25, No. 137. Pl. 4.3.)</p>
                  <p>75</p>
                  <p>16-18. IMP CAESAR VESPASIANVS AVG (beginning low r., outwardly). Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. PON MAX TRP COS VI. Pax seated l., holding branch.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">B.M.C</hi>., II, pp. 30, 31, Nos. 161-164. Pl. 4.20.) 76</p>
                  <p>19, 20. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. COS VII Eagles standing on garlanded base, head l.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">B.M.C</hi>., p. 34, Nos. 180-182. Pl. 5.14.)</p>
                  <pb n="13"/>
                  <p>21. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. PON MAX TRP COS VII. Victory standing l., on prow holding wreath and palm.</p>
                  <p>(Not in B.M., <hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 25, No. 100.) <hi rend="italic">Plate I</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>77/78</p>
                  <p>22. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. COS VIII. Mars standing l., holding spear and trophy.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">B.M.C</hi>., II, p. 37, Nos. 200-202. Pl. 6.4.)</p>
                  <p>23. CAESAR VESPASIANVS AVG (beginning low r., outwardly). Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. IMP XIX (in ex.). Sow l., with three young.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">B.M.C</hi>., II, p. 39, Nos. 212, 213. Pl. 6.13.)</p>
                  <p>24. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. IMP XIX (across field). Modius, standing on three legs, containing five ears of corn upright and two hanging over at the sides.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">B.M.C</hi>., II, p. 39, No. 216. Pl. 6.15.)</p>
                  <p>75-79</p>
                  <p>25. IMP CAESAR VESPASIANVS AVG (beginning low r., outwardly). Head r., laur.</p>
                  <pb n="14"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. IOVIS CVSTOS. Jupiter standing l., sacrificing out of patera over altar and holding scepter.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">B.M.C</hi>., II, p. 49, Nos. 276-278. Pl. 8.11.)</p>
                  <p>78/79</p>
                  <p>26-29. CAESAR VESPASIANVS AVG (beginning low r., outwardly). Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. ANNONA AVG. Annona seated l., holding corn ears in lap.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">B.M.C</hi>., II, p. 51, Nos. 295, 296. Pl. 9.1.)</p>
                  <p>80/81</p>
                  <p>30. DIVVS AVGVSTVS VESPASIANVS (beginning low r., outwardly). Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. SC on shield supported by two capricorns; below, a globe.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">B.M.C</hi>., II, p. 245, No. 132. Pl. 47.9.)</p>
               </div3>
               <div3 xml:id="d413e804" type="subsection">
                  <head>TITUS <hi rend="italic">DENARIUS</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <placeName>Rome</placeName> 75</p>
                  <p>31. T CAESAR IMP VESPASIAN (beginning low r., outwardly). Head r., laur.</p>
                  <pb n="15"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. PONTIF TR P COS IIII. Pax seated l., holding branch.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">B.M.C</hi>., II, p. 32, No. 172. Pl. 5.8.) <hi rend="italic">Plate I</hi>
                  </p>
               </div3>
               <div3 xml:id="d413e827" type="subsection">
                  <head>
                     <persName>DOMITIAN</persName>
                     <hi rend="italic">DENARII</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">
                        <placeName>Rome</placeName>
                     </hi> 74</p>
                  <p>32. CAES AVG F DOMIT COS III (beginning low r., outwardly). Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. PRINCEPS IVVENTVT. Spes advancing l., holding flower and raising skirt.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">B.M.C</hi>., II, p. 29, No. 156. Pl. 4.16.) 76</p>
                  <p>33. CAESAR AVG F DOMITIANVS (beginning low r., outwardly). Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. COS IIII. Pegasus walking r.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">B.M.C</hi>., II, p. 36, Nos. 193-195. Pl. 6.1.)</p>
                  <p>79</p>
                  <p>34. CAESAR AVG F DOMITIANVS COS VI (beginning low r., outwardly). Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. PRINCEPS IVVENTVTIS. Salus standing r., leaning on column and feeding snake.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">B.M.C</hi>., II, p. 47, Nos. 265, 266. Pl. 8.6.)</p>
                  <pb n="16"/>
                  <p>80</p>
                  <p>35. CAESAR DIVI F DOMITIANVS COS VII (beginning low r., outwardly). Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. PRINCEPS IVVENTVTIS. Goat standing l. in laurel wreath.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">B.M.C</hi>., II, p. 239, Nos. 88-90. Pl. 46.9.) <hi rend="italic">Plate I</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>90</p>
                  <p>36. IM CAES DOMIT AVG GERM PM TR P VIIII. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. IMP XXI COS XV CENS PPP. Minerva r. on prow, brandishing javelin and holding shield; at her feet, owl.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">B.M.C</hi>., II, p. 333, No. 166. Pl. 64.20.)</p>
                  <p>92</p>
                  <p>37. IMP CAES DOMIT AVG GERM PM TRP XI. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. IMP XXI COS XVI CENS PPP. Minerva standing 1. with spear. (<hi rend="italic">B.M.C</hi>., II, p. 333, No. 168. Pl. 65.2.)</p>
               </div3>
               <div3 xml:id="d413e915" type="subsection">
                  <head>
                     <persName>NERVA</persName>
                     <hi rend="italic">DENARIVS</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">
                        <placeName>Rome</placeName>
                     </hi> 96 or 97</p>
                  <p>38. IMP NERVA CAES AVG PM TRP (or TRP II) COS II (or III) PP. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <pb n="17"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. LIBERTAS PVBLICA. Libertas standing l., holding pileus and scepter.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 223, No. 7 or p. 224, No. 19 or p. 225, No. 31. Pl. VII,118 (rev.).) <hi rend="italic">Plate I</hi>
                  </p>
               </div3>
               <div3 xml:id="d413e940" type="subsection">
                  <head>
                     <persName>TRAJAN</persName>
                     <hi rend="italic">DENARII</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">
                        <placeName>Rome</placeName>
                     </hi> 98/99</p>
                  <p>39. IMP CAES NERVA TRAIAN AVG GERM. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. PONT MAX TR POT COS II. Abundantia seated l., holding scepter, on chair with crossed cornucopiae as arms; fold of drapery over lap.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 245, No. 11.)</p>
                  <p>40. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Same inscription. Concordia seated l., holding patera and double cornucopiae; before her an altar.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 245, No. 12.)</p>
                  <p>41. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Same inscription. Felicitas standing l., holding caduceus and cornucopiae.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 245, No. 13.) <hi rend="italic">Plate II</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="18"/>
                  <p>101-102</p>
                  <p>42. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. PM TRP COS IIII PP. Mars walking r. with spear and trophy.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 248, No. 52.)</p>
                  <p>43, 44. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Same inscription. Victory standing r. on prow ending in serpent,, holding wreath and palm.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 248, No. 59.)</p>
                  <p>45, 46. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. PM TRP COS IIII PP. Victory walking 1. with wreath and palm.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 248, No. 60.)</p>
                  <p>103-111</p>
                  <p>47. IMP NERVA TRAIANVS AVG GERM DACICVS. Head r., laur., drapery over l. shoulder.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. PM TRP COS V PP. Dacian seated r. on shield in attitude of mourning.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 250, No. 89 has "below, curved sword.") <hi rend="italic">Plate II</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>48-51. IMP TRAIANO AVG GER DAC PM TRP. Head r., laur. drapery over l. shoulder.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. DAC CAP (in ex.) COS V PP SPQR OPTIMO PRINC (around). Dacian
<pb n="19"/>
seated l., mourning; various arms on ground.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p 251, No. 98.)</p>
                  <p>52-54. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. COS V PP SPQR OPTIMO PRINC. Roma standing l. with spear and Victory.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 252, No. 115.)</p>
                  <p>55, 56. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Same inscription. Roma seated l., holding spear and Victory.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 252, No. 116.)</p>
                  <p>57-61. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Same inscription. Aequitas standing l., holding scales and cornucopiae.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 252, No. 118, given only as gold.) <hi rend="italic">Plate II</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>62. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Same inscription. Felicitas standing l., holding caduceus and leaning on column.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 252, No. 120.)</p>
                  <p>63. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Same inscription. Spes walking l., holding flower and raising skirt.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 253, No. 127 has <hi rend="italic">obv</hi>. Head draped. Pl. VIII, 138 (rev.).) <hi rend="italic">Plate II</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="20"/>
                  <p>64. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Same inscription. Victory standing l., half draped, holding wreath and palm.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 253, No. 128.)</p>
                  <p>65, 66. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Same inscription. Victory walking l. with wreath and palm.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 253, No. 131.)</p>
                  <p>67. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Same inscription. Trophy with one round and two hexagonal shields; at base, a sword, two javelins and two shields.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 254, No. 147 b has <hi rend="italic">obv</hi>. Head draped.)</p>
                  <p>68. IMP TRAIANO AVG GER DAC PM TRP COS V PP. Head r., laur., drapery over 1. shoulder.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. SPQR OPTIMO PRINCIPI. Felicitas standing l., holding caduceus and cornucopiae.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 256, No. 172.)</p>
                  <p>69. Same inscription. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Same inscription. Pax standing l., holding olive branch and cornucopiae, foot on Dacian.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 257, No. 190 a has <hi rend="italic">obv</hi>. with aegis. Pl. VIII, 144 (rev.).)</p>
                  <pb n="21"/>
                  <p>70. Same inscription. Head r., laur., drapery on l. shoulder.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Same inscription. Spes advancing l., holding flower and raising skirt.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 257, No. 191.) <hi rend="italic">Plate II</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>111</p>
                  <p>71. IMP TRAIANO AVG GER DAC PM TRP COS V DES VI. Head r., laur., drapery on l. shoulder.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Same inscription. Victory standing r.; foot on helmet; she inscribes DACICA on shield attached to palm tree.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 259, No. 234.) <hi rend="italic">Plate II</hi> 112-114</p>
                  <p>72-74. IMP TRAIANO AVG GER DAC PM TRP COS VI PP. Head r., laur., drapery over l. shoulder.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Same inscription. Abundantia standing l., holding ears of corn and cornucopiae; at her feet child standing, holding roll. ALIM ITAL (in ex.).</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 261, No. 243. Pl. IX.156 (rev.).)</p>
                  <p>75. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Same inscription. Mars, nude, walking r. with spear and trophy.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 263, No. 270.)</p>
                  <pb n="22"/>
                  <p>76, 77. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Same inscription. Felicitas standing l., holding caduceus and cornucopiae.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 263, No. 272.)</p>
                  <p>78. Same inscription. Head r., laur., draped.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Same inscription. <persName>Trajan</persName>'s column surmounted by statue of the emperor; at base, two eagles.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 264, No. 292.)</p>
                  <p>114-117</p>
                  <p>79. IMP CAES NER TRAIANO OPTIMO AVG GER DAC. Head r., laur., draped.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. PM TRP COS VI PP SPQR. Fortuna seated l., holding rudder and cornucopiae. FORT RED (in ex.).</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 267, No. 318.)</p>
                  <p>80. IMP CAES NER TRAIAN OPTIM AVG GERM DAC. Head r., laur., draped.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. PARTHICO PM TRP COS VI PP SPQR. Mars walking r. with spear and trophy.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 267, No. 331.)</p>
                  <p>81. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Same inscription. Felicitas standing l., holding caduceus and cornucopiae.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 268, No. 332.) <hi rend="italic">Plate II</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="23"/>
                  <p>82-85. IMP CAES NER TRAIAN OPTIMO AVG GERM DAC. Head r., laur., draped.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Same inscription. Virtus standing r., holding spear and parazonium; foot on helmet.</p>
                  <p>(.<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 268, No. 334.)</p>
                  <p>86. IMP CAES NER TRAIANO OPTIMO AVG GER DAC. Head r., laur., draped.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. PM TRP COS VI PP SPQR. Mars walking r. with spear and trophy.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 268, No. 337.)</p>
                  <p>87. Same inscription. Head r., laur., drapery over l. shoulder.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Same inscription. Felicitas standing l., holding caduceus and cornucopiae.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 268, No. 343 has <hi rend="italic">obv</hi>. Head draped.) <hi rend="italic">Plate II</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>88. Same inscription. Bust r., laur., draped, in cuirass.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Same.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 268, No. 344.) <hi rend="italic">Plate II</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>89. IMP CAES NER TRAIAN OPTIM AVG GER DAC PARTHICO. Head r., laur., draped.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. PRO VID (across field) PM TRP COS VI PP SPQR (around). Providentia
<pb n="24"/>
standing l., holding scepter and pointing at globe.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 269, No. 365.)</p>
               </div3>
               <div3 xml:id="d413e1363" type="subsection">
                  <head>
                     <persName>HADRIAN</persName>
                     <hi rend="italic">DENARII</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">
                        <placeName>Rome</placeName>
                     </hi> 117</p>
                  <p>90. IMP CAES TRAIAN HADRIANO AVG DIVI TRA. Bust r., laur., in cuirass.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. PARTH F DIVI NER NEP PM TRP COS. Justitia seated l., holding patera and scepter. IVSTITIA (in ex.).</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 340, No. 11.)</p>
                  <p>91. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Same inscription. Pietas veiled standing l., raising r. hand.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 340, No. 13.) <hi rend="italic">Plate II</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>118</p>
                  <p>92. IMP CAESAR TRAIAN HADRIANVS AVG. Head r., laur., drapery over l. shoulder.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. PM TRP COS II (or III which would be 119-122). Concord seated l. CONCORD (in ex.).</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 345, No. 39 or p. 354, No. 118.)</p>
                  <pb n="25"/>
                  <p>93. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. PM TRP COS II. Pietas standing l., veiled, raising r. hand. PIETAS (in ex.).</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 345, No. 45.)</p>
                  <p>119–122</p>
                  <p>94. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. PM TRP COS III. Mars advancing r., holding spear and trophy.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 348, No. 67.)</p>
                  <p>95, 96. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Same inscription. Roma, helmeted, seated l. on cuirass, holding Victory and spear, behind, shield.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 349, No. 77.)</p>
                  <p>97, 98. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Same inscription. Aequitas standing l., holding scales and cornucopiae.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 350, No. 80.)</p>
                  <p>99. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Same inscription. <persName>Hadrian</persName> standing l., holding rudder on globe, and spear.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 353, No. 110. Pl. XII, 232 <hi rend="italic">(rev.).) Plate III</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>100. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Same inscription. Felicitas seated l., holding caduceus and cornucopiae. FEL PR (in ex.).</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 354, No. 120.)</p>
                  <pb n="26"/>
                  <p>101. Same inscription. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Same inscription. Libertas seated l., holding branch and scepter. LIB PVB (in ex.).</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 355, No. 127.)</p>
                  <p>102. Same inscription. Head r., laur., drapery over l. shoulder.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Same inscription. Providentia standing l., pointing to globe at her feet and holding scepter. PRO AVG (in field).</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 356, No. 133.)</p>
                  <p>103, 104. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Same inscription. Salus seated l., feeding snake coiled around altar. SAL AVG (in ex.).</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 356, No. 137.)</p>
                  <p>105. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Same inscription. Pietas, veiled, standing r., raising both hands. VOT PVB (in field).</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 357, No. 141.)</p>
                  <p>125-128</p>
                  <p>106. HADRIANVS AVGVSTVS. Head r., laur., drapery over l. shoulder.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. COS III. Hercules seated r. on cuirass, holding Victory and club which rests on shield.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 358, No. 148.) <hi rend="italic">Plate III</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="27"/>
                  <p>107. HADRIANVS AVGVSTVS PP. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Same inscription. Minerva standing r., holding spear and leaning on shield.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 358, No. 152.) <hi rend="italic">Plate III</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>108. HADRIANVS AVGVSTVS. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Same inscription. Roma seated l. on cuirass and shield, holding branch and scepter.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 360, No. 165.)</p>
                  <p>109, 110. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Same inscription. Seven stars above crescent.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 362, No. 202. Pl. XIII, 251 <hi rend="italic">(rev.)</hi> has inscription in ex.) <hi rend="italic">Plate III</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>134-138</p>
                  <p>111. HADRIANVS AVG COS III PP. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. ADVENTVS AVG. Roma standing r., holding spear and clasping hands with <persName>Hadrian</persName> standing l.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 366, No. 225. Pl. XIII, 264.)</p>
                  <pb n="28"/>
                  <p>112. Same inscription. Head r., bare.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. FELICITAS AVG. Felicitas standing l., holding caduceus and cornucopiae.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 367, No. 233.) <hi rend="italic">Plate III</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>113. Same inscription. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Same inscription. Felicitas standing l., holding caduceus and branch.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 367, No. 234.)</p>
                  <p>114. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Same inscription. Felicitas standing l., holding caduceus and clasping hands with <persName>Hadrian</persName> standing r.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 368, No. 237.)</p>
                  <p>115-117. Same inscription. Head r., bare.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. FIDES PVBLICA. Fides standing r., holding corn ears and basket of fruit.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 368, No. 241 A.)</p>
                  <p>118. Same inscription. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. MONETA AVG. Moneta standing l., holding scales and cornucopiae.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 369, No. 256.)</p>
                  <p>119. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. SALVS AVG. Salus standing r., feeding snake coiled round altar.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>. II, p. 371, No. 267.)</p>
                  <pb n="29"/>
                  <p>120. Same inscription. Head r., bare.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. SPES PR. Spes advancing l., holding flower and raising skirt.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 371, No. 274.)</p>
                  <p>121. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. VENERIS FELICIS. Venus seated l., holding Cupid and leaning on reversed spear.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 372, No. 280. Pl. XIV, 281.)</p>
                  <p>122. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. VOTA PVBLICA. <persName>Hadrian</persName>, veiled, standing l., sacrificing out of patera over tripod.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 373, No. 290.)</p>
                  <p>123. HADRIANVS AVGVSTUS PP. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. COS III. Abundantia seated l., holding hook and cornucopiae; in front, modius and corn ears.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 379, No. 338.)</p>
                  <p>124. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Same inscription. Pudicitia, veiled, seated l.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 380, No. 343.)</p>
                  <p>125, 126. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Same inscription. Victory seated l., holding wreath and palm.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 380, No. 345.)</p>
               </div3>
               <div3 xml:id="d413e1753" type="subsection">
                  <pb n="30"/>
                  <head>
                     <persName>SABINA</persName>
                     <hi rend="italic">DENARII</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">
                        <placeName>Rome</placeName> 134-138</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>127. SABINA AVGVSTA. Bust r., diademed, hair in queue.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. CONCORDIA AVG. Concordia standing l., leaning on column holding patera and cornucopiae.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 386, No. 390.) <hi rend="italic">Plate III</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>128. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Same inscription. Concordia seated l., holding patera and scepter.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R. I. C</hi>., II, p. 386, No. 391.)</p>
                  <p>129, 130. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. IVNONI REGINAE. Juno standing l., holding patera and scepter.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 386, No. 395.)</p>
                  <p>131. SABINA AVGVSTA HADRIANI AVG PP. Same type.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. CONCORDIA AVG. Concordia seated l., holding patera and leaning l. elbow on figure of Spes; under chair, cornucopiae.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., p. 387, No. 398.)</p>
               </div3>
               <div3 xml:id="d413e1812" type="subsection">
                  <pb n="31"/>
                  <head>
                     <persName>ANTONINVS PIUS</persName>
                     <hi rend="italic">DENARII</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">
                        <placeName>Rome</placeName>
                     </hi> 139</p>
                  <p>132. IMP T AEL CAES HADR ANTONINVS. Head r., bare.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. AVG PIVS PM TRP COS II. Clasped hands holding winged caduceus.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., Ill, p. 29, No. 27.)</p>
                  <p>133. ANTONINVS AVG PIVS PP. Head r., bare.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. TRP COS II. Pax standing l., holding branch and cornucopiae.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 30, No. 42. Pl. I, 7 <hi rend="italic">(rev.)</hi> but there TR POT.)</p>
                  <p>140-143</p>
                  <p>134. ANTONINVS AVG PIVS PP TRP COS III. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. ANNONA AVG. Modius with cornears and poppies.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 33, No. 62.)</p>
                  <p>135. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. CLEMENTIA AVG. Clementia standing l., holding patera and scepter.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 33, No. 64.)</p>
                  <pb n="32"/>
                  <p>136. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. ITALIA. Italia, turreted, seated l. on globe holding cornucopiae and scepter.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 34, No. 73.)</p>
                  <p>137. ANTONINVS AVG PIVS PP. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. TR POT COS III. Clementia seated l., holding patera and scepter.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 36, No. 84.)</p>
                  <p>138. ANTONINVS AVG PIVS PP COS III. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. VIRTVS AVG. Virtus standing l., holding spear reversed and parazonium.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 38, No. 102d.)</p>
                  <p>143-144(?)</p>
                  <p>139. ANTONINVS AVG PIVS PP TRP COS III. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. IMPERATOR II. Victory l., holding wreath and palm.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 39, No. Ill b.)</p>
                  <p>149-150</p>
                  <p>140. ANTONINVS AVG PIVS PP TRP XII. Head, r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. COS IIII. Aequitas standing l., holding scales and cornucopiae.</p>
                  <pb n="33"/>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 48, No. 177. Pl. II, 33.)</p>
                  <p>150-151</p>
                  <p>141. ANTONINVS AVG PIVS PP TRP XIIII. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Same inscription. Genius standing l., holding patera and ears of corn.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 50, No. 196.)</p>
                  <p>142. IMP CAES T AEL HADR ANTONINVS AVG PIVS PP. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. TR POT XIIII COS IIII. Pietas standing r., holding hind by the neck and plate of fruits; beside her to r., altar. PIETAS (in ex.).</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 50, No. 201.) <hi rend="italic">Plate III</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>152-153</p>
                  <p>143, 144. ANTONINVS AVG PIVS PP TRP XVI. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. COS IIII. Fortuna standing r. with rudder on globe and cornucopiae.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 53, No. 222.) <hi rend="italic">Plate III</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>155, 156</p>
                  <p>145. ANTONINVS AVG PIVS PP IMP II. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. TR POT XIX COS IIII. Annona seated r., holding cornucopiae in
<pb n="34"/>
both hands; at feet modius. Barbarous.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 56, No. 250. Pl. II, 43 <hi rend="italic">(rev.).) Plate III</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>156, 157</p>
                  <p>146. ANTONINVS AVG PIVS PP IMP II. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. TR POT XX COS IIII. Annona standing r., l. foot on prow, holding rudder and modius.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 57, No. 260.)</p>
                  <p>147. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Same inscription. Salus seated l., feeding snake coiled round altar.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 57, No. 264.)</p>
                  <p>148. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Same inscription. Securitas seated l., holding scepter, elbow resting on arm of chair.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 58, No. 265.) <hi rend="italic">Plate IV</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>159-160</p>
                  <p>149. ANTONINVS AVG PIVS PP TRP XXIII. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. ROMA COS IIII. Roma seated l., holding Victory and spear.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 63, No. 303. Pl. II, 48 <hi rend="italic">(rev.).)</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="35"/>
                  <p>After 161.</p>
                  <p>150, 151. DIVVS ANTONINVS. Head r., bare.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. CONSECRATIO. Pyre of four tiers, decorated with hangings and garlands, surmounted by quadriga.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 247, No. 436. Pl. IX, 185.)</p>
               </div3>
               <div3 xml:id="d413e2064" type="subsection">
                  <head>
                     <persName>FAUSTINA SENIOR</persName>
                     <hi rend="italic">DENARII</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">
                        <placeName>Rome</placeName>
                     </hi> After 141</p>
                  <p>152. DIVA FAVSTINA. Bust r., draped.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. AETERNITAS. Providentia standing l., holding globe and scepter.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 70, No. 350 a. Pl. III, 55 with bust veiled.)</p>
                  <p>153-155. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Same inscription. Faustina standing l., veil blown out behind head, holding globe.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 70, No. 351.) <hi rend="italic">Plate IV</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>156, 157. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. AVGVSTA. Ceres, veiled, standing l., holding torch and scepter.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 70, No. 356. Pl. III, 60 <hi rend="italic">(rev</hi>.).)</p>
                  <pb n="36"/>
                  <p>158, 159. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Same inscription. Ceres, standing l., holding corn ears and torch.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 71, No. 360. Pl. III, 59 (<hi rend="italic">rev</hi>.).)</p>
                  <p>160. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Same inscription. Ceres, standing l., raising r. hand and holding torch.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 71, No. 361.)</p>
                  <p>161. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Same inscription. Ceres standing l. holding torch and holding up fold of skirt.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 71, No. 362.)</p>
                  <p>162. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Same inscription. Juno veiled, seated r., holding scepter.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 71, No. 363.)</p>
                  <p>163. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Same inscription. Venus standing l., holding apple and resting l. hand on shield.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 71, No. 366.) <hi rend="italic">Plate IV</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>164. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Same inscription. Pietas standing l. by altar, raising r. hand, l. hand at side.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 72, No. 374.) <hi rend="italic">Plate IV</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="37"/>
                  <p>165. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. CERES. Ceres, veiled, standing l., holding corn ears and torch.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 72, No. 378.)</p>
                  <p>166, 167. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. CONSECRATIO. Ceres standing l., veiled, raising r. hand and holding torch.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 73, No. 382 b.)</p>
                  <p>168. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Same inscription. Peacock walking r., head l.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 73, No. 384. Pl. III, 64 (<hi rend="italic">rev</hi>.).)</p>
                  <p>169, 170. DIVA AVG FAVSTINA. Bust r., draped.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. PIETAS AVG. Pietas, veiled, standing l., dropping incense on altar and holding box.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 74, No. 394 a.)</p>
               </div3>
               <div3 xml:id="d413e2238" type="subsection">
                  <head>
                     <persName>MARCUS AURELIUS</persName>
                     <hi rend="italic">DENARII</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">
                        <placeName>Rome</placeName>
                     </hi> 145-147</p>
                  <p>171, 172. AVRELIVS CAESAR AVG PII F. Head r., bare, unbearded.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. COS II. Honos standing l., holding branch and cornucopiae.</p>
                  <pb n="38"/>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 80, No. 429 a. Pl. IV, 77 <hi rend="italic">(rev.).) Plate IV</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>156, 157</p>
                  <p>173. AVRELIVS CAES ANTON AVG PII F. Head r., bare, bearded.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. TR POT XI COS II. Securitas standing l., leaning on column, raising r. hand and holding scepter.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 88, No. 472.) <hi rend="italic">Plate IV</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>157, 158</p>
                  <p>174. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. TR POT XII COS II. Felicitas standing l., leaning on column and holding caduceus and scepter.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 89, No. 475 a.)</p>
                  <p>162-163</p>
                  <p>175. IMP M ANTONINVS AVG. Head r., bare.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. CONCORD AVG TR P XVII. Concordia seated l., holding patera; cornucopiae under seat of chair; COS III (in ex.).</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 218, No. 59.)</p>
                  <pb n="39"/>
                  <p>165-166</p>
                  <p>176. M ANTONINVS AVG ARMENIACVS. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. PAX AVG TRP XX COS III. Pax standing l., holding branch and cornucopiae.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 224, No. 146.)</p>
                  <p>169-170</p>
                  <p>177. M ANTONINVS AVG TRP XXIIII. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. FELICITAS AVG COS III. Felicitas standing l., holding caduceus and scepter.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 230, No. 218.) <hi rend="italic">Plate IV</hi>
                  </p>
               </div3>
               <div3 xml:id="d413e2335" type="subsection">
                  <head>FAUSTINA JUNIOR <hi rend="italic">DENARII</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">
                        <placeName>Rome</placeName>
                     </hi> After 145</p>
                  <p>178-180. FAVSTINA AVGVSTA. Bust r. draped.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. AVGVSTI PII FIL. Venus standing l., holding Victory and resting l. hand on shield, set on helmet.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 93, No. 495 a. Pl. IV, 90 (<hi rend="italic">rev</hi>.).)</p>
                  <pb n="40"/>
                  <p>181. FAVSTINA AVG ANTONINI AVG PII FIL. Bust r., draped.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. CONCORDIA. Concordia standing front, head r., holding cornucopiae and raising skirt with r.</p>
                  <p>(Cf. <hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., p. 93, No. 500 b, where the <hi rend="italic">obv</hi>. reads FAVSTINAE.) <hi rend="italic">Plate V</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>182, 183. FAVSTINA AVG PII AVG FIL. Bust r., draped.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. CONCORDIA. Concordia seated l., holding flower, resting elbow on cornucopiae which is by her chair; under chair, globe.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 93, No. 502 a.)</p>
                  <p>184. FAVSTINAE AVG PII AVG FIL. Bust r., with stephane.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. LAETITIAE PVBLICAE. Laetitia standing l., holding wreath and scepter.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 94, No. 506 c. Pl. IV, 95.) <hi rend="italic">Plate V</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>185. Same inscription. Bust r., draped.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. PVDICITIA. Pudicitia standing l., half drawing veil over face and raising skirt.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 94, No. 507 a. Pl. IV, 96 <hi rend="italic">(rev</hi>.).)</p>
                  <pb n="41"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">After 161</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>186, 187. FAVSTINA AVGVSTA. Bust r., draped.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. FECVNDITAS. Fecunditas standing r., holding scepter and infant.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 269, No. 677. Pl. XI, 218. The bust there is diademed, though not so described.)</p>
                  <p>161-176</p>
                  <p>188. Same inscription. Bust r., diademed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. SAECVLI FELICIT. Pulvinar on which are <persName>Commodus</persName> and Antoninus.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 271, No. 712.) <hi rend="italic">Plate V</hi> 176-180</p>
                  <p>189. DIVA AVG FAVSTINA. Bust r., veiled.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. CONSECRATIO. Funeral pyre surmounted by biga.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 273, No. 747.) <hi rend="italic">Plate V</hi>
                  </p>
               </div3>
               <div3 xml:id="d413e2463" type="subsection">
                  <head>
                     <persName>LUCIUS VERUS</persName>
                     <hi rend="italic">DENARIUS</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">
                        <placeName>Rome</placeName>
                     </hi> 162, 163</p>
                  <p>190. IMP L VERVS AVG. Head r., bare.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. PROV DEOR TRP III COS II.</p>
                  <p>Providentia standing l., holding globe and cornucopiae.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 253, No. 491.) <hi rend="italic">Plate V</hi>
                  </p>
               </div3>
               <div3 xml:id="d413e2489" type="subsection">
                  <pb n="42"/>
                  <head>
                     <persName>LUCILLA</persName>
                     <hi rend="italic">DENARII</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">
                        <placeName>Rome</placeName>
                     </hi> 164-180</p>
                  <p>191. LVCILLA AVGVSTA. Bust r., draped.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. PVDICITIA. Pudicitia seated l., veiled, r. hand on breast.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 276, No. 780.)</p>
                  <p>192. LVCILLAE AVG ANTONINI AVG F. Bust r., draped.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. VESTA. Vesta, veiled, standing l. by altar decorated and lighted, holding simpulum and palladium.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 276, No. 788.) <hi rend="italic">Plate V</hi>
                  </p>
               </div3>
               <div3 xml:id="d413e2525" type="subsection">
                  <head>
                     <persName>COMMODUS</persName>
                     <hi rend="italic">DENARII</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">
                        <placeName>Rome</placeName>
                     </hi> 179</p>
                  <p>193. L AVREL COMMODVS AVG. Bust r., laur., draped, in cuirass, unbearded.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. TRP IIII IMP II COS PP. Salus seated, holding branch, her l. arm resting on chair; at her feet, snake.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 267, No. 657.) <hi rend="italic">Plate V</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>190</p>
                  <p>194. M COMM ANT P FEL AVG BRIT PP. Head r., laur., bearded.</p>
                  <pb n="43"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. LIB AVG PM TRP XV COS VI. Libertas standing l., holding pileus and rod.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 389, No. 208.) <hi rend="italic">Plate VI</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>192</p>
                  <p>195. L AEL AVREL COMM AVG P FEL. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. PM TRP XVII IMP VIII COS VI PP. Victory advancing l., holding wreath and palm; star in field, l.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 393, No. 237.)</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">After 193</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>196. M COMM ANTON AVG PIVS BRIT. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. CONSECRATIO. Eagle on globe l., head r.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 397, No. 263 b.) <hi rend="italic">Plate VI</hi>
                  </p>
               </div3>
               <div3 xml:id="d413e2595" type="subsection">
                  <head>
                     <persName>SEPTIMIUS SEVERUS</persName>
                     <hi rend="italic">TETRA DRACHM</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">
                        <placeName>Antioch</placeName>
                     </hi> 202</p>
                  <p>197. AϒT KAI CЄOϒHPOC CЄ B. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. ΔΗΜΑΡΧЄΞΤΠΑϒΟΓ. Eagle on leg and thigh of animal, head r., wreath in beak.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">B.M.C</hi>., Galatia, etc., p. 193, No. 351. Pl. XXIII, 6.) <hi rend="italic">Plate VI</hi>
                  </p>
               </div3>
               <div3 xml:id="d413e2619" type="subsection">
                  <pb n="44"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi rend="italic">DENARII</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">
                        <placeName>Antioch</placeName> 193</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>198, 199. IMP CAE L SEP SEV PERT AVG. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. MONETAE AVG. Moneta standing l., holding scales and cornucopiae. (Cf. C. 4, p. 37, No. 329.) <hi rend="italic">Plate VI</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>194</p>
                  <p>200. IMP CAE L SEP SEV PERT AVG COS II. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. BONA SPES. Spes walking l., holding flower and raising skirt.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 9, No. 58.) <hi rend="italic">Plate VI</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>201-203. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. BONI EVENTVS. Fides standing l., holding basket of fruit and two ears of corn. (No. 203 EVENTVC.)</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 10, No. 68.) <hi rend="italic">Plate VI</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>204. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. CERER FRVG. Ceres standing l., holding torch and two ears of corn. (C. 4, p. 10, No. 69.) <hi rend="italic">Plate VI</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>205. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. FORT REDVC. Fortuna standing l., holding rudder and cornucopiae. (C. 4, p. 21, No. 160, gives this <hi rend="italic">rev</hi>. with <hi rend="italic">obv</hi>. IMP II instead of COS II.) <hi rend="italic">Plate VI</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="45"/>
                  <p>206. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. FORTVN REDVC. Fortuna standing l., holding long palm and cornucopiae.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 22, No. 175, gives this <hi rend="italic">rev</hi>. with <hi rend="italic">obv</hi>. COS I.) <hi rend="italic">Plate VII</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>207, 208. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Same inscription. Fortuna seated l., holding branch and cornucopiae.</p>
                  <p>(No. 208 plated.)</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 23, No. 177.) <hi rend="italic">Plate VII</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>209. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. LIBERAL AVG. Liberalitas standing l., holding tessera and cornu-copiae.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 32, No. 283.) <hi rend="italic">Plate VII</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>210. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. LIR(sic) AVG. Liberalitas seated l., holding tessera and cornucopia.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Plate VII</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>211. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. MINER VICT. Minerva helmeted standing l., leaning on spear, l. hand at her side. <hi rend="italic">Plate VII</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>212-214. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. MONET AVG. Moneta standing l., holding scales and cornucopiae.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 37, No. 330.)</p>
                  <pb n="46"/>
                  <p>215. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. SAECVLL FELLCIT (Sic). Crescent with seven stars.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 66, No. 628, has SAECVLI FELICIT.) <hi rend="italic">Plate VII</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>216. IMP CAE L SEP SEV PERT AVG. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. VICTOR IVST AVG II COS (Sic). Victory l., holding wreath and palm. (C. 4, p. 77, No. 738, has VICT IVST AVG.) <hi rend="italic">Plate VII</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>195</p>
                  <p>217. L SEPT SEV PERT AVG IMP V. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. APOLLINI AVGVSTO. Apollo with long hair standing l., holding patera and lyre.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 8, No. 46.) <hi rend="italic">Plate VII</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>218, 219. IMP CAE L SEP SEV PERT AVG COS II. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. TRP III IMP V COS II. Captive seated r., on ground, arms bound; before him, shields, bow and quiver. (C. 4, p. 69, No. 661.) <hi rend="italic">Plate VII</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="47"/>
                  <p>196</p>
                  <p>220. L SEPT SEV PERT AVG IMP VIII. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. PM TRP V COS II PP. Pax seated l., holding olive branch and scepter. (C. 4, p. 47, No. 444.) <hi rend="italic">Plate VIII</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>198</p>
                  <p>221. L SEPT SEV AVG IMP XI PART MAX. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. CONCORDIAE MILITVM. Concordia standing l., holding standard in each hand.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 11, No. 78.) <hi rend="italic">Plate VIII</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">
                        <placeName>Rome</placeName>
                     </hi> 194</p>
                  <p>222. L SEPT SEV PERT AVG IMP IIII. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. SECVRITAS PVBLICA. Securitas seated l., holding a glove.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 67, No. 646.)</p>
                  <p>198-201</p>
                  <p>223. SEVERVS AVG PART MAX. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. RESTITVTOR VRBIS. Emperor standing l., sacrificing on lighted tripod, holding spear.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 63, No. 599.) <hi rend="italic">Plate VIII</hi>
                  </p>
               </div3>
               <div3 xml:id="d413e2837" type="subsection">
                  <pb n="48"/>
                  <head>
                     <persName>JULIA DOMNA</persName>
                     <hi rend="italic">DENARIVS</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">
                        <placeName>Antioch</placeName>
                     </hi> 193-196</p>
                  <p>224. IVLIA DOMNA AVG. Bust r., draped.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. VENERI VICT. Venus, half nude, r., holding palm and apple and leaning with l. elbow on column.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 121, No. 193 has VICTR.) <hi rend="italic">Plate VIII</hi>
                  </p>
               </div3>
               <div3 xml:id="d413e2860" type="subsection">
                  <head>
                     <persName>CARACALLA</persName>
                     <hi rend="italic">DENARIUS</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">
                        <placeName>Rome</placeName>
                     </hi> (?) 201</p>
                  <p>225. Inscription off flan. Head r., laur., bearded.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. P]M TRP IIII C[OS —. Fortuna standing l., holding rudder on globe and cornucopiae. <hi rend="italic">Plate VIII</hi>
                  </p>
               </div3>
               <div3 xml:id="d413e2879" type="subsection">
                  <head>
                     <persName>DIADUMENIANUS</persName>
                     <hi rend="italic">TETRADRACHM</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">
                        <placeName>Tyre</placeName>
                     </hi> 218</p>
                  <p>226. MOΠANTWNI. Bust r., bare, draped.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. ΔH[M]APXЄ[ΞOϒC]IAC. Eagle, head r., between legs, murex shell; beneath, club. <hi rend="italic">Plate VIII</hi>
                  </p>
               </div3>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d413e2898" type="section">
               <pb n="49"/>
               <head>HOARD IV</head>
               <div3 xml:id="d413e2902" type="subsection">
                  <head>
                     <persName>VITELLIUS</persName>
                     <hi rend="italic">DENARIUS</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">
                        <placeName>Rome</placeName> 69</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>1. A VITELLIVS GERM IMP AVG TRP. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. CONCORDIA PR. Concordia seated l., holding patera and cornucopiae. (<hi rend="italic">B.M.C</hi>., I, p. 371, No. 20. Pl. 60.27 <hi rend="italic">(obv.)</hi>, Pl. 60, 18, 19 <hi rend="italic">(rev</hi>. type).)</p>
               </div3>
               <div3 xml:id="d413e2928" type="subsection">
                  <head>
                     <persName>VESPASIAN</persName>
                     <hi rend="italic">DENARIUS</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">
                        <placeName>Rome</placeName>
                     </hi> 60-70</p>
                  <p>2. IMP CAESAR VESPASIANVS AVG. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. COS ITER FORT RED. Fortuna standing l., holding prow and cornucopiae.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">B.M.C</hi>., II, p. 2, Nos. 8, 9. Pl. 1.3.)</p>
               </div3>
               <div3 xml:id="d413e2950" type="subsection">
                  <head>
                     <persName>TRAJAN</persName>
                     <hi rend="italic">TRI DRACHM</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">
                        <placeName>Caesarea</placeName> 100</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>3. AϒTOKP KAIC NEP TPAIANOC CЄB ΓΕΡΜ. Bust r., laur., drapery at neck.</p>
                  <pb n="50"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. ΔΗΜΑΡΧЄΞΤΠΑϒΟΓ. Roma seated l., on cuirass and arms, holding Victory, and parazonium [9.41 gm.].</p>
                  <p>(Sydenham, <hi rend="italic">Numismatic Circular</hi>, Oct. 1930, col. 426, No. 180.) <hi rend="italic">Plate IX</hi>
                  </p>
               </div3>
               <div3 xml:id="d413e2975" type="subsection">
                  <head>
                     <hi rend="italic">DENARIUS</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">
                        <placeName>Rome</placeName>
                     </hi> 103-111</p>
                  <p>4. IMP TRAIANO AVG GER DAC PM TRP COS V PP. Bust r., laur., drapery on l. shoulder.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. SPQR OPTIMO PRINCIPI. Trophy.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 259, No. 226.)</p>
               </div3>
               <div3 xml:id="d413e2995" type="subsection">
                  <head>
                     <persName>HADRIAN</persName>
                     <hi rend="italic">DENARIUS</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">
                        <placeName>Rome</placeName>
                     </hi> 119-122</p>
                  <p>5. IMP CAESAR TRAIAN HADRIANVS AVG. Bust r., laur., drapery on l. shoulder.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. PM TRP COS III. Aeternitas standing l., holding heads of sun and moon.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 350, No. 81.) <hi rend="italic">Plate IX</hi>
                  </p>
               </div3>
               <div3 xml:id="d413e3019" type="subsection">
                  <pb n="51"/>
                  <head>
                     <persName>LUCIUS AELIUS</persName>
                     <hi rend="italic">DENARIUS</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">
                        <placeName>Rome</placeName>
                     </hi> 137</p>
                  <p>6. L AELIVS CAESAR. Head r., bare.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. TR POT COS II. Felicitas standing l., holding caduceus and cornucopiae.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 392, No. 430.) <hi rend="italic">Plate IX</hi>
                  </p>
               </div3>
               <div3 xml:id="d413e3044" type="subsection">
                  <head>
                     <persName>SABINA</persName>
                     <hi rend="italic">DENARIUS</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">
                        <placeName>Rome</placeName> 134-138</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>7. SABINA AVGVSTA. Bust r., hair in queue.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. VENERI GENETRICI. Venus standing r., drawing up robe over shoulder and holding apple.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., II, p. 387, No. 396. Pl. XIV, 287 <hi rend="italic">(rev.).) Plate IX</hi>
                  </p>
               </div3>
               <div3 xml:id="d413e3068" type="subsection">
                  <head>
                     <persName>ANTONINUS PIUS</persName>
                     <hi rend="italic">DENARII</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">
                        <placeName>Rome</placeName> 138</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>8. IMP T AEL CAES HADRI ANTONINVS. Head r., bare.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. AVG PIVS PM TRP COS DES II. Aequitas standing l., holding scales and cornucopiae.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 26, No. 10.)</p>
                  <pb n="52"/>
                  <p>140-143</p>
                  <p>9. ANTONINUS AVG PIVS PP TRP COS III. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. AEQVITAS AVG. Aequitas standing l., holding scales and rod.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 33, No. 61.)</p>
                  <p>145-161</p>
                  <p>10. ANTONINVS AVG PIVS PP. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. COS IIII. Clasped hands holding caduceus and corn ears.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 43, No. 136.) <hi rend="italic">Plate IX</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>149, 150</p>
                  <p>11. ANTONINVS AVG PIVS PP TRP XII. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. COS IIII. Aequitas standing l., holding scales and cornucopiae.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 48, No. 77.) <hi rend="italic">Plate IX</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>150, 151</p>
                  <p>12. IMP CAES T AEL HADR ANTONINVS AVG PIVS PP. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. TR POT XIIII COS IIII. Tranquilinas standing r., holding rudder and corn ears, TRANQ (in ex.).</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 51, No. 202.) <hi rend="italic">Plate IX</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="53"/>
                  <p>153, 154</p>
                  <p>13. ANTONINVS AVG PIVS PP TRP XVII. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. COS IIII. Annona standing l., holding corn ears and setting l. hand on modius set on ship.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 54, No. 231. Pl. II, 42.)</p>
                  <p>155, 156</p>
                  <p>14. ANTONINVS AVG PIVS PP TRP XIX. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. TR POT XIX COS IIII. Fortuna standing r., holding rudder on globe and cornucopiae.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 56, No. 251.)</p>
                  <p>159, 160</p>
                  <p>15, 16. ANTONINVS AVG PIVS PP TRP XXII. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. VOTA SVSCEPTA DEC III. Antoninus standing l., sacrificing from patera over tripod. COS IIII (in ex.).</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 62, No. 294.) <hi rend="italic">Plate X</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>After 161</p>
                  <p>17. DIVVS ANTONINVS. Head r., bare.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. CONSECRATIO. Eagle standing r., head 1.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 247, No. 429. Pl. IX, 186 <hi rend="italic">(rev.).) Plate X</hi>
                  </p>
               </div3>
               <div3 xml:id="d413e3209" type="subsection">
                  <pb n="54"/>
                  <head>
                     <persName>FAUSTINA SENIOR</persName>
                     <hi rend="italic">DENARIUS</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">
                        <placeName>Rome</placeName>
                     </hi> After 141</p>
                  <p>18. DIVA FAVSTINA. Bust r., draped.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. CERES. Ceres standing l., veiled, holding corn ears and torch.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 72, No. 378.)</p>
               </div3>
               <div3 xml:id="d413e3233" type="subsection">
                  <head>
                     <persName>MARCUS AURELIUS</persName>
                     <hi rend="italic">TETRADRACHM</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">
                        <placeName>Antioch</placeName>
                     </hi> 177</p>
                  <p>19. AϒTOKP ANTΩNЄNOC CЄB. Bust r., laur., in cuirass.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. ΔΗΜΑΡΧ[ЄΞ]TO ΛΑϒΠΑΤΟ. Eagle, head l., on leg and thigh of animal. [12.05 gm.].</p>
                  <p>(Cf. <hi rend="italic">B.M.C</hi>., Galatia, etc., p. 192, No. 343.) Mistakenly read as AI instead of ΛΓ Cf. Pl. XXIII, 5, and R.N., 32 (1929), p. 24. <hi rend="italic">Plate X</hi>
                  </p>
               </div3>
               <div3 xml:id="d413e3257" type="subsection">
                  <head>
                     <hi rend="italic">DENARII</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">
                        <placeName>Rome</placeName>
                     </hi> 169, 170</p>
                  <p>20. M ANTONINVS AVG TRP XXIIII. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. COS III. Minerva standing r., hurling javelin and holding shield.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 229, No. 211.)</p>
                  <pb n="55"/>
                  <p>172, 173</p>
                  <p>21. Μ ANTONINVS AVG TRP XXVII. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. IMP VI COS III. Aequitas standing l., holding scales and cornucopiae.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 234, No. 271.)</p>
                  <p>177, 178</p>
                  <p>22. M AVREL ANTONINVS AVG. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. TRP XXXII IMP VIIII COS III PP. Mars standing r., holding spear, l. hand on shield.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 243, No. 284.)</p>
                  <p>23. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Same inscription. Annona standing l., holding two corn ears and cornucopiae; on l. modius, on r. ship.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 243, No. 390 has modius <hi rend="italic">r</hi>. ship <hi rend="italic">I</hi>.) <hi rend="italic">Plate X</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>After 180</p>
                  <p>24. DIVVS M ANTONINVS PIVS. Head r., bare.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. CONSECRATIO. Eagle standing r. on bar.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 398, No. 265.) <hi rend="italic">Plate X</hi>
                  </p>
               </div3>
               <div3 xml:id="d413e3339" type="subsection">
                  <pb n="56"/>
                  <head>
                     <persName>FAUSTINA JUNIOR</persName>
                     <hi rend="italic">DENARII</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">
                        <placeName>ROME</placeName>
                     </hi> After 145</p>
                  <p>25. FAVSTINA AVGVSTA. Bust r., draped.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. AVGVSTI PII FIL. Venus standing l., holding Victory and resting l. hand on shield set on helmet.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 93, No. 495. Pl. IV, 90 <hi rend="italic">(rev.).)</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>After 161</p>
                  <p>26. FAVSTINA AVGVSTA. Bust r., draped.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. VESTA. Vesta, veiled, seated l., holding palladium and scepter.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 272, No. 737.) <hi rend="italic">Plate X</hi>
                  </p>
               </div3>
               <div3 xml:id="d413e3379" type="subsection">
                  <head>
                     <persName>LUCILLA</persName>
                     <hi rend="italic">DENARIUS</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">
                        <placeName>ROME</placeName>
                     </hi> 164-180</p>
                  <p>27. LVCILLA AVGVSTA. Bust r., draped.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. PVDICITIA. Pudicitia seated l., veiled, r. hand on breast.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 276, No. 781.) <hi rend="italic">Plate XI</hi>
                  </p>
               </div3>
               <div3 xml:id="d413e3403" type="subsection">
                  <pb n="57"/>
                  <head>
                     <persName>COMMODUS</persName>
                     <hi rend="italic">DENARII</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">
                        <placeName>Rome</placeName>
                     </hi> 179</p>
                  <p>28. L AVREL COMMODVS AVG. Head r., laur., unbearded.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. TRP IIII IMP III COS II PP. Victory seated l., holding patera and palm.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 268, No. 666.) <hi rend="italic">Plate XI</hi> 183, 4</p>
                  <p>29. M COMMODVS ANTON AVG PIVS.</p>
                  <p>Head r., laur., bearded.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. TRP VIIII IMP VI COS IIII PP. Minerva advancing r., brandishing javelin and holding shield; at feet, owl.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 374, No. 82.) <hi rend="italic">Plate XI</hi> 186</p>
                  <p>30. M COMM ANT P FEL AVG BRIT. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. PM TRP XI IMP VII COS V PP. Fortuna seated l., holding rudder on globe and cornucopiae; wheel under seat. FOR RED (in ex.).</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 380, No. 131.)</p>
                  <pb n="58"/>
                  <p>186-189</p>
                  <p>31. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. OPTIME MAXIME. Jupiter standing l., holding thunderbolt and scepter. CVPP (in ex.).</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 387, No. 192. Pl. XIV, 292 <hi rend="italic">(rev.).)</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>190</p>
                  <p>32. M COMM ANT P FEL AVG BRIT PP. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. LIB AVG PM TRP XV COS VI. Libertas standing l., holding pileus and rod.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 389, No. 208.)</p>
                  <p>190, 1</p>
                  <p>33. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. ROM FEL PM TRP XVI COS VI. Roma seated l., holding Victory and spear.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 391, No. 224.)</p>
                  <p>191</p>
                  <p>34. L AEL AVREL COMM AVG P FEL. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. PM TRP XVII IMP VIII COS VI PP. Fides standing l., holding scepter and cornucopiae; star in field, r.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 392, No. 234.)</p>
                  <pb n="59"/>
                  <p>192</p>
                  <p>35. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. PM TRP XVII IMP VIII COS VII PP. Pietas seated l., extending hand to child and holding transverse scepter; star in field, l.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 393, No. 236. Pl. XV, 307 (<hi rend="italic">rev</hi>.).)</p>
                  <p>191, 2</p>
                  <p>36. Same inscription. Head r., in lion's skin.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. HERCVL ROMAN AVGV. Club in wreath.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 395, No. 251.) <hi rend="italic">Plate XI</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>37. Same inscription. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. SERAPIDI CONSERV AVG. Serapis, radiate, standing front, head l., holding branch and scepter.</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">R.I.C</hi>., III, p. 397, No. 261. Pl. XV, 312 (<hi rend="italic">rev</hi>.).)</p>
               </div3>
               <div3 xml:id="d413e3560" type="subsection">
                  <head>
                     <persName>PESCENNIUS NIGER</persName>
                     <hi rend="italic">DENARIUS</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">
                        <placeName>Antioch</placeName>
                     </hi> 193</p>
                  <p>38. IMP C PESC NIGER IVS AVG COS II. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. MONETAE AVG. Moneta standing l., with modius on her head, holding scales and cornucopiae.</p>
                  <pb n="60"/>
                  <p>(C. 3, p. 411, No. 55 has this <hi rend="italic">obv</hi>., No. 56 has this <hi rend="italic">rev.) Plate XI</hi>
                  </p>
               </div3>
               <div3 xml:id="d413e3585" type="subsection">
                  <head>
                     <persName>SEPTIMIUS SEVERUS</persName>
                     <hi rend="italic">TETRADRACHMS</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">
                        <placeName>Antioch</placeName>
                     </hi> 202</p>
                  <p>39, 40. AϒT KAI CЄOϒHPOC CЄ. Bust r., laur., wearing paludamentum.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. ΔΗΜΑΡΧ ЄΞ ϒΠATOC ΤΟΓ. Eagle, head l., between legs, star. [11.97, 11. 43 gm.]</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">B.M.C</hi>., Galatia, etc., p. 193, No. 347. Pl. XXIII, 9 <hi rend="italic">(obv.).) Plate XI</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>41, 42. Same inscription. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Same. [12.25, 11.15 gm.]</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">B.M.C</hi>., Galatia, etc., p. 193, No. 349.) <hi rend="italic">Plate XII</hi>
                  </p>
               </div3>
               <div3 xml:id="d413e3622" type="subsection">
                  <head>
                     <hi rend="italic">DENARII</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">
                        <placeName>Antioch</placeName> 193</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>43. IMP CAE L SEP SEV PERT AVG COS I. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. FORTVN REDVC. Fortuna standing l., wearing modius and holding rudder and cornucopiae.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 22, No. 174.)</p>
                  <pb n="61"/>
                  <p>44, 45. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Same inscription. Fortuna standing l., wearing modius and holding palm and cornucopiae.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 22, No. 175.)</p>
                  <p>46. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. VIRT AVG TRP COS. Roma standing l., holding Victory and reversed spear.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 78, No. 752 has <hi rend="italic">obv</hi>. without COS I.) <hi rend="italic">Plate XI</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>47. L SEPT SEV PERT AVG IMP I. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. INVICTO IMP. Trophy at foot of which spear and helmet to l., two spears and two shields to r.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 28, No. 230 has this <hi rend="italic">obv</hi>., No. 232 has this <hi rend="italic">rev.)</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>194</p>
                  <p>48. IMP CAE L SEPT SEV PERT AVG COS</p>
                  <p>II. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. BONAE SPEI. Spes l., holding flower and raising skirt.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 9, No. 61.) <hi rend="italic">Plate XII</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>49. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. CERER FRVG. Ceres standing l., wearing modius, holding two ears of wheat and torch.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 10, No. 69.) <hi rend="italic">Plate XII</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="62"/>
                  <p>50. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. FORTVNA REDVC. Fortuna standing l. before lighted altar holding patera and cornucopiae.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 24, No. 185.)</p>
                  <p>51. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. FORTVN REDVC. Fortuna standing l., wearing modius and holding rudder and cornucopiae.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 22, No. 174, has this <hi rend="italic">rev</hi>., No. 177 has this <hi rend="italic">obv.) Plate XII</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>52, 53. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. INVICTO IMP. Trophy at foot of which spear and helmet to l., two spears and two shields to r.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 28, No. 232.)</p>
                  <p>54.<ref target="#CH1-n4">
                        <hi rend="sup">1</hi>
                     </ref> Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. LEG XIIII GEM M V. Legionary eagle, with collar around the neck, between two standards. TRP COS (in ex.). Broken.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 32, No. 274.)</p>
                  <p>55. IMP CAE L SEP SEV PERT AVG COS II.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. MARTI VICTOR. Mars nude walking r., carrying spear and trophy.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 37, No. 324, has on <hi rend="italic">obv</hi>. CA for CAE; PER for PERT and on
<pb n="63"/>
                     <hi rend="italic">rev</hi>. MART for MARTI (only the bottom of the I is here preserved).) <hi rend="italic">Plate XII</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>56-58. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. MONET AVG. Moneta standing l., holding scales and cornucopiae.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 37, No. 330.) <hi rend="italic">Plate XII</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>59. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. MONETA II AVG. Moneta wearing modius seated l., holding scales and cornucopiae.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 39, No. 346.) <hi rend="italic">Plate XIII</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>60. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. SPQR OPTIMO PRINCIPI. <persName>Severus</persName> on horseback 1.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 68, No. 652.) <hi rend="italic">Plate XIII</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>61. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. SAECVLI FELICIT. Crescent and seven stars.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 66, No. 628.) <hi rend="italic">Plate XIII</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>62. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. VICT AVG. Victory l., holding wreath and palm.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 70, No. 675 has on <hi rend="italic">obv</hi>. VC (sic) for AVG.)</p>
                  <p>63. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. VIRT AVG TRP II COS II PP. Roma standing l., holding Victory and reversed spear.</p>
                  <pb n="64"/>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 78, No. 755 has this <hi rend="italic">rev</hi>. with <hi rend="italic">obv</hi>. IMP III.)</p>
                  <p>64. L SEPT SEV PERT AVG IMP IIII. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. PM TRP II COS II PP. Pallas standing l., holding shield and transverse spear.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 42, No. 381.)</p>
                  <p>194, 195</p>
                  <p>65. IMP CAEL SEPT SEV PERT AVG. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. APOLLINI AVGVSTO. Apollo l., holding patera and lyre.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 47, No. 43.) <hi rend="italic">Plate XIII</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>195</p>
                  <p>66. L SEPT SEV PERT AVG IMP VII. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. ARAB ADIAB COS II PP. Victory l., with wreath and palm.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 8, No. 50.)</p>
                  <p>196</p>
                  <p>67. L SEPT SEV PERT AVG IMP VIII. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. VICTOR AVG. Victory walking l., holding branch.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 73, No. 699 has Victory holding wreath and palm.) <hi rend="italic">Plate XIII</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="65"/>
                  <p>198</p>
                  <p>68. L SEPT SEV AVG IMP XI PART MAX. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. MONETA AVG. Moneta seated l., holding scales and cornucopiae.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 39, No. 345.) <hi rend="italic">Plate XIII</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>69. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. AEQVITATI AVGG. Aequitas standing l., holding scales and cornucopiae.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 6, No. 21.)</p>
                  <p>70. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. COS II PP. Victory l., holding wreath and palm.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 13, No. 100 has COS III.) <hi rend="italic">Plate XIII</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>71. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. VICT PARTHICAE. Victory l., holding wreath and trophy, at her feet, Parthian seated.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 77, No. 741.) <hi rend="italic">Plate XIII</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>72. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. VICTORIAE AVGG FEL. Victory flying l., with diadem on both sides; before her, shield on column lying on its side.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 75, No. 719.) <hi rend="italic">Plate XIII</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="66"/>
                  <p>73. L SEP SEVERVS PER AVG PM IMP XI. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. VICT AVGG COS II PP. Victory l., with wreath and palm.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 72, No. 695.)</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">
                        <placeName>Rome</placeName>
                     </hi> 194</p>
                  <p>74. L SEPT SEV PERT AVG IMP II. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. MART VICTOR. Mars walking r., holding spear and trophy.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 37, No. 323.)</p>
                  <p>75. L SEPT SEV PERT AVG IMP III. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. LIBERO PATRI. Bacchus nude standing l., panther skin behind him, holding jug and thyrsus; at his feet, panther.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 34, No. 301.) <hi rend="italic">Plate XIV</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>196</p>
                  <p>76. L SEPT SEV PERT AVG IMP VIII. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. ADVENTVI AVG FELICISSIMO. <persName>Severus</persName> on horseback r., raising r. hand.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 4, No. 6.) <hi rend="italic">Plate XIV</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="67"/>
                  <p>77. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. INDVLGENTIA AVG. Indulgentia seated l., with patera and scepter.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 26, No. 216.)</p>
                  <p>78. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. MVNIFICENTIA AVG. Elephant r. (C. 4, p. 39, No. 348.)</p>
                  <p>79, 80. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. PM TRP IIII COS II PP. Pax seated l., holding olive branch and scepter.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 46, No. 429.)</p>
                  <p>81, 82. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. VOTA PVBLICA. <persName>Severus</persName> veiled standing l., sacrificing over burning altar.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 80, No. 777.)</p>
                  <p>197</p>
                  <p>83–85. L SEPT SEV PERT AVG IMP VIII. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. PM TRP V COS II PP. Fortuna standing l., holding rudder on globe and cornucopiae.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 47, No. 442.)</p>
                  <p>86. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Same inscription. Genius standing l. by lighted altar, sacrificing with l.
<pb n="68"/>
hand from patera and holding corn ears.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 46, No. 437.)</p>
                  <p>87. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Same inscription. Sol, radiate, standing l., raising r. hand and holding whip.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 46, No. 433.) <hi rend="italic">Plate XIV</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>88. L SEPT SEV PERT AVG IMP X. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. LIBERO PATRI. Bacchus nude l., crowning himself and holding thyrsus; at his feet, panther.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 35, No. 305.) <hi rend="italic">Plate XIV</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>89. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. MARTI PACIFERO. Mars standing l., foot on cuirass, holding olive branch and reversed spear.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 36, No. 315.)</p>
                  <p>90-94. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. PACI AETERNAE. Pax seated l., holding olive branch and scepter.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 40, No. 357.)</p>
                  <p>95. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. SALVTI AVGG. Salus seated l., feeding from patera snake around altar.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 67, No. 641.)</p>
                  <pb n="69"/>
                  <p>96. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Same, but back of throne is formed by two cornucopiae. <hi rend="italic">Plate XIV</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>97. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. VICT AVGG COS II PP. Victory l., with wreath and palm.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 72, No. 694.) <hi rend="italic">Plate XIV</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>198-201</p>
                  <p>98. SEVERVS PIVS AVG. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. FVNDATOR PACIS. <persName>Severus</persName> veiled standing l., holding olive branch and book.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 25, No. 205.) <hi rend="italic">Plate XIV</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>99. SEVERVS AVG PART MAX. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Same.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 25, No. 203.) <hi rend="italic">Plate XIV</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>100. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. VIRT AVGG. Roma, helmeted, standing l., holding Victory and leaning on shield and spear.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 79, No. 761.)</p>
                  <p>200</p>
                  <p>101, 102. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. PM TRP VIII COS II PP. Victory flying l. with diadem in both hands;
<pb n="70"/>
before her, shield on column lying on its side.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 48, No. 457.) <hi rend="italic">Plate XV</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>201</p>
                  <p>103. SEVERVS PIVS AVG. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. VICTORIAE AVGG. Victory in a biga galloping r.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 74, No. 713.) <hi rend="italic">Plate XV</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>104. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. LIBERALITAS AVG. Liberalitas standing l., holding tessera and cornucopiae.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 33, No. 292.)</p>
                  <p>210</p>
                  <p>105. SEVERVS PIVS AVG. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. PMTRPXVIIICOSIII PP. Between the infants <persName>Caracalla</persName> and Geta, Jupiter standing l., his mantle behind him, holding thunderbolt and scepter.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 57, No. 539.) <hi rend="italic">Plate XV</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>211</p>
                  <p>106. SEVERVS PIVS AVG BRIT. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. PM TRP XIX COS III PP. Same type.</p>
                  <pb n="71"/>
                  <p>(C. gives this type only for 209, 210 and 211.) <hi rend="italic">Plate XV</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Uncertain date</p>
                  <p>107. L SEP SEV PERT A[VG. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. LIBER —. Liberalitas standing l. with tessera and cornucopiae.</p>
                  <p>108. IMP CAE L SEP SE PER. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. MONETA. Moneta standing l., holding scales and cornucopiae.</p>
                  <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n4">
                     <seg type="note-symbol">
                        <hi rend="sup">1</hi>
                     </seg>
                     <p>This may be <placeName>Rome</placeName>.</p>
                  </note>
               </div3>
               <div3 xml:id="d413e4217" type="subsection">
                  <head>
                     <persName>JULIA DOMNA</persName>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">
                        <placeName>Antioch</placeName>
                     </hi> 193-196</p>
                  <p>109. IVLIA DOMNA AVG. Bust r., draped</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. LIBERAL AVG. Liberalitas standing l., holding tessera and cornucopia.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 114, No. 103.)</p>
                  <p>110. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. VENER VICTOR. Venus standing l., r. hand raised, holding scepter with l. <hi rend="italic">Plate XV</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>196</p>
                  <p>111. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. VENERI VICTR. Venus, half nude, r., holding palm and apple and leaning with l. elbow on column. (C. 4, p. 121, No. 194.) <hi rend="italic">Plate XV</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="72"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">
                        <placeName>Rome</placeName> 196</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>112. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Same. (Perhaps <placeName>Antioch</placeName>.) <hi rend="italic">Plate XV</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>196-211</p>
                  <p>113. IVLIA AVGVSTA. Bust r., draped.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. CERERI FRVGIF. Ceres seated l., holding corn ears and torch.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 107, No. 14.) <hi rend="italic">Plate XV</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>114. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. DIANA LVCIFERA. Diana standing l., crescent behind neck, holding torch in both hands.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 108, No. 27.)</p>
                  <p>115. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. HILÁRITAS. Hilaritas standing l., holding long palm and cornucopiae.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 112, No. 72.)</p>
                  <p>116. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. IVNO. Juno standing l., holding long palm and cornucopiae.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 113, No. 82.) Perhaps <placeName>Antioch</placeName>. <hi rend="italic">Plate XV</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>117. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. IVNO REGINA. Juno standing l., veiled, holding patera and scepter: at her feet, peacock.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 113, No. 97.)</p>
                  <pb n="73"/>
                  <p>118, 119. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. MATER DEVM. Cybele, turreted, seated l. between two lions, holding branch and scepter, her l. elbow resting on tympanum.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 115, No. 123.) <hi rend="italic">Plate XVI</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>120. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. PIETAS PVBLICA. Pietas, veiled, standing l. before flaming altar, raising both hands.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 118, No. 156.)</p>
                  <p>121. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. PVDICITIA. Pudicitia seated l., r. hand on her breast.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 119, No. 168.) Perhaps <placeName>Antioch</placeName>. <hi rend="italic">Plate XVI</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>122. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. SAECVLI FELICITAS. Isis standing r., her foot on prow, nourishing Horus; behind her an altar with a rudder against it.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 119, No. 174.)</p>
                  <p>123. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. VENERI GENETRICI. Venus standing l., with patera and scepter.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 121, No. 185.) <hi rend="italic">Plate XVI</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="74"/>
                  <p>124-126. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. VENVS FELIX. Venus standing half l. holding apple and drawing robe from shoulder.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 122, No. 198.) <hi rend="italic">Plate XVI</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>127. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. VESTAE SANCTAE. Vesta standing l., holding patera and scepter.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 126, No. 246.) <hi rend="italic">Plate XVI</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>198-217</p>
                  <p>128. IVLIA PIA FELIX AVG. Bust r., draped.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. DIANA LVCIFERA. Diana standing l., holding torch in both hands.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 108, No. 32.)</p>
                  <p>211, 212</p>
                  <p>129. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. MAT AVGG MAT SEN M PATR. <persName>Julia</persName> seated l., holding corn ears and scepter. Broken.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 114, No. 111.) <hi rend="italic">Plate XVI</hi>
                  </p>
               </div3>
               <div3 xml:id="d413e4419" type="subsection">
                  <head>
                     <persName>CARACALLA</persName>
                     <hi rend="italic">TETRADRACHMS</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">
                        <placeName>Antioch</placeName>
                     </hi> 208</p>
                  <p>130-133. AϒT KAI ANTΩNЄINOC CЄ B. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <pb n="75"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. ΔΗΜΑΡΧЄΞΤΠΑϒΟΓ TOC TO Γ. Eagle on leg and thigh of animal; head r. [13.68, 12.9, 10.42, 10.37 gm.]</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">B.M.C</hi>., Galatia, etc., p. 194, No. 359 has ϒΠΑΤΟ Γ.) <hi rend="italic">Plate XVI</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>134-137. AϒT KAI ANTΩNЄINOC CЄ. Bust r., laur., wearing paludamentum.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Same inscription. Eagle, head 1.; between legs, star. [12.82, 10.85, 10.77, 10.37 gm.]</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">(B.M.C.y</hi> Galatia, etc., p. 194, No. 360 has TIIATOC Γ.) <hi rend="italic">Plate XVI</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>138. AϒT KAI ANTΩNЄINOC CЄ B. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Same inscription. Eagle, head r.; to l. and r., stars. [10.98 gm.] <hi rend="italic">Plate XVII</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>213</p>
                  <p>139. AϒT KMA ANTΩNЄINOC CЄB. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. ΔΗΜΑΡΧЄΞϒΠΑΤΟ Δ. Eagle, head r. on leg and thigh of animal. [7.85 gm. badly corroded.]</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">B.M.C</hi>., Galatia, etc., p. 195, No. 361 has Eagle, head 1.)</p>
                  <p>140. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. ΔΗΜΑΡΧЄΞϒΠΑTOC TO Δ. Eagle, head l., between legs, star. [8.65 gm.]</p>
                  <pb n="76"/>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">B.M.C</hi>., Galatia, etc., p. 195, No. 364.) <hi rend="italic">Plate XVII</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>141, 142. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. ΔΗΜΑΡΧЄΞϒΠΑΤΟ Δ. Eagle on thunderbolt, head r. [10.42, 7.5 gm. both badly corroded.]</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">
                        <placeName>Beroea</placeName> 213</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>143. AϒTK MAϒ ΑΝΤΩΝЄΙΝΟC CЄB. Bust r., laur., in cuirass and paludamentum.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. ΔΗΜΑΡΧЄΞϒΠΑTOC TO Δ. Eagle, head 1.; between legs BЄ and fantastic bird. [7.25 gm.] <hi rend="italic">Plate XVII</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">
                        <placeName>Tyre</placeName>
                     </hi> 208</p>
                  <p>144. AϒT KAI ANTWNINOC CЄ. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. ΔΗΜΑΡΧЄΞϒΠΑTOC TO Γ. Eagle on club (handle to 1.) head 1.; between legs, murex shell. [11.6 gm.]</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">B.M.C</hi>., Phoenicia, p. 304, No. 36, Pl. XXXVII, 3.) <hi rend="italic">Plate XVII</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">Uncertain Mint 213</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>145. AϒTK MAϒ ΑΝΤΩΝЄΙΝΟC CЄB. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. ΔΗΜΑΡΧЄΞϒΠΑTOC TO Δ. Eagle, head l., on torch entwined by serpent. [8.07 gm. badly corroded.]</p>
                  <pb n="77"/>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">B.M.C</hi>., Galatia, etc., p. 197, No. 378. Cf. <placeName>Dura</placeName>
                     <hi rend="italic">Hoard</hi> I, Nos. 17, 18.)</p>
               </div3>
               <div3 xml:id="d413e4550" type="subsection">
                  <head>
                     <hi rend="italic">DENARII</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">
                        <placeName>Antioch</placeName>
                     </hi> 197</p>
                  <p>146. M AVR ANTON CAES PONTIF. Young bust r., bare, draped.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. SECVRITAS PERPETVA. Pallas standing l., leaning on shield and holding reversed spear.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 202, No. 566.) <hi rend="italic">Plate XVII</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>198</p>
                  <p>147. IMP CAE M AVR ANT AVG P TRP. Young bust r., draped, laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. SPES PVBLICA. Spes walking l., holding flower and lifting skirt.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 205, No. 599.) <hi rend="italic">Plate XVIII</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>210</p>
                  <p>148. ANTONINVS PIVS AVG BRIT. Head, bearded, r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. MARTI PROPVGANATORI (Sic). Mars rushing l., holding spear and trophy. <hi rend="italic">Plate XVII</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>149. ANTONINVS PIVS AVG. Head bearded, r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. VICTORIAE BRIT. Victory walking
<pb n="78"/>
r., holding trophy in both hands.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 209, No. 629 has <hi rend="italic">obv</hi>. ANTONINVS PIVS AVG BRIT.)</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Plate XVIII</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">
                        <placeName>Rome</placeName>
                     </hi> 196, 7</p>
                  <p>150. M AVR ANTONINVS CAES. Young bust r., bare, draped.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. SECVRITAS PERPETVA. Pallas standing l. leaning on shield and holding reversed spear.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 202, No. 562.) <hi rend="italic">Plate XVIII</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>197</p>
                  <p>151. M AVR ANTON CAES PONTIF. Young bust r., bare, draped.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. DESTINATO IMPERATORE. Lituus, cap, bucranium and sprinkler.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 147, No. 53.) <hi rend="italic">Plate XVIII</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>152, 153. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. SAECVLI FELICITAS. Felicitas standing l., holding caduceus.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 201, No. 557, a defective specimen.) <hi rend="italic">Plate XVIII</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>154, 155. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. SECVRITAS PERPETVA. Pallas standing l., leaning on shield and holding reversed spear.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 202, No. 566.) <hi rend="italic">Plate XVIII</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="79"/>
                  <p>200</p>
                  <p>156. ANTONINVS AVGVSTVS. Young bust r., draped, laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. PONTIF TRP III. Sol (?) standing l., holding globe and reversed spear.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 186, No. 413.) <hi rend="italic">Plate XVIII</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>201</p>
                  <p>157. ANTONINVS PIVS AVG. Young bust r., draped, laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. PART MAX PONT TRP IIII. Trophy between two captives seated on the ground.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 162, No. 175.)</p>
                  <p>201-204</p>
                  <p>158, 159. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. FELICITAS AVGG. Felicitas standing l., holding caduceus and cornucopiae.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 148, No. 64.) No. 158 is perhaps from <placeName>Antioch</placeName>. <hi rend="italic">Plates XVIII</hi> and <hi rend="italic">XIX</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>160. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. VIRTVS AVGG. Mars standing l., holding Victory and reversed spear. (C. 4, p. 212, No. 667.)</p>
                  <pb n="80"/>
                  <p>161. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. INDVLGENTIA AVGG. Goddess of Carthage, holding thunderbolt and scepter seated on lion leaping r., behind, rock from which water issues. IN CARTH (in ex.).</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 153, No. 97.) <hi rend="italic">Plate XIX</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>203</p>
                  <p>162. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. IIII LIBERALITAS AVGG. Liberalitas standing l. with tessera and cornucopiae.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 156, No. 122.) <hi rend="italic">Plate XIX</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>206</p>
                  <p>163. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. PONTIF TRP VIIII COS II. Mars standing l., leaning on shield and holding spear.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 187, No. 424.)</p>
                  <p>210</p>
                  <p>164. Same inscription. Head, bearded, r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. PONTIF TRP XIII COS III. Concordia seated l. beside altar, holding cornucopiae.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 194, No. 485 has <hi rend="italic">obv</hi>. ANTONINVS PIVS AVG BRIT.) <hi rend="italic">Plate XIX</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="81"/>
                  <p>165. ANTONINVS PIVS AVG BRIT. Head, bearded, r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. MARTI PROPVGNATORI. Mars rushing l., holding spear and trophy. (C. 4, p. 160, No. 150.) <hi rend="italic">Plate XIX</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>166. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. MONETA AVG. Moneta standing l., holding scales and cornucopiae. (C. 4, p. 161, No. 165.)</p>
                  <p>212</p>
                  <p>167. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. PM TRP XV COS III PP. Salus seated l., holding cornucopiae and feeding snake around altar.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 166, No. 206.) <hi rend="italic">Plate XIX</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>168. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. PM TRP XVI COS IIII PP. Hercules, nude, standing l., holding olive branch and club with lion's skin.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 165, No. 196.) <hi rend="italic">Plate XIX</hi>
                  </p>
               </div3>
               <div3 xml:id="d413e4793" type="subsection">
                  <head>
                     <persName>PLAUTILLA</persName>
                     <hi rend="italic">DENARII</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">
                        <placeName>Rome</placeName> 202-212</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>169. PLAVTILLAE AVGVSTAE. Bust r., draped.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. CONCORDIAE. Concordia seated l., holding patera and cornucopiae. (C. 4, p. 247, No. 6.)</p>
                  <pb n="82"/>
                  <p>170. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. CONCORDIAE AETERNAE. Plautilla r., giving her hand to <persName>Caracalla</persName> 1.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 247, No. 10.) <hi rend="italic">Plate XIX</hi>
                  </p>
               </div3>
               <div3 xml:id="d413e4824" type="subsection">
                  <head>
                     <persName>GETA</persName>
                     <hi rend="italic">TETRADRACHMS</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">
                        <placeName>Antioch</placeName>
                     </hi> 208</p>
                  <p>171, 172. AϒT KAI ΓЄTAC CЄ. Bust r., laur., in cuirass and paludamentum.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. ΔΗΜΑΡΧЄΞΠΑTOC TO B. Eagle, head l.; between legs, star. [11.2, 11. 15 gm.] <hi rend="italic">Plate XX</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>173. AϒT KAI ΓЄTAC CЄΒ. Head r., laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. ΔΗΜΑΡΧЄΞϒΠΑTOC TO Β. Eagle, head r., to l. and r. stars. [9.47 gm.] <hi rend="italic">Plate XX</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">
                        <persName>Tyre</persName>
                     </hi> 208</p>
                  <p>174, 175. Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Same inscription. Eagle on club (handle to 1.) head r.; between legs, murex shell. [13.0, 9.08 gm.]</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">B.M.C</hi>., Phoenicia, p. 305, No. 42 has <hi rend="italic">obv</hi>. bust r.) <hi rend="italic">Plate XX</hi>
                  </p>
               </div3>
               <div3 xml:id="d413e4872" type="subsection">
                  <pb n="83"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi rend="italic">DENARII</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">
                        <placeName>Rome</placeName> 198-209</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>176. L SEPTIMIVS GETA CAES. Bust r., bare.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. FELICITAS TEMPOR. Felicitas standing l. with caduceus and cornucopiae.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 258, No. 44.) Perhaps <placeName>Antioch</placeName>, C. says "Fabrique orientale." <hi rend="italic">Plate XX</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>177. P SEPT GETA CAES PONT. Bust r., bare.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. PRINC IVVENTVTIS. Geta l., holding branch and spear, behind him trophy with shield at its base. (C. 4, p. 270, No. 157.) <hi rend="italic">Plate XX</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>208</p>
                  <p>178. P SEPTIMIVS GETA CAES. Bust r., bare, draped.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. PONTIF COS II. Geta standing l., holding globe and parazonium. Broken.</p>
                  <p>(C. 4, p. 265, No. 117.)</p>
               </div3>
               <div3 xml:id="d413e4914" type="subsection">
                  <pb n="84"/>
                  <head>
                     <persName>MACRINUS</persName>
                     <hi rend="italic">TETRADRACHMS</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">
                        <placeName>Antioch</placeName>
                     </hi> 218</p>
                  <p>179. AϒT K MOΠCЄ MAKPINOC CЄB. Bust r., wearing cuirass and paludamentum.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. ΔΗΜΑΡΧЄΞϒΠΑΤΟ. Eagle on leg and thigh, head r., in field, to l. and r. Δ@. [10.85 gm.]</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">B.M.C</hi>., Galatia, etc., p. 199, No. 393 has a variant of the <hi rend="italic">obv</hi>. inscription.) <hi rend="italic">Plate XX</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">
                        <placeName>Aradus</placeName> 218</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>180. AϒT M O CЄ MAKPINOC CЄB. Bust r., draped, laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Same inscription. Eagle head r., between legs head of humped bull. [6.25 gm. badly corroded.]</p>
                  <p>(<placeName>Dura</placeName>, <hi rend="italic">Hoard I</hi>, No. 8.)</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">
                        <placeName>Mopsus</placeName> 218</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>181. AϒT ΜΟΠ CЄ MAKPINOC CЄB. Bust r., draped, laur.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">Rev</hi>. Same inscription. Eagle head l., between legs, altar. [8.75 gm. badly corroded.]</p>
                  <p>(<hi rend="italic">B.M.C</hi>., Galatia, etc., p. 199, No. 397 has variants of the inscriptions. <placeName>Dura</placeName>, <hi rend="italic">Hoard I</hi>, No. 14.)</p>
               </div3>
            </div2>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n1">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">1</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>The two hoards unearthed in the Campaign of 1928–29 have already been published in this series. <hi rend="italic">(Two Roman Hoards from <placeName>Dura-Europos</placeName>
                  </hi>, Numismatic Notes and Monographs No. 49, 1931.)</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n2">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">2</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>
                  <persName>Mr. Mattingly</persName> has been good enough to read the MS and has given me the benefit of many valuable suggestions.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n3">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">3</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>Mattingly believes that these were all struck under <persName>Caracalla</persName>.</p>
            </note>
         </div1>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div1 xml:id="d413e4985" type="backma">
            <pb n="85"/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="bold">COMBINED SUMMARY</hi>
            </head>
            <table rows="34" cols="6">
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell cols="2">
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">DENARII</hi>
                  </cell>
                  <cell cols="3">
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">TETRADRACHMS</hi>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>
                     <persName>Rome</persName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>
                     <persName>Antioch</persName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>Ant.</cell>
                  <cell>Other Mints</cell>
                  <cell>Tot.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <persName>Nero</persName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>1</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>1</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <persName>Galba</persName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>2</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>2</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <persName>Vitellius</persName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>2</cell>
                  <cell>(Lugdunum 1)</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>3</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <persName>Vespasian</persName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>26</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>26</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <persName>Titus</persName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>1</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>1</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <persName>Domitian</persName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>6</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>6</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <persName>Nerva</persName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>1</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>1</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <persName>Trajan</persName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>52</cell>
                  <cell>— </cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>(Tridrachm, Caesarea 1)</cell>
                  <cell>53</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <persName>Hadrian</persName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>38</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>38</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <persName>L. Aelius</persName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>1</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>1</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <persName>Sabina</persName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>6</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>6</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <persName>Pius</persName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>30</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>30</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <persName>Faustina Sr.</persName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>20</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>20</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <persName>M. Aurelius</persName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>12</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>1</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>13</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <persName>Faustina Jr</persName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>14</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>14</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <persName>L. Verus</persName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>1</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>1</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <persName>Lucilla</persName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>3</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>3</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <persName>Commodus</persName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>14</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>14</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <persName>Niger</persName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>1</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>1</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <persName>Severus</persName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>37</cell>
                  <cell>55</cell>
                  <cell>5</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>97</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <persName>Julia</persName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>18</cell>
                  <cell>4</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>22</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <persName>Caracalla</persName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>20</cell>
                  <cell>4</cell>
                  <cell>13</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Beroea</placeName> 1</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Tyre</placeName> 1</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>Uncertain 1</cell>
                  <cell>40</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <persName>Plautilla</persName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>2</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>2</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <persName>Geta</persName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>3</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>3</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Tyre</placeName> 2</cell>
                  <cell>8</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <persName>Macrinus</persName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>1</cell>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Aradus</placeName> 1</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Mopsus</placeName> 1</cell>
                  <cell>3</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <persName>Diadumenianus</persName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName>Tyre</placeName> 1</cell>
                  <cell>1</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
                  <cell>—</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>310</cell>
                  <cell>65</cell>
                  <cell>23</cell>
                  <cell>8</cell>
                  <cell>407</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>(including 1 Lugdunum</cell>
                  <cell/>
                  <cell>(plus 1 Tridrachm)</cell>
                  <cell/>
               </row>
            </table>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d413e5447" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>DURA H'D III</head>
            <div2 xml:id="d413e5451" type="section">
               <head>PL. I</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-03">
                  <graphic url="NNM55_92.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d413e5456" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>DURA H'D III</head>
            <div2 xml:id="d413e5460" type="section">
               <head>PL. II</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-04">
                  <graphic url="NNM55_93.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d413e5465" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>DURA H'D III</head>
            <div2 xml:id="d413e5469" type="section">
               <head>PL. III</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-05">
                  <graphic url="NNM55_94.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d413e5474" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>DURA H'D III</head>
            <div2 xml:id="d413e5478" type="section">
               <head>PL. IV</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-06">
                  <graphic url="NNM55_95.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d413e5483" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>DURA H'D III</head>
            <div2 xml:id="d413e5487" type="section">
               <head>PL. V</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-07">
                  <graphic url="NNM55_96.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d413e5492" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>DURA H'D III</head>
            <div2 xml:id="d413e5496" type="section">
               <head>PL. VI</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-08">
                  <graphic url="NNM55_97.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d413e5501" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>DURA H'D III</head>
            <div2 xml:id="d413e5505" type="section">
               <head>PL. VII</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-09">
                  <graphic url="NNM55_98.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d413e5510" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>DURA H'D III</head>
            <div2 xml:id="d413e5514" type="section">
               <head>PL. VIII</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-10">
                  <graphic url="NNM55_99.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d413e5519" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>DURA H'D IV</head>
            <div2 xml:id="d413e5523" type="section">
               <head>PL. IX</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-11">
                  <graphic url="NNM55_100.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d413e5528" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>DURA H'D IV</head>
            <div2 xml:id="d413e5532" type="section">
               <head>PL. X</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-12">
                  <graphic url="NNM55_101.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d413e5538" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>DURA H'D IV</head>
            <div2 xml:id="d413e5542" type="section">
               <head>PL. XI</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-13">
                  <graphic url="NNM55_102.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d413e5547" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>DURA H'D IV</head>
            <div2 xml:id="d413e5551" type="section">
               <head>PL. XII</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-14">
                  <graphic url="NNM55_103.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d413e5556" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>DURA H'D IV</head>
            <div2 xml:id="d413e5560" type="section">
               <head>PL. XIII</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-15">
                  <graphic url="NNM55_104.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d413e5565" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>DURA H'D IV</head>
            <div2 xml:id="d413e5569" type="section">
               <head>PL. XIV</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-16">
                  <graphic url="NNM55_105.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d413e5574" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>DURA H'D IV</head>
            <div2 xml:id="d413e5578" type="section">
               <head>PL. XV</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-17">
                  <graphic url="NNM55_106.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d413e5583" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>DURA H'D IV</head>
            <div2 xml:id="d413e5587" type="section">
               <head>PL. XVI</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-18">
                  <graphic url="NNM55_107.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d413e5592" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>DURA H'D IV</head>
            <div2 xml:id="d413e5596" type="section">
               <head>PL. XVII</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-19">
                  <graphic url="NNM55_108.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d413e5601" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>DURA H'D IV</head>
            <div2 xml:id="d413e5605" type="section">
               <head>PL. XVIII</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-20">
                  <graphic url="NNM55_109.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d413e5610" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>DURA H'D IV</head>
            <div2 xml:id="d413e5614" type="section">
               <head>PL. XIX</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-21">
                  <graphic url="NNM55_110.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d413e5619" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>DURA H'D IV</head>
            <div2 xml:id="d413e5623" type="section">
               <head>PL. XX</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-22">
                  <graphic url="NNM55_111.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d413e5628" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">Numismatic Notes and Monographs</hi>
            </head>
            <list type="numbered">
               <item n="1.">
                  <persName>Sydney P. Noe</persName>. Coin Hoards. 1921. 47 pp. 6 pls. 50c.</item>
               <item n="6.">
                  <persName>Agnes Baldwin</persName>. Five Roman Gold Medallions. 1921. 103 pp. 8 pls. $1.50.</item>
               <item n="7">
                  <persName>Sydney P. Noe</persName>. Medallic Work of A. A. <placeName>Weinman</placeName>. 1921. 31 pp. 17 pls. $1.00.</item>
               <item n="8.">
                  <persName>Gilbert S. Perez</persName>. The Mint of the <placeName>Philippine Islands</placeName>. 1921. 8 pp. 4 pls. 50c.</item>
               <item n="9.">
                  <persName>David Eugene Smith</persName>, LL.D. Computing Jetons. 1921. 70 pp. 25 pls. $1.50.</item>
               <item n="10.">
                  <persName>Edward T. Newell</persName>. The First Seleucid Coinage of Tyre. 1921. 40 pp. 8 pls. $1.00.</item>
               <item n="12.">
                  <persName>Howland Wood.</persName> Gold Dollars of 1858. 1922. 7 pp. 2 pls. 50c.</item>
               <item n="13.">
                  <persName>R. B. Whitehead</persName>. Pre-Mohammedan Coinage of N. W. <placeName>India</placeName>. 1922. 56 pp. 15 pls. $2.00.</item>
               <item n="14.">
                  <persName>George F. Hill</persName>. Attambelos I of Characene. 1922. 12 pp. 3 pls. $1.00.</item>
               <item n="15.">
                  <persName>M. P. Vlasto</persName>. Taras Oikistes (A Contribution to Tarentine Numismatics). 234 pp. 13 pls. $3.50.</item>
               <item n="17.">
                  <persName>Agnes Baldwin</persName>. Six Roman Bronze Medallions. 1923. 39 pp. 6 pls. $1.50.</item>
               <item n="18.">
                  <persName>Howland Wood</persName>. Tegucigalpa Coinage of 1823. 1923. 16 pp. 2 pls. 50c.</item>
               <item n="19.">
                  <persName>Edward T. Newell</persName>. <persName>Alexander Hoards</persName>—II. Demanhur Hoard. 1923. 162 pp. 8 pls. $2.50.</item>
               <item n="20.">
                  <persName>Harrold E. Gillingham</persName>. Italian Orders of Chivalry and Medals of Honour. 146 pp. 34 pls. $2.00.</item>
               <item n="21.">
                  <persName>Edward T. Newell</persName>. <persName>Alexander Hoards</persName>—III. Andritsaena. 1924. 39 pp. 6 pls. $1.00.</item>
               <item n="22.">
                  <persName>C. T. Seltman</persName>. A Hoard from Side. 1924. 20 pp. 3 pls. $1.00.</item>
               <item n="23.">
                  <persName>R. B. Seager</persName>. A Cretan Coin Hoard. 1924. 55 pp. 12 pls. $2.00.</item>
               <item n="24.">
                  <persName>Samuel R. Milbank</persName>. The Coinage of Aegina. 1925. 66 pp. 5 pls. $2.00.</item>
               <item n="25.">
                  <persName>Sydney P. Noe</persName>. A Bibliography of Greek Coin Hoards. 1925. 275 pp. $2.50.</item>
               <item n="26.">
                  <persName>Edward T. Newell</persName>. Mithradates of Parthia and Hyspaosines of Characene. 18 pp. 2 pls. 50c.</item>
               <item n="27.">
                  <persName>Sydney P. Noe</persName>. The Mende (Kaliandra) Hoard. 1926. 73 pp. 10 pls. $2.00.</item>
               <item n="28.">
                  <persName>Agnes Baldwin</persName>. Four Medallions from the Arras Hoard. 1926. 36 pp. 4 pls. $1.50.</item>
               <pb/>
               <item n="29.">
                  <persName>H. Alexander Parsons</persName>. The Earliest Coins of <placeName>Norway</placeName>. 1926. 41 pp. 50c.</item>
               <item n="30.">
                  <persName>Edward T. Newell</persName>. Some Unpublished Coins of Eastern Dynasts. 1926. 21 pp. 2 pls. 50c.</item>
               <item n="31.">
                  <persName>Harrold E. Gillingham</persName>. Spanish Orders of Chivalry and Decorations of Honour. 1926. 165 pp. 40 pls. $3.00.</item>
               <item n="32.">
                  <persName>Sydney P. Noe</persName>. The Coinage of Metapontum. 1927 (Part I). 134 pp. 23 pls. $3.00.</item>
               <item n="33.">
                  <persName>Edward T. Newell</persName>. Two Recent Egyptian Hoards—Delta and Keneh. 34 pp. 3 pls. $1.00.</item>
               <item n="34.">
                  <persName>Edward Rogers</persName>. The Second and Third Seleucid Coinage of Tyre. 1927. 33 pp. 4 pls. $1.50.</item>
               <item n="35.">
                  <persName>Alfred R. Bellinger</persName>. The Anonymous Byzantine Bronze Coinage. 1928. 27 pp. 4 pls. $1.50.</item>
               <item n="36.">
                  <persName>Harrold E. Gillingham</persName>. Notes on the Decorations and Medals of the <placeName>French</placeName> Colonies and Protectorates. 1928. 62 pp. 31 pls. $2.00.</item>
               <item n="37.">
                  <persName>Oscar Ravel</persName>. The "Colts" of Ambracia. 1928. 180 pp. 19 pls. $3.00.</item>
               <item n="38.">
                  <persName>Howland Wood</persName>. The Coinage of the Mexican Revolutionists. 1928. 53 pp. 15 pls. $2.50.</item>
               <item n="39.">
                  <persName>Edward T. Newell</persName>. <persName>Alexander Hoards</persName>. IV. Olympia. 1929. 31 pp. 9 plates. $1.50.</item>
               <item n="40.">
                  <persName>Alien B. West</persName>. Fifth-Fourth Century Gold Coins from Thracian Coast. 1929. 183 pp. 16 pls. $3.00.</item>
               <item n="41.">
                  <persName>Gilbert S. Perez</persName>. The Leper Colony Currency of Culion. 1929. 10 pp. 3 pls. 50c.</item>
               <item n="42.">
                  <persName>Alfred R. Bellinger</persName>. Two Hoards of Attic Bronze Coins. 1930. 14 pp. 4 pls. 50c.</item>
               <item n="43.">
                  <persName>D. H. Cox</persName>. The Caparelli Hoard. 1930. 14 pp. 2 pls. 50c.</item>
               <item n="44.">
                  <persName>Geo. F. Hill</persName>. On the Coins of Narbonensis with Iberian Inscriptions. 1930. 39 pp. 6 pls. $1.00.</item>
               <item n="45.">
                  <persName>Bauman L. Belden</persName>. A Mint in <placeName>New York</placeName>. 1930. 40 pp. 4 pls. 50c.</item>
               <item n="46.">
                  <persName>Edward T. Newell</persName>. The Küchük Köhne Hoard. 1931. 33 pp. 4 pls. $1.00.</item>
               <item n="47.">
                  <persName>Sydney P. Noe</persName>. The Coinage of Metapontum. Part II. 1931. 134 pp. 43 pls. $3.00.</item>
               <item n="48.">
                  <persName>D. W. Valentine</persName>. The United States Half Dimes. 1931. 79 pp. 47 pls. $5.00.</item>
               <item n="49.">
                  <persName>Alfred R. Bellinger</persName>. Two Roman Hoards from <placeName>Dura-Europos</placeName>. 1931. 66 pp. 17 $1.50.</item>
               <item n="50.">
                  <persName>George F. Hill</persName>. Notes on the Ancient Coinage of Hispania Citerior. 196 pp. 36 36 plates $4.00.</item>
               <item n="51.">
                  <persName>Alan W. Hazelton</persName>. The Russian Imperial Orders. 932. 102 pp. 20 plates. $3.00</item>
            </list>
         </div1>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
