<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xml:id="nnan107534">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>leper colony currency of Culion</title>
            <author>
               <name>Perez, Gilbert S. (Gilbert Somers), 1885-</name>
               <idno type="URI">http://viaf.org/viaf/88785503</idno>
            </author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>TEI P5 XML markup in conformance with the TEI DTD</resp>
               <name>AEL Data</name>
            </respStmt>
            <funder>Open access edition funded by the National Endowment for the Humanities/Andrew W. Mellon Foundation Humanities Open Book Program.</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <name>American Numismatic Society</name>
               <idno type="URI">http://numismatics.org/authority/american_numismatic_society</idno>
            </publisher>
            <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
            <date>1929</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">This work is made available under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International license</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Numismatic Notes and Monographs</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">41</biblScope>
            <idno type="URI">http://numismatics.org/library/195778</idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>Donum</title>
               <idno type="URI">http://numismatics.org/library/107534</idno>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <title>Worldcat</title>
               <idno type="URI">http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/488865630</idno>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <title>Worldcat Works</title>
               <idno type="URI">http://worldcat.org/entity/work/id/31421593</idno>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://nomisma.org/">
               <term ref="http://nomisma.org/id/greek_numismatics">Greek Numismatics</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2018-04-02">Ran TEI file through XSLT process, detailed in the Mellon EBook migration Google Document.</change>
         <change when="2018-04-02">Included normalized entity labels and URIs from
				previous OpenRefine process.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div1 xml:id="d238e30" type="cover">
            <pb/>
            <figure xml:id="fig-001">
               <graphic url="NNM41_001.jpg"/>
            </figure>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d238e34" type="frontma">
            <pb/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="bold">PUBLICATIONS</hi>
            </head>
            <p rend="hang">
               <hi rend="bold">The American Journal of Numismatics, 1866–1920.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Monthly, May, 1866-April, 1870.</p>
            <p>Quarterly, July, 1870-October, 1912.</p>
            <p>Annually, 1913-1920.</p>
            <p rend="hang">With many plates, illustrations, maps and tables. Less than a dozen complete sets of the Journal remain on hand. Prices on application.</p>
            <p rend="hang">The numbers necessary to complete broken sets may in most cases be obtained. An index to the first fifty volumes has been issued as part of Volume LI. It may be purchased separately for $3.00.</p>
            <p rend="hang">The American Numismatic Society. Catalogue of the International Exhibition of Contemporary Medals. March, 1910. New and revised edition. <placeName>New York</placeName>. 1911. xxxvi, 412 pages, 512 illustrations. $10.00.</p>
            <p rend="hang">The <placeName>American</placeName> Numismatic Society. Exhibition of <placeName>United States</placeName> and Colonial Coins. 1914. vii. 134 pages, 40 plates. $1.00.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d238e65" type="frontma">
            <pb/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="bold">NUMISMATIC NOTES AND MONOGRAPHS</hi>
            </head>
            <p/>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d238e71" type="dedication">
            <pb/>
            <p>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">Numismatic Notes and Monographs</hi> is devoted to essays and treatises on subjects relating to coins, paper money, medals and decorations, and is uniform with Hispanic Notes and Monographs published by the Hispanic Society of <placeName>America</placeName>, and with Indian Notes and Monographs issued by the Museum of the American Indian—Heye Foundation.</p>
            <list>
               <head>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">Publication Committee</hi>
               </head>
               <item>
                  <persName>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">Agnes Baldwin Brett</hi>
                  </persName>, <hi rend="italic">Chairman</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <persName>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">W. Gedney Beatty</hi>
                  </persName>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <persName>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">Henry Russell Drowne</hi>
                  </persName>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <persName>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">John Reilly, Jr.</hi>
                  </persName>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">Editorial Staff</hi>
               </head>
               <item>
                  <persName>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">Sydney Philip Noe</hi>
                  </persName>, <hi rend="italic">Editor</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <persName>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">Howland Wood</hi>
                  </persName>, <hi rend="italic">Associate Editor</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d238e121" type="colophon">
            <pb/>
            <p>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">Copyright, 1929, by The American Numismatic Society</hi>
            </p>
            <pb/>
            <figure xml:id="fig-002">
               <graphic url="NNM41_006.jpg"/>
               <p>VIEW OF <placeName>CULION</placeName> LEPER COLONY, <placeName>CULION,</placeName> PHILIPPINE ISLANDS.</p>
            </figure>
         </div1>
         <titlePage>
            <pb/>
            <docTitle>
               <titlePart type="main">THE LEPER COLONY CURRENCY OF CULION</titlePart>
            </docTitle>
            <byline>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">By</hi> GILBERT S. PEREZ
</byline>
            <figure xml:id="fig-003">
               <graphic url="NNM41_007.jpg"/>
            </figure>
            <docImprint>
               <publisher>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">The American Numismatic Society</hi>
               </publisher>
               <pubPlace>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">Broadway at</hi> 156<hi rend="smallcaps">th Street</hi>
               </pubPlace>
               <pubPlace>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">New York</hi>
               </pubPlace>
               <date>1929</date>
            </docImprint>
         </titlePage>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div1 xml:id="d238e164" type="chapter">
            <pb n="1"/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="bold">THE LEPER COLONY CURRENCY OF CULION</hi>
            </head>
            <byline>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">By Gilbert S. Perez</hi>
            </byline>
            <p>The interest of the people of this country during the past year has been directed to the condition of the sufferers from leprosy in the Philippine Islands, through a successful campaign for funds to aid the doctors charged with stamping out this terrible disease. There is every reason to believe that a few years will see great changes there, and that after the efforts now to be instituted shall have achieved their high aim, there will come a time when the currency used in <placeName>Culion</placeName> will have become another of the records of bygone things whose facts and whose past are called to mind by coins the intrinsic value of which is far surpassed by their historical significance.</p>
            <p>Nothing will bring to the mind of the outside world the absolute isolation of the leper patients of <placeName>Culion</placeName> so vividly as the currency which the Philippine Government has issued for the use of the inhabitants of that lonely island in the <placeName>China</placeName> Sea. In that spot about 5,300 patients await the time when death shall have made an end to their suffering or medical skill afforded them the much desired negative test which restores them to their
<pb n="2"/>
homes and to their loved ones. Strangely enough in 1923, of the 34 who were released from <placeName>Culion,</placeName> three decided to remain in the colony. Perhaps it was because they foresaw the glances of fear and horror they would receive from friends and neighbors when they returned to their homes, officially cured but still carrying with them the stigma of the living death from which they had recently escaped.</p>
            <p>The most extensively used drug in <placeName>Culion</placeName> is the iodized ethyl ester which may be considered as the standard compound for fighting the disease. If treatment is taken shortly after the appearance of the symptoms, the chances for recovery are very bright. During 1922, more than 500 were declared negative, of which 292 were paroled or discharged and the rest kept under a two-year period of observation. Leprosy is no respecter of persons and the patients on the island include exgovernors, lawyers, doctors, teachers, and men of wealth as well as laborers.</p>
            <p>Although the <placeName>Culion</placeName> Leper Colony was established in May, 1906, the first issue of coins was not placed in circulation until 1913. This issue was struck in aluminum in the die establishment of Frank &amp; Co., Manila. The design is a simple one, the coins resembling the ordinary hacienda token. On the obverse is the caduceus; around this is the legend "Bureau of Health," with the date 1913 between two stars. On the reverse
<pb n="3"/>
appears the value numeral surrounded by the legend "<placeName>Culion</placeName> Leper Colony Philippine Islands." The denominations struck were the ½-centavo, 5-centavo, 10-centavo, 20-centavo, and the peso all made of aluminum.</p>
            <p>The second issue (1920) of similar design and also struck in aluminum comprises the 10-centavo, 20-centavo and peso. These were coined at the government mint at Manila.</p>
            <p>As aluminum deteriorates very easily in a tropical climate, and because of the corrosive effect of the disinfectants in use, it was found advisable to change to an alloy of copper and nickel for this currency, the proportion being 75% of copper and 25% of nickel.</p>
            <p>The third issue consists of the twenty-centavo of nickel and one-peso pieces struck in nickel bronze; it was instituted in 1922.</p>
            <p>In 1925, a radical change was made in the design and the coins now have the appearance of a regular currency. The obverse shows the bust of <persName>Dr. José Rizal</persName>, the Filipino patriot who was executed in Manila in 1896; the reverse the new seal of the Philippine Health Service. One denomination only, the peso, was struck by the Philippine Mint.</p>
            <p>In 1927, one-centavo and 5-centavo pieces were minted. The effigy of Mabini was used in the one-centavo piece and that of Rizal in the five-centavo piece. While these coins were being
<pb n="4"/>
struck at the Manila mint, the die of the one-centavo piece was broken and had to be replaced. Nearly all of these coins were defaced and melted and a new die made. The last die was less carefully executed—it shows only one button on the coat instead of the two buttons of the broken die.</p>
            <p>In 1925, Director of Health Fajardo recommended that the special coins in circulation at the <placeName>Culion</placeName> Leper Colony be adopted for the inmates of the Manila Leprosarium. Insular Auditor Wright objected on the ground of illegality. He said, however, that should the Attorney General rule otherwise he would be perfectly willing to abide by the decision. On April 20, 1926, Attorney General Jaranilla announced his opinion that Director <persName>Fajardo's</persName> plan would not violate Section 13 of Act No. 1754 which prohibits the use of tokens. Two thousand 10-centavo pieces and 1,500 of the peso pieces of the third issue were transferred from the <placeName>Culion</placeName> Leper Colony to the San Lazaro Hospital. On October 23, 1926, 2,000 of the 10-centavo and 1,500 of the one-peso of the third issue were transferred from <placeName>Culion</placeName> to San Lazaro. On August 12, 1927, 10,000 of the new one-centavo piece and 6,000 of the new five-centavo piece were issued to the San Lazaro Hospital.</p>
            <p>The Mint and Health officials did not take cognizance of the similarity in size between the
<pb n="5"/>
regular five-centavo nickel and the one-centavo leper coins and it is not uncommon to find in circulation, a leper colony one-centavo piece which has netted the inmate of San Lazaro a profit of four centavos. It is, therefore, very probable that these will be recalled and a coin of different size issued by the Health Bureau and the Philippine Mint.</p>
            <p>On July the first, the following regulations governing the use of special <placeName>Culion</placeName> coins were issued by the Bureau of Health:</p>
            <div2 xml:id="d238e244" type="section">
               <head>"PHILIPPINE HEALTH SERVICE <placeName>CULION</placeName> LEPER COLONY"</head>
               <div3 xml:id="d238e250" type="subsection">
                  <head>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">Regulations Governing the Use of Special <placeName>Culion</placeName> Currency</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>"As a sanitary measure and with a view to stopping the circulation of special currency at present observed among the non-lepers in <placeName>Culion</placeName> and elsewhere who have commercial dealings with the inmates of the Colony; and also the circulation of the Philippine currency inside the Colony proper, the following regulations are hereby issued to take effect July 1, 1925:</p>
                  <p>(1) In all money transactions in the non-leper settlement, only the Philippine currency shall be used.</p>
                  <p>(2) In the Colony proper, the legal currency shall be the special currency, commonly known as
<pb n="6"/>
"leper money," expressly made for the exclusive use of the inmates thereof.</p>
                  <p>(3) All non-lepers having special currency in their possession should exchange same for Philippine currency at the office of the Disbursing Officer during work days (except Sundays and legal holidays).</p>
                  <p>(4) All those inmates having Philippine currency in their possession should exchange same for special currency at the <placeName>Culion</placeName> Store in the Colony proper during work days (except Sundays and legal holidays).</p>
                  <p>(5) All exchanges shall be made at par value.</p>
                  <p>(6) The use of Philippine currency for the payment of any kind of transaction, commercial or otherwise, to the inmates themselves or to non-lepers, is not permitted inside the Colony proper. Likewise, the circulation of special currency in Balala, Jardin and Culañgo is strictly prohibited, said circulation being absolutely confined within the Colony.</p>
                  <p>(7) Any non-leper vendor desiring to sell merchandise to the inmates, such as foodstuffs, building materials, etc., shall first obtain the necessary permit to do so from the Chief of the Colony, or his authorized agent, which permit may be issued him with the understanding that such vendor shall strictly comply with the existing regulations governing currency.</p>
                  <p>(8) All payments from such commercial transactions with the inmates shall be made in special currency which should be deposited with the authorized representative of the Disbursing Officer to be found at the gate, who shall issue a receipt for the amount received. This receipt may be presented at the office of the Disbursing Officer for exchange with Philippine currency.</p>
                  <pb n="7"/>
                  <p>(9) The Chief of Police and his agents should, see that provisions of these regulations are strictly complied with. They are empowered to arrest or to report to the proper authorities any person violating any of the provisions hereof.</p>
                  <p>(10) Any person found violating any of the provisions of these regulations shall be punished by a fine of not more than <hi rend="smallcaps">FIFTEEN PESOS</hi> (15), or imprisonment not to exceed <hi rend="smallcaps">One Month</hi>, or <hi rend="smallcaps">Both</hi>.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <persName>Jacobo Fajardo</persName>
                        <hi rend="italic">Director of Health</hi>
Approved:
<hi rend="smallcaps">
                           <persName>E. A. Gilmore</persName>
                        </hi>
                        <hi rend="italic">Secretary of Public Instruction</hi>"</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div3>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d238e312" type="section">
               <p>The Japanese government has made a special study of the <placeName>Culion</placeName> Leper Colony and has established a similar colony in <placeName>Japan</placeName>. All of the rules and regulations pertaining to the <placeName>Culion</placeName> colony have been adopted by the Japanese government in the administration of the Japanese Leper Colony. A set of the Japanese colony tokens varying in size and shape, of japanned brass are illustrated on Plate III.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d238e324" type="section">
               <pb n="8"/>
               <head>NUMBER OF COINS MINTED</head>
               <table rows="7" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">First Issue-1913</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">Denomination</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">Pieces</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi rend="italic">Pesos</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>½-centavo</cell>
                     <cell rend="right">17,000</cell>
                     <cell rend="right">85</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>1-centavo</cell>
                     <cell rend="right">32,500</cell>
                     <cell rend="right">325</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>5-centavo</cell>
                     <cell rend="right">6,600</cell>
                     <cell rend="right">330</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>10-centavo</cell>
                     <cell rend="right">6,600</cell>
                     <cell rend="right">660</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>20-centavo</cell>
                     <cell rend="right">10,000</cell>
                     <cell rend="right">2,000</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>1-peso</cell>
                     <cell rend="right">8,600</cell>
                     <cell rend="right">8,600</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>Aluminum-Struck by Frank &amp; Co., Manila</p>
               <table rows="3" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>Second Issue-1920</cell>
                     <cell rend="right">10-centavo</cell>
                     <cell rend="right">20,000</cell>
                     <cell rend="right">2,000</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>20-centavo</cell>
                     <cell rend="right">10,000</cell>
                     <cell rend="right">2,000</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>1-peso</cell>
                     <cell rend="right">4,000</cell>
                     <cell rend="right">4,000</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>Aluminum-Struck at the Philippine Mint</p>
               <table rows="2" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>Third Issue-1922</cell>
                     <cell rend="right">20-centavo</cell>
                     <cell rend="right">10,155</cell>
                     <cell rend="right">2,031</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>1-peso</cell>
                     <cell rend="right">8,280</cell>
                     <cell rend="right">8,280</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>Nickel Bronze-Struck at the Philippine Mint</p>
               <table rows="3" cols="4">
                  <row>
                     <cell>Fourth Issue-1925</cell>
                     <cell rend="right">1-peso</cell>
                     <cell rend="right">20,000</cell>
                     <cell rend="right">20,000</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Fifth Issue-1927</cell>
                     <cell rend="right">1-centavo</cell>
                     <cell rend="right">30,000</cell>
                     <cell rend="right">300</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell/>
                     <cell>5-centavo</cell>
                     <cell rend="right">16,000</cell>
                     <cell rend="right">800</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>Nickel Bronze—Struck at the Philippine Mint</p>
               <p>There are two varieties of these 1927 coins, one is well executed with the legend "For a healthy nation" in the ribbon under the seal of the Bureau of Health. In the new die of this issue the ribbons show no inscription.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d238e471" type="section">
               <pb n="9"/>
               <head>COMPLETE LIST OF COINS STRUCK TO DATE</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="bold">1</hi>. Peso. Obv. in center 1 Peso, surrounded by the legend, <hi rend="smallcaps">
                        <placeName>culion</placeName> leper colony</hi> and <hi rend="smallcaps">philippine islands</hi>. Rev., Caduceus with legend, <hi rend="smallcaps">bureau of health</hi>, * 1913.* Aluminum. Plate I.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="bold">2</hi>. 20-centavo. Obv. similar to No. 1, but with value 20 <hi rend="smallcaps">centavos</hi>. Rev. similar, but letters without serifs. Aluminum. Plate I.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="bold">3</hi>. 10-centavo. Obv. similar to No. 1, but with value 10 <hi rend="smallcaps">centavos</hi>. Rev. similar to No. 1. Aluminum. Plate I.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="bold">4</hi>. 5-centavo. Obv. similar to No. 1, but with value 5 <hi rend="smallcaps">centavos</hi>. Rev. similar to No. 1. Aluminum. Plate I.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="bold">5</hi>. 1-centavo. Obv. similar to No. 1, but with value 1 <hi rend="smallcaps">CENTAVO.</hi> Rev. similar to No. 2. Aluminum. Plate II.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="bold">6</hi>. ½-centavo. Obv. similar to No. 1, but with value ½ <hi rend="smallcaps">centavo</hi>. Rev. similar to No. 2. Aluminum. Plate II. Philippine Mint.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="bold">7</hi>. 1-peso. Obv. similar to No. 1, but dated 1920. Aluminum. Plate II.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="bold">8</hi>. 20-centavo. Obv. similar to No. 2, but dated 1920.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="bold">9</hi>. 10-centavo. Obv. similar to No. 3, but dated 1920.</item>
                  <pb n="10"/>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="bold">10</hi>. 1-peso. Obv. similar to No. 1. Small incuse in field, PM (Philippine Mint). Rev. <hi rend="smallcaps">philippine health service</hi> 1922 surrounding caduceus. Nickel bronze. Plate II.</item>
                  <item>11. 20-centavo. Obv. similar to No. 2, but value 20 <hi rend="smallcaps">centavos</hi>. Rev. similar to No. 10. Nickel bronze.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="bold">12</hi>. 1-peso. Obv. bust of José Rizal. Legend, <hi rend="smallcaps">
                        <placeName>culion</placeName> leper colony philippine islands</hi>. Rev. <hi rend="smallcaps">philippine health service</hi> * 1925 <hi rend="smallcaps">one peso</hi>.* In center, seal of the Health Service. Nickel bronze. Plate III.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="bold">13</hi>. 5-centavo. Obv. similar to No. 12, but letters without serifs. Rev. similar to No. 11, but 5 <hi rend="smallcaps">centavos</hi> instead of 1 peso and date 1927. Nickel bronze, rare. Plate III.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="bold">14</hi>. Similar but less carefully executed. No inscription in the ribbon under the seal. Nickel bronze.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="bold">15</hi>. 1-centavo. Obv. similar to No. 12, but with bust of Mabini. Rev. similar to No. 13, but with value <hi rend="smallcaps">one centavo</hi>. Excessively rare. Nickel bronze. Plate III.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="bold">16</hi>. Similar to No. 15, but less carefully executed—no inscription in ribbon. Nickel bronze.</item>
               </list>
            </div2>
         </div1>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div1 xml:id="d238e590" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="bold">
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">Culion Leper Currency</hi>
               </hi>
            </head>
            <div2 xml:id="d238e596" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">Plate I</hi>
               </head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-004">
                  <graphic url="NNM41_018.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d238e602" type="section">
               <pb/>
               <head>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">Plate II</hi>
               </head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-005">
                  <graphic url="NNM41_019.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d238e609" type="section">
               <pb/>
               <head>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">Plate III</hi>
               </head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-006">
                  <graphic url="NNM41_020.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d238e616" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="bold">
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">Numismatic Notes and Monographs</hi>
               </hi>
            </head>
            <list type="numbered">
               <item rend="hang" n="1.">
                  <persName>Sydney P. Noe</persName>. Coin Hoards. 1921. 47 pp. 6 pls. 50c.</item>
               <item rend="hang" n="4.">
                  <persName>Howland Wood</persName>. The <placeName>Mexican</placeName> Revolutionary Coinage. 1913–1916. 1921. 44 pp. 26 pls. $2.00.</item>
               <item rend="hang" n="6.">
                  <persName>Agnes Baldwin</persName>. Five Roman Gold Medallions. 1921. 103 pp. 8 pls. $1.50.</item>
               <item rend="hang" n="7.">
                  <persName>Sydney P. Noe</persName>. Medallic Work of A. A. <placeName>Weinman</placeName>. 1921. 31 pp. 17 pls. $1.00.</item>
               <item rend="hang" n="8.">
                  <persName>Gilbert S. Perez</persName>. The Mint of the <placeName>Philippine Islands</placeName>. 1921. 8 pp. 4 pls. 50c.</item>
               <item rend="hang" n="9.">
                  <persName>David Eugene Smith</persName>, LL.D. Computing Jetons. 1921. 70 pp. 25 pls. $1.50.</item>
               <item rend="hang" n="10.">
                  <persName>Edward T. Newell</persName>. The First Seleucid Coinage of Tyre. 1921. 40 pp. 8 pls. $1.00.</item>
               <item rend="hang" n="11.">
                  <persName>Harrold E. Gillingham</persName>. <placeName>French</placeName> Orders and Decorations. 1922. 110 pp. 35 pls. $2.00.</item>
               <item rend="hang" n="12.">
                  <persName>Howland Wood</persName>. Gold Dollars of 1858. 1922. 7 pp. 2 pls. 50c.</item>
               <item rend="hang" n="13.">
                  <persName>R. B. Whitehead</persName>. Pre-Mohammedan Coinage of N. W. <placeName>India</placeName>. 1922. 56 pp. 15 pls. $2.00.</item>
               <item rend="hang" n="14.">
                  <persName>George F. Hill</persName>. Attambelos I of Characene. 1922. 12 pp. 3 pls. $1.00.</item>
               <item rend="hang" n="15.">
                  <persName>M. P. Vlasto</persName>. <placeName>Taras</placeName> Oikistes (A Contribution to Tarentine Numismatics). 1922. 234 pp. 13 pls. $3.50.</item>
               <item rend="hang" n="16.">
                  <persName>Howland Wood</persName>. Commemorative Coinage of <placeName>United States</placeName>. 1922. 63 pp. 7 pls. $1.50.</item>
               <item rend="hang" n="17.">
                  <persName>Agnes Baldwin</persName>. Six Roman Bronze Medallions. 1923. 39 pp. 6 pls. $1.50.</item>
               <item rend="hang" n="18.">
                  <persName>Howland Wood</persName>. Tegucigalpa Coinage of 1823. 1923. 16 pp. 2 pls. 50c.</item>
               <item rend="hang" n="19.">
                  <persName>Edward T. Newell</persName>. Alexander Hoards—II. Demanhur Hoard. 1923. 162 pp. 8 pls. $2.50.</item>
               <item rend="hang" n="20.">
                  <persName>Harrold E. Gillingham</persName>. Italian Orders of Chivalry and Medals of Honour. 1923. 146 pp. 34 pls. $2.00.</item>
               <item rend="hang" n="21.">
                  <persName>Edward T. Newell</persName>. Alexander Hoards—III. Andritsaena. 1924. 39 pp. 6 pls. $1.00.</item>
               <item rend="hang" n="22.">
                  <persName>C. T. Seltman</persName>. A Hoard from Side. 1924. 20 pp. 3 pls. $1.00.</item>
               <pb/>
               <item rend="hang" n="23.">
                  <persName>R. B. Seager</persName>. A Cretan Coin Hoard. 1924. 55 pp. 12 pls. $2.00.</item>
               <item rend="hang" n="24.">
                  <persName>Samuel R. Milbank</persName>. The Coinage of Aegina. 1925. 66 pp. 5 pls. $2.00.</item>
               <item rend="hang" n="25.">
                  <persName>Sydney P. Noe</persName>. A Bibliography of Greek Coin Hoards. 1925. 275 pp. $2.50.</item>
               <item rend="hang" n="26.">
                  <persName>Edward T. Newell</persName>. Mithradates of Parthia and Hyspaosines of Characene. 1925. 18 pp. 2 pls. 50c.</item>
               <item rend="hang" n="27.">
                  <persName>Sydney P. Noe</persName>. The Mende (Kaliandra) Hoard. 1926. 73 pp. 10 pls. $2.00.</item>
               <item rend="hang" n="28.">
                  <persName>Agnes Baldwin</persName>. Four Medallions from the Arras Hoard. 1926. 36 pp. 4 pls. $1.50.</item>
               <item rend="hang" n="29.">
                  <persName>H. Alexander Parsons</persName>. The Earliest Coins of <placeName>Norway</placeName>. 1926. 41 pp. 50c.</item>
               <item rend="hang" n="30.">
                  <persName>Edward T. Newell</persName>. Some Unpublished Coins of <placeName>Eastern Dynasts</placeName>. 1926. 21 pp. 2 pls. 50c.</item>
               <item rend="hang" n="31.">
                  <persName>Harrold E. Gillingham</persName>. Spanish Orders of Chivalry and Decorations of Honour. 1926. 165 pp. 40 pls. $3.00.</item>
               <item rend="hang" n="32.">
                  <persName>Sydney P. Noe</persName>. The Coinage of Metapontum. 1927 (Part I). 134 pp. 23 pls. $3.00.</item>
               <item rend="hang" n="33.">
                  <persName>Edward T. Newell</persName>. Two Recent Egyptian Hoards—Delta and Keneh. 1927. 34 pp. 3 pls. $1.00.</item>
               <item rend="hang" n="34.">
                  <persName>Edward Rogers</persName>. The Second and Third Seleucid Coinage of Tyre. 1927. 33 pp. 4 pls. $1.50.</item>
               <item rend="hang" n="35.">
                  <persName>Alfred R. Bellinger</persName>. The Anonymous Byzantine Bronze Coinage. 1928. 27 pp. 4 pls. $1.50.</item>
               <item rend="hang" n="36.">
                  <persName>Harrold E. Gillingham</persName>. Notes on the Decorations and Medals of the <placeName>French</placeName> Colonies and Protectorates. 1928. 62 pp. 31 pls. $2.00.</item>
               <item rend="hang" n="37.">
                  <persName>Oscar Ravel</persName>. The "Colts" of Ambracia. 1928. 180 pp. 19 pls. $3.00.</item>
               <item rend="hang" n="38.">
                  <persName>Howland Wood</persName>. The Coinage of the <placeName>Mexican</placeName> Revolutionists. 1928. 53 pp. 15 pls. $2.50.</item>
               <item rend="hang" n="39.">
                  <persName>Edward T. Newell</persName>. Alexander Hoards. IV. Olympia. 1929. 31 pp. 9 plates. $1.50.</item>
               <item rend="hang" n="40.">
                  <persName>Allen B. West</persName>. Fifth and Fourth Century Gold Coins from the Thracian Coast. 1929. 183 pp. 16 plates. $3.00.</item>
            </list>
         </div1>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>