<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd"
     xml:id="nnan129962">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Coinage of Metapontum, Part 1</title>
            <author>
               <name>Noe, Sydney P. (Sydney Philip), 1885-1969</name>
               <idno type="URI">http://numismatics.org/authority/noe</idno>
            </author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>TEI P5 XML markup in conformance with the TEI DTD</resp>
               <name>AEL Data</name>
            </respStmt>
            <funder>Open access edition funded by the National Endowment for the Humanities/Andrew W. Mellon Foundation Humanities Open Book Program.</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <name>American Numismatic Society</name>
               <idno type="URI">http://numismatics.org/authority/american_numismatic_society</idno>
            </publisher>
            <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
            <date>1927</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">This work is made available under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial
                  4.0 International license</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Numismatic Notes and Monographs</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">32</biblScope>
            <idno type="URI">http://numismatics.org/library/195778</idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>Donum</title>
               <idno type="URI">http://numismatics.org/library/129962</idno>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <title>Worldcat</title>
               <idno type="URI">http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/390432</idno>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <title>Worldcat Works</title>
               <idno type="URI">http://worldcat.org/entity/work/id/2908507734</idno>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <title>HathiTrust</title>
               <idno type="URI">https://hdl.handle.net/2027/inu.30000104994359</idno>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <particDesc>
            <listPerson>
               <person xml:id="numismatics_brett">
                  <persName>Brett, Agnes Baldwin, 1876-1955</persName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://numismatics.org/authority/brett</idno>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="viaf_307456146">
                  <persName>Beatty, William Gedney</persName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://viaf.org/viaf/307456146</idno>
                  <!-- W. Gedney Beatty -->
               </person>
               <person xml:id="viaf_34463266">
                  <persName>Smith, David Eugene, 1860-1944</persName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://viaf.org/viaf/34463266</idno>
               </person>
            </listPerson>
         </particDesc>
         <settingDesc>
            <listPlace>
               <place xml:id="nomisma_magna_graecia">
                  <placeName>Magna Graecia</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/magna_graecia</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="nomisma_metapontum">
                  <placeName>Metapontum</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/metapontum</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="nomisma_croton">
                  <placeName>Croton</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/croton</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="nomisma_syracuse">
                  <placeName>Syracuse</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/syracuse</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="nomisma_sybaris">
                  <placeName>Sybaris</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/sybaris</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="nomisma_poseidonia">
                  <placeName>Poseidonia</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/poseidonia</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="nomisma_athens">
                  <placeName>Athens</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/athens</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="nomisma_berlin">
                  <placeName>Berlin</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/berlin</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="nomisma_paris">
                  <placeName>Paris</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://www.nomisma.org/id/paris</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="geonames_2653941">
                  <placeName>Cambridge</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://www.geonames.org/2653941</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="nomisma_london">
                  <placeName>London</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://www.nomisma.org/id/london</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="viaf_3172394">
                  <placeName>Naples</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://www.geonames.org/3172394</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="viaf_2618425">
                  <placeName>Bement</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://www.geonames.org/4233552</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="pleiades_530834">
                  <placeName>Corcyra</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">https://pleiades.stoa.org/places/530834</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="nomisma_boston">
                  <placeName>Boston</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/boston</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="nomisma_india">
                  <placeName>India</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/india</idno>
               </place>
            </listPlace>
         </settingDesc>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://nomisma.org/">
               <term ref="http://nomisma.org/id/greek_numismatics">Greek Numismatics</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2016-08-11">Ran TEI file through XSLT process, detailed in the Mellon EBook migration Google Document.</change>
         <change when="2016-08-31">Reprocessed: restructured TOC list into table; added HathiTrust URI; added funder</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div1 xml:id="d1e32" type="cover">
            <pb/>
            <figure xml:id="fig-1">
               <graphic url="NNM32_001.jpg"/>
            </figure>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d1e36" type="frontma">
            <pb/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="bold">PUBLICATIONS</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi rend="bold">The American Journal of Numismatics, 1866-1920.</hi>
            </p>
            <p rend="hang">Monthly, May, 1866—April, 1870.</p>
            <p rend="hang">Quarterly, July, 1870—October, 1912.</p>
            <p rend="hang">Annually, 1913-1920.</p>
            <list>
               <item rend="hang">With many plates, illustrations, maps and tables. Less than a dozen complete sets of the Journal remain on hand. Prices on
                  application.</item>
               <item rend="hang">The numbers necessary to complete broken sets may in most cases be obtained. An index to the first fifty volumes has been
                  issued as part of Volume LI. It may also be purchased separately for $3.00.</item>
            </list>
            <p rend="hang">The American Numismatic Society. Catalogue of the International Exhibition of Contemporary Medals. March, 1910. New and revised
               edition. New York. 1911. xxxvi, 412 pages, 512 illustrations. $10.00.</p>
            <p rend="hang">The American Numismatic Society. Exhibition of United States and Colonial Coins. 1914. vii, 134 pages, 40 plates. $1.00.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d1e59" type="frontma">
            <pb/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="bold">NUMISMATIC</hi>
            </head>
            <p>NOTES AND MONOGRAPHS</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d1e66" type="dedication">
            <pb/>
            <p>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">Numismatic Notes and Monographs</hi> is devoted to essays and treatises on subjects relating to coins, paper money, medals
               and decorations, and is uniform with Hispanic Notes and Monographs published by the Hispanic Society of America, and with Indian Notes and
               Monographs issued by the Museum of the American Indian—Heye Foundation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">Publication Committee</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">
                  <persName>Agnes Baldwin Brett</persName>
               </hi>, <hi rend="italic">Chairman</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">
                  <persName corresp="#viaf_307456146">W. Gedney Beatty</persName>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">
                  <persName>Henry Russell Drowne</persName>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">
                  <persName>John Reilly, Jr</persName>.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">Editorial Staff</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">
                  <persName>Sydney Philip Noe</persName>
               </hi>, <hi rend="italic">Editor</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">
                  <persName>Howland Wood</persName>
               </hi>, <hi rend="italic">Associate Editor</hi>
            </p>
         </div1>
         <pb/>
         <div1 xml:id="d1e113" type="copyright">
            <p>COPYRIGHT 1927 BY</p>
            <p>THE AMERICAN NUMISMATIC SOCIETY</p>
            <p>PANDICK PRESS, INC., NEW YORK</p>
         </div1>
         <titlePage>
            <pb/>
            <pb/>
            <docTitle>
               <titlePart type="main">THE COINAGE OF METAPONTUM (PART ONE)</titlePart>
            </docTitle>
            <byline>
               <persName>SYDNEY P. NOE</persName>
            </byline>
            <figure xml:id="fig-2">
               <graphic url="NNM32_007.jpg"/>
            </figure>
            <docImprint>
               <publisher>The American Numismatic Society</publisher>
               <pubPlace>Broadway at 156th Street</pubPlace>
               <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
               <date>1927</date>
            </docImprint>
         </titlePage>
         <pb n="1"/>
         <div1 xml:id="d1e141" type="foreword">
            <head>
               <hi rend="bold">FOREWORD.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>The following pages, comprising the initial portion of a classification of the coinage of Metapontum, deal with the incuse coinage of that city,
               as the first natural division. This material can make no claim to being a corpus, although all of the large national collections have been
               studied either from the coins themselves or from casts, and all of the important private collections to which access was possible, have also paid
               tribute. In consequence, the debt of obligation to the custodians and owners of these collections is a heavy one. I am grateful for the
               courtesies shown me by the authorities of the British Museum and especially by <persName>Mr. Hill</persName> and <persName>Mr. E.
                  S. G. Robinson</persName>. At the Bibliothque Nationale, both <persName>M. Babelon</persName> and his son were helpful. <persName>Dr. MacDonald</persName> gave generously of his time to permit me to examine the Metapontine coins of the Hunterian collection. At Naples and at
               the Athens National Numismatic Museum especial consideration was shown me. The Cabinets at Berlin, Vienna and Leningrad have been generous in
               providing casts. Considerable benefit and great pleasure came with <pb n="2"/> the opportunity to inspect the coins of Metapontum in the
               collections of <persName>M. Jameson</persName> (<placeName>Paris</placeName>), Baron Pennisi (Acireale), Mr. <persName>G.
                  Empedocles</persName> (<placeName corresp="#nomisma_athens">Athens</placeName>) and <persName>Sir Arthur J. Evans</persName>. In <placeName>America</placeName>,
               the pieces in the collections of the members of the American Numismatic Society have been freely placed at my disposal.</p>
            <p>Messrs. <persName>Spink</persName> &amp;Son very kindly sent me for examination and study, the portion of the Taranto Hoard which was still
               in their possession and this comprised a considerable number of the pieces of Metapontum found. Dr. <persName>Jacob Hirsch</persName>
               courteously made arrangements whereby casts of the specimens of these coins in several of the Geneva sales were sent me.</p>
            <p>There was great benefit for me in helpful discussion of some of my problems with M. <persName>Vlasto</persName>. Nearer at home there has
               been frequent recourse to the experience of Mr. <persName>Wood</persName>, my colleague on the staff of the Museum of the American
               Numismatic Society, in questions of die-varieties or alterations. My heaviest debt, however, is to the interest and aid given constantly by Mr.
               Edward <persName>T. Newell</persName>, who not only placed his important private collection of the coins of this city in my hands for study,
               but whose advice and sound judgment have contributed mightily to the results now submitted. Others whose support has been not inconsiderable
               will, I trust, take satisfaction in the <pb n="3"/> record which follows of the effort to co-ordinate the beautiful coinage of this Greek colony
               in Southern Italy.</p>
            <p>A final explanation should be presented. When this work was first considered in the early part of 1921, I learned through Dr. <persName>Regling</persName> that a study of this coinage had been begun by Professor <persName>Lauri O. T. Tudeer</persName> of Helsingfors. After
               some correspondence Professor <persName>Tudeer</persName> withdrew from the field reserving for himself the question of the overstruck
               pieces only. His action has laid me under a very heavy obligation and until a short time ago it had been the hope of our Publication Committee
               that his article might precede my own. He has promised its completion at an early date.</p>
         </div1>
      </front>
      <body>
         <pb/>
         <div1 xml:id="d1e214" type="chapter">
            <head>THE COINAGE OF METAPONTUM</head>
            <byline>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">By Sydney P. Noe</hi>
            </byline>
            <p>In submitting a new classification of the issues of Metapontum there should be slight need for an apologia, but it may not be obvious why a study
               of the coinage of this city has greater urgency than have those of most of the other Greek cities. Many city-states have had an uninterrupted
               coinage extending over more than three centuries, and of their history we know just as little or even less. Few, however, have coins possessing
               so wide a variation of obverse types. This consideration is of the greatest importance because the badge of the city, the barley ear, which
               occupies the reverse throughout the double-relief coinage, is so distinctive through symbols and style, that the combinations with the changing
               obverse types—the so-called muling—enables a close approximation to the chronological order in which these types appeared. This peculiarity is
               the strongest reason for giving the coinage of this city our attention— but there is the greater incentive because previous <pb n="6"/> efforts
               in this direction have not been instituted since the introduction of photography. Carelli<ref target="CH1-n1">1</ref> and Garrucci<ref target="CH1-n2">2</ref> used engraved plates which record many inaccuracies. The British Museum Catalogue for Italy was among the first of
               that series, but it is without the photographic plates which aid in making the later volumes such treasure-houses of facts. The sequence of
               <placeName corresp="#nomisma_tarentum">Tarentum</placeName>'s "Horsemen" has been worked out by <persName>Sir Arthur Evans</persName>, but Tarentum was the only Dorian Colony in <placeName>South Italy</placeName>, whereas Metapontum, like the others, is Achaean.</p>
            <p>Fortunately there is no question concerning the location of Metapontum. Strabo's account<ref target="CH1-n3">3</ref> is free from ambiguity, and
               the remains of a sixth century Doric temple<ref target="CH1-n4">4</ref> of which fifteen columns are still standing leave no room for further
               questioning. Excavations conducted by the Due de Luynes in 1828, and published by him in a thin elephantfolio,<ref target="CH1-n5">5</ref> offer
               further confirmation of what little literary evidence we have. The identification of a second Doric temple, through a dedicatory inscription, as
               sacred to Apollo (Lycaeus?) is of first importance.<ref target="CH1-n6">6</ref> This second structure is thought to date from the end of the
               sixth century, and lies within the walls of the town, which have been traced for some distance. The sites of the Agora and of a theatre were
               established, and give indications of the importance of the city. There are <pb n="7"/> also remains of an artificial harbor<ref target="CH1-n7">7</ref> of moderate size, as well as traces of what has been considered an ancient canal feeding into this harbor. If the belief that this
               was a canal is warrantable, there would be room for thinking that irrigation may have played some part in developing the agricultural wealth of
               Metapontum.</p>
            <p>Metapontum today is hardly more than a railway station at the junction of the lines from Potenza and Reggio to <placeName>Taranto</placeName>.
               The plain has been over-run with sand and is partially covered with scrub-growths. The dangers of malaria during summer make spring and the late
               fall the best times for visits. There is no need to doubt the accounts of the extreme fertility of this territory at the time of the city's
               founding, for the change would be amply accounted for by the deforestation which has taken place since then. This would apply to the upland as
               well as to the plain, and with wooded slopes to retain the rainfall, there is every reason to credit the early accounts of the attractiveness of
               the district. The site lies on the coast between two rivers—the Casuentus on the west and the Bradanus on the east, and is nearest the latter,
               giving point to Strabo's observation that its recolonisation from <placeName corresp="#nomisma_sybaris">Sybaris</placeName> after the destruction of the earliest settlement by the "Samnites" was
               for the purpose of opposing the spread of the influence of <placeName corresp="#nomisma_tarentum">Tarentum</placeName>, something less than <pb n="8"/> thirty miles distant. The Bradanus thus
               offers one line of defense, but save for the difficulty of a surprise attack over the surrounding plain, there were few other advantages of a
               defensive nature. A small, but excellent map, is to be found in Baedeker's <placeName>"Southern Italy"</placeName>.</p>
            <p>The literary sources for the history of Metapontum afford but little help. Strabo records of the city that "they so prospered from farming, it is
               said, that they dedicated a golden harvest at Delphi." This has frequently been interpreted as a counterpart of the badge of the city, in gold—
               or possibly a sheaf of golden barley. R. Egger<ref target="CH1-n8">8</ref> offers reasons for thinking that the offering consisted merely of a
               holder in which some twelve or more golden spears of barley were fixed. The reproduction on page 9, for permission to use, which I am indebted to
               the kindness of <persName>Dr. Jacob Hirsch</persName>, shows an offering of wheat ears which is believed to have come from <placeName corresp="#nomisma_syracuse">Syracuse</placeName>. Save as
               indication of Metapontum's prosperity, we obtain little aid from this passage.</p>
            <p>At Olympia there was a "treasury" belonging to the Metapontines, and this has been given perhaps undue weight (cf. Nissen<ref target="CH1-n9">9</ref> et al.) in having been accepted as a further indication of the wealth of the city.<ref target="CH1-n10">10</ref> That these
               treasuries had in measure some such connotation is undeniable, but Dyer<ref target="CH1-n11">11</ref> has shown that they are to be considered
                  <pb n="9"/>
               <figure xml:id="fig-3">
                  <graphic url="NNM32_009.jpg"/>
                  <p>Wheat-ear of gold from <placeName corresp="#nomisma_syracuse">Syracuse</placeName>.</p>
               </figure>
               <pb n="10"/> communal houses rather than places in which to store costly gifts or offerings. For this reason, that the treasury of Metapontum at
               Olympia was associated with those of such cities as Sybaris, Megara, <placeName corresp="#nomisma_syracuse">Syracuse</placeName>, Gela and Sicyon is stronger testimony of Metapontum's importance
               than that it should have filled such a structure with "treasure".</p>
            <p>Pythagoras was received with honor at Metapontum after having fled from Croton, but little can be deduced from this. Nor can we gain a great deal
               from the statement that Metapontum sent two ships to the aid of <placeName corresp="#nomisma_athens">Athens</placeName> against <placeName corresp="#nomisma_syracuse">Syracuse</placeName>,<ref target="CH1-n12">12</ref> unless we are to adjudge
               this number as either the maximum possible or the minimum they were willing to risk. So too with the reference to Aristeas,<ref target="CH1-n13">13</ref> although this may have a bearing on one of the coin types, as we shall see later.</p>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e300" type="section">
               <head>THE NEIGHBORING CITIES.</head>
               <p>An effort to visualize the status of these Achaean colonies before B. C. 510 should prove suggestive.</p>
               <p>The size and wealth of <placeName corresp="#nomisma_sybaris">Sybaris</placeName> must have given that city a predominance over her neighbors, some of which were, like Metapontum, founded by
                  her. If we seek the foundation of the growth and wealth of Sybaris in her commercial relations, it is fairly obvious that her land-trade must
                  have <pb n="11"/> been of greater importance than her traffic by sea. Her pre-eminence has been attributed to having control over the shortest
                  and easiest of the routes between the Ionian and Tyrrhenian Seas, over the narrow instep of the great boot of the Italian peninsula.<ref target="CH1-n14">14</ref> Trade rivalry with Siris, a city controlling a rival trans-isthmus route, is usually accepted as the reason for
                  the destruction of that city at the hands of Sybaris, Croton and <placeName corresp="#nomisma_metapontum">Metapontum</placeName>—although this may not have been the sole cause. It is entirely
                  possible that the demands of her Etruscan and other markets on the Tyrrhenian shore absorbed the entire supply of what Sybaris had to offer,
                  as well as other commodities purchased from the Achaean cities—such as grain from Metapontum—material which Sybaris could transport over the
                  shorter road within her control more economically than any of her neighbors.</p>
               <p>Miletus was in close relationship with Sybaris, and there is evidence that this had some commercial basis. Whether it was sufficiently
                  extensive to give Sybaris any considerable advantage as an <hi rend="italic">entrepreneur</hi> is not apparent, but whatever the commodity,
                  Sybaris had a double market—her Greek neighbors and the Etruscans. Furthermore she was able to prevent the latter, and in all probability the
                  Greeks as well, from having direct contact with Miletus, and thus could exact a double profit on a single transaction. Speck states that <pb n="12"/> the woolen fabrics of Miletus were exchanged for grain.<ref target="CH1-n15">15</ref>
               </p>
               <p>Save for the Milesian and other Ionian cities, and with the important exception of trade among themselves, which must have been considerable,
                  the only sea market open to these Greeks of <placeName>South Italy</placeName> would have been the mother country. The Achaeans were a
                  farming rather than a maritime people, and this characteristic the colonies shared. None of them possessed a large natural haven— <placeName corresp="#nomisma_tarentum">Tarentum</placeName> was
                  Dorian, and controlled the only secure harbor. Sicily and the straits of Messina were in the control of the Chalcidians, and the Adriatic was
                  under the sway of the Corinthians. The size of the ships and the consequent smallness of their cargoes would necessitate the carrying of some
                  commodity of high value within small compass before its worth would be such as to exert much economic pressure. The income of these cities
                  must therefore have been from their landward side. It would not be surprising to have archaeologists at some future day find evidence that
                  there was mineral wealth in these mountains—Lenormant states that silver mines were operated in southern Italy up to the time that the
                  discovery of America's store made their operation no longer profitable.</p>
               <p>The fall of Sybaris brought many important changes. It is hardly likely that any of the other <pb n="13"/> cities could have continued the
                  contact with the Milesian market, and only sixteen years intervened before Miletus fell to the Persians. The sheltered position of South Italy
                  during the period the <placeName>Greeks</placeName> were fighting the hosts of Darius and the Sicilians the Carthaginians, has slight
                  bearing on the period of the incuse coinage. Before passing to the issues of Metapontum, it is desirable that we examine the coinage of this
                  group of cities to see what evidence their money may have for their history.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e333" type="section">
               <head>THE INCUSE FABRIC.</head>
               <p>The fabric of the incuse coins used in common by almost all of the Achaean cities before the fall of <placeName corresp="#nomisma_sybaris">Sybaris</placeName>, was accepted by Lenormant as
                  cause for thinking that there must have been a monetary confederation, and the issues in this form of Dorian <placeName corresp="#nomisma_tarentum">Tarentum</placeName> and Chalcidian
                  Rhegium—trade rivals of the other cities—did not deter him. Dr. George Macdonald has shown,<ref target="CH1-n16">16</ref> however, that there
                  are other serious objections, the chief of which is the variation in the weight standards within the presumed confederation. He seeks an
                  explanation in some practical consideration— adopting Mr. Hill's idea that the form may have been dictated by a desire to stack or pack the
                     coins.<ref target="CH1-n17">17</ref> The difficulty in the way of accepting this will be evident if one tries to "stack" even a <pb n="14"/> few of the staters of Sybaris or <placeName corresp="#nomisma_metapontum">Metapontum</placeName>—they form a very unstable column. Is it possible that we may find some better and more
                  practical explanation ?</p>
               <p>What has been said of the preeminence of Sybaris, at once suggests the probability that this city was the originator of the incuse fabric.
                  Metapontum and <placeName corresp="#nomisma_poseidonia">Poseidonia</placeName> were both colonies of Sybaris, and it is hardly likely that they would have instituted the form. Croton or Caulonia
                  might have initiated this style of coining, but neither were of a size or importance to have their practice seized upon by their so much
                  larger neighbor. It seems, strangely enough, to have been a spontaneous invention and to have been evolved without any evolutionary
                  development. Mr. Head's position<ref target="CH1-n18">18</ref> that the swastika-incuse issues of Corinth were used as a model does not carry
                  full conviction. Possibly the trade relations between <placeName corresp="#nomisma_magna_graecia">Magna Graecia</placeName> and <placeName corresp="#nomisma_corinth">Corinth</placeName> may have brought the germ of the idea, but the hiatus between
                  the two forms is too great to say that the one is derived from the other. We have one of these Corinthian issues used for the flan of a late
                  Metapontum stater of the thickened type which must have been struck about 490 B. C., and the idea that it had been the pattern would imply
                  that the Corinthian piece had been in circulation more than sixty years before restriking. <pb n="15"/> Having only the slight value which
                  attaches to negative evidence, is the circumstance that these pieces have seldom or never been found in hoards unearthed outside Italy. This
                  carries the suggestion that the consideration of preventing the export of money and, consequently, of restricting its circulation to South
                  Italy must have been prominent in the minds of those responsible for originating the form. Again, we rarely find these incuse pieces
                  overstruck. Any attempt to attribute the form to Pythagoras will have to take into consideration that he must have left Samos a fairly
                  considerable number of years after the earliest issues.</p>
               <p>There is one circumstance in this incuse coinage as a whole that is of help in our study of the issues of Metapontum. It affords in certain
                  cases a parallel evolution, but Croton alone covers satisfactorily the same period as Metapontum. The destruction of Sybaris in 510 is
                  invaluable as a dating criterion. Up to that time, the coins of Sybaris were of the wide, thin flans, although examination reveals a barely
                  perceptible diminution in the size of the flans, but, more particularly, in the size of the dies.</p>
               <p>We should be under no illusion that we have a complete or even an approximately complete series of these incuse coins. The next hoard of them
                  that is unearthed will, doubtless, provide <pb n="16"/> pieces from dies whose like has never been seen before. It follows almost without
                  saying, therefore, that there can be no claim to completeness for this material, even though we try to record all the varieties at present in
                  cabinets devoted to Greek coins.</p>
               <p>Whether what we now have sufficiently approaches completeness to permit a probable reconstruction of the coinage of Metapontum, is quite
                  another question, the answer to which is obviated by the fact that we must obtain what benefit we can from the facts in hand. Should
                  additional facts at some future time make rearrangement of this material necessary, it will have provided in the meantime means for the
                  identification and, perhaps, for the further classification of the issues of this city.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e361" type="section">
               <head>THE MINTING PROCESS.</head>
               <p>Turning to the coins of Metapontum, in the light of the evidence afforded by the coins themselves, it is at once apparent that they are struck
                  from a pair of inter-locking dies. The cutting of the obverse die would be comparatively simple. It is in the reverse die that difficulties
                  are met, and this is due especially to the circumstance that the ear is in such high relief. In some of the specimens, the high point of the
                  middle row of grains is 4 mm. from the field. If the reader is <pb n="17"/> interested in the technical discussion which follows, he will be
                  greatly aided by taking one of these incuse staters and making an impression of the reverse in sealing wax or any soft modeling wax or
                  plastolene. Failing that, if he will take one of our plates and conceive of the lighting for the reverses as coming from the direction
                  opposite to that actually used; through an optical illusion the reverse of the coin will appear as though in relief and consequently like the
                  die itself. He can then follow the argument with sufficient closeness.</p>
               <p>To cut the reverse die directly, the die-cutter would have had to remove the entire surface of the die, with the exception of the ear itself
                  and the rim, and he would have had to cut to a depth equal to the relief of the highest point of the ear. In other words, about three-quarters
                  of the surface to a uniform depth of nearly 4 mm. would have to be removed and all of the delicate portions of the relief would have to be
                  left untouched, including the rim as well as the awns. This feat is not impossible, but that it could have been carried out for so extended a
                  coinage without having left some traces is almost inconceivable. Was there any other manner of preparing the die which was open to our
                  artist?</p>
               <p>We know very little about ancient dies, especially Greek ones, because almost none that are above suspicion have come down to us. Mr. G. F.
                     <pb n="18"/> Hill, in a very carefully thought-out article on ancient methods of coining,<ref target="CH1-n19">19</ref> summarizes the
                  evidence to be drawn from them. We do not know whether the ancient dies were of steel or of bronze hardened in a manner with which we are not
                  acquainted, and as much depends upon knowing this, our reasoning has to be speculative. It seems probable that some method of hardening the
                  dies was known, just as some method of annealing the silver flans to be struck seems to have been practiced. The circumstances because of
                  which it is impossible to believe that the reverse dies were cut directly at Metapontum, i.e., in relief (cameo) have just been cited. All of
                  these difficulties would be eliminated, however, if what is known as a "hub" in the making of modern medals were used. From the hub, which is
                  the negative of the die, a die can be struck and hardened. Being the negative of the reverse die (which we have seen is in high relief), the
                  hub for this reverse would have to be cut intaglio, just as the obverse had been and as all the gems of this period were cut. If tempering was
                  practiced, the obverse die and the reverse hub would be cut intaglio in the untempered metal and later hardened. Into this hardened hub, the
                  reverse die, probably in a heated state, would have been driven. The die so obtained was then finished and after hardening was ready for
                  use.</p>
               <pb n="19"/>
               <p>If the reverse die was forced into a "steel" hub in a heated state it would have "drawn the temper" of that hub; that is, its heated condition
                  would have burnt out the carbon of the hub and softened it. Unless the ancients had a knowledge of retempering such a hub, it could not have
                  been used again. The reverse dies are fully as numerous as the obverse ones and no evidence of re-using these hubs has been found, although we
                  have reverse dies showing re-cutting (Classes IX and X), and obverse dies with alterations (Cf. Nos. 1-4 and 151). We can hardly escape the
                  conclusion, in the light of these facts, that the "hub" which has been postulated was used simply to get around the difficulty of cutting the
                  reverse die directly in relief.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e381" type="section">
               <head>THE INCUSE FORMAT ELSEWHERE.</head>
               <p>If we have reached a conviction that hubs were used at <placeName corresp="#nomisma_metapontum">Metapontum</placeName>, it does not follow that this method was used for the entire incuse coinage
                  of South Italy. Where the reverse is very deep, the same reasons in favor of hubs found for Metapontine coins apply, but the shallow incuse
                  coins of <placeName corresp="#nomisma_poseidonia">Poseidonia</placeName> and Caulonia give one pause, and make a more careful and detailed examination of them advisable before forming an opinion.
                  The engraved details for the coins of both of these <pb n="20"/> cities, such as the trident and drapery for Poseidonia and the horns of the
                  stag for Caulonia, as well as the inscriptions, could have been added to the die whether it had been prepared from a hub or cut directly. The
                  herring-bone rim could also have been cut either way—a circumstance which is not true of the reverse awns of the Metapontine dies. Certain of
                  the Poseidonia pieces have very shallow incuses and the design is limited to two planes, the second of which is only slightly separated from
                  the other. These would not present the difficulties of modelling which the barley ear provides at <placeName corresp="#nomisma_metapontum">Metapontum</placeName> or the bull at <placeName corresp="#nomisma_sybaris">Sybaris</placeName>. In favor
                  of the hubbing theory, however, certain of the dies which do not have such simple treatment of the design (Pl. 23, G, H, I) must be cited.
                  Here there is cause for believing that the bungling nature of the modelling could have been due to nothing else than an attempt to cut the die
                  directly and the contrast of this crudity with more usual finish of the other dies supports the position that hubs were customary.</p>
               <p>The first coin illustrated on Pl. xxiii—the beautiful stater in the collection of M. Vlasto— shows the procedure at <placeName corresp="#nomisma_tarentum">Tarentum</placeName>, where but few of
                  the <hi rend="italic">incusi</hi> were struck. Note on the reverse, that the lines of the breast, the strings of the lyre, and the locks of
                  the hair are in relief on the coin, and were therefore cut intaglio on the <pb n="21"/> die. Had the die been cut direct, these elements would
                  have had to be kept in mind from the very beginning, and the whole planned accordingly. In the stater of <placeName corresp="#nomisma_sybaris">Sybaris</placeName> with the locust (B), note the
                  wealth of linear detail—it is hard to conceive that these lines were cut other than intaglio on the die after it came from the hub. In the PAA
                  piece (D), note that the reverse rim must have been done similarly—i.e., after the die had come from the hub with a simple raised rim, this
                  attempt to reproduce a cable border was made by countersinking the dots and by engraving the tiny lines between them; both the dots and the
                  lines are in relief on the coin. In the piece from Poseidonia (F), the inscription, the trident, the details of the drapery, the features and
                  the lines of the torso are all in relief. Note that the drapery passes behind the body, just as on the obverse—on many of the reverses of
                  Poseidonia, it passes in front of the figure. In the stater of Croton shown, from the Hunterian collection, note that the reverse decorations
                  of an octopus and a dolphin have no relation to the crab of the obverse.</p>
               <p>Referring to Plate xii, it will be seen that Class VIII of the incuse ears consists entirely of what have been called "imitations". There
                  seems to have been an attempt with at least three of these reverse dies to cut them directly, just as has been described for the late issues
                  of Caulonia. <pb n="22"/> As a result, the barley ear is very crude and the manner of cutting the awns and the border is entirely
                  misunderstood. The awns have been engraved in the die and therefore show in relief on the coins. The border has been formed by leaving a flat
                  rim which has been cut across at unequal intervals giving a result that is coarse and irregular. Some of the other coins on this plate leave
                  the impression that they may have been from official dies which had fallen into unworthy hands and had been re-worked. No single explanation
                  serves for all of them, but the treatment of the border and the awns at once reveals the novice's hand and furnishes a basis for the
                  conclusion that the incuse format may have been a means of keeping counterfeiters from imitating these issues. A variety which had not come to
                  my attention until after Plate xii was finished is reproduced herewith— No. 154c.</p>
               <p>The issue for Croton and Pandosia is another latent argument for the hub theory. Please note (Pl. xxiii, E) that the bull of the reverse is in
                  relief on a sunken rectangular field. Had it not been for the fixed idea of the die-cutter that there must be an incuse element to force the
                  metal into the die—that is, had he not been unconscious that this result would have been accomplished with equal effectiveness by cutting the
                  design in the surface plane of the die, rather than in the inta- <pb n="23"/> glio reserve—the piece would have differed not at all from the
                  usual double-relief issues which must have followed it very closely.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e403" type="section">
               <head>DIE ALTERATIONS.</head>
               <p>The difficulties of working with the incuse pieces of <placeName corresp="#nomisma_metapontum">Metapontum</placeName> may have been one reason for their apparent neglect. Aside from double
                  striking and poor preservation there are handicaps due to poor casts or worse photographs. In addition there is the question of altered dies
                  to make further complications. One rather more than usually involved case occurs at the very beginning. In number I, the obverse die shows
                  signs of a break above the apex of the ear and just inside the border. To eliminate these, the border was re-cut and fortunately there are
                  traces of the older border which are still to be discerned. These remedies, however, did not prove sufficient, for in a third state we have
                  the ear apparently cut deeper in the die and the field on either side, including the section occupied by the awns, planed down and the awns
                  re-cut. Previous to this planing down the inscription had been preserved by deepening with tiny punch marks or drill holes and these are to be
                  seen in specimen I c together with the traces of the awns at the previous angle in the field to the left. In the last change, the inscription
                  has been made linear. On the reverse, pos- <pb n="24"/> sibly the old one, but apparently the third used with this obverse, the inscription
                  has been engraved in the die and therefore shows itself raised on the coin. Changes so extensive as these were not frequent in the incuse
                  coinage, or if they were, traces of them, with a few exceptions, have been obliterated. One of these exceptions is the obverse of No. 151 (Pl.
                  xii). Here not only traces of the earlier awns are to be seen but in the field to the left may be discerned the outline of one of the divided
                  inscriptions. <graphic url="NNM32_sym1.jpg"/> is quite plain and strange to say, no coin with the letters in this position has as yet been
                  found by me.</p>
               <p>It is the reverse dies which oftenest show alterations and many of these have to do with the border which had to withstand the tendency of the
                  silver to spread in striking. Number 22 shows a reverse die that is broken across the inscription. Number 43 shows a reverse die from which a
                  segment has broken in the field to the right. In Class III, however, where the raised rim becomes more regular we find sections of this rim
                  occasionally shearing off as in number 76. When this occurs, because there is nothing to force the metal into the obverse die, the obverse
                  border shows a blank for the space involved, which, in number 76 happens to be just below that occupied by the inscription. In Class IV, a
                  number of the specimens show very considerable skill in mending such <pb n="25"/> breaks of the reverse rim. Number 89 is a case in point and
                  others will be found with numbers 96 and elsewhere. With casts of two or three specimens from the same die it is often possible to notice the
                  development of the flaws and the means used to check further spreading of the fracture. Another form of break for the reverse die is shown in
                  number 87 where the high points of the ear have flaked away leaving the coin filled in throughout the middle row of grains. This is partly due
                  to the boldness of the relief and the size of the flan and possibly also to the incautious pairing of dies, the one imperfectly interlocking
                  with the other. Under such conditions the grains are sometimes found worn through, leaving a hole, but because such coins are not considered
                  desirable by numismatists, they are met with only infrequently. Another form of break which is much rarer is to be observed in number 93 where
                  in the obverse die starting at the base of the ear, a seam has opened which extends above the inscription in the field to the left and along
                  the cable border to a point just above the apex of the ear. Part of the border at the left has been broken away. I do not recall any die-break
                  as extensive as this in any of the other coins which have come under my observation.</p>
               <p>For the thick flan staters, another peculiarity is to be observed. A great many of them bear, in <pb n="26"/> what is obviously their center
                  point, a small pellet or dot. This same pellet is also to be observed in the center of the thick flan staters of Croton, with the incuse
                  flying eagle, Cf. Pl. xxiii, L. The following is submitted as the explanation of its being there. It will be observed that in most of these
                  cases in which a dot appears at the center, the border consists of wedge-like strokes rather coarser than the usual border and pointing toward
                  a common center, that common center being the aforementioned dot. By some mechanical means, with this center as an application point and with
                  a contrivance having a uniform radius, it seems to have been possible to cut the border, or possibly to re-cut it This application point,
                  which in the die exists as a depression, when the die is used for striking, appears on the coin as a pellet. Without some agency such as the
                  foregoing, it is hard to explain either the mechanical regularity or the coarseness of the border as compared with the fineness of workmanship
                  which occurs on the rest of the design of the Croton staters with the eagle reverse, as well as on some of the thick flan staters of
                  Metapontum. In the latter case it will be observed that occasionally the central point of application for the mechanical device postulated is
                  no longer observable through surface corrosion of the piece or the breaking of the die itself at this point. Illustrations for the Metapontum
                  pieces <pb n="27"/> of the foregoing may be noticed in numbers 233, 249 and 191. The practice at <placeName corresp="#nomisma_metapontum">Metapontum</placeName> was apparently not so extensive as
                  at Croton.</p>
               <p>Another form of alteration which seems to have been confined almost entirely to the thick flan staters was designed to permit re-cutting of
                  the border. The function of this reverse border was to force the metal into the die so that the rim on the obverse should come out clearly and
                  sharply. It served as a grip on the flan and kept the flan from spreading. When, with use, the little segments into which it was divided began
                  to wear and to lose their power of gripping, it seems to have been the practice to re-cut the border and, as we have seen, some mechanical
                  device aided in doing this for a number of these thick flan staters. This device, however, was not used for all of them, and re-cutting was
                  accomplished without its agency. It was possible to cut away the field of the die close to the worn rim and to bevel it down so that the
                  transition from the old level was gradual. The greatest cutting away of the field was nearest the rim. It was simple, then, to re-cut the rim
                  thus obtained and once more to have it gripping the flan and keeping it from slipping during the striking. In some cases the re-cut border has
                  trespassed on the outline of the ear and very frequently the point at which the recutting has begun can be established where the <pb n="28"/>
                  end of the work overlaps the beginning. (Compare Nos. 184, 205 and 218.)</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e426" type="section">
               <head>TYPES.</head>
               <p>The types and symbols of the incusi do not begin to compare in importance with those of the double-relief coinage. The παρά#x03C3;ημον of the
                  city is the barley ear, and the conformation of the head of grain is such that there is faint cause for believing it to be wheat. The kernels
                  of wheat are placed irregularly—those of barley are in groups of three. If one attempts to remove a kernel of barley, it will be found that
                  there are two others joined to it and tending to leave the stem at the same time. This badge of the city is constant throughout the coinage
                  with relatively few exceptions—on some of the bronze issues. On one type of the double-relief staters it occurs on both sides, while in one of
                  the gold issues, we find two ears. This occurs also on the "Hannibalic half-units" identified by <persName>M. Vlasto</persName>.</p>
               <p>For the earliest issues we have the stater, the third and the twelfth, all with the barley-ear-incuse reverse. It is possible that there were
                  also sixths, but from the style and the manner of dividing the inscription, it is hard to believe that the pieces of this denomination with
                  the bull's head incuse reverse came into use before the thick-flan staters and it seems probable that the twelfths with the <pb n="29"/>
                  barley grain (incuse) reverse (Pl. xxi) were contemporaneous with these sixths.</p>
               <p>It should be noticed that the bull's head on the reverse of the sixths is not a bucranium. There are marked variations in the type as an
                  examination of plates xxii and xxi will show. The circular frame of the die permitted the designer but scant liberty and the curves of the
                  animal's horns are presumably a resultant of this condition. On numbers 283 and 290 the bull has short horns— either a deliberate indication
                  of the animal's not having reached full growth or less probably a reproduction of a shorthorned variety. The downward curve of the horns is in
                  contrast to their normal position and might lead us to think that the intention was to represent the head of an ox or bullock. The shorthorned
                  type will bear comparison with the issues of Phocis, which, of course, are in relief. Thus, by analogy with the use of the barley ear, this
                  type is a reference to the flocks and herds of the city as a contributory source of its wealth. We may see therein support for identification
                  of the horned male head of the double relief series as that of Apollo Karneios rather than Zeus Ammon.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e440" type="section">
               <head>SUBSIDIARY SYMBOLS.</head>
               <p>Although the barley ear is an almost constant type throughout the Metapontine coinage, the sub- <pb n="30"/> sidiary symbols have exceptional
                  variety. With the double relief issues the barley ear occupies the reverse and the obverse types change frequently. It is not my present
                  purpose to consider these type-changes. The subsidiary symbols are not frequent on the incuse coinage, but they must be considered as a whole
                  and, therefore, their use on the later issues must be anticipated here.</p>
               <p>Perhaps, the first significant condition revealed by study of these symbols at <placeName corresp="#nomisma_metapontum">Metapontum</placeName> is that the explanation that answers for the
                  earliest issues does not suffice for the later ones and that the procedure from 325 to 300 B. C. is certainly not the same as that from 425 to
                  400.</p>
               <p>(a) During the period of the incuse coinage symbols are used very sparingly. Nos. 100-102, 104-105, have on the obverse a grasshopper and on
                  the reverse (incuse), a dolphin. Others (thick flan) have as subsidiary symbols a ram's head (Nos. 221-228), a mule's head (Nos. 231-2),
                  lizard (Nos. 209-220), murex (Nos. 229-30), and grasshopper (Nos. 258-261), while a grain of barley (or wheat) occurs on one of the thirds
                  (Nos. 108-9). With the exception of the barley grain (and strictly, this can hardly be called an exception) all these symbols are animate.</p>
               <p>(b) In the period of c. 335 B. C. we might take as typical the tetradrachms with the head of Leukippos<ref target="CH1-n20">20</ref> on the
                  obverse. These have as subsidiary <pb n="31"/> symbols the forepart of a lion and the letters A <graphic url="NNM32_sym2.jpg"/> H. The reverse
                  has a club as a symbol and the letters AMI. The name AMI occurs on didrachms with the same symbols<ref target="CH1-n21">21</ref> and also with
                  an open-winged bird as a reverse symbol.<ref target="CH1-n22">22</ref> The name A <graphic url="NNM32_sym2.jpg"/> H occurs on other didrachms
                  with the forepart of a Pegasus<ref target="CH1-n23">23</ref> (although not so directly associated as with the forepart of the lion), and
                  elsewhere with a crescent.<ref target="CH1-n24">24</ref> A M I also occurs on the obverse without a symbol.<ref target="CH1-n25">25</ref>
               </p>
               <p>(c) About 400 the procedure is much simpler —we have either the symbol or the initial letters —sometimes neither. The last condition, however,
                  is easily explainable, for the obverse type changes would serve to distinguish the issues.</p>
               <p>At Maroneia we find the names alone and later the names with symbols in addition. For this city the names are often complete and leave no
                  question of two persons having names with the same initial letters. We find the same names recurring after a fairly considerable interval, the
                  interval being indicated by weight, style or technique.</p>
               <p>The warrant for believing these symbols to be magistrates' badges rests on a fairly firm foundation. As shown by Sir Arthur Evans,<ref target="CH1-n26">26</ref> the Heracleian tables<ref target="CH1-n27">27</ref> offer a close analogy, which might fairly be applied to the
                  period to which they are attributed and therefore the procedure <pb n="32"/> outlined by them is reasonably certain to have been in use for a
                  term sufficiently long to have become established.</p>
               <p>If we try to believe that these badges are those of magistrates appointed annually, we get into difficulties for at Maroneia we have the same
                  name recurring two, three or even four times and at intervals. But it is obvious that these badges do serve to distinguish one issue of the
                  coinage of a city from another. Ostensibly they have as their purpose the tracing back to a responsible individual of questions of debasing or
                  underweight or other forms of unrighteousness in connection with their manufacture.</p>
               <p>Viewing the question from the angle of the small city state, it is hardly reasonable to suppose that the coinage needs of the many Greek towns
                  with mints were uniform from year to year. No mint of the modern world puts forth equal issues for each successive twelve-month—why should the
                  requirements of the comparatively small towns of Greece be independent of the score of conditions which affect the amount of currency required
                  for local needs ? Certainly during conflicts with neighboring rivals, the needs were greater than in times of peace. This is shown for <ref target="http://coinhoards.org/id/igch0358">Mende
                  by the hoard found there in 1914</ref>. M. Babel on decided upon 423 as the year in which the hoard was probably buried,<ref target="CH1-n28">28</ref> and working independently <pb n="33"/> and viewing the evidence from another angle, my own conclusions coincided with his.<ref target="CH1-n29">29</ref> This was the year in which the city surrendered to the Athenians and the hoard shows unmistakably a quickening of
                  the coinage just preceding its burial. This evidence may be drawn from the circumstance that there is an increase in the number of dies or
                  rather an increase in the number of dies which are muled one with the other, thus showing their contemporaneity. These dies are distinguished
                  by exergual-symbols which recur on differing dies and which, therefore, may not be identified as artists' symbols or die-distinctions.
                  Insistence here is merely upon the point that the coinage needs of Mende were greater during the period of its conflict with <placeName corresp="#nomisma_athens">Athens</placeName> than at a
                  normal period and that the coinage shows this. It is now generally accepted as proven that the occasional gold issues of cities not
                  customarily striking gold coins are attributable to a time of war—the best illustrations being the gold issues of <placeName corresp="#nomisma_tarentum">Tarentum</placeName> at the time of the
                  coming of Alexander of Molossos and the gold issues for Athens. Unquestionably the silver issues must have felt some of this stimulus— and the
                  more so in cities which never put forth gold issues.</p>
               <p>In contrast, for a small city state during a long stretch of peaceful years, there must have been many conditions which would have affected
                  the <pb n="34"/> number of coins minted. In agricultural districts, the failure of crops would automatically have cut down the expenditures of
                  its citizens and reduced the need for media of exchange. Other modifications would vary with each of the cities.</p>
               <p>Turning to the economic aspect of the mint itself, very few of these towns had mines to provide the metal they needed for their coins. Whence
                  did it come and how was the purchase of the metal arranged? When brought from a distance it was subject to capture by enemies, to loss in
                  transit or to any of the many chances which one's imagination can supply. Taking such conditions into consideration, are we not compelled to
                  give to the monetary magistrate a higher place than has hitherto been assigned him? His was a position of responsibility. He was trusted to
                  keep the metal unadulterated—his probity was subjected to many other tests. He must have received some remuneration and this coupled with the
                  responsibility must have made the office a desirable one. For such cities as Corinth, where the badge of the city, Pegasus, remained
                  unchanged, and where the symbol for the issue appears beside the Athena head of the reverse, there would have been not the slightest
                  difficulty in handing on the Pegasus die from one "magistrate" to the next. In certain of the mints there seems to be a reference through the
                  symbols to some local occurrence rather than <pb n="35"/> to a personal badge. This, however, offers but a slight difficulty if we realize
                  that the person responsible for such an issue would presumably be well known, and therefore, need no identification on the coin itself.</p>
               <p>Would not most of our difficulties be eliminated, if we could see in these symbols, the identification for a particular issue, thereby
                  admitting that the symbol might be a badge or a reference to the agency responsible for it, whether that agent were an individual, whether
                  that agency had some connection with a religious festival or a more direct relation to the temple of a local deity, or whether there were some
                  intention of investing the symbol with significance of a purely civic or local nature, such as a victory?</p>
               <p>But some will say, "Wherein then lies the difference between all this and the magistrate-symbol idea?" The difference lies in the application,
                  but it is much greater than it seems. The advantage of the theory is that it gets away from the time element—from our modern way of thinking
                  of a uniform number of coins struck for each year or that the "magistrate" was appointed for a set period. Our theory admits of there having
                  been periods in the smaller cities during which no coins at all were struck. It also considers that during a season of stress many times the
                  normal requirements must have been issued and by associating <pb n="36"/> an increase in the coinage with known crises in the history of the
                  city concerned, we are given a basis for dating which may prove very valuable. It has also a very direct bearing on the employment of artists
                  for the die-cutting and makes plausible the recurrence of their signatures in more than one of the cities of <placeName>Magna
                     Graecia</placeName>.</p>
               <p>To test the theory, permit me first to apply it to <placeName corresp="#nomisma_metapontum">Metapontum</placeName>'s issues. Mention has been made of the di-staters with the head of Leukippos.
                  These form the only issue of this denomination at Metapontum and as one of the two issues of gold coins also has for its type the head of
                     Leukippos,<ref target="CH1-n30">30</ref> there is no reason for questioning the assignment to the period of Alexander of Epirus, if we
                  accept the customary explanation regarding such gold issues. Just as might be expected, we find an increase in the output of staters also at
                  this time and this is established by the occurrence of the same initials as appear on the di-staters. We find more than twenty-two dies with
                  the lion's head for symbol with A M I and club on reverse, and sixteen dies for this type with the seated dog. We also find staters of this
                  type with other symbols and with varying combinations of symbols and initials. We find the thunderbolt which occurs on the coinage of
                  Alexander of Epirus and which we are accustomed to accept as his signet, associated with A M I, a name which also oc- <pb n="37"/> curs
                  without the Alexander reference. We might read from this "struck by A M I, the agent of Alexander."</p>
               <p>The magnitude of these respective issues is indicated by the number of dies, but instead of an issue which extended over an interval equal to
                  the collective life of the dies, it is much more logical to believe the issue to have been struck within a comparatively short period.</p>
               <p>Earlier in the coinage of Metapontum (c. 400), we find a beautiful head of Kore bearing the first three letters of the name of Aristoxenos at
                  the base of the neck, a position favored by this artist who signs two other dies in a similar position.<ref target="CH1-n31">31</ref> This
                  die, easily identified as a single die by a slight defect which gradually enlarges, is found coupled with seven reverse dies, two of which
                  bear symbols and the others of which show slight differences in the position of the inscription or of the accompanying leaf. <hi rend="italic">None of these reverse dies are found coupled with any other obverse</hi>. It seems only reasonable to believe that these reverses were
                  used for successive issues, which were presumably frequent and which must have been comparatively small in size to permit the obverse die to
                  outlive all seven reverse dies.</p>
               <p>One further illustration before passing to the incuse issues which most directly concern us here. Shortly after the adoption of the double-
                     <pb n="38"/> relief style for this city, we find a series of coins with the horned head of Apollo Karneios (7 dies plus two
                     imitations).<ref target="CH1-n32">32</ref> These dies bear neither symbols nor initials. The reverse dies differ very slightly in the
                  arrangement of the awns, of the leaf or of the ear. Is it not reasonable to see here an issue which for some reason sought to honor Apollo
                  Karneios—an issue of a size necessitating the number of dies indicated? The issue may have been for a single year or may have extended over a
                  longer time.</p>
               <p>For the incuse pieces, the grasshopper-dolphin issue illustrated on Plate viii is typical. We have the grasshopper on the obverse coupled (1)
                  with a reverse which is blank, Nos. 101 and 103; (2) with a dolphin in outline—incised in the die and, therefore, in relief on the coin; (3)
                  and with the dolphin incuse—two dies. If the grasshopper is a magistrate's badge,<ref target="CH1-n33">33</ref> what shall we say of the
                  dolphin? Lenormant's belief that the insect was introduced with a propitiatory significance makes no allowance for the dolphin—there may have
                  been a plague of locusts but could there have been a plague of dolphins ?<ref target="CH1-n33">33</ref>
               </p>
               <p>Going back to the theory with which we started, however, there is every reason to believe that whatever its significance on these seven dies,
                  the grasshopper is placed there to distinguish the issue. The die-combinations connote this and com- <pb n="39"/> pared with this circumstance
                  for our present purposes, the significance of the symbol is secondary. In a similar way we may consider the lizard, which appears later on the
                  thick-flan issues. Have we not the well-known statue of Apollo Sauroktonos? Similarly the ram's head symbol might be a further reference to
                  Apollo Karneios, but again the significance is less important for our purpose than the probability that in each case we have a single
                  issue.</p>
               <p>It should be noted that the grasshopper is found repeatedly throughout the Metapontine coinage— there are at least four recurrences of the
                  symbol, all readily distinguishable, and each separated from the other by an appreciable interval. This gives color to the suggestion that
                  this may have been the arms of a family rather than of an individual. Its use as a symbol would have been sufficient to indicate the
                  responsibility for the issue because there would have been a general knowledge as to which member of the clan had been entrusted with the
                  striking of that issue. On one of the later staters there is a combination which seems to support such a suggestion.</p>
               <p>We find on this piece of about 343-39 B. C., in the field of the reverse, an owl devouring a grasshopper. Now owls are nocturnal and
                  grasshoppers are not; furthermore, there are abundant instances of the accuracy of the Greeks' observation in such <pb n="40"/> matters and we
                  can hardly believe that such a combination would occur without intention. The owl, too, occurs previously on the Metapontine issues but
                  without the grasshopper. Have we then a record of a feud between members of the grasshopper clan and the family whose arms were the owl,
                  possibly for the purpose of indicating their Athenian origin? It is interesting to note that the letters which appear on this issue are A Φ A
                  and that there are at least two dies. But the use of the grasshopper as a clan symbol does not explain its occurrence elsewhere—Messana,
                  Mende, Velia, Sybaris. Again we are forced to the conclusion that the evidence is insufficient for dogmatism and all that we can safely deduce
                  is that the issues with this combination of symbols belong together.</p>
               <figure xml:id="fig-4">
                  <graphic url="NNM32_040.jpg"/>
               </figure>
               <p>It would be presumptuous for me to try to apply this principle to the other coinages on which symbols occur. No other explanation I have
                  found, however, works so well for the Corinthian issues, with the coinage of Abdera, or with that of the other cities whose issues have been
                  tested. In <pb n="41"/> the recently published British Museum Catalogue for Cyrene, p. lxxxix-xc, a table is given for pieces bearing
                  magistrates' names. Just as might be expected, certain of the names are found on tetradrachms alone, while others occur on two or more
                  denominations. Would not this connote that A's commission was the striking of tetradrachms only, from a fixed appropriation or quantity of
                  silver, while Magistrate B's task required the issue of all denominations? If some system involving seignorage was in use, B's would probably
                  have been the more desirable appointment. The practice must have varied in the different cities and suffered modifications from century to
                  century, so that each mint's procedure must be studied independently. Metapontum is fairly representative of a number of Greek city-states,
                  and the method used there may be not dissimilar to those of other centers.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e569" type="section">
               <head>CLASSIFICATION.</head>
               <p>The incuse coinage of <placeName corresp="#nomisma_metapontum">Metapontum</placeName> has been considered as a monotonous repetition of the barley ear type, but monotonous it is not. The
                  ingenuity with which the design is varied is impressive, and the splendid quality behind these variations is no less wonderful. The relief
                  ranges from exceeding boldness to the greatest delicacy. The die-cutter seems to have taken advantage of every <pb n="42"/> faintest
                  possibility of the material, utilizing not only the subsidiary symbols, such as the grasshopper, but making very decorative groupings of the
                  initial letters of the city's name as well.</p>
               <p>In describing these issues, it is desirable to eliminate undue repetition and to decide upon a form which will leave room for no mistake. It
                  will be noticed that the end of the barley ear sometimes tapers and sometimes is square-cut. For distinguishing these dies (such as that of
                  No. 88), it has been found advisable to state the number of grains in each row. The outer rows of No. 88 contain six grains each, while the
                  one in the middle has seven, and on either side of the topmost central grain there are two tiny additional grains. In describing the dies it
                  is the outer rows which have been counted because very often the middle row is worn and it is difficult to distinguish the number of its
                  grains. In consequence, the formula used herein is "six-grained barley ear with small additional terminal grains." Doublestriking and wear
                  make it advisable to rely on the number of grains to the ear except where there are no other outstanding points of differentiation.</p>
               <p>From each of the grains in the ear extend the long lines of what we call the "beard" of the grain. The units are technically known as awns and
                  as such are referred to hereinafter. Later, <pb n="43"/> with the double relief coinage, each of these awns is shown with the small barbs with
                  which they are equipped in nature—an instance of the closeness of observation of the Greeks, of which we shall have many another
                  illustration.</p>
               <p>Another convention which has been used throughout applies to the inscription. Neither the British Museum Catalogue nor that of the Berlin
                  Museum is entirely satisfactory or entirely free from ambiguity on this score. The scheme used is a modification of one outlined by M. Arthur
                  Sambon in the Revue Numismatique for 1916.<ref target="CH1-n34">34</ref> Again referring to No. 88, it will be seen that we have the first
                  four letters of the city's name and that these are divided, the two on the left being read downward, the two on the right upward. By using a
                  colon to indicate the ear and placing a line above the letters to show which part of the letters (i. e., the top or the base) is nearest the
                  awns (<graphic url="NNM32_sym3.jpg"/>), there is no longer any room for doubt as to the order of the letters. When, however, as with No. 135,
                  the inscription is straightforward on one side and retrograde on the other, it seems wiser not to print the latter portion of the inscription
                  backwards but to make our convention meet the case by indicating the uppermost letter by a dot over that letter. The formula for 135 thus
                  becomes <graphic url="NNM32_sym4.jpg"/> Nor does it seem wise to repeat the archaic letters <pb n="44"/> again and again. Oftentimes the
                  printed letter is but a poor approximation to what appears on the coins. Moreover, in the majority of cases, the letters are readily
                  distinguishable on the plates which presumably would first be consulted for purposes of identification.</p>
               <p>It remains to indicate the broad classes into which the early coinage divides itself. For this purpose the form of border is the first
                  criterion, although the size of the flan does enter, especially with the latest class.</p>
               <p>CLASS I (Nos. 1-36; 37-39 imitations). For the first class the distinctive mark of difference is the pair of tiny folioles or bracts at the
                  base of the ear of barley on the obverse. These do not occur in any other series or class. Besides this, the border is also distinctive.
                  Usually it is described as "of coarse dots" or <hi rend="italic">"grènetis".</hi> It will be seen that inside this coarse border an inner
                  border, very much finer, begins early, (Plate II) and that this develops by steps which have a clear evolutionary trend and ultimately becomes
                  continuous and linear. The inscription is usually confined to the first three letters of the city's name, sometimes, but not frequently,
                  retrograde; on the obverse, with one or two exceptions they are to the left of the ear—on the reverse, to the right. These three letters also
                  occur in a few reverse dies but <hi rend="italic">in relief</hi>—that is they have been <pb n="45"/> engraved in the reverse die after it was
                  otherwise complete and therefore are in relief on the coin itself. This peculiarity is not found elsewhere in the incuse coinage until we
                  reach the Class XI with the pieces of smallest module.</p>
               <p>CLASS II (Nos. 40-50) is not large in numbers. In contrast with Class I, the rim is not coarse and is in the same plane or almost the same
                  plane as the field. It is not raised as in succeeding classes. The inner linear circle which supplemented the coarser one in Class I has now
                  as a complement, an <hi rend="italic">outside</hi> circle as well, so that the border now becomes a circle of dots between two linear circles.
                  The bracts which occur throughout Class I are absent. The inscription is uniformly to the left and of three letters only. The relief
                  throughout is very flat, the ears are short and well-centered, and the stem long.</p>
               <p>CLASSES III to VIII really form a single large group which has been separated for convenience of identification. There is a sharp break
                  between this group and the two earlier groups, and no satisfactory connecting link has been found. Whether this means that there was a break
                  in the coinage or merely a change of workmen and a consequent change of style in the output, it is impossible to say. What is more likely is
                  that no hoard has furnished us with the issues of just this time. The classification is not strictly <pb n="46"/> chronological, but neither
                  is it purely arbitrary; the arrangement endeavors to obviate the difficulties of identifying the dies in view of the close similarity of some
                  of them.</p>
               <p>CLASS III (Nos. 54-84). The distinctive feature of this class is the increased module, some dies reaching 31 mm. in diameter. This is larger
                  than any other class within the coinage. The border is similar in form to that of Class II, but is now pronouncedly raised. It should be noted
                  also that the border for the reverse die has undergone a change and is now beautifully regular. In Class I this reverse border was coarse; in
                  the next division it had become less crude but without having reached the form in which it appears here. (Cf. the discussion of the technical
                  elements of this under die-making and die-breaks.) The ears are in exceptionally high relief but modelled with the greatest of delicacy. The
                  inscriptions are uniformly to the right and either MET or META and in only one case retrograde. A comparison of numbers 58 and 79 will show
                  that the line of progression to the next class is none too certain. It will be noticed that the reverse of the former coin has eight grains to
                  the ear while the obverse has six.</p>
               <p>CLASS IV (Nos. 85-99). In this class the inscription is divided, save for one exception—85a —where it is to the left. (Cf. also Class VIII for
                     <pb n="47"/> imitations.) The style is close to that of Class III in some specimens but in general the barley ears are composed of rows
                  having six very large grains. The relief is bold and well-modelled. In this and in the succeeding class we have the introduction of the
                  guilloche border, which is also found on some of the thick flan staters, on the coinage of <placeName corresp="#nomisma_sybaris">Sybaris</placeName>, as well as on some of the other incuse
                  coinages of Magna Graecia. At the end of the series there are one or two dies of a reduced module (26 mm.) which have been placed here because
                  of their divided inscription. They serve to indicate that the order within these classes was independent of our arbitrary arrangement and that
                  these two dies probably came close to the beginning of what we call Class IX, the thick flan staters.</p>
               <p>CLASS V (Nos. 100-111) is easily to be distinguished by the presence of the subsidiary symbols of the grasshopper on the obverse and the
                  dolphin on the reverse, the latter in outline only, as well as <hi rend="italic">intaglio.</hi> The dies vary from 28 mm. to 26 mm. in
                  diameter and are thought by some to show the high-water mark for the incuse coinage. Border guillochée.</p>
               <p>CLASS VI (Nos. 112-135). This class is distinguished from Class III, aside from style, chiefly by its smaller module (26 to 27.5 mm.). The
                  inscription is in four letters but not divided (see <pb n="48"/> also Class VIII for imitations). There are nineteen varieties with
                  inscription to right, five to left. The letter A is frequently the most helpful criterion in distinguishing dies, not only in its special
                  relation to the rest of the design but in view of its form—round or pointed top and with its cross bar downward to either right or left.</p>
               <p>CLASS VII (Nos. 136-144). This class is easily distinguishable because of its five-letter inscription. The variations in the form of the ear
                  show that these staters were not issued as a class. Comparison with the other issues demonstrates that they should be interpolated among the
                  coins arranged arbitrarily (like these) on preceding plates. The coins are rather less common than most of the other varieties and show the
                  gradual decrease in module which has been noticed in some of the preceding classes. The last two varieties really belong to the thick flan
                  staters.</p>
               <p>CLASS VIII (Nos. 145-154b). Imitations. These pieces because of the crudity of their style or of their lettering or of both, have been
                  separated and placed in a class by themselves. They have been discussed at length in considering the making of dies. In general, they exhibit
                  a lack of understanding of the methods used for the rest of the incuse coinage—a difference so great as to warrant considering them unofficial
                  imitations. An examination of the reverse dies will bring this <pb n="49"/> out very clearly, especially in the treatment of the awns and the
                  borders.</p>
               <p>CLASS IX (Nos. 155-208). Thick flan staters without symbols. Module approximately 24 mm. This class for convenience is sub-divided into (1)
                  inscriptions right, (a) with three letters, (b) with four letters, and (2) inscriptions left (a) with three letters, (b) with four
                  letters.</p>
               <p>This is perhaps the least interesting class of the entire incuse coinage. The dies are difficult to distinguish one from another, especially
                  when the coins are at all worn. The chief variations occur in the inscriptions, but these may have been recut in some cases. The rims of the
                  reverses are sometimes recut—compare Nos. 176 and 191.</p>
               <p>CLASS X (Nos. 209-232). Thick flan staters with symbols (excepting the grasshopper types of class XII). These symbols are the lizard, ram's
                  head, mule's head, murex. The module varies from 24 to 16 mm. Some of the reverses have inscriptions engraved in the die and in relief on the
                  coins, notably 228, 229, 230.</p>
               <p>CLASS XI (Nos. 233-257); Small flans without symbols, ranging from 20 mm. to 16 mm. As with Class X, some of the coins have inscriptions
                  engraved on the reverse dies (Cf. numbers 246, 247, 248).</p>
               <p>CLASS XII (Nos. 258-261). The grasshopper types of the thick flan issues. These are separated <pb n="50"/> and placed here because of their
                  connection with the double relief issues.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e648" type="section">
               <head>DATING OF THE INCUSE ISSUES</head>
               <p>There is slight reason for thinking that the date assigned by Head in <ref target="http://nomisma.org/id/head_1911">Historia Numorum</ref> for the incuse coinages of <placeName corresp="#nomisma_metapontum">Metapontum</placeName> needs any
                  changing, although there is not much positive evidence to justify making 470 the date for the last of the incuse issues. For the beginning of
                  the coinage, we can only gauge that it must have been well before the destruction of <placeName corresp="#nomisma_sybaris">Sybaris</placeName> (510). The extensive coinage of that city
                  warrants believing that it may have begun as early as 550 B. C. The great influence of <placeName corresp="#nomisma_sybaris">Sybaris</placeName> must have been partly responsible for the
                  continued use of the thin <hi rend="italic">incusi</hi> up to the time of Croton's victory, but for this there is only the negative evidence
                  of hoards that the thin form did not long continue after the downfall of <placeName corresp="#nomisma_sybaris">Sybaris</placeName>. The practice of overstriking was much more common with the
                  thick flan staters and especially with the later issues. But these, save with some of the issues from Agrigentum, offer little help in dating.
                  M. Babelon in his Traité illustrates the Achelous piece as coming before 470 and in view of its having an obverse die identical with that of
                  No. 91, his conclusions, based on style and lettering, are borne out. There seems <pb n="51"/> small reason for doubting that the somewhat
                  similar standing Apollo and Hercules issues in double relief also followed closely upon the thick-flan <hi rend="italic">incusi.</hi> The
                  early stater issued by Pandosia, which is so obviously modeled on these issues of Metapontum, helps to confirm this placing of them (Cf.
                  Head's illustration and remarks).<ref target="CH1-n35">35</ref> With the Metapontine issues in mind, it is easy to complete the obverse type,
                  which the bad preservation of the British Museum specimen has made indefinite in the cut used by Head. The object at the lower left is clearly
                  an altar similar to that on several dies of Metapontum.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e664" type="section">
               <head>HOARDS</head>
               <p>With the exception of the <ref target="http://coinhoards.org/id/igch1881">Curinga</ref> and the <ref target="http://coinhoards.org/id/igch1874">Taranto</ref> hoards, we have no adequate account of hoards in which the incuse coins of <placeName corresp="#nomisma_metapontum">Metapontum</placeName> occur.
                  Those listed in the introduction of Sambon's "Recherches sur les Monnaies Antiques de l'Italie" are helpful but as the varieties are not
                  distinguished, their value is limited. A very important hoard is recorded by von Duhn <ref target="CH1-n36">36</ref> It was found at
                  <ref target="http://coinhoards.org/id/igch1889">Cittanuova in 1879</ref> and must have contained data which would have settled many questions regarding these South Italian issues, but aside from
                  the portion secured for the Berlin cabinet, we know very little of its make up. Mention has already been made that so far as our present <pb n="52"/> knowledge goes, these <hi rend="italic">incusi</hi> are not found outside of Italy.</p>
               <p>The Curinga hoard is one of which we have record of two-thirds of the pieces unearthed. A list of the varieties is given in a note.<ref target="CH1-n38">38</ref> These show that the hoard must have been buried some time after the adoption of the thick-flan fabric and before
                  the flan had been reduced to its smallest format. B. C. 490 would be a fair approximate date, judging by the issues of Metapontum alone. There
                  are comparatively few of the issues which I consider the earliest. There are none of the grasshopper-dolphin pieces and few or none of the
                  wide-flan and divided-inscription issues of Classes III and IV. Casts of the Metapontum pieces were prepared for me through the kindness of
                  Dr. Orsi.</p>
               <p>The Taranto hoard in the record made by M. Babelon provides much valuable data. It was possible to supplement this by a study of the pieces
                  which still remained in the possession of Messrs. Spink &amp;Son, who courteously permitted me access to this residue. The list appended gives
                  the varieties seen.<ref target="CH1-n39">39</ref> This hoard, again judging by Metapontum's pieces alone, would seem to have been formed at
                  least a decade before the Curinga accumulation. There was at least one of the thick-flan staters but the crystallized condition of most of the
                  pieces left little room for deductions concerning their circulation, although at the same <pb n="53"/> time it served as a reason for
                  believing that this thick flan stater could hardly have been an intrusion. Additions to the hoard must have ceased about the time of the
                  beginning of the use of the thick flan format. It may have been in the process of formation during an extended period since there was a large
                  proportion of the earlier varieties.</p>
               <p>No. 100b, struck over a <placeName corresp="#nomisma_croton">Croton</placeName>
                  <ref target="http://nomisma.org/id/stater">stater</ref>, shares with the <placeName corresp="#nomisma_poseidonia">Poseidonia</placeName> issue struck over the Metapontine type (De Luynes Coll. 524), the
                  distinction of being one of the few overstruck <hi rend="italic">incusi</hi> known to us.</p>
               <p>It is to be hoped that some future hoard will give us more facts upon which to build. The history of <placeName corresp="#nomisma_metapontum">Metapontum</placeName> is so fragmentary that further
                  data would be very welcome.</p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d1e696" type="chapter">
            <pb n="54"/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="bold">DESCRIPTIONS</hi>
            </head>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e701" type="section">
               <head>CLASS I.</head>
               <p>1a <graphic url="NNM32_sym5.jpg"/>
                  <ref target="CH2-n1*">1*</ref> Eight-grained barley ear with bracts or folioles at the base. Border narrow and light. Die-break to left of the
                  apex of the ear and extending to 1. to outermost awn. Double-struck—note awn to r.</p>
               <p>℞ Eight-grained barley ear incuse, tapering slightly toward top.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 28 mm. 8.00 Curinga Hoard.</p>
               <p>1b Same die as 1a. The break has developed. The border is recut and is now coarse. The traces of the earlier border may be seen at the lower
                  1. The enlarging of the border has been at the expense of the field, and has partly eliminated the break above the inscr.</p>
               <p>℞ Die of ia.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 28 mm. 7.78 Taranto Hoard.</p>
               <p>1c Die 1a with further re-cutting. The inscr. has been preserved in its relative position by deepening its outline with some sharp tool so
                  that it is now a sequence of fine points. The rim and pos- <pb n="55"/> sibly the ear have been deepened. The die-break at the apex has been
                  almost, but not entirely eliminated. The awns, now at an angle of 45 degrees do not obliterate those of the earlier stage of the die, and
                  these may be seen in the field to the left.</p>
               <p>℞ A new die with ear having eight grains and a coarse borde—double struck.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 28 mm. 7.97 The American Numismatic Society (ex Taranto H'd).</p>
               <p>1d Die in later stage than 1c. The die-break at the apex has deepened. The inscr. has been made linear, although there are traces of the
                  stippling visible in 1c.</p>
               <p>℞ Probably same die as 1c, altered by the addition of the inscr. which has been cut in the die and is therefore in relief on the coin.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 28 mm. 7.77 Cambridge (McClean—ex Taranto H'd?); Brandis 72—8.10 (not certainly these dies).</p>
               <p>2 <graphic url="NNM32_sym5.jpg"/> Eight-grained ear. Inscription compact and with die-break to left of the M.</p>
               <p>℞ Very similar to No. 1d—possibly the same die.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 29 mm. —. —Sir Arthur J. Evans; Sir Herman Weber Coll. 734, 7.47.</p>
               <p>3 <graphic url="NNM32_sym5.jpg"/> Eight-grained barley ear. The dots of the border instead of being coarse are fine and regular.</p>
               <pb n="56"/>
               <p>℞ Eight-grained ear, the uppermost grain very small. The border narrow and finer than usual.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 28 mm. 7.90 The American Numismatic Society; Naples (Fiorelli 2283); Spink &amp;Son, ex Taranto H'd, 4
                  specimens, 7.58, 7.78, 7.97 and 7.97; Naville V, 427—8.15; Paris (illustr. in La Musee, 1908. p. 126); <placeName>Berlin</placeName>;
                  Curinga H'd—8.02.</p>
               <p>4 <graphic url="NNM32_sym5.jpg"/> Broad barley ear, 14 mm. wide at base, with flattened bracts which touch the border. Relief very high and
                  bold. Inscr. weakly cut.</p>
               <p>℞ <graphic url="NNM32_sym7.jpg"/> More boldly cut than obv. Base of ear of same width as obv. Inscr. in relief.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 28 mm. 8.06 Jameson (ex Taranto H'd); Bement 150—8.19; E. T. Newell, 6.69; Vienna, 7.74; Cambridge (McClean
                  896), 8.16; Hirsch XXX, 158— 8.20; London (B. M. C. 2), 7.84; Munich; Spink and Son, 7.90, 7.97, 7.76, 7.97, 8.10, 7.81—all ex Taranto H'd,
                  and possibly from variant dies.</p>
               <p>5 <graphic url="NNM32_sym5.jpg"/> Barley ear less broad than No. 4 which this piece may possibly precede. Die shows signs of having broken at
                  border.</p>
               <p>℞ No inscription. Similar to No. 4, but the middle row of grains is narrower.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 28.5 mm. —.— Paris (Taranto H'd. Cf. Rev. Num., 1912, Pl. IV, 12).</p>
               <pb n="57"/>
               <p>6 <graphic url="NNM32_sym7.jpg"/> Eight-grained barley ear tapering toward the top and with short folioles at the base. The border very crude
                  but with an inner circle of dots.</p>
               <p>℞ Nine-grained barley ear, longer and broader than obverse. Border very crude.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 29 mm. —.— Taranto H'd, 1911; The American Numismatic Society, 7.32 (ex Taranto H'd).</p>
               <p>7 <graphic url="NNM32_sym5.jpg"/> The bracts are only slightly curved and do not touch border. Width of ear 8 mm.</p>
               <p>℞ <graphic url="NNM32_sym7.jpg"/> Similar to No. 2. Width of ear 10 mm.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 29.5 mm. 7.84. Taranto H'd, Spink &amp;Son—three, 7.97, 7.90, 8.10; London, B. M. Cat. 4, 7.70.</p>
               <p>8 <graphic url="NNM32_sym5.jpg"/> Eight-grained ear in high relief. The bracts are almost semi-circular and touch the border. Width of ear 8.8
                  mm.</p>
               <p>℞ <graphic url="NNM32_sym7.jpg"/> in relief. Ear, 10 mm. wide, is broader than on obv.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 29 mm. 8.18 Bement 152; Spink and Son, ex Taranto H'd, 2 pcs. weighing 7.97.</p>
               <p>9 <graphic url="NNM32_sym5.jpg"/> Eight-grained barley ear. The middle row constricted to little more than a line. As in No. 12, the
                  workmanship is very crude. The ear is crooked. The inner border of dots is coarse.</p>
               <pb n="58"/>
               <p>℞ The die-workmanship is crude. The border is unlike anything heretofore.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 28.5 mm. 8.10 <placeName corresp="#nomisma_paris">Paris</placeName>.</p>
               <p>10 <graphic url="NNM32_sym5.jpg"/> Eight-grained ear. Inner border of dots well defined. Foliole to left curves upward at outer extremity.</p>
               <p>℞ Eight-grained ear, larger than ear of obv.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 27 mm. 8.00 Vienna; London, B. M. Cat. 5, 7-78; The American Numismatic Society, 7.61; Spink &amp;Son (Taranto
                  H’d), two, one weighng 8.00.</p>
               <p>11 <graphic url="NNM32_sym5.jpg"/> Eight-grained ear. Thick stem.</p>
               <p>℞ Similar to No. 10.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 27 mm. 8.00 Curinga Hoard and one—possibly two others; Charles H. Imhoff; Berlin; Naples (Fiorelli 2284);
                  Munich; Spink &amp;Son (Taranto H’d), two, one 7.97.</p>
               <p>12 <graphic url="NNM32_sym5.jpg"/> Note that E has elongated vertical stroke.</p>
               <p>℞ Similar to No. 10.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 28 mm. 7.07 Curinga Hoard.</p>
               <p>13 <graphic url="NNM32_sym5.jpg"/> Stem very short. The border of dots more pronounced. The ear broader at the centre than at the base.</p>
               <p>℞ Similar to No. 10. Note line just within border.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 27.5 mm. 8.02 Bement Sale 151; Curinga <pb n="59"/> Hoard—two 8.01 and 8.00; Spink &amp;Son (Taranto
                  H’d—7.78).</p>
               <p>14 <graphic url="NNM32_sym5.jpg"/> Similar to No. 13, but bracts more pronounced.</p>
               <p>℞ Similar to No. 13 but with awns at wider angle.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 27.5 mm. 8.21 E. T. Newell; Curinga Hoard, 7.09; Cambridge (Corpus Christi—Lewes Coll.); Spink &amp;Son
                  (Taranto H’d)—four or five, 7.81 (identification not certain), 7.97, 7.84 (two), 7.90; Naville V, 428—7.94.</p>
               <p>15 <graphic url="NNM32_sym5.jpg"/> Compact inscription, the vertical stroke of the T extending slightly beyond the horizontal. Right bract
                  touches border.</p>
               <p>℞ Similar to Nos. 10-14.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 25.5 mm. 8.01 Curinga Hoard.</p>
               <p>16 <graphic url="NNM32_sym5.jpg"/> Similar to No. 14 but the M and the E of the inscription are separated by an interval equal to that which
                  separates the E from the T.</p>
               <p>℞ The ear similar to No. 11.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 28 mm. 8.11 Berlin; Paris (ex Taranto Find, illus. Rev. Num. 1912, PI. IV, No. 11; ten (?) other specimens
                  weighing from 7.50 to 8.15, see also No. 11); W. Gedney Beatty; Arolsen; Curinga Hoard 8.00; Headlam Sale 196, 8.27; Spink &amp;Son (Taranto
                  H’d),— 7.97.</p>
               <p>17 <graphic url="NNM32_sym5.jpg"/> Eight-grained, square-topped ear. Short stem. Inner circle of dots well defined.</p>
               <pb n="60"/>
               <p>℞ Similar to No. 16.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 29 mm. 8.29 (Spink &amp;Son—ex Taranto H'd).</p>
               <p>18 <graphic url="NNM32_sym5.jpg"/> Similar to No. 17.</p>
               <p>℞ Ear tapering slightly toward top.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 28 mm. –.— Naples (Fiorelli 2285).</p>
               <p>19 <graphic url="NNM32_sym5.jpg"/> Short, compact ear of eight grains. The awns at the apex have an interval greater than heretofore.</p>
               <p>℞ Eight-grained ear slightly larger than that of obv.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 28 mm. 7.97 Spink &amp; Son (ex Taranto H'd); Allotte de la Fuye Sale 61, 8.20.</p>
               <p>20 <graphic url="NNM32_sym5.jpg"/> Similar to No. 19. The bracts are unequal in length, and each touches circle of dots inside the main
                  border.</p>
               <p>℞ Closely similar to No. 19.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 29.5 mm. 7.96 Locker-Lampson Coll. 17; Spink's Circular, 53358 (ex Taranto H'd), 8.29 and four others —8.10,
                  8.10, 8.07, 7.78; Curinga Hoard, 8.01; G. F. Marlier, Pittsburgh.</p>
               <p>21 <graphic url="NNM32_sym5.jpg"/> Closely similar to No. 20–possibly same die with inner border made linear. Eightgrained ear, tapering
                  towards top.</p>
               <p>℞ Eight-grained ear, tapering towards top.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 28 mm. –.— <persName>E. P. Robinson</persName>, Newport; Naville V. 64–8.19.</p>
               <pb n="61"/>
               <p>22 Similar to No. 20.</p>
               <p>℞ <graphic url="NNM32_sym8.jpg"/> In relief. Eight-grained ear.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 27.5 mm. —.— <placeName>Berlin</placeName>; Pozzi 156, 7.96; Naville V, 429—7.98; Spink &amp;Son (Taranto
                  H'd), 7.71, 7.97 and 7.41.</p>
               <p>23 <graphic url="NNM32_sym5.jpg"/> Eight-grained ear. Well defined circle within border.</p>
               <p>℞ <graphic url="NNM32_sym7.jpg"/> In relief. Eight-grained barley ear tapering toward apex.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 27.5 mm. 8.05 Curinga Hoard; Hunterian 1, 7.77; Spink &amp;Son (Taranto H'd)—two, one weighing 8.10; Caprotti
                  188, 7.70.</p>
               <p>24 Similar to 18 but the ear not so broad and the inner circle linear.</p>
               <p>℞ <graphic url="NNM32_sym7.jpg"/> In relief. Eight-grained ear.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 27 mm. 8.16 E. T. Newell.</p>
               <p>25 <graphic url="NNM32_sym5.jpg"/> Eight-grained ear of even width. The flan is more than usually cupped. The awns have been deepened to form
                  a continuous line. The border shows recutting in some specimens.</p>
               <p>℞ A broken die. The break at the end of the awn farthest to the right has been repaired and the die recut for a short distance. The crack in
                  the field to the r. has become continuous.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 28.5 mm. —. ——7.99, 816. American Numismatic (2); <placeName corresp="#nomisma_berlin">Berlin</placeName>;
                  Curinga H'd, 8.00.</p>
               <pb n="62"/>
               <p>26 Die of No. 25.</p>
               <p>℞ <graphic url="NNM32_sym7.jpg"/> In relief. Otherwise similar to No. 25.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 28 mm. —.— Spink and Son (Taranto H'd?).</p>
               <p>27 <graphic url="NNM32_sym5.jpg"/> The awns more widely separated than heretofore. The flattened bracts do not touch the border which has an
                  inner linear circle, but no apparent outer circle.</p>
               <p>℞ Similar to Obv. in dimensions. The bracts are present at the base of the ear for the single time on the r. in the entire incuse series.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 27.5 mm. 8.00 E. T. Newell.</p>
               <p>28 <graphic url="NNM32_sym7.jpg"/> Seven-grained ear tapering toward top; with folioles. Coarse border similar to that of Nos. 1-5.</p>
               <p>℞ Seven-grained ear.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 16.5 mm. 1/3 stater 2.69 E. T. Newell.</p>
               <p>29 <graphic url="NNM32_sym5.jpg"/> Tapering seven-grained ear with small additional terminal grains; folioles at base.</p>
               <p>℞ <graphic url="NNM32_sym7.jpg"/> Seven-grained ear with tiny additional terminal grains.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 19.5 mm. 1/3 stater 2.59 Spink &amp;Son 53376; <placeName corresp="#nomisma_berlin">Berlin</placeName>
                  (2).</p>
               <pb n="63"/>
               <p>30 <graphic url="NNM32_sym5.jpg"/> Seven-grained ear. Folioles very slight.</p>
               <p>℞ Seven-grained ear.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 19 mm. 1/3 stater —.— Paris; Vienna (2, 2.43 and 2.46).</p>
               <p>31 <graphic url="NNM32_sym5.jpg"/> Seven-grained ear similar to No. 28.</p>
               <p>℞ Seven-grained ear.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 18.5 mm. 1/3 stater 2.66 G. F. Marlier, Pittsburgh.</p>
               <p>32 <graphic url="NNM32_sym5.jpg"/> Seven-grained ear with right foliole higher than 1. Coarse border.</p>
               <p>℞ Seven-grained ear.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 17.5 mm. 1/3 stater —.— Berlin; C. S. Bement; <persName>E. S. G. Robinson;</persName>
                  <persName>Arolsen;</persName>
                  <persName>Vienna</persName>, 2.42; <persName>H. Chapman</persName>.</p>
               <p>33 <graphic url="NNM32_sym5.jpg"/> Narrow seven-grained ear with folioles, similar to Nos. 7-8.</p>
               <p>℞ Seven-grained ear, very broad at base.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 17.5 mm. 1/3 stater 2.61 American Numismatic Society (ex Taranto H'd); <persName>Berlin</persName>.</p>
               <p>34 Broad five-grained ear. Coarse border.</p>
               <p>℞ Five-grained ear.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 8.5 mm. Obol 0.46 Naville VI, 159.</p>
               <pb n="64"/>
               <p>35 <graphic url="NNM32_sym5.jpg"/> Broad five-grained ear. Coarse border.</p>
               <p>℞ Five-grained ear.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 8.5 mm. Obol 0.40 London, B. M. Cat. 35.</p>
               <p>36 Inscription obliterated ? Six-grained ear. Coarse border.</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained ear.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 10 mm. Obol —.— <placeName>Berlin</placeName>.</p>
               <p>37 <graphic url="NNM32_sym5.jpg"/> Crude seven-grained ear, evidently imitating No. 14; border unusual, it shows that the die-cutter had no
                  conception of the way it had been cut in his model.</p>
               <p>℞ Eight-grained ear tapering toward apex; the awns do not extend to the rim.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 28 mm. 6.88 Naples (Santangelo 3900).</p>
               <p>38 <graphic url="NNM32_sym5.jpg"/> Crude eight-grained ear in low relief, possibly imitating No. 9. The inner border of dots almost as heavy
                  as in No. 37.</p>
               <p>℞ Eight-grained ear tapering toward apex.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 29 mm. 7.73 Cambridge (Leake).</p>
               <p>39 <graphic url="NNM32_sym9.jpg"/> Seven-grained ear in high relief with small additional terminal grains. Folioles at base. The awns, formed
                  by a series of dots, are very awkwardly spread. The lettering is <pb n="65"/> crude. Border of dots between two lines—a type of border not
                  used with Class I.</p>
               <p>℞ Eight-grained ear—border unlike preceding pieces.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 19 mm. 1.90 London, B. M. Cat. 30.</p>
               <note place="end" xml:id="CH2-n1">
                  <seg type="note-symbol">*</seg>
                  <p>For explanation of the convention used to record inscr., see p. 43.</p>
               </note>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e1149" type="section">
               <head>CLASS II.</head>
               <p>40 <graphic url="NNM32_sym5.jpg"/> Seven-grained ear with square top. The ear is more compact than in Class I, the stem longer, and the
                  folioles are lacking. The border is of dots between two linear circles, but in same plane as the rest of the design.</p>
               <p>℞ Similar to Obv. Die has begun to wear on lowest grain on the left side.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 29 mm. 8.10. Taranto Find, Spink's Circular No. 53355; <placeName corresp="#nomisma_berlin">Berlin</placeName>.</p>
               <p>41 <graphic url="NNM32_sym5.jpg"/> Eight-grained barley ear narrowing at base and apex. The stem is long.</p>
               <p>℞ Double struck; eight grains in left row and nine grains in right.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 29 mm. 8.19. <persName>E. T. Newell;</persName> Naples (Fiorelli 2285 and 2289); Hirsch XXX, 162—8.15;
                     <persName>W. Gedney</persName> Beatty Coll.—7.96.</p>
               <p>42 <graphic url="NNM32_sym5.jpg"/> Similar to No. 40, but inscription less compact.</p>
               <p>℞ Similar.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 29 mm. —.—Taranto H'd, 6 specimens— <pb n="66"/> 7.97, 7.78, 7.65, 8.03, 7.90. Spink's Circular No. 53358b,
                  and 53356; London, B. M. Cat. 6, 7.64; <placeName>Paris</placeName> (ex same find—Rev. Num., 1912, PI. IV, 7); <persName>W. Gedney
                     Beatt</persName>y Coll. 8.12; One hundred specimens of this general type occurred in Taranto hoard.</p>
               <p>43 <graphic url="NNM32_sym5.jpg"/> Ear a trifle wider than in No. 42. Inscription differs.</p>
               <p>℞ Usual type. Note that the die is broken at the border at both sides; at the right, it has been mended by hammering (?) the edge inward so
                  that a segment of the border has disappeared.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 30 mm. 7.91. <persName>E. T. Newell;</persName> Taranto H'd, Spink's Circular No. 53357a; Spink &amp;Son
                  (Taranto H'd) (6), 8.10 (2), 8.16 (2), 7.90 and 7.32; American Numismatic Society—7.89; Hoyt Miller Coll.—8.05.</p>
               <p>44 <graphic url="NNM32_sym5.jpg"/> Seven-grained ear, short and broad but uniform in width.</p>
               <p>℞ Similar to Obv., but the ear is eight-grained and slightly narrower at apex than at base.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 30 mm. 8.13. Spink's Circular No. 61998; Copenhagen, 7.80.</p>
               <p>45 <graphic url="NNM32_sym5.jpg"/> Similar to No. 44, but stem slightly longer.</p>
               <p>℞ Seven-grained barley ear, the two uppermost grains very small.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 28 mm. 7.54. Vienna.</p>
               <p>46 <graphic url="NNM32_sym9.jpg"/> Eight-grained ear—the uppermost <pb n="67"/> grains small. The M of the inscription not extended.</p>
               <p>℞ Similar to Obv. The border finer than in the preceding pieces.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 28 mm. –.— <placeName>Paris</placeName> (Rev. Num., 1912, Pl. IV, 6); Munich; Spink &amp; Son (Taranto
                  H'd), 7.97.</p>
               <p>47 <graphic url="NNM32_sym5.jpg"/> Closely similar to No. 46. Compact inscription.</p>
               <p>℞ Eight-grained ear; the upper grains small.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 30 mm. –.— Naples (Santangelo 3893).</p>
               <p>48 <graphic url="NNM32_sym5.jpg"/> Seven-grained ear, with small additional terminal grains. Border of dots between two lines. Similar to No.
                  6 in shape of ear, but without folioles and with border of Class II.</p>
               <p>℞ Seven-grained ear similar to obverse. Traces of inscription (?) in field to r.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 19 mm. 2.58. Naville V, 438; <persName>Dr. Petsalis</persName>, <placeName corresp="#nomisma_athens">Athens</placeName>.</p>
               <p>49 <graphic url="NNM32_sym5.jpg"/> Graceful five-grained ear with small additional terminal grains, similar to No. 42.</p>
               <p>℞ Five-grained ear.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 19 mm. –.— Paris and a second piece illustrated. Rev. Num. 1912, Pl. IV, 8 (2.36).</p>
               <p>50 Six-grained ear, somewhat similar to No. 40. Border of coarse dots only. No folioles at base.</p>
               <pb n="68"/>
               <p>℞ Five-grained ear with rounded top.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 10 mm. 0.38. Vienna.</p>
               <p>51 <graphic url="NNM32_sym11.jpg"/> Six-grained ear with small additional terminal grains. Border of dots between two lines.</p>
               <p>℞ Narrow six-grained ear.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 18 mm. 2.71. <persName>Sir H. Weber</persName> Coll. 738, (ex Bunbury, 126); Vienna (2.20).</p>
               <p>52 <graphic url="NNM32_sym5.jpg"/> Six-grained barley ear with small additional terminal grains.</p>
               <p>℞ Eight-grained ear with rounded top, and additional terminal grains.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 19 mm. 2.70. <persName corresp="#numismatics_newell">E. T. Newell</persName>.</p>
               <p>53 <graphic url="NNM32_sym5.jpg"/> Five-grained ear in high relief. Border of dots between two lines.</p>
               <p>℞ Five-grained ear with small additional terminal grains. The whole slightly longer and broader than on obverse.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 18 mm. 2.56. Brussels (de Hirsch).</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e1317" type="section">
               <head>CLASS III.</head>
               <p>54 <graphic url="NNM32_sym7.jpg"/> Ear longer and in considerably higher relief than in Class II, and stem entirely lacking or merely
                  indicated. Border raised to form a rim. Barley ear with eight grains on left <pb n="69"/> and nine on right. Ear 21.5 x 8 mm. Base of ear
                  broken at border.</p>
               <p>℞ Die very boldly cut. Six-grained barley ear with grains at the left pronouncedly narrower than those on the right.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 30 mm. 7.91. Taranto Find, Spink's Circular No. 53370; Naples (Fiorelli 2294)'</p>
               <p>55 <graphic url="NNM32_sym11.jpg"/> Eight-grained ear with rounded top.</p>
               <p>℞ Nine-grained ear.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 31 mm. –.— Naples (Fiorelli 2280 and 81); Arolsen; Naville III, 65—8.07.</p>
               <p>56 <graphic url="NNM32_sym11.jpg"/> Eight-grained ear with small additional terminal grain, and rounded top. The awns curve outward
                  slightly.</p>
               <p>℞ Nine-grained ear—the two upper grains smaller.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 30 mm. 8.18. Naville V, 431.</p>
               <p>57 Similar to 56 but the inscription has the tops of the letters closer to the outermost awn.</p>
               <p>℞ Die of 56.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 30 mm. –.— <placeName corresp="#nomisma_berlin">Berlin</placeName>.</p>
               <p>58 <graphic url="NNM32_sym11.jpg"/> Six-grained ear of even width (22 × 8 mm.). Slight break in die at apex of ear.</p>
               <p>℞ Eight-grained barley ear with two addi- <pb n="70"/> tional terminal grains. The ear is slightly larger than on Obv.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 30.5 mm. 8.21. Brussels (de Hirsch); Vienna 7.77; <persName>E. T. Newell</persName> 8.17; Curinga
                  H'd—8.01.</p>
               <p>59 <graphic url="NNM32_sym11.jpg"/> Seven-grained ear with small additional terminal grains.</p>
               <p>℞ Seven-grained ear with square top.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/>30 mm. –.— Naples.</p>
               <p>60 No inscription. Five grains on 1. and six on r. row of ear. Narrow, in high relief. A pronounced border of dots between two lines.</p>
               <p>℞ Five-grained ear. Border possibly recut.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 9.5 mm. Obol 0.37. London—B. M. Cat. 37.</p>
               <p>61 No inscription. Five-grained ear with short stem.</p>
               <p>℞ Five-grained ear, much narrower than obverse.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 9 mm. Obol. –.— <placeName corresp="#nomisma_berlin">Berlin</placeName>.</p>
               <p>62 No inscription. Five-grained ear. No stem.</p>
               <p>℞ Five-grained ear.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 9 mm. Obol. —.— <placeName corresp="#nomisma_berlin">Berlin</placeName>.</p>
               <p>63 No inscription. Six-grained ear.</p>
               <p>℞ Six grained ear.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 10 mm. Obol. –.— E. S. G. Robinson Collection, London.</p>
               <pb n="71"/>
               <p>64 Crude. Four (?) grained ear in low relief, with leaf to left in the field.</p>
               <p>℞ Five-grained ear.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 7 mm. Obol. 0.40. Vienna.</p>
               <p>65 <graphic url="NNM32_sym5.jpg"/> Four-grained ear with two additional terminal grains. Coarse border.</p>
               <p>℞ Four-grained ear—awns widely separated.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 10.5 mm. Obol. –.— <placeName corresp="#nomisma_berlin">Berlin</placeName>.</p>
               <p>66 <graphic url="NNM32_sym5.jpg"/> Six-grained ear with distinctive apex.</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained ear.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 9 mm. Obol. –.— Naples (Santangelo) Turin, Medagliere del Rè, (Fabretti 17967—0.50).</p>
               <p>67 <graphic url="NNM32_sym11.jpg"/> Compact six-grained ear with small additional terminal grains.</p>
               <p>℞ Seven-grained ear.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 9 mm. Obol. –.— <placeName corresp="#nomisma_berlin">Berlin</placeName>.</p>
               <p>68 <graphic url="NNM32_sym13.jpg"/>(Ṫ) Wide six-grained ear touching border at both extremities.</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained ear, narrower than on Obverse.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 9 mm. Obol. –.— <placeName corresp="#nomisma_berlin">Berlin</placeName>.</p>
               <p>69 <graphic url="NNM32_sym14.jpg"/> Compact five-grained ear in high relief.</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained ear.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 9 mm. Obol. –.— <placeName corresp="#nomisma_berlin">Berlin</placeName>.</p>
               <pb n="72"/>
               <p>70 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> Compact seven-grained ear in high relief.</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained ear with small additional terminal grains.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 10 mm. Obol. —.— Henry Chapman (stock).</p>
               <p>71 <graphic url="NNM32_sym11.jpg"/> Compact six-grained ear with widely separated terminal awns.</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained ear with rounded top.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 9.5 mm. Obol. .40 Vienna.</p>
               <p>72 <graphic url="NNM32_sym16.jpg"/> Six-grained ear. Border of dots between two lines.</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained ear.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 9 mm. Obol. —.— Naples (Santangelo).</p>
               <p>73 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> Eight-grained ear with small additional terminal grains. Ear is long and narrow. The A has a rounded top
                  and cross-bar downward to 1.</p>
               <p>℞ Ten-grained barley ear with square top.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 31 mm. —.— <placeName>Berlin</placeName>.</p>
               <p>74 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> Six-grained ear with two additional terminal grains. The A has rounded top and cross-bar downward to
                  1.</p>
               <p>℞ Nine-grained barley ear, the uppermost grains small.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 29 mm. –.— Arolsen; Curinga Hoard (2)— <pb n="73"/> 8.00 and 8.01; Naples (Santangelo 3914); Turin, Royal
                  Collection 8.10; W. Gedney Beatty Collection 8.14.</p>
               <p>75 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> Eight-grained ear with small additional terminal grains. For die-cutting Cf. No. 126. The A round-topped
                  and with cross-bar downward to r.</p>
               <p>℞ Nine-grained barley ear with square top. Note break in rim at extremity of outermost awn to r.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 30 mm. –.— <placeName>Berlin</placeName>; <persName>R. Jameson</persName> Coll. 260— ex Hirsch XVI,
                  91—8.19.</p>
               <p>76 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> Trace of stem showing. The bar of the A is downward to r. The break in the reverse die is the cause of the
                  blank segment of the border beneath the inscription on the obverse. The break keeps the metal from being forced into the obverse die.</p>
               <p>℞ Nine-grained ear similar to No. 75 but ear is longer.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 30 mm. –.— <persName>A. B. Cook</persName>, <placeName>Cambridge</placeName>; Egger XLV, 138—Hartwig
                  208, 8.12; Taranto H'd, 7.71.</p>
               <p>77 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> Eight-grained barley ear with two smaller additional terminal grains; the awns curve slightly at the outer
                  extremities. The A with rounded top and cross-bar slightly downward to r.</p>
               <pb n="74"/>
               <p>℞ Nine-grained barley ear similar to No. 76 possibly an earlier state of that die.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 31 mm. Stater –.— <persName>Sir Arthur J. Evans</persName> Coll.; Curinga Hoard—8.00. Naville V,
                  430—8.17.</p>
               <p>78 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> Eight-grained barley ear with two small additional terminal grains. The crossbar of the A downward to
                  1.</p>
               <p>℞ Seven-grained barley ear with additional terminal grain.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 30.5 mm. —.— W. B. Osgood Field Coll.; <placeName>Paris</placeName>; Curinga Hoard (2) 8.01 and 7.09
                  (?).</p>
               <p>79 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> Eight-grained barley ear in high relief similar to No. 75. The A with cross-bar downward to left.</p>
               <p>℞ Eight-grained ear with rounded top—rim broken at extremity of outermost awn to 1.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 19.5 mm. —.— C. H. Imhoff.</p>
               <p>80 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> Eight-grained barley ear in high relief. The letters of the legend very small; crossbar of the A downward
                  to r. Compare with No. 126.</p>
               <p>℞ Eight-grained barley ear with rounded top.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 18 mm. 2.33 Vienna.</p>
               <p>81 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> Short six-grained barley ear with small additional terminal grains. The A with <pb n="75"/> cross-bar
                  downward to r. Compare with Nos. 53 and 58.</p>
               <p>℞ Eight-grained ear with additional terminal grains—markedly longer than obverse ear.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 18 mm. 2.16. E. T. Newell; Vienna (2.48); <placeName corresp="#geonames_2653941">Cambridge</placeName>
                  (McClean, 903—2.67).</p>
               <p>82 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> Six-grained ear with additional terminal grain. A with pointed top and crossbar downward to right.</p>
               <p>℞ Badly worn, but apparently six-grained ear with additional terminal grain.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 18 mm. —.— Hermitage.</p>
               <p>83 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> Six-grained barley ear. Inscription follows the rim; the A with pointed top and cross-bar downward to
                  r.</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained ear with rounded top.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 16.5 mm. 2.6 5. Pozzi Sale, 161; <placeName corresp="#nomisma_berlin">Berlin</placeName>; Vienna
                  (2.59).</p>
               <p>84 <graphic url="NNM32_sym17.jpg"/> Six-grained barley ear with small additional terminal grains. Stem showing.</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained ear, broader at base than at apex.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 18 mm. –.— <placeName corresp="#nomisma_berlin">Berlin</placeName>; Egger XL, 155 (2.56)</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e1660" type="section">
               <pb n="76"/>
               <head>CLASS IV.</head>
               <p>85 <graphic url="NNM32_sym5.jpg"/> The six-grained barley ear is appreciably bolder and wider.</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained ear. The awns have the same acute angle as on the obv.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 30 mm. 7.84. Spink (Taranto Hoard), second piece 8.10; Barron Sale (Hirsch XXX, 159—8.30); <persName>Sir Arthur Evans;</persName> Naville V, 426—8.02.</p>
               <p>86 <graphic url="NNM32_sym18.jpg"/> Similar in style to 77. Very short stem; the nine-grained ear is consequently low on the flan. Die broken
                  at the base of the ear.</p>
               <p>℞ Seven-grained ear with square top, similar to No. 85 and notably different from obverse.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 31 mm. 7.97. Taranto Find (Spink's Circular No. 53365); H. Chapman; Naples (Santangelo 3910).</p>
               <p>87 <graphic url="NNM32_sym19.jpg"/> Six-grained ear in high relief. Stem lacking.</p>
               <p>℞ Similar to No. 86. Die broken at the centre, the surface having flaked off.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 29 mm. 7.91. Taranto Find (Spink's Circular No. 53364); Berlin; 5.92 (sic); Sambon-Canessa Sale, 1907,
                  28—8.25.</p>
               <p>88 <graphic url="NNM32_sym20.jpg"/> Six-grained barley ear with small additional terminal grains. The letters larger than in No. 87. The awns
                  are unusually thick.</p>
               <pb n="77"/>
               <p>℞ Ear larger than obv. and longer than in preceding pieces of C1. III.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 30.5 mm. 7.58. <placeName corresp="#nomisma_berlin">Berlin</placeName>; Hirsch XXX, 165—8.15.</p>
               <p>89 <graphic url="NNM32_sym20.jpg"/> Seven-grained ear. Similar to No. 87. Short stem.</p>
               <p>℞ Similar to No. 85. Die broken at the border on the right and recut for half of the circumference.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 32 mm. 8.25. <persName>E. T. Newell;</persName> Munich; Copenhagen, 7.67; Spink &amp;Son (Taranto Find
                  7.78).</p>
               <p>90 <graphic url="NNM32_sym21.jpg"/> Seven-grained ear with small additional terminal grains.</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained ear with square top.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 28 mm. 8.00. <placeName corresp="#geonames_2653941">Cambridge</placeName> (Leake); <persName>S. P.
                     Noe</persName> 8.13.</p>
               <p>90a Die of No. 88.</p>
               <p>℞ Die of No. 90.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 29 mm. (flan broken). <placeName>Paris</placeName> (Rev. Num. 1912, PI. IV, 9); Miami University, Oxford,
                  O.</p>
               <p>91 <graphic url="NNM32_sym21.jpg"/> Similar to No. 90—possibly same die.</p>
               <p>℞ Barley ear with six grains in side rows, and seven in middle row. The rim in various stages of mending.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 30 mm. 8.22. Hoyt Miller Coll. (ex Chapman Sale July 25, 1922—Reimer's Coll.); American Numismatic <pb n="78"/> Society, 8.25; Berlin, 8.09; Sambon-Canessa Sale, 1907, 29—8.18; C. T. Seltman, 7.55.</p>
               <p>91a Die of No. 91.</p>
               <p>℞ Closely similar to No. 88—possibly same die.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 30 mm. Paris (Rev. Num. 1912, P1. IV, 10); Arolsen; Spink's Circular, 53366 (7.84).</p>
               <p>92 <graphic url="NNM32_sym20.jpg"/> Similar to Nos. 88 and 89. Seven-grained ear with same proportions as Obv.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 29.5 mm. 8.12. Vienna (= Egger XL, 150); <placeName>London</placeName>, B. M. Cat. 11 (Head's Guide, Pl 7,
                  No. 10), 8.04; Spink's Circular 53362; <placeName corresp="#nomisma_athens">Athens</placeName>; Bement Sale 154—8.13, <persName>W. Gedney Beatty</persName> Coll., 7.91.</p>
               <p>93 <graphic url="NNM32_sym21.jpg"/> Six-grained barley ear. Cable border. A die-break extends from the base of the ear above the letters at
                  the left, to the rim, and along it to a point above the apex of the ear.</p>
               <p>℞ Similar to 89.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 31 mm. 8.35. <persName corresp="#numismatics_newell">E. T. Newell</persName>.</p>
               <p>94 <graphic url="NNM32_sym18.jpg"/> Six-grained ear, cable border. Short stem.</p>
               <p>℞ Similar to No. 54. Break in center row of ear near top. Awns widely separated.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 30 mm. 7.78. Cambridge (<persName>McClean</persName> Coll., 889); <pb n="79"/>
                  <placeName>London</placeName>, <persName>B. M. Cat</persName>. 14—8.18; Merzbacher Sale, 1919, No. 91—8.39; Hirsch XIV, No.
                  83—8.17.</p>
               <p>95 <graphic url="NNM32_sym22.jpg"/> Six-grained ear with small additional terminal grains; high relief. Cable border.</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained ear, similar to No. 93.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 30 mm. –.— <persName>Sir A. J. Evans</persName>.</p>
               <p>96 Die of No. 95.</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained ear, similar to No. 94—possibly same die.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 32 mm. –.— Naples (Fiorelli); American Numismatic Society (flan broken).</p>
               <p>97 <graphic url="NNM32_sym23.jpg"/> Seven-grained ear with border of dots between two lines. The cross-bar of the A is horizontal.</p>
               <p>℞ Seven-grained ear with rounded apex. Awns very slight.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 26 mm. 7.65. <placeName>Berlin</placeName>; Arolsen; Vienna, 7.85; Curinga Hoard, 8.01; E. S. G. Robinson,
                  London.</p>
               <p>98 <graphic url="NNM32_sym21.jpg"/> Eight-grained ear, slightly broader than at the apex. Stem short.</p>
               <p>℞ Ear similar in proportions to obv. The rim is unusual. Stem does not show.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 27.3 mm. 7.43. Boston Museum of Fine Arts, (Regling-Warren, 64—ex Bunbury 1896, 124).</p>
               <p>99 <graphic url="NNM32_sym23.jpg"/> 6-grained barley ear.</p>
               <p>℞ Seven-grained ear with square top.</p>
               <pb n="80"/>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 17.5 mm. 1/3 stater 2.54. <persName>S. P. Noe;</persName>
                  <placeName corresp="#nomisma_berlin">Berlin</placeName>; Munich; Arolsen.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e1865" type="section">
               <head>CLASS V.</head>
               <p>100 <graphic url="NNM32_sym17.jpg"/> Seven-grained barley ear. Grasshopper in field to right, its body parallel with awns and its head toward
                  their extremities. Cable border.</p>
               <p>℞ Dolphin to left, engraved in die and therefore with outline in relief.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 28 mm. 7.85. <placeName>Berlin</placeName>; Hirsch XV, 533—7.53.</p>
               <p>100a Same die as No. 100, struck over a stater of Croton. The three legs of the tripod cross the ear at right angles. The Croton stater seems
                  to have been hammered almost flat before being restruck—most of the details are obliterated. This is the earliest of the <placeName corresp="#nomisma_metapontum">Metapontum</placeName> staters I
                  have found struck over the piece of another city.</p>
               <p>℞ Same die as No. 100, but broken at the base and apex of the ear. The lines of the tripod show faintly.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 28.5 mm. 7.80. <persName>Jameson Coll</persName>.</p>
               <p>101 Die of No. 100.</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained ear with square top.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 29 mm. 7.39. <persName>E. T. Newell</persName>.</p>
               <p>102 <graphic url="NNM32_sym17.jpg"/> Seven-grained barley ear—the stem is almost eliminated by the proximity of the <pb n="81"/> base of the
                  ear to the rim. The inscription differs from that of No. 100 in the forms of the E and A. Grasshopper, at r., head upward.</p>
               <p>℞ Barley ear similar in proportions to obv. At the left, in raised outline, a dolphin with head upwards.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 28 mm. 8.15. Brussels (de Hirsch); Hirsch XXX, 167—8.20.</p>
               <p>103 Die of 102.</p>
               <p>℞ A badly worn die, unlike previous dies. Several imperfections show—at the apex of the ear, at the middle of the right row of grains, and at
                  several points in the border. These appear to be chips from the surface of the die.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 27.5 mm. 8.07. Barron Sale (Hirsch XXX, 166).</p>
               <p>104 <graphic url="NNM32_sym17.jpg"/> Seven-grained barley ear having grasshopper with head upwards to right. The insect is shorter than
                  heretofore. Cable border.</p>
               <p>℞ Ear similar in proportions to No. 102 but the dolphin with head upward on the right is <hi rend="italic">intaglio.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 27 mm. 7.87. <placeName>Berlin</placeName>; B. M. Cat. 15—7.50. <persName>E. T. Newell ex
                     Jameson</persName> 259 and Delbeke Sale, 17— 8.22; <placeName>Paris</placeName> (Babelon, Traite PI. LXVI, 9—8.02); Gotha; Locker-Lampson
                  Coll., 8.09.</p>
               <p>105 <graphic url="NNM32_sym17.jpg"/> Similar to No. 104 but with greater interval between the E and T. The ear <pb n="82"/> broader and in
                  lower relief, and the grasshopper shorter. Border of dots between two lines.</p>
               <p>℞ Seven-grained barley ear with square top. In field to left a dolphin intaglio, much smaller than in No. 104.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 25½ mm, —.— <placeName corresp="#nomisma_berlin">Berlin</placeName>; Arolsen.</p>
               <p>106 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> Six-grained barley ear. In field to left, grasshopper with head upward.</p>
               <p>℞ Seven-grained ear.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 18 mm. 1/3 stater. 2.46. <placeName>Berlin</placeName>; Boston, Warren-Regling, 68, ex Bunbury, 124—2.64;
                  The Hague; Bement, 158—2.66.</p>
               <p>107 <graphic url="NNM32_sym5.jpg"/> Five-grained barley ear in high relief. In field to right, a ram's head pointing downward. Compare Nos.
                  221-228.</p>
               <p>℞ Five-grained ear with small additional terminal grains.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 19 mm. —.—<placeName corresp="#nomisma_berlin">Berlin</placeName>; Arolsen.</p>
               <p>108 <graphic url="NNM32_sym25.jpg"/> Seven-grained barley ear in high relief. In field at right a grain of barley.</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained ear with rounded top.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 18.5 mm. 1/3 stater 2.57. <persName>A. H. Lloyd ex Bement</persName> 157; <placeName>Berlin</placeName>.</p>
               <p>109 <graphic url="NNM32_sym25.jpg"/> Closely similar to 108. Variations in the inscription and awns. Possibly a re-cut die.</p>
               <pb n="83"/>
               <p>℞ Six-grained ear narrower than No. 108. Border re-cut.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 17 mm. 2.47. Naville, XII, 392.</p>
               <p>110 <graphic url="NNM32_sym5.jpg"/> Narrow six-grained ear. In the field to right a barley grain. Border of dots between two lines.</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained ear.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 9 mm. 0.32. <placeName>London</placeName>, <persName>B. M. Cat</persName>. 38.</p>
               <p>111 <graphic url="NNM32_sym111.jpg"/> Inscription questionable. Fivegrained ear with small additional terminal grains. In field to left a
                  ram's head (?) upwards.</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained ear.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 10 mm. —.— Naples (Santangelo).</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e2028" type="section">
               <head>CLASS VI.</head>
               <p>112 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> The flan (26 mm.) is nearer in size to No. 105 than to 100 (28 mm.). Sevengrained barley ear, topmost
                  grains very small. The A with a pointed apex and crossbar sloping downward to right. Border of dots between two linear circles.</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained ear with small additional terminal grain. Top of ear nearly square.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> mm. 8.00. Curinga Hoard; Vienna—6.46; Naples (Santangelo and Fiorelli 2311).</p>
               <pb n="84"/>
               <p>113 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> Similar to 112, save that the awns are much further apart. The cross-bar of the A points sharply upwards
                  to the right.</p>
               <p>℞ Seven-grained ear.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 27 mm. 7.05. Curinga Hoard; Naples (Fiorelli 2314).</p>
               <p>114 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> Compact eight-grained ear with small additional terminal grain.</p>
               <p>℞ Ear of eight grains with additional terminal grain.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 28 mm. —.— Hoyt Miller Collection.</p>
               <p>115 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> Seven-grained barley ear, the awns with more than the usual interval. The A has a rounded apex with
                  cross-bar slightly upward to the right.</p>
               <p>℞ Seven-grained barley ear, the topmost grain very small.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 27 mm. —.— Arolsen; American Numismatic Society—8.04.</p>
               <p>116 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> Short six-grained barley ear with small additional terminal grains. The A is broad, round-topped, and
                  with cross-bar slanting downward to right.</p>
               <p>℞ Seven-grained barley ear, square-topped with awns at sharper angle than on obv.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 27 mm. 8.01. Curinga Hoard.</p>
               <pb n="85"/>
               <p>117 <graphic url="NNM32_sym11.jpg"/> Eight-grained ear of beautiful proportions; the outermost awns on the left curve slightly.</p>
               <p>℞ Eight-grained ear of not uniform width. Both the ear and the border are shallow.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/>
                  <hi rend="italic">2</hi>8 mm. —.— Sir Arthur Evans.</p>
               <p>118 <graphic url="NNM32_sym24.jpg"/> Eight-grained ear—the A with cross-bar downward to right. The E is archaic.</p>
               <p>℞ Eight-grained ear.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 28 mm. Stater 7.95. Milan; Naples (Fiorelli).</p>
               <p>119 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> Eight-grained barley ear with small additional terminal grains. The A with rounded top and cross-bar
                  downward to left.</p>
               <p>℞ Eight-grained barley ear with rounded top.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 27 mm. —.— <placeName>Berlin</placeName>; Spink &amp;Son—8.00.</p>
               <p>120 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> An interval between the M and the E—the T almost touches the top of the A. The bar of the A upwards to
                  right—a die flaw above the A between the second and third awn.</p>
               <p>℞ Eight-grained ear, slightly broader than obverse.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/>
                  <hi rend="italic">27.5</hi> mm. 7.97. Vienna; <placeName>Berlin</placeName>; Curinga Hoard —8.01; Hunterian 3.</p>
               <p>121 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> Eight-grained ear with small additional terminal grain. The A with rounded top and cross-bar downward to
                  right.</p>
               <pb n="86"/>
               <p>℞ Nine-grained ear with square top.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 27.5 mm. Stater 8.00. Hunterian 2; <persName>W. Gedney Beatty Coll</persName>. 8.20.</p>
               <p>122 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> Eight-grained barley ear with two smaller terminal grains. The A with rounded top; cross-bar downward to
                  left.</p>
               <p>℞ Eight-grained ear with small additional terminal grain.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 28.5 mm. 7.78. Taranto Find, Spink's Circular 53372 (and 53373); <placeName>London</placeName>, <persName>B. M. Cat</persName>. 9, 7.72; Copenhagen, 7.99; Curinga Hoard—8.01; <persName>S. P. Noe</persName>.</p>
               <p>123 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> Nine-grained ear.</p>
               <p>℞ Seven-grained barley ear with small additional terminal grain, and squared top. Die-break below the middle of the ear.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 27 mm. 8.00. Curinga Hoard.</p>
               <p>124 Die of 123.</p>
               <p>℞ Closely similar to No. 122.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 28 mm. 7.78. Taranto Find, Spink's Circular No. 53374.</p>
               <p>125 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> Similar to No. 124, but in bolder relief. Die-break between M and E.</p>
               <p>℞ Eight-grained ear with rounded top.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 28.5 mm. —.— <placeName>Berlin</placeName>; Naples (Stevens); <persName>Baron S. Pennisi di
                     Floristella</persName>, Acireale; C. T. Seltman; Naville V, 432—8.13; Hoyt Miller, —.—; <persName>E. T. Newell</persName>—8.17; Ratto
                  1912, 245—8.22; Egger XLVI, 34— 8.19.</p>
               <pb n="87"/>
               <p>126 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> Eight-grained ear in high relief, with smaller additional terminal grain. The middle row is in
                  considerably higher relief than the two side rows. The stem breaks the line of the rim.</p>
               <p>℞ Closely similar to No. 125.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 27.5 mm. 7.15. Brussels (de Hirsch); Vienna, 7.60.</p>
               <p>127 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> Eight-grained barley ear with tiny additional terminal grain. Inscription compact and letters small.</p>
               <p>℞ Nine-grained barley ear; the uppermost grains have the appearance of having been recut.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 28 mm. 8.14. Brussels (de Hirsch); Cambridge (Corpus Christi—Lewes Coll.).</p>
               <p>128 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> Seven-grained barley ear, with small additional terminal grain, the whole in low, flat relief. The
                  letters of inscription are evenly spaced.</p>
               <p>℞ Eight-grained ear with a rounded apex.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 28 mm. —.— Munich; Vienna (7.80).</p>
               <p>129 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> Similar to No. 116. The A has rounded top and cross-bar downward to left.</p>
               <p>℞ Seven-grained barley ear.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 26 mm. 8.00. Curinga Hoard.</p>
               <pb n="88"/>
               <p>130 <graphic url="NNM32_sym26.jpg"/> Initial stroke of the E unusually long. Stem short, and like the vertical stroke of the T, it turns to
                  the right at its lower extremity.</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained ear.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 27 mm. 7.90. Vienna; Egger XL (Prowe), 149— 7.75.</p>
               <p>131 <graphic url="NNM32_sym26.jpg"/> Seven-grained barley ear, the apex is distinctive. The A with pointed top and cross-bar downward to
                  right.</p>
               <p>℞ Seven-grained barley ear, square top. Finely cut (recut?) border. Compare with Nos. 137 and 139.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 26 mm. — —— Berlin; Turin, 909.</p>
               <p>132 <graphic url="NNM32_sym26.jpg"/> Die of No. 131.</p>
               <p>℞ Seven-grained barley ear with recut (?) border. Cf. No. 28.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 26 mm. 8.02. Curinga Hoard; Cambridge (McClean 898—7.94); Naville V, 66—8.20.</p>
               <p>133 <graphic url="NNM32_sym26.jpg"/> Narrow, seven-grained barley ear, with distinctive apex.</p>
               <p>℞ Seven-grained barley ear. Recut (?) border.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 26 mm. 8.01. Curinga Hoard; <placeName corresp="#nomisma_athens">Athens</placeName>, 7.81; Spink &amp;Sons—7.96.</p>
               <p>134 <graphic url="NNM32_sym17.jpg"/> The ear is well centered, squaretopped and has a short stem showing.</p>
               <pb n="89"/>
               <p>℞ Similar to obv. but ear slightly wider and stem wanting.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 29 mm. 8.12. Bement 153 (ex Carfrae, II and O'Hagan, 46). Curinga Hoard—8.01; Hermitage.</p>
               <p>135 <graphic url="NNM32_sym27.jpg"/> Seven-grained ear with small additional terminal grains; high relief. Compare square top with that of No.
                  139.</p>
               <p>℞ Seven-grained ear.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 27 mm. Stater 8.00. London (ex Sir Herman Weber, 7.33 and Baron v. Berner, 1888); Naples (Fiorelli 2310—two
                  specimens).</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e2289" type="section">
               <head>CLASS VII.</head>
               <p>136 <graphic url="NNM32_sym28.jpg"/> Narrow eight-grained ear with small additional terminal grains. Border of dots between two lines. Compare
                  with 118 and 122.</p>
               <p>℞ Eight-grained barley ear slightly longer than obverse and with square top.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 28.5 mm. — —— Berlin.</p>
               <p>137 <graphic url="NNM32_sym28.jpg"/> Narrow seven-grained ear. The inscription is parallel with the awns instead of following the line of the
                  rim.</p>
               <p>℞ The ear is narrower, less blunt at the top than No. 136 and is likewise without stem. The edge is of exceptional regularity and
                  delicacy.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 27.5 mm. 7.91. E. P. Robinson Coll. Newport; <pb n="90"/> London, B. M. Cat. 12, 7.94; Paris, 7.56; Berlin
                  (broken flan).</p>
               <p>138 <graphic url="NNM32_sym28.jpg"/> The inscription follows the curve of the rim. A very narrow, nine-grained ear, of exquisite
                  proportions.</p>
               <p>℞ Eight-grained ear, slightly wider than on obverse.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 28 mm. 7.80. Vienna.</p>
               <p>139 <graphic url="NNM32_sym28.jpg"/> The first three letters of the inscription are crowded together. Seven-grained ear, 19.5 x 7.7 mm.</p>
               <p>℞ The ear is slightly broader than on obverse. Stem wanting.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 26 mm. 8.11. <persName>Hoyt Miller</persName> ex Bement 155; Berlin; Naples (Fiorelli 2308); Hermitage;
                  Pozzi Sale 158; E. T. Newell, 7.64.</p>
               <p>140 <graphic url="NNM32_sym29.jpg"/> Less careful in style than No. 139. A joint or node shows beneath the ear. Compare 136.</p>
               <p>℞ Much coarser in style than No. 139.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 27 mm. 8.02. Curinga H'd; Coll. de Sartiges, 31 (ex Hirsch XI, 40); The Hague; <placeName>London</placeName>, B. M. Cat. 13—5.92.</p>
               <p>141 <graphic url="NNM32_sym28.jpg"/> Seven-grained ear with square top, lower in relief than No. 136, which see.</p>
               <p>℞ Seven-grained ear with small additional terminal grain; the top rounded. The left row of <pb n="91"/> the ear is wider and shallower than
                  the right; and the apex shallower than the base.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 27.5 mm. — —— Naples (Santangelo 3874).</p>
               <p>142 <graphic url="NNM32_sym29.jpg"/> Seven-grained ear similar to No. 139. The inscription is retrograde as No. 140.</p>
               <p>℞ Similar to 137 but the ear narrower.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 28 mm. — —— Naples (Fiorelli 2309).</p>
               <p>143 <graphic url="NNM32_sym30.jpg"/> Thickened flan. Seven-grained ear, narrower and in high relief. Narrow cable border. The inscription in a
                  straight line.</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained ear with apex touching the border, which has been recut; break shows at the left.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 25 mm. 8.01. Curinga Hoard; Berlin.</p>
               <p>144 <graphic url="NNM32_sym31.jpg"/> Thickened flan. Seven-grained ear, wider and in lower relief than No. 143. Cable border.</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained ear. The lower part very coarse. The border irregular (recut?)</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> Stater 23 mm. — —— Berlin.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e2385" type="section">
               <head>CLASS VIII.</head>
               <p>145 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> Eight-grained ear, the two uppermost grains small. Coarse rim lacking inside linear circle. The A with
                  rounded top and crossbar <pb n="92"/> downward to left. The awns formed by first engraving the lines and then using a drill throughout their
                  length.</p>
               <p>℞ Crude seven-grained barley ear, poorly cut; the awns are engraved in the die just as on obverse. The border is very irregular. See text
                  regarding technique.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 29 mm. 8.15. Naville X 59 ex Pozzi Sale 157; Berlin.</p>
               <p>146 <graphic url="NNM32_sym32.jpg"/> Eight-grained ear; the uppermost ones small. Coarse rim lacking inside linear circle.</p>
               <p>℞ Eight-grained ear, very poorly cut. The awns are engraved in the die and, consequently, in relief on the coin. Border very crude; broken
                  above the ear.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 29 mm. 8.00. Dresden.</p>
               <p>147 Die of 146.</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained ear with rounded top. Crude border. The awns engraved in the die.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 30 mm. 8.36. London, B. M. Cat. 8.</p>
               <p>148 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> Nine-grained ear, the uppermost one very small. The A has pointed top and crossbar is sharply upward to
                  right. Letters of inscription thick.</p>
               <p>℞ Poorly cut and unsymmetrical ear. The awns thick and crude. The border off-flan, show- <pb n="93"/> ing that this die is slightly larger
                  than the obverse. Possibly not barbaric.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 29 mm. — —— Florence.</p>
               <p>149. <graphic url="NNM32_sym33.jpg"/> The seven-grained ear very crudely modelled. The lettering also coarse. Border of dots between two
                  lines. Awns recut above letters M E.</p>
               <p>℞ Five-grained barley ear with two smaller terminal grains. The border is much cruder than even the earliest of the preceding series; and
                  although the awns are cut in a similar way, the workmanship is of the coarsest. The die is broken at the upper right.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 30 ½ mm. 7.91. Berlin.</p>
               <p>150 <graphic url="NNM32_sym33.jpg"/> Eight (?)-grained barley ear in high relief, with middle row well defined. The awns are widely separated
                  and the inscription is crude. The A of the inscription is of unusual form. The border is a series of separated dots between two continuous
                  lines.</p>
               <p>℞ Die of No. 149.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 30 mm. 7.78. Taranto Find, Spink's Circular, 53363; Vatican.</p>
               <p>151 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> Seven-grained barley ear, the topmost grains smaller than the others. A with pointed top and cross-bar
                  slightly downward to right. Border of dots between two lines. The <pb n="94"/> style heavy and crude. The die has been recut, and traces of a
                  former inscription are visible in the field to left where <graphic url="NNM32_sym1.jpg"/> can be deciphered. The awns of the first state of
                  the die show at left and right.</p>
               <p>℞ Seven-grained barley ear with rounded top; the awns are broad (recut?).</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 28 mm. 6.08 (?) Curinga Hoard; American Numismatic Society—6.12; G. Empedocles—8.00.</p>
               <p>152 <graphic url="NNM32_sym20.jpg"/> Broad, seven-grained ear with small additional terminal grain. The border coarse. The E is of unusual
                  form. The middle row shows a line extending from the base to the apex.</p>
               <p>℞ Seven-grained ear with small additional terminal grain. The middle row also shows a line (an awn?) extending from base to apex. The border
                  is unlike any occurring elsewhere in the Metapontine series, but similar to that used at <placeName corresp="#nomisma_sybaris">Sybaris</placeName>.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> Stater 30 mm. 7.64. Sir H. Weber Coll., 736.</p>
               <p>153 <graphic url="NNM32_sym34.jpg"/> Nine-grained ear in low relief, the grains smaller on the right than in the left row. The border a crude
                  linear circle, outside of which are crude dots.</p>
               <p>℞ Nine-grained ear tapering slightly toward top. Usual border.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 28 mm. Stater 8.54. E. T. Newell.</p>
               <pb n="95"/>
               <p>154 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> Broad six-grained barley ear with small additional terminal grain. The inscription compact; the A with
                  cross-bar downward to right. Cable border.</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained barley ear. Very broad awns are engraved in the die and, therefore, in relief on the coin. The border crude and apparently not
                  recut.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 25 mm. —.—— Berlin.</p>
               <p>154a <graphic url="NNM32_sym8.jpg"/> Crude six-grained barley ear with coarse awns. Border of large dots between two lines.</p>
               <p>℞ Five-grained ear.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 18.5 mm. 1/3 Stater —.—— Paris.</p>
               <p>154b <graphic url="NNM32_sym35.jpg"/> Narrow seven-grained ear tapering toward apex. Border of dots. The whole differing markedly in style
                  from other pieces in the series.</p>
               <p>℞ Small bull's head incuse with absurdly long horns curving downward. The border differs from the others of the series, Nos. 264-296.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 12.5 mm. 1.40. Berlin; Vienna (1.16).</p>
               <pb n="96"/>
               <p>154c <graphic url="NNM32_sym17.jpg"/> Crude six-grained ear with tiny additional terminal grains. Border of dots on a raised rim. Stem very
                  short.</p>
               <figure xml:id="fig-5">
                  <graphic url="NNM32_096.jpg"/>
               </figure>
               <p>℞ Six-grained ear with rounded top. The awns are similar to those of Nos. 145-147.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 30 mm. 7.72 E. T. Newell (ex Sambon, <hi rend="italic">1927.</hi> Sale, Obv. of 298. Rev. of 299 on Pl.
                  X).</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e2521" type="section">
               <head>CLASS IX.</head>
               <p>155 <graphic url="NNM32_sym11.jpg"/> Broad six-grained ear with two small additional grains.</p>
               <p>℞ Broad seven-grained ear, touching the rim at top and bottom. The awns are thick. The border is recut as is also the ear in the upper left
                  row.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/>. 24 mm. 7.47.—.—— Berlin (plated?).</p>
               <p>156 <graphic url="NNM32_sym11.jpg"/> Six-grained ear with additional terminal grain. Compact inscription.</p>
               <p>℞ Shallow six-grained ear. Coarse border.</p>
               <pb n="97"/>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 25 mm. —.—— Berlin; C. H. Imhoff Coll.</p>
               <p>157 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> Five-grained ear with small additional terminal grain. The A with pointed top and cross-bar slightly
                  downward to right.</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained ear with rounded top.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> Stater 24 mm. 7.90. Naville V, 433; Copenhagen—7.94.</p>
               <p>158 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> Similar to 157—the ear in higher relief. The inscription differs slightly.</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained ear, wider than on obverse.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 24 mm. —.—— Canessa, Naples.</p>
               <p>159 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> Five-grained ear with small additional terminal grain. Interval between T and A.</p>
               <p>℞ Similar to 158—possibly same die.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 25 mm. —.—— Naples.</p>
               <p>160 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> Six-grained ear, the topmost grains small. The A has pointed top and crossbar, slightly downward to left.
                  Rim of more than usual width—the flan slightly smaller.</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained ear.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 23.5 mm. 7.85. E. T. Newell; Naples (Santangelo).</p>
               <p>161 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> Six-grained ear. The A has a pointed top with nearly horizontal cross-bar.</p>
               <pb n="98"/>
               <p>℞ Six-grained ear—double-struck. The original impress was upside down.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 22 mm. 7.54. Vienna.</p>
               <p>162 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> Six-grained ear with square top. Letters of inscription very large, filling the field to right. The A
                  with pointed top and crossbar downward to left.</p>
               <p>℞ Shallow six-grained ear.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> Stater 22 mm. 8.04. Spink &amp;Son; Hermitage; Naples.</p>
               <p>163 Plated. <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> Both ear and inscr. of poor style. Border of dots on raised rim.</p>
               <p>℞ Copper core shows plainly at left.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> Plated. 24 mm. —.—— Commerce.</p>
               <p>164 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> Six-grained ear with small additional terminal grain. The top of the A rounded, the cross-bar slants
                  pronouncedly downward to the right.</p>
               <p>℞ Seven-grained ear.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 24 mm. —.—— Berlin; London, B. M. Cat. 17—8.05; Cambridge; Paris; Munich; Naples (Santangelo).</p>
               <p>165 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> Six-grained ear with small additional terminal grains. The awns curve outward slightly. The A with
                  rounded top and crossbar downward to right.</p>
               <pb n="99"/>
               <p>℞ Seven-grained ear, broader than obverse.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 24 mm. 8.01. Curinga Hoard; Naville V, 4347.98; Bowdoin College, Brunswick, Me.</p>
               <p>166 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> Six-grained ear with small additional terminal grains. The A has pointed top and cross-bar downward to
                  right.</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained ear with rounded top.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 25 mm. 8.00. Curinga Hoard.</p>
               <p>167 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> On this coin, and on the others of plate XIV (i. e. Nos. 161-178 inclusive) the barley ear has six grains
                  in the left row, with a small additional terminal grain. The form of the A is taken as the easiest means of distinguishing the varieties. A
                  with rounded top and cross-bar downward to right.</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained ear with additional terminal grain. The die broken at lowest grain of the middle row.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 25 mm. 7.97. Cambridge (McClean) 892; Paris.</p>
               <p>168 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> Similar to 167—inscription varies.</p>
               <p>℞ Grains at apex and base smaller than others—the lowest in the left row little more than a line.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 23.5 mm. 8.00. Curinga Hoard; <persName>Sir A. J. Evans</persName>.</p>
               <pb n="100"/>
               <p>169 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> A with pointed top and crossbar downward to r.</p>
               <p>℞ Die of 168.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 25 mm. 8.09. London, B. M. Cat. 18; Spink's Circular 53383—7.06.</p>
               <p>170 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> The A has a pointed top. The cross-bar is inclined slightly downward to right.</p>
               <p>℞ Seven-grained barley ear, topmost grains very small.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 24.5 mm. –.— Munich.</p>
               <p>171 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> Similar to 170. The A as in 168.</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained ear with small additional terminal grains.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 24 mm. 8.00. Curinga (Catanzaro) Hoard; Naples (Fiorelli 2320, Santangelo 3939 and one other).</p>
               <p>172 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> Closely similar to 170—possibly same die.</p>
               <p>℞ Possibly same die as 171.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 24 mm. Stater 8.00. Curinga Hoard; Milan (?); Spink &amp;Son—8.05.</p>
               <p>173 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> The cross-bar of the A downward to left; the awns to the left show double cutting.</p>
               <p>℞ Seven-grained ear with breaks in centre row at top and bottom.</p>
               <pb n="101"/>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 25.5 mm. Stater 7.98. Cambridge (McClean) 890; Naples (Santangelo).</p>
               <p>174 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> Ear in high relief. The A with pointed top and cross-bar downward to right. The E has archaic form.</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained barley ear. Recut border.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 25 mm. 8.00. Curinga Hoard (2nd spec. 8.01); Naples (Fiorelli 2322).</p>
               <p>175 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> Similar to 173, save that the A has the cross-bar downward to right.</p>
               <p>℞ Eight-grained barley ear, the two topmost grains smaller than the others.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 24.5 mm. —.—— Toronto.</p>
               <p>176 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> Similar to 175 save for inscription.</p>
               <p>℞ Similar to 168—border and ear recut.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 24 mm. 8.01. Curinga Hoard.</p>
               <p>177 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> Ear similar to 173—the A with cross-bar downward to right.</p>
               <p>℞ Seven-grained barley ear.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 24 mm. —.—— Berlin.</p>
               <p>178 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> A with pointed top and crossbar downward to left.</p>
               <p>℞ Shallow six-grained ear with small additional terminal grain and crude border.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 25 mm. —.—— Naples.</p>
               <pb n="102"/>
               <p>179 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> Six-grained ear with small additional terminal grain. The A with rounded top and cross-bar downward to
                  right. Cable border.</p>
               <p>℞ Six (?) grained ear.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 24 mm. —.—— Hoyt Miller Coll.</p>
               <p>180 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> Similar to 175, save in spacing of letters of inscription.</p>
               <p>℞ Similar to 170.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> mm. 8.00. Hoyt Miller Coll.</p>
               <p>181 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> Seven-grained ear.</p>
               <p>℞ Seven-grained ear.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 24 mm. 8.01. Curinga Hoard.</p>
               <p>182 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> Narrow, seven-grained ear. The A pointed and with cross-bar downward to left.</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained ear.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 24 mm. 8.05. Vienna; <placeName corresp="#nomisma_athens">Athens</placeName> (struck over a Selinus (?) didrachm) 8.03; E. Beesley Collection; Curinga
                  Hoard—8.05.</p>
               <p>183 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> Broad seven-grained ear. The A has pointed top and cross-bar downward to right.</p>
               <p>℞ Seven-grained ear.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 25 mm. —.—— Munich.</p>
               <p>184 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> Seven-grained ear—the middle <pb n="103"/> row in more than usually high relief. Inscription follows
                  curve of narrow cable border.</p>
               <p>℞ Ear touches border at apex and base.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 25 mm. 8.10. Spink's Circular 70328; Egger XL, 151, 7-99; Arolsen.</p>
               <p>185 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> Seven-grained ear. The A has pointed top and cross-bar downward to left.</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained ear of even width.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 24 mm. —.—— Arolsen.</p>
               <p>186 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> Seven-grained ear; the topmost grain smaller. Cable border. The A is distinctive.</p>
               <p>℞ Die of 185.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 23.5 mm. 8.11. Curinga Hoard; American Numismatic Society—7.80.</p>
               <p>187 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> Narrow seven-grained ear. The A with rounded top and cross-bar downward to r.</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained barley ear. Die broken in the rim at left.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 24 mm. 8.00. Curinga Hoard.</p>
               <p>188 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> Similar to No. 187, save that the letters of the inscription are larger and the A is different.</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained ear, slightly broader than obverse. Die broken at the rim on right.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 25 mm. 8.01. Curinga Hoard.</p>
               <pb n="104"/>
               <p>189 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> The eight-grained ear is long and narrow, the A similar to that of No. 186.</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained ear; touches border at apex. Border recut?</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 25 mm. —.—— <placeName>Berlin</placeName>; Curinga Hoard—8.00; Spink’s Circular 53383a. <persName>B. M. Cat</persName>. 16—8.12; Naville XII, 388—8.10.</p>
               <p>190 <graphic url="NNM32_sym36.jpg"/> Seven-grained ear—compare with 180. The traces of a pointed top A are visible on the cast. This has been
                  changed by the addition of a stroke which makes the letter seem an H.</p>
               <p>℞ Seven-grained ear—unusually short.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 23 mm. 7.87. Berlin.</p>
               <p>191 <graphic url="NNM32_sym37.jpg"/> Six-grained ear with small additional terminal grains. Border of dots between two lines.</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained ear. Recut border—note pivot mark at center of die.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 23.5 mm. 8.01. Curinga Hoard (and four others—each weighing 8.00); Vienna, 7.76, 8.10; <placeName>Cambridge</placeName> (<persName>McClean</persName> 900—7.85); Egger XLV, 140—7.14; <placeName>Berlin</placeName>; <persName>E. S. G. Robinson</persName>, <placeName>London</placeName>.</p>
               <p>192 <graphic url="NNM32_sym38.jpg"/> Six-grained ear with small additional terminal grains. Wide cable border.</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained ear.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 24 mm. 8.03. <placeName>Berlin</placeName>; Curinga Hoard—8.01; <pb n="105"/>
                  <placeName>London</placeName>, <persName>B. M. Cat</persName>. 21—8.26; Naples (Fiorelli 2338, 2340 and 2341).</p>
               <p>193 <graphic url="NNM32_sym38.jpg"/> Similar to 192 but less high in relief.</p>
               <p>℞ Eight-grained ear touching border at top and bottom.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 24 mm. —. <placeName>Paris</placeName>; Spink’s Circular 53384 (7.52); <persName>E. Beesley</persName>
                  Collection; Curinga Hoard—8.01; Copenhagen—8.03.</p>
               <p>194 <graphic url="NNM32_sym38.jpg"/> Seven-grained ear, the topmost grains smaller than the others. The grains in right row are higher than
                  their corresponding ones in the left row. Guilloche border.</p>
               <p>℞ Seven-grained ear. Border recut—note pivot mark at center of ear.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 25 mm. 8.01. Curinga Hoard (2).</p>
               <p>195 <graphic url="NNM32_sym38.jpg"/> Possibly same die as 193.</p>
               <p>℞ Seven-grained ear, touching border at apex.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 23.5 mm. 7.86. Vienna; Commerce.</p>
               <p>196 <graphic url="NNM32_sym8.jpg"/> Six-grained ear.</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained ear, much broader than on obv.; touches border at apex.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 23 mm. 8.08. <persName>E. T. Newell;</persName> Vienna.</p>
               <p>197 <graphic url="NNM32_sym8.jpg"/> Seven-grained ear.</p>
               <pb n="106"/>
               <p>℞ Seven-grained ear. Recut border.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 23.5 mm. —. <placeName corresp="#nomisma_berlin">Berlin</placeName>; Curinga Hoard—8.00.</p>
               <p>198 <graphic url="NNM32_sym8.jpg"/> Six-grained ear in high relief, the topmost grain small.</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained ear.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 22 mm. —. <placeName>Berlin</placeName>.</p>
               <p>199 <graphic url="NNM32_sym8.jpg"/> Six-grained ear. Die-crack through first two letters of inscription. Uppermost grain in left row not
                  uniform with right.</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained ear. Recut border.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 23 mm. Naples (Fiorelli 2291); Curinga Hoard, 8.01, (2).</p>
               <p>200 <graphic url="NNM32_sym26.jpg"/> Six-grained ear. Possibly die of No. 199 recut and with A of inscription added. Note the die-crack.
                  Guilloche border.</p>
               <p>℞ Five-grained ear slightly larger than on obverse.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 23 mm. —. <placeName>Paris</placeName>; Vienna; <persName>W. Gedney</persName> Beatty
                  Collection—8.17.</p>
               <p>201 <graphic url="NNM32_sym26.jpg"/> Six-grained ear is in higher relief than No. 199. The A is nearly square topped and with cross-bar
                  downward to right.</p>
               <p>℞ The six-grained ear extends from rim to rim.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 28.5 mm. —. <persName>Dr. Van Buren</persName>
                  <placeName>Collection, Rome; Naples</placeName> (Fiorelli 2332 and Santangelo); Curinga Hoard (2), 8.00; <placeName>London</placeName>,
                     <persName>B. M. Cat</persName>. 19—7.92.</p>
               <pb n="107"/>
               <p>202 <graphic url="NNM32_sym26.jpg"/> Six-grained ear similar to No. 200, but the inscr. more extended.</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained ear, the topmost grains smaller than the others.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 23 mm. 8.01. Curinga Hoard, (2).</p>
               <p>203 <graphic url="NNM32_sym26.jpg"/> Six-grained ear similar to No. 200. Inscr. slightly more extended with differences in the E and A.</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained ear.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 23 mm. 8.00. Curinga Hoard. Cambridge (<persName>McClean</persName> 894—8.11).</p>
               <p>204 <graphic url="NNM32_sym26.jpg"/> Six-grained ear. Die-break shows between second and third grains in right row. A with cross-bar downward
                  to left.</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained ear.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 24 mm. —.—— <placeName>Berlin; Naples, Fiorelli</placeName> (2334) I Copenhagen, 7.69; <placeName>London</placeName>, <persName>B. M. Cat</persName>. 20— 8.02 (struck over archaic Corinthian Stater—illus. Head, Guide to Coins of the
                  Ancients, PI. VII, II. The identification of this type is not certain because details have been eliminated in the striking).</p>
               <p>205 Same die as No. 204, but with the break further developed and with the inscr. recut; the A has cross-bar downward to r. whereas in the
                  first state of the die it was downward to 1.</p>
               <p>℞ Die of No. 204.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 24 mm. —.—— <placeName>Berlin; Naples</placeName> 3886.</p>
               <pb n="108"/>
               <p>206 <graphic url="NNM32_sym26.jpg"/> Six-grained ear, the topmost pair of grains smaller than the others.</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained ear with recut border.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 24 mm. —. <placeName>Florence; Curinga Hoard; Copenhagen</placeName>, 8.02.</p>
               <p>207 <graphic url="NNM32_sym14.jpg"/> Six-grained ear; cable border of more than usual width.</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained ear slightly broader than on Obv. and with dot at centre as in 233 (evidence of re-cut border).</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 24 mm. 8.14. <persName>Sir H. Weber</persName>, 735 (ex Von Wotoch, 101 ?); Vienna; <placeName>Paris</placeName>; Curinga Hoard—8.01; <persName>Sir A. J. Evans</persName>.</p>
               <p>208 <graphic url="NNM32_sym39.jpg"/> Seven-grained ear with small additional terminal grains. Guilloche border.</p>
               <p>℞ Eight-grained ear touching rim at top and bottom.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 25 mm. Stater 8.13 Cambridge (<persName>McClean</persName>— 895). <placeName>Cambridge
                     (Leake)</placeName>—7.83.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e3135" type="section">
               <head>CLASS X.</head>
               <p>209 <graphic url="NNM32_sym25.jpg"/> Seven-grained barley ear. Large lizard with head upward at r. Border of dots between two lines.</p>
               <p>℞ Similar to No. 196. Six-grained barley ear. The border is coarsely cut; the specimen last <pb n="109"/> described shows it much finer and
                  possibly the border has been recut after wearing down. The die-break across ear shows in all the pieces described below.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 24.5 mm. —.—— Pozzi Coll. 160, 8.03; American Numismatic Society; <placeName>Cambridge</placeName> (<persName>McClean</persName> 904— 7.80); <persName>A. H. Lloyd Coll</persName>.</p>
               <p>210 Die of No. 209.</p>
               <p>℞ Possibly the same die as No. 82 with the border and awns recut. Note the break across the middle of the ear.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 25 mm. —.—— (Feuardent).</p>
               <p>211 <graphic url="NNM32_sym25.jpg"/> Six grained ear, with a lizard in field to right, that is smaller than the one on 209. This symbol as
                  well as the flan is somewhat smaller than on Nos. 209, 210.</p>
               <p>℞ Seven-grained ear with re-cut border.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 24 mm. 8.00. Curinga Hoard, (2).</p>
               <p>212 <graphic url="NNM32_sym25.jpg"/> Six-grained ear. At r. a small lizard with head upward.</p>
               <p>℞ Seven-grained ear.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 23 mm. 8.11. <persName>A. H. Lloyd Coll</persName>, ex Coll. Marquis Ginori; <placeName>Paris</placeName>, (<persName>De Luynes</persName> 454—8.00); <placeName>Berlin</placeName>; Naville V, 437—8.03.</p>
               <p>213 <graphic url="NNM32_sym25.jpg"/> Six-grained barley ear, the topmost grains small, higher in relief than No. 212 <pb n="110"/> and
                  narrower. Possibly recut die of 212. At r., a small lizard, head upwards.</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained barley ear having proportions of obv.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 21.8 mm. 7.55. Spink’s Circular 53388; Vienna; Naples (Fiorelli 2302).</p>
               <p>214 <graphic url="NNM32_sym25.jpg"/> Six-grained ear, tapering slightly toward top. The lizard at r. has head and body curved toward ear. The
                  M touches lower grain at 1.</p>
               <p>℞ Broad seven-grained ear, wider than obv.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 22 1/2 mm. Stater 7.58. <persName>E. S. G. Robinson</persName>.</p>
               <p>215 <graphic url="NNM32_sym25.jpg"/> Six-grained ear. In field to r. a lizard—higher on flan than in preceding.</p>
               <p>℞ Seven-grained ear with re-cut border.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 22 mm. 8.01. Curinga H’d; Copenhagen, 8.02; Gotha; Berlin; Egger XL, 153—801.</p>
               <p>216 <graphic url="NNM32_sym25.jpg"/> Six-grained ear. In field to right small lizard with head upward. The M of the inscription nearly touches
                  the mid-stroke of the E.</p>
               <p>℞ Similar to No. 212.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 22.5 mm. Naples (Fiorelli 2301 and two others); <placeName>Berlin</placeName>; <persName>Sir
                     Arthur Evans;</persName> Vienna—7.90.</p>
               <p>217 <graphic url="NNM32_sym25.jpg"/> Six-grained ear. Small lizard to r., head upwards. Guilloche Border.</p>
               <p>℞ Similar to No. 212. Border possibly recut.</p>
               <pb n="111"/>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 22 mm. 7.41. <persName>E. T. Newell; Sir Arthur J. Evans</persName>.</p>
               <p>218 <graphic url="NNM32_sym40.jpg"/> Eight-grained barley ear in bold relief. At the left, a small lizard, head downward, the body forming a
                  double curve. Note that the flan although large, does not accommodate the border.</p>
               <p>℞ Eight-grained ear.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 24.5 mm. —.—— <persName>C. H. Imhoff</persName>.</p>
               <p>219 <graphic url="NNM32_sym37.jpg"/> Seven-grained ear, with rounded apex. At the 1., a lizard (?), head upward, seen from the side; the legs
                  touch the border, and the body forms an almost straight line. Border very unusual—showing that the die-cutter had not grasped the method used
                  on other pieces. Possibly modern.</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained ear.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 20 mm. 7.61. <persName corresp="#numismatics_newell">E. T. Newell</persName>.</p>
               <p>220 <graphic url="NNM32_sym37.jpg"/> Six-grained ear, the topmost ones notably smaller than the others. In field to 1. ram’s head upward.</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained ear.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 20 mm. 7.77. Copenhagen.</p>
               <p>221 <graphic url="NNM32_sym32.jpg"/> The A larger than the other letters in the inscription. Six-grained ear. Border of dots between two
                  lines. At r. a rani’s head <pb n="112"/> pointing upward, the cross-section squared. Border of dots on a raised rim.</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained ear, with usual border.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 20 mm. 8.07. Bement 161; <placeName>London</placeName>—7.78; <placeName>Paris; Berlin</placeName>—7.96;
                  Naples (Fiorelli 2298); <persName>S. R. Milbank</persName>—7.64.</p>
               <p>222 <graphic url="NNM32_sym32.jpg"/> Similar to 221—the ram’s head larger.</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained ear.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 20 mm. —.—— <placeName>Berlin</placeName>; <persName>Baron S. Pennisi di Floristella</persName>,
                  Acireale; <persName>E. T. Newell</persName>—7.51; <placeName>Vatican; Cambridge</placeName> (<persName>McClean</persName>
                  905)—7.86; Sir Arthur Evans; <placeName>London</placeName>, <persName>B. M. Cat</persName>. 27—7.76.</p>
               <p>223 <graphic url="NNM32_sym37.jpg"/> Five-grained ear with small additional terminal grains. To the 1., a ram’s head upward, similar to
                  221.</p>
               <p>℞ Six (?)—grained ear.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 19.5 mm. Stater 8.03. <persName>Sir H. Weber Coll</persName>. 744; Gotha; Munich; <placeName>Naples</placeName> (Fiorelli 2307—struck over(?)); Copenhagen, 7.77; <persName>E. S. G. Robinson</persName>, <placeName>London</placeName>; <persName>Naville V</persName>, 436—7.82.</p>
               <p>224 <graphic url="NNM32_sym37.jpg"/> Broad, five-grained ear with small additional terminal grain. The awns are coarse and more extended than
                  in any of the pieces of this series. Large ram’s head (upward) to 1. <hi rend="italic">Plated</hi>.</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained ear, of good workmanship.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 205 mm. 6.42. Pozzi Sale, 159. Another plated piece—similar—5.64, is in Vienna.</p>
               <pb n="113"/>
               <p>225 <graphic url="NNM32_sym41.jpg"/> Beautifully proportioned sixgrained ear. At r. a ram’s head pointing upward, the lower jaw next the
                  ear.</p>
               <p>℞ Die of 223.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 18 mm. 7.97. <persName corresp="#numismatics_newell">E. T. Newell</persName>.</p>
               <p>226 <graphic url="NNM32_sym42.jpg"/> Five-grained ear. To the right a large ram’s head upward with the lower jaw next to the ear.</p>
               <p>℞ Similar to 223.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 18 mm. —.—— Munich; Hoyt Miller Coll.— 7.56.</p>
               <p>227 <graphic url="NNM32_sym43.jpg"/> Six-grained ear. At the left, small ram’s head (?) upward with lower jaw next to the ear.</p>
               <p>℞ Similar to 223.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 18 mm. 7.85. Vienna.</p>
               <p>228 Probably same die as 226.</p>
               <p>℞ <graphic url="NNM32_sym44.jpg"/> Inscr. engraved in die.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 17 mm. —.—— <placeName corresp="#nomisma_berlin">Berlin</placeName>; Copenhagen—8.02.</p>
               <p>229 <graphic url="NNM32_sym32.jpg"/> Six-grained ear. In field to left, murex slanting diagonally to left.</p>
               <p>℞ <graphic url="NNM32_sym45.jpg"/> Six-grained ear with awns as well as the inscription engraved in the die.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 15 mm. —.—— Naples (Stevens Coll, and Fiorelli 2300). <persName>Dr. Petsalis Coll</persName>., <placeName>Athens</placeName>.</p>
               <pb n="114"/>
               <p>230 Die of 229.</p>
               <p>℞ Die of 228.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 16 mm. Stater —.—— Naples (Fiorelli 2299).</p>
               <p>231 <graphic url="NNM32_sym32.jpg"/> Seven-grained barley ear. To the left, a mule’s head upward and with the lower jaw next to the ear.
                  Border of dots on a raised rim.</p>
               <p>℞ Seven-grained barley ear.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 19 mm. 8.15. <placeName>Paris</placeName> (<persName>De Luynes</persName> 456); <placeName>Cambridge</placeName> (McClean 907—6.81); Vienna—7.57.</p>
               <p>232 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> Seven-grained ear of great crudity. Border of dots between two lines. In field to left, an indefinite
                  symbol—a ram’s (?) head upward, or possibly the symbol of No. 231.</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained ear with central dot indicating re-cut border.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 22.5 mm. Stater 7.14. Cambridge (McClean, 901).</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e3476" type="section">
               <head>CLASS XI.</head>
               <p>233 <graphic url="NNM32_sym32.jpg"/> Six-grained ear. Border of dots on slightly raised rim.</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained ear. Border incomplete or broken at lower 1.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 19 mm. —.—— Cleveland Museum; Hunterian 4—7.28 (struck over Corcyra stater)—see PI. XIX.</p>
               <pb n="115"/>
               <p>234 Die of 233.</p>
               <p>℞ Recut border—note application point of device used for recutting border at center of ear. Originally die of 233?</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 20 mm. 8.10. <persName>E. T. Newell;</persName>
                  <placeName corresp="#nomisma_berlin">Berlin</placeName>; Munich; Hoyt Miller Coll., ex Stiavelli Sale 60—8.14; A. H. Lloyd Coll, (ex
                  Naville V, 435)—8.13.</p>
               <p>Struck over Agrigentum:</p>
               <p>
                  <placeName corresp="#nomisma_berlin">Berlin</placeName>,</p>
               <p>
                  <placeName corresp="#nomisma_paris">Paris</placeName> (<persName>De Luynes</persName> 455—8.10).</p>
               <p>
                  <placeName corresp="#nomisma_london">London</placeName> (ex Hasbrouck Coll. 8.12).</p>
               <p>
                  <placeName corresp="#viaf_2618425">Bement</placeName> (160—8.10).</p>
               <p>
                  <placeName corresp="#nomisma_syracuse">Syracuse</placeName>:</p>
               <p>
                  <placeName corresp="#nomisma_paris">Paris</placeName>—Bab. Traité 2078—8.08.</p>
               <p>Corinth:</p>
               <p>Gotha.</p>
               <p>Gela:</p>
               <p>
                  <placeName corresp="#nomisma_paris">Paris</placeName> (<persName>De Luynes</persName> 458—8.00).</p>
               <p>
                  <placeName corresp="#nomisma_london">London</placeName> (<persName>B. M. Cat</persName>. 25—8.15).</p>
               <p>
                  <placeName corresp="#pleiades_530834">Corcyra</placeName> (Dyrrachium according to Babelon, Fils):</p>
               <p>
                  <placeName corresp="#nomisma_paris">Paris</placeName> (<persName>De Luynes</persName> 460—8.05).</p>
               <p>235 Die of 233—the rim not struck up.</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained ear with weak border which explains weak border on obverse.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 20 mm. 8.00. <placeName corresp="#nomisma_london">London</placeName>, <persName>B. M. Cat</persName>.
                  23.</p>
               <p>236 Similar to No. 233 but the ear is smaller and the inscription more compact. Border of dots on raised rim.</p>
               <p>℞ Shallow six-grained ear and border.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 21 mm. 7.93. Copenhagen; Hermitage; Baron Pennisi di Floristella.</p>
               <pb n="116"/>
               <p>237 Die of 236. Struck over Corinthian (?) didrachm.</p>
               <p>℞ Small six-grained ear—border broken at lower 1. Note awns at apex of ear.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 20 mm. 7.95. <placeName corresp="#nomisma_paris">Paris</placeName> (<persName>de Luynes</persName>
                  457).</p>
               <p>238 <graphic url="NNM32_sym32.jpg"/> Six-grained ear in high relief. Inscr. followed curve of border.</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained ear. Recut border.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 20 m. —.—— <placeName corresp="#nomisma_berlin">Berlin</placeName>.</p>
               <p>239 <graphic url="NNM32_sym32.jpg"/> Six-grained ear. Border off flan.</p>
               <p>℞ Five-grained ear. Border recut.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 18 mm. —.—— Berlin.</p>
               <p>240 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> Six-grained ear with small additional terminal grains. The A with pointed top and crossbar slightly
                  downward to right.</p>
               <p>℞ Seven-grained ear with small additional terminal grains.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 19.5 mm. 6.97. Vienna.</p>
               <p>241 <graphic url="NNM32_sym46.jpg"/> Six-grained ear; border of dots on a raised rim.</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained ear.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 19.5 mm. —.—— <placeName corresp="#nomisma_paris">Paris</placeName>.</p>
               <p>242 <graphic url="NNM32_sym37.jpg"/> Six-grained ear with raised border.</p>
               <pb n="117"/>
               <p>℞ Six-grained ear larger than that of obv.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 20 mm. Stater —.—— Naples (Fiorelli 2342), <persName>Sir A. Evans</persName> (not certainly this type)
                  over stater of Thasos.</p>
               <p>243 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> Seven-grained ear with additional terminal grains. A with rounded top and cross-bar downwards to left.
                  Border of dots between two lines.</p>
               <p>℞ Seven-grained ear with small additional terminal grains—ear with rounded top.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 18.5 mm. —.—— <placeName corresp="#viaf_3172394">Naples</placeName> (Fiorelli 2326).</p>
               <p>244 <graphic url="NNM32_sym32.jpg"/> Six-grained ear. Border of dots on raised rim (possibly cable border).</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained ear with square top.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 19.5 mm. 8.16. <placeName>London</placeName>, <persName>B. M. Cat</persName>., 22; Naples (Fiorelli
                  2345); Copenhagen, 7.62 (?).</p>
               <p>245 <graphic url="NNM32_sym37.jpg"/> Compact six-grained ear. The letters of the inscription are badly cut.</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained barley ear.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 19 mm. 8.11. <placeName corresp="#nomisma_boston">Boston</placeName> (Regling-Warren 65 ?— traces of
                  millsail incuse under type).</p>
               <p>246 <graphic url="NNM32_sym47.jpg"/> Six-grained ear in bold relief. The border is a raised band with some traces of dots.</p>
               <p>℞ <graphic url="NNM32_sym48.jpg"/> Six-grained ear. The awns and inscriptions engraved in die and therefore in relief on coin.</p>
               <pb n="118"/>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 17 mm. —.—— <placeName corresp="#nomisma_berlin">Berlin</placeName>; Hoyt Miller Coll., ex Naville XII,
                  391—8.04.</p>
               <p>247 <graphic url="NNM32_sym49.jpg"/> Narrow six-grained ear with square top.</p>
               <p>℞ <graphic url="NNM32_sym49.jpg"/> engraved in die and, therefore, in relief on coin. These letters are so slight that it is difficult to see
                  them except on well-preserved specimens. They fail to carry through the photographer’s process, and therefore do not show on the plates.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 17.5 mm. —.—— American Numismatic Society; Dresden, 8.04; <placeName>London; Berlin</placeName>; <persName>G. Empedocles, Athens</persName>—7.80.</p>
               <p>248 <graphic url="NNM32_sym32.jpg"/> Six-grained ear, with folioles at base as in first incuse coinage. In field at 1. an “x”.</p>
               <p>℞ Barley ear with same proportions as obv. with “x” in the field at both left and right—possibly punched in die as the letters are in relief
                  on the coin.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/>18 mm. —.—— <placeName>Berlin; Cambridge</placeName> (<persName>McClean</persName>, 108—ex Egger XL,
                  154—7 84).</p>
               <p>249 <graphic url="NNM32_sym39.jpg"/> Six-grained ear with small additional terminal grains. The A of the inscription has the cross-bar
                  horizontal; the die is broken at the letter E, giving it a crescent shape.</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained ear with square top.</p>
               <pb n="119"/>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 17 mm. –.— <placeName>Berlin; Cambridge</placeName> (<persName>McClean</persName>, 909—7.31).</p>
               <p>250 Six-grained ear or possibly a die-break that has obliterated the inscr. The border, a markedly raised rim.</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained ear; the flan shows the "ears" which are found on the <placeName corresp="#nomisma_syracuse">Syracuse</placeName> tetradrachms and elsewhere.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 16 mm. –.— <persName>Wayte Raymond; Baron S</persName>. Pennisi di Floristella, Acireale; American
                  Numismatic Society.</p>
               <p>251 <graphic url="NNM32_sym26.jpg"/> Six-grained ear. The A is pointed and has the cross-bar very slightly downward to the right.</p>
               <p>℞ Ear with seven grains. Traces of overstriking.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 18 mm. 7.97. <placeName corresp="#nomisma_boston">Boston</placeName> (Regling 66—ex Bunbury 124).
                  Vienna.</p>
               <p>252 <graphic url="NNM32_sym26.jpg"/> Six-grained ear. Border of dots between two lines.</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained ear. Recut border.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 19 mm. –.— <placeName corresp="#nomisma_berlin">Berlin</placeName>.</p>
               <p>253 <graphic url="NNM32_sym26.jpg"/> Six-grained ear, the awns curving outward slightly.</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained ear. Border recut.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 20 mm. 8.01. Curinga Hoard; Naples (Fiorelli 2336); Naples—(struck over Gela didr.).</p>
               <pb n="120"/>
               <p>254 <graphic url="NNM32_sym26.jpg"/> Six-grained ear in high reliet. Border of dots between two lines.</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained ear with square top. Border possibly recut.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 18 mm. —.—— <placeName corresp="#viaf_3172394">Naples</placeName> (Fiorelli 2337).</p>
               <p>255 <graphic url="NNM32_sym26.jpg"/> Small six-grained ear in moderately high relief. Border of dots between two lines.</p>
               <p>℞ Five-grained ear, and two small additional terminal grains.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 21 mm. 7.83. <persName>E. T. Newell;</persName>
                  <placeName>London</placeName>, <persName>B. M. Cat</persName>. 24—7.72; Jameson—8.16 (struck over Gela stater— inscription legible on
                  R.).</p>
               <p>256 Six-grained ear. The inscription divided; on the left, the letter T or E discernible; on the right, the lower of the two letters is a
                  pointed-top A with cross-bar downward to r. The second letter resembles the archaic I with three strokes. Of barbaric style.</p>
               <p>℞ Six-grained ear; the style crude. No middle row of grains.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 17 mm. 7.04. Berlin.</p>
               <p>257 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> Narrow seven-grained ear of very delicate proportions; the raised border is off flan. Note that this die
                  is combined with what must, for that reason, be considered one of the earliest double-relief types, Plate XX.</p>
               <pb n="121"/>
               <p>℞ Narrow seven-grained ear. Border indefinite.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 20 mm. Stater —.—— <placeName corresp="#viaf_3172394">Naples</placeName> (Fiorelli <hi rend="italic">2323).</hi>
               </p>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e3853" type="section">
               <head>CLASS XII.</head>
               <p>258 <graphic url="NNM32_sym39.jpg"/> Eight-grained ear—the topmost ones very small. Along the outermost awn to r. a locust with head downward.
                  Border of dots (without a raised rim).</p>
               <p>℞ Seven-grained ear.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 21 mm. 8.25. <placeName>Paris</placeName> (<persName>Luynes</persName> 453); Spink’s Circular
                  53389—7.78; <placeName>London</placeName>, <persName>B. M. Cat</persName>. <hi rend="italic">26</hi> (Over Corinth)—7.78; <persName>Copenhagen</persName>—7.21; <placeName>Cambridge</placeName> (<persName>McClean</persName> 906—5.25, plated); <placeName>Bement</placeName> 162—7.74; <persName>G. Empedocles</persName>, Athens—8.05; <placeName>Egger</placeName> XLVI, 35 (ex
                     <persName>Hirsch</persName> XXXIII, 134).</p>
               <p>259 Closely similar to 258, and possibly the same die, with some re-cutting especially in the thorax of the locust.</p>
               <p>℞ Possibly the die of No. 90, with recut border and awns; the latter are here slightly curved.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/>20.5 mm. Stater —.—— <placeName>Berlin; Paris</placeName>.</p>
               <p>260 <graphic url="NNM32_sym32.jpg"/> Broad six-grained ear in pronounced relief; on the outermost awn to the 1. a locust with head upward; the
                  rim, evidently an attempt to cut a guilloche border, shows the die-cutter's inability to understand the method of doing it.</p>
               <pb n="122"/>
               <p>℞ <graphic url="NNM32_sym41.jpg"/> Seven-grained ear.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 19 mm. 7.75. Berlin; E. T. Newell 8.33; Vienna; Dresden.</p>
               <p>261 <graphic url="NNM32_sym40.jpg"/> Six-grained ear; on the outermost awn to 1. a locust with head upward. Narrow cable border on a raised
                  rim. This die is also combined with the famous stater inscribed <graphic url="NNM32_123a.jpg"/>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_123b.jpg"/> (Plate XXI).</p>
               <p>℞ Eight-grained ear, much longer than on obv. The rim is unlike any others of the series.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 21 mm. 7.63. E. T. Newell; Naples (Fiorelli 2306 and Santangelo 3952, the latter struck over Corinthian stater
                  type of B. M. Corinth Pl. II, 5 (?); Hermitage.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e3938" type="section">
               <head>FRACTIONS.</head>
               <p>264 Without inscription. Six-grained ear. Border of dots between two lines.</p>
               <p>℞ Ox head incuse with horns curved downward. Border similar to that of thick flan incuse staters. Note dot at center of die.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 13 mm. Diobol ——.——— Berlin, (2); Copenhagen; Naville VI, 442—1.34.</p>
               <p>265 Without inscription. Six-grained ear similar to 264, but with a greater interval between awns.</p>
               <p>℞ Narrow ox head, incuse.</p>
               <pb n="123"/>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 13 mm. Diobol 1.25. Dresden; London. B. M. Cat. 43—1.32.</p>
               <p>266 No inscription. Coarse five-grained ear.</p>
               <p>℞ Ox head, incuse.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 13 mm. Diobol —— ——— Commerce.</p>
               <p>267 No inscr. Similar to 264.</p>
               <p>℞ Ox head, incuse. The horn to r. recut (?).</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 12 mm.— ——_ E. T. Newell.</p>
               <p>268 <graphic url="NNM32_sym12.jpg"/> Compact six-grained ear which does not touch rim at base.</p>
               <p>℞ Similar to 264, save that the horns are short, and sharply curved.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 13 mm. Diobol 1.22. Vienna.</p>
               <p>269 <graphic url="NNM32_sym14.jpg"/> Five-grained ear.</p>
               <p>℞ Ox head, incuse. The horn to right is the longer. The forehead is decorated by concentric semi-circular lines.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 13 mm. Diobol 1.24. Naville, VI, 440.</p>
               <p>270 Die of 269.</p>
               <p>℞ Ox-head incuse—forehead with three semicircular rows of dots.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 13 mm.—— ——_ H. A. Green, Providence, R. I.</p>
               <p>271 <graphic url="NNM32_sym52.jpg"/> Five-grained ear.</p>
               <p>℞ Ox head incuse.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 13 mm. Diobol 1.25. Naville VI, 439.</p>
               <pb n="124"/>
               <p>272 <graphic url="NNM32_sym5.jpg"/> Five-grained ear with barbs on outside of the awns. Border of dots between two lines.</p>
               <p>℞ Ox head, incuse, with top of r. horn slightly higher than 1.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 12.5 mm. Diobol 0.68. Bement Sale 163; Vienna (1.00); Munich.</p>
               <p>273 <graphic url="NNM32_sym8.jpg"/> Broad five-grained ear.</p>
               <p>℞ Ox head incuse. Straight horns, downward.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 12 mm. Diobol — ——_ Berlin.</p>
               <p>274 <graphic url="NNM32_sym5.jpg"/> Five-grained ear broader at the base than at the top.</p>
               <p>℞ Ox head, incuse.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 12 mm. Diobol 1.08. Vienna.</p>
               <p>275 <graphic url="NNM32_sym11.jpg"/> Six-grained ear.</p>
               <p>℞ Ox head incuse.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 13.5 mm. Diobol —— ——— Berlin and second piece; Arolsen Coll.; Vienna (1.09), Cambridge (McClean 910—1.20).
                  Egger XLV, 141—1.16.</p>
               <p>276 <graphic url="NNM32_sym11.jpg"/> Five-grained ear with small additional terminal grains.</p>
               <p>℞ Ox head incuse.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 12.5 mm. Diobol — ——_ Berlin; Vienna (1.26); E. T. Newell (1.13).</p>
               <p>277 <graphic url="NNM32_sym11.jpg"/> Five-grained ear.</p>
               <pb n="125"/>
               <p>℞ Ox head with short horns, slightly curved downward. Forehead bears granular decoration.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 13 mm. Diobol 1.24. Copenhagen.</p>
               <p>278 <graphic url="NNM32_sym11.jpg"/> Five-grained ear with additional terminal awns. Inscription less compact than 277.</p>
               <p>℞ Ox head, incuse. The forehead has linear, and the muzzle granular decoration.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 11.5 mm. Diobol 0.98. London, 41.</p>
               <p>279 <graphic url="NNM32_sym11.jpg"/> Compact five-grained ear in high relief, with additional terminal awns. Ear does not touch the rim at the
                  base.</p>
               <p>℞ Similar to foregoing.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 12 mm. Diobol 1.32. Sartiges Cat. 32.</p>
               <p>280 <graphic url="NNM32_sym11.jpg"/> Five-grained ear with small additional terminal grains. Cable border.</p>
               <p>℞ Ox head incuse.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 12.5 mm. Diobol 1.14. Vienna.</p>
               <p>281 <graphic url="NNM32_sym11.jpg"/> Five-grained ear with the leaf in the field to the left.</p>
               <p>℞ Ox head, incuse, with short and only slightly curved horns.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 13 mm. Diobol 1.24. Cambridge, McClean, 912; Vienna, 1.08; Munich.</p>
               <p>282 <graphic url="NNM32_sym11.jpg"/> Crude five-grained ear with very broad base—possibly double struck.</p>
               <pb n="126"/>
               <p>℞ Ox head incuse.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 12 mm. Diobol 0.98. Pozzi, 162.</p>
               <p>283 <graphic url="NNM32_sym17.jpg"/> Six-grained ear in high relief. Border of dots between two lines.</p>
               <p>℞ Ox head incuse with short horns (which do not curve downward) and ears showing.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 14 mm. Diobol — —— Berlin.</p>
               <p>284 <graphic url="NNM32_sym51.jpg"/> Six-grained ear in high relief, the uppermost grains smaller than the others. The A of inscription with
                  cross-bar downward to 1.</p>
               <p>℞ Ox head, incuse.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 13 mm. Diobol — —— Berlin; Arolsen, E. S. G. Robinson, London.</p>
               <p>285 <graphic url="NNM32_sym51.jpg"/> Five-grained ear with small additional terminal grain.</p>
               <p>℞ Similar to 285.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 12 mm. Diobol 1.13. London; Munich.</p>
               <p>286 <graphic url="NNM32_sym51.jpg"/> Six-grained ear, the terminal grains smaller than the others.</p>
               <p>℞ Ox head, incuse, with thick horns.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 13 mm. Diobol — ——— Berlin; Hermitage.</p>
               <p>287 <graphic url="NNM32_sym51.jpg"/> Five-grained ear with additional terminal grain and rounded top.</p>
               <pb n="127"/>
               <p>℞ Ox head; right horn slightly longer than left one.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 13 mm. 1.24. Naville VI, 441; Paris.</p>
               <p>288 <graphic url="NNM32_sym54.jpg"/> Five-grained ear with wide border of dots between two lines.</p>
               <p>℞ Ox head, incuse.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 13 mm. Diobol — ——_ Paris.</p>
               <p>289 <graphic url="NNM32_sym55.jpg"/> Crude five-grained ear. Border of dots between two lines.</p>
               <p>℞ Ox head, incuse.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 12.5 mm. Diobol — —— Berlin.</p>
               <p>290 <graphic url="NNM32_sym20.jpg"/> Six-grained ear with additional terminal awns. Ear touches rim at the base.</p>
               <p>℞ Short-horned ox head, similar to 283.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 13 mm. Diobol 1.17. Vienna.</p>
               <p>291 <graphic url="NNM32_sym23.jpg"/> Six-grained ear.</p>
               <p>℞ Ox head with horns downward and almost straight. Space between the horns has a granular decoration instead of the vertical lines in most of
                  this series.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 12 mm. Diobol 1.02. Cambridge, McClean, 911.</p>
               <p>292 <graphic url="NNM32_sym20.jpg"/> Six-grained ear in high relief. Border of dots between two lines.</p>
               <p>℞ Ox head incuse with straight horns downward. Coarse border.</p>
               <pb n="128"/>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 13.5 mm. Diobol — —— Berlin; American Numismatic Society.</p>
               <p>293 <graphic url="NNM32_sym56.jpg"/> Six-grained ear with coarse awns. Border of dots between two lines.</p>
               <p>℞ Ox head, incuse, with short horns, downward, and slightly curved.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 13.5 mm. Diobol 1.34. W. Gedney Beatty (ex Sir H. Weber, 739); Jameson 262—1.21; Berlin, Egger XL (Prowe),
                  156—1.21.</p>
               <p>294 <graphic url="NNM32_sym57.jpg"/> The last two letters of inscr. are very faint. Broad five-grained ear.</p>
               <p>℞ Ox head incuse, the horns straight downward.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 13.5 mm. Diobol 1.33. E. T. Newell; London. B. M. Cat. 39—124; Berlin (2); Vienna—1.29; Merzbacher, Nov.,
                  1909, 2238—1.24.</p>
               <p>295 Die of 294.</p>
               <p>℞ Ox-head incuse, with straight horns, as in 294. The forehead has granular decorations, and the muzzle is indicated by two horizontal
                  lines.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 13 mm. 1.24. London, B. M. Cat. 39.</p>
               <p>296 <graphic url="NNM32_sym15.jpg"/> Six-grained ear.</p>
               <p>℞ Small ox-head incuse with vertical lines between horns and faint scale-surface between the eyes.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 13 mm. — ——_ E. Beesley Coll. (not illustrated—through error the Berlin specimen of No. 294 is shown on Pl.
                  xxi).</p>
               <pb n="129"/>
               <p>297 Six-grained ear of low relief and irregular shape. No inscr.</p>
               <p>℞ Incuse barley-grain.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 10 mm. Obol 0.63. Copenhagen.</p>
               <p>298 Six-grained ear.</p>
               <p>℞ Barley-grain incuse.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 10 mm. Obol 0.68. Naville Sale V, 443.</p>
               <p>299 Five-grained ear. Border of heavy dots (?).</p>
               <p>℞ A barley-corn incuse with an annulet each side.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 10.5 mm. Diobol — —— Munich.</p>
               <p>300 Four-grained ear.</p>
               <p>℞ Similar to No. 297 but annulets larger.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 10 mm. Diobol 0.84? Berlin.</p>
               <p>301 Very crude four-grained ear—the upper grains are smaller.</p>
               <p>℞ Similar to No. 297.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 10 mm. Diobol — —— Berlin.</p>
               <p>302 Four-grained ear. Similar to No. 298 but in higher relief and with more pronounced awns.</p>
               <p>℞ Similar to No. 298.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 10 mm. Diobol 0.70. Vienna.</p>
               <p>303 Five-grained ear with linear border.</p>
               <pb n="130"/>
               <p>℞ Similar to No. 297.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 10.5 mm. Diobol –.— Naples (Santangelo)</p>
               <p>304 Narrow six-grained ear touching the linear border at the bottom.</p>
               <p>℞ Similar to No. 297 save that the barleycorn is larger and very shallow.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 11 mm. × 7.5 mm. wide. Diobol 0.75. Cambridge (Leake).</p>
               <p>305 Six-grained ear with an annulet in field on either side.</p>
               <p>℞ Similar to No. 297.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 10 mm. Diobol –.— Berlin; Naples (Santangelo); Vienna (o.66); Cambridge (McClean 913—0. 81).</p>
               <p>306 Four-grained ear with heavy linear border and annulets on either side of the ear.</p>
               <p>℞ Barley-corn, incuse, with annulets on either side.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 8.5 mm. Diobol 0.65. Sir H. Weber Coll. 741.</p>
               <p>307 Six-grained ear with an annulet in the field on either side.</p>
               <p>℞ Barley grain with annulet in field on either side. Note dot at center of die.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 10 mm. Obol. –.— Hermitage.</p>
               <p>308 <graphic url="NNM32_sym58.jpg"/> Small five-grained ear. Border of dots. In field to 1 an ivy leaf with tip upward.</p>
               <pb n="131"/>
               <p>℞ Similar to No. 775.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 10.5 mm. Diobol 0.69. Berlin.</p>
               <p>309 <graphic url="NNM32_sym59.jpg"/>? Four-grained ear. In field to 1.</p>
               <p>a grasshopper, head upward.</p>
               <p>℞ Similar to No. 297.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM32_sym6.jpg"/> 11 mm. Diobol. –.— Berlin.</p>
            </div2>
         </div1>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div1 xml:id="d1e4346" type="backma">
            <pb n="132"/>
            <head>NOTES.</head>
            <note xml:id="CH1-n1" place="end">
               <seg type="note-symbol">1</seg>
               <p>Carelli. Numorum Italiæ Veteris. Lipsiæ, 1850.</p>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="CH1-n2" place="end">
               <seg type="note-symbol">2</seg>
               <p>Garrucci. Le Monete dell'Italia Antica. Roma, 1885.</p>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="CH1-n3" place="end">
               <seg type="note-symbol">3</seg>
               <p>Strabo. Geography, Bk. VI, I, 15, and Bk. VI, III, I.</p>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="CH1-n4" place="end">
               <seg type="note-symbol">4</seg>
               <p>R. Koldewey. O. Puchstein. Die Griechischen Tempeln in Unteritalien und Sicilien. Berlin, 1899.</p>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="CH1-n5" place="end">
               <seg type="note-symbol">5</seg>
               <p>De Luynes et Debacq. Metaponte. Paris, 1833.</p>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="CH1-n6" place="end">
               <seg type="note-symbol">6</seg>
               <p>M. Lacava. Topografia e storia di Metaponto. Naples, 1891.</p>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="CH1-n7" place="end">
               <seg type="note-symbol">7</seg>
               <p>K. Lehmann-Hartleben. Die antiken Hafenanlagen des Mittelmeeres. Leipzig, 1923. References. to other writers are given on page <hi rend="italic">270.</hi>
               </p>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="CH1-n8" place="end">
               <seg type="note-symbol">8</seg>
               <p>Num. Zeit. XXXV, 1903, page 203.</p>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="CH1-n9" place="end">
               <seg type="note-symbol">9</seg>
               <p>Nissen. Italische Landeskunde, II, 2, page 912.</p>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="CH1-n10" place="end">
               <seg type="note-symbol">10</seg>
               <p>Cf. Pausanias, VI, 19, II; V, 22, 5.</p>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="CH1-n11" place="end">
               <seg type="note-symbol">11</seg>
               <p>Jour. Hellenic Studies, 1905, page 294.</p>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="CH1-n12" place="end">
               <seg type="note-symbol">12</seg>
               <p>Thucydides, VII, 33.</p>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="CH1-n13" place="end">
               <seg type="note-symbol">13</seg>
               <p>Herodotus, IV, 15.</p>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="CH1-n14" place="end">
               <seg type="note-symbol">14</seg>
               <p>Lenormant. La Grande-Grèce. Paris, 1881. Although many of Lenormant's statements are speculative, they have been generally accepted, and are
                  drawn from a very wide knowledge of classical writers.</p>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="CH1-n15" place="end">
               <seg type="note-symbol">15</seg>
               <p>E. Speck. Handelsgeschichte des Altertums, Vol. II, 331.</p>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="CH1-n16" place="end">
               <seg type="note-symbol">16</seg>
               <p>G. Macdonald. Coin Types, page 12.</p>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="CH1-n17" place="end">
               <seg type="note-symbol">17</seg>
               <p>G. F. Hill, Greek and Roman Coins, page 152.</p>
            </note>
            <pb n="133"/>
            <note xml:id="CH1-n18" place="end">
               <seg type="note-symbol">18</seg>
               <p>Head. Historia Numorum. Introduction, page liii.</p>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="CH1-n19" place="end">
               <seg type="note-symbol">19</seg>
               <p>Num. Chron., 1922, pages 19-21.</p>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="CH1-n20" place="end">
               <seg type="note-symbol">20</seg>
               <p>Collection R. Jameson, No. 306.</p>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="CH1-n21" place="end">
               <seg type="note-symbol">21</seg>
               <p>Pozzi Sale, Naville I, 184.</p>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="CH1-n22" place="end">
               <seg type="note-symbol">22</seg>
               <p>Collection R. Jameson, No. 308.</p>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="CH1-n23" place="end">
               <seg type="note-symbol">23</seg>
               <p>Egger XLV, 145.</p>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="CH1-n24" place="end">
               <seg type="note-symbol">24</seg>
               <p>Babelon. Collection De Luynes, 485.</p>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="CH1-n25" place="end">
               <seg type="note-symbol">25</seg>
               <p>Hirsch XXX, 175.</p>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="CH1-n26" place="end">
               <seg type="note-symbol">26</seg>
               <p>Evans. Horsemen of <placeName corresp="#nomisma_tarentum">Tarentum</placeName>, page 25, note.</p>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="CH1-n27" place="end">
               <seg type="note-symbol">27</seg>
               <p>Cf. Mazochius. Comm. in Reg. Herculanensis Aenaeas Tabulas. Naples, 1754.</p>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="CH1-n28" place="end">
               <seg type="note-symbol">28</seg>
               <p>Rev. Num., 1922, page 103.</p>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="CH1-n29" place="end">
               <seg type="note-symbol">29</seg>
               <p>Num. Notes and Monogr. No. 27, page 52.</p>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="CH1-n30" place="end">
               <seg type="note-symbol">30</seg>
               <p>Collection R. Jameson, Tome III, No. 1867.</p>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="CH1-n31" place="end">
               <seg type="note-symbol">31</seg>
               <p>Collection R. Jameson, Tome III, No. 324.</p>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="CH1-n32" place="end">
               <seg type="note-symbol">32</seg>
               <p>Collection R. Jameson, Tome III, No. 272.</p>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="CH1-n33" place="end">
               <seg type="note-symbol">33</seg>
               <p>However, compare Petrone in Bolletino del Circolo Num, Napoletano, 1927, p. 23, who distinguishes two species of dolphins. Reference should
                  also be made to the <hi rend="italic">χρ03C5;σῶ****ν τεττíγωυ</hi> mentioned by Thucydides (Book I, vi).</p>
               <p>"Their (the Athenian) older men of the wealthier class gave up wearing tunics of linen and fastening up their hair in a knot held by a golden
                  grasshopper as a brooch; and this same dress obtained for a long time among the elderly men of the Ionians also, owing to their kinship with
                  the Athenians." Can there have been any way by which this probably symbolic use of the grasshopper could have a bearing upon the employment of
                  the symbol on these staters?</p>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="CH1-n34" place="end">
               <seg type="note-symbol">34</seg>
               <p>Rev. Num., 1916, page 24.</p>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="CH1-n35" place="end">
               <seg type="note-symbol">35</seg>
               <p>Historia Numorum, page 106.</p>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="CH1-n36" place="end">
               <seg type="note-symbol">36</seg>
               <p>Zeit. f. Num., 1880, page 308.</p>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="CH1-n37" place="end">
               <seg type="note-symbol">37</seg>
               <p>Atti e Mem. dell'Ist. Ital di Num., Vol. Ill, page 31.</p>
            </note>
            <pb n="134"/>
            <note xml:id="CH1-n38" place="end">
               <seg type="note-symbol">38</seg>
               <p>The following varieties, numbered according to my classification, occurred in the Curinga Hoard: 1a, 3, 11 (2±1), 12, 13 (2), 15, 16, 20, 23,
                  25, 58, 74 (2), 77, 78 (2), 97, 112, 113, 116, 120, 122, 123, 129, 132, 133, 134, 140, 143, 151, 165, 166, 168, 171, 172, 174 (2), 176, 181,
                  182, 186, 187, 188, 189, 191 (5), 192, 193, 194 (2), 197, 199 (2), 201 (2), 202 (2), 203, 206, 207, 211 (2), 215, 253. One unidentified.</p>
            </note>
            <note xml:id="CH1-n39" place="end">
               <seg type="note-symbol">39</seg>
               <p>The following varieties are known to have been in the Taranto Hoard. The list is but partial. Except where parentheses enclose a larger
                  figure, but one specimen has been traced: 1b, 1c, 1d, 3 (4), 4 (7±), 5, 6 (2), 7 (3), 8 (2), 10 (2), 11 (2), 13, 14 (4±1), 16, 17, 19, 20, 22
                  (3), 23 (2), 26, 29, 33, 40, 42 (3), 43 (6+), 46, 54, 76, 85 (2), 86, 87, 89, 124.</p>
               <p>For M. Babelon's description of the hoard, see Rev. Num., 1912, page 1.</p>
            </note>
            <pb/>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d1e4560" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>METAPONTUM</head>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e4564" type="backma">
               <head>Class I</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-6">
                  <graphic url="NNM32_141.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e4569" type="backma">
               <pb/>
               <head>Plate I</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-7">
                  <graphic url="NNM32_142.jpg"/>
                  <p>Nos. 1-9.</p>
               </figure>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d1e4577" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>METAPONTUM</head>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e4581" type="backma">
               <head>Class I</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-8">
                  <graphic url="NNM32_143.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e4586" type="backma">
               <pb/>
               <head>Plate II</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-9">
                  <graphic url="NNM32_144.jpg"/>
                  <p>Nos. 10-21.</p>
               </figure>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d1e4594" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>METAPONTUM</head>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e4598" type="backma">
               <head>Class I</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-10">
                  <graphic url="NNM32_145.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e4603" type="backma">
               <pb/>
               <head>Plate III</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-11">
                  <graphic url="NNM32_146.jpg"/>
                  <p>Nos. 22-36.</p>
               </figure>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d1e4611" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>METAPONTUM</head>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e4615" type="backma">
               <head>Class II</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-12">
                  <graphic url="NNM32_147.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e4620" type="backma">
               <pb/>
               <head>Plate IV</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-13">
                  <graphic url="NNM32_148.jpg"/>
                  <p>Nos. 40-49.</p>
               </figure>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d1e4628" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>METAPONTUM</head>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e4632" type="backma">
               <head>Class III</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-14">
                  <graphic url="NNM32_149.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e4637" type="backma">
               <pb/>
               <head>Plate V</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-15">
                  <graphic url="NNM32_150.jpg"/>
                  <p>Nos. 54-72.</p>
               </figure>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d1e4645" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>METAPONTUM</head>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e4649" type="backma">
               <head>Class III</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-16">
                  <graphic url="NNM32_151.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e4654" type="backma">
               <pb/>
               <head>Plate VI</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-17">
                  <graphic url="NNM32_152.jpg"/>
                  <p>Nos. 73-84.</p>
               </figure>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d1e4662" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>METAPONTUM</head>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e4666" type="backma">
               <head>Class IV</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-18">
                  <graphic url="NNM32_153.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e4671" type="backma">
               <pb/>
               <head>Plate VII</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-19">
                  <graphic url="NNM32_154.jpg"/>
                  <p>Nos. 87-98.</p>
               </figure>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d1e4679" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>METAPONTUM</head>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e4683" type="backma">
               <head>Class V</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-20">
                  <graphic url="NNM32_155.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e4688" type="backma">
               <pb/>
               <head>Plate VIII</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-21">
                  <graphic url="NNM32_156.jpg"/>
                  <p>Nos. 100-111.</p>
               </figure>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d1e4696" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>METAPONTUM</head>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e4700" type="backma">
               <head>Class VI</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-22">
                  <graphic url="NNM32_157.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e4705" type="backma">
               <pb/>
               <head>Plate IX</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-23">
                  <graphic url="NNM32_158.jpg"/>
                  <p>Nos. 112-123.</p>
               </figure>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d1e4713" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>METAPONTUM</head>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e4717" type="backma">
               <head>Class VI</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-24">
                  <graphic url="NNM32_159.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e4722" type="backma">
               <pb/>
               <head>Plate X</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-25">
                  <graphic url="NNM32_160.jpg"/>
                  <p>Nos. 124-135.</p>
               </figure>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d1e4731" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>METAPONTUM</head>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e4735" type="backma">
               <head>Class VII</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-26">
                  <graphic url="NNM32_161.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e4740" type="backma">
               <pb/>
               <head>Plate XI</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-27">
                  <graphic url="NNM32_162.jpg"/>
                  <p>Nos. 136-144.</p>
               </figure>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d1e4748" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>METAPONTUM</head>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e4752" type="backma">
               <head>Class VIII</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-28">
                  <graphic url="NNM32_163.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e4757" type="backma">
               <pb/>
               <head>Plate XII</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-29">
                  <graphic url="NNM32_164.jpg"/>
                  <p>Nos. 145-154b.</p>
               </figure>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d1e4765" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>METAPONTUM</head>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e4769" type="backma">
               <head>Class IX</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-30">
                  <graphic url="NNM32_165.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e4774" type="backma">
               <pb/>
               <head>Plate XIII</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-31">
                  <graphic url="NNM32_166.jpg"/>
                  <p>Nos. 155-166.</p>
               </figure>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d1e4782" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>METAPONTUM</head>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e4786" type="backma">
               <head>Class IX</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-32">
                  <graphic url="NNM32_167.jpg"/>
                  <p>METAPONTUM</p>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e4793" type="backma">
               <pb/>
               <head>Plate XIV</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-33">
                  <graphic url="NNM32_168.jpg"/>
                  <p>Nos. 167-178.</p>
               </figure>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d1e4801" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>METAPONTUM</head>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e4805" type="backma">
               <head>Class IX</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-34">
                  <graphic url="NNM32_169.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e4810" type="backma">
               <pb/>
               <head>Plate XV</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-35">
                  <graphic url="NNM32_170.jpg"/>
                  <p>Nos. 179-190.</p>
               </figure>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d1e4818" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>METAPONTUM</head>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e4822" type="backma">
               <head>Class IX</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-36">
                  <graphic url="NNM32_171.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e4827" type="backma">
               <pb/>
               <head>Plate XVI</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-37">
                  <graphic url="NNM32_172.jpg"/>
                  <p>Nos. 191-202.</p>
               </figure>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d1e4835" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>METAPONTUM</head>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e4839" type="backma">
               <head>Class IX (to 208)</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-38">
                  <graphic url="NNM32_173.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e4844" type="backma">
               <pb/>
               <head>Plate XVII</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-39">
                  <graphic url="NNM32_174.jpg"/>
                  <p>Class X (209-14).</p>
               </figure>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d1e4852" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>METAPONTUM</head>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e4856" type="backma">
               <head>Class X</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-40">
                  <graphic url="NNM32_175.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e4861" type="backma">
               <pb/>
               <head>Plate XVIII</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-41">
                  <graphic url="NNM32_176.jpg"/>
                  <p>Nos. 215-228.</p>
               </figure>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d1e4869" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>METAPONTUM</head>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e4873" type="backma">
               <head>Class X (to 232)</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-42">
                  <graphic url="NNM32_177.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e4878" type="backma">
               <pb/>
               <head>Plate XIX</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-43">
                  <graphic url="NNM32_178.jpg"/>
                  <p>Class XI (233-242).</p>
               </figure>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d1e4886" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>METAPONTUM</head>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e4890" type="backma">
               <head>Class XI</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-44">
                  <graphic url="NNM32_179.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e4895" type="backma">
               <pb/>
               <head>Plate XX</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-45">
                  <graphic url="NNM32_180.jpg"/>
                  <p>Nos. 243-257.</p>
               </figure>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d1e4903" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>METAPONTUM</head>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e4907" type="backma">
               <head>Class XII</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-46">
                  <graphic url="NNM32_181.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e4912" type="backma">
               <pb/>
               <head>Plate XXI</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-47">
                  <graphic url="NNM32_182.jpg"/>
                  <p>Nos. 258-261.</p>
               </figure>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d1e4921" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>METAPONTUM</head>
            <figure xml:id="fig-48">
               <graphic url="NNM32_183.jpg"/>
            </figure>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e4927" type="backma">
               <pb/>
               <head>Plate XXII</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-49">
                  <graphic url="NNM32_184.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d1e4933" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>METAPONTUM</head>
            <figure xml:id="fig-50">
               <graphic url="NNM32_185.jpg"/>
            </figure>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e4939" type="backma">
               <pb/>
               <head>Plate XXIII</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-51">
                  <graphic url="NNM32_186.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d1e4945" type="backma">
               <pb/>
               <head>
                  <hi rend="smalcaps">Numismatic Notes and Monographs</hi>
               </head>
               <list rend="numbered">
                  <item n="1.">
                     <placeName>Sydney</placeName> P. Noe. Coin Hoards. 1921. 47 pp. 6 pls. 50c.</item>
                  <item n="4.">Howland Wood. The Mexican Revolutionary Coinage 1913-1916. 1921. 44 pp. 26 pls. $2.00.</item>
                  <item n="6.">
                     <persName corresp="#numismatics_brett">Anges Balwdin</persName>. Five Roman Gold Medallions, 1921. 103 pp. 8 pls. $1.50.</item>
                  <item n="7.">
                     <placeName>Sydney</placeName> P. Noe. Medallic Work of A. A. Weinman. 1921. 31 pp. 17 pls. $1.00.</item>
                  <item n="8.">
                     <persName>Gilbert S</persName>. Perez. The Mint of the Philippine Islands. 1921. 8 pp. 4 pls. 50c.</item>
                  <item n="9.">
                     <persName corresp="#viaf_34463266">David Eugene Smith</persName>, LL.D. Computing Jetons. 1921. 70 pp. 25 pls. $1.50.</item>
                  <item n="10.">
                     <persName>Edward T</persName>. Newell. The First Seleucid Coinage of Tyre. 1921. 40 pp. 8 pls. $1.00.</item>
                  <item n="11.">
                     <persName>Harrold E</persName>. <placeName>Gillingham</placeName>. French Orders and Decorations. 1922. 110 pp. 35 pls.
                     $2.00.</item>
                  <item n="12.">Howland Wood. Gold Dollars of 1858. 1922. 7 pp. 2 pls. 50c.</item>
                  <item n="13.">R. B. Whitehead. Pre-Mohammedan Coinage of N. W. <placeName corresp="#nomisma_india">India</placeName>. 1922. 56 pp. 15 pls.
                     $2.00.</item>
                  <item n="14.">
                     <persName>George F</persName>. Hill. Attambelos I of Characene. 1922. 12 pp. 3 pls. $1.00.</item>
                  <item n="15.">M. P. Vlasto. Taras Oikistes (A Contribution to Tarentine Numismatics). 1922. 234 pp. 13 pls. $3.50.</item>
                  <item n="16.">Howland Wood. Commemorative Coinage of <placeName>United States</placeName>. 1922. 63 pp. 7 pls. $1.50.</item>
                  <item n="17.">Agnes Baldwin. Six Roman Bronze Medallions. 1923. 39 PP. 6 pls. $1.50.</item>
                  <pb/>
                  <item n="18.">Howland Wood. Tegucigalpa Coinage of 1823. 1923. 16 pp. 2 pls. 50c.</item>
                  <item n="19.">Edward T. Newell. Alexander Hoards—II. Demanhur Hoard. 1923. 162 pp. 8 pls. $2.50.</item>
                  <item n="20.">Harrold E. Gillingham. Italian Orders of Chivalry and Medals of Honour. 1923. 146 pp. 34 pls. $2.00.</item>
                  <item n="21.">Edward T. Newell. Alexander Hoards—III. Andritsaena. 1924. 39 pp. 6 pls. $1.00.</item>
                  <item n="22.">C. T. Seltman. A Hoard from Side. 1924. 20 pp. 3 pls. $1.00.</item>
                  <item n="23.">R. B. Seager. A Cretan Coin Hoard. 1924. 55 pp. 12 pls. $2.00.</item>
                  <item n="24.">Samuel R. Milbank. The Coinage of Aegina. 1925. 66 pp. 5 pls. $2.00.</item>
                  <item n="25.">Sydney P. Noe. A Bibliography of Greek Coin Hoards. 1925. 275 pp. $2.50.</item>
                  <item n="26.">Edward T. Newell. Mithradates of Parthia and Hyspaosines of Characene. 1925. 18 pp. 2 pls. 50c.</item>
                  <item n="27.">Sydney P. Noe. The Mende (Kaliandra) Hoard. 1926. 73 pp. 10 pls. $2.00.</item>
                  <item n="28.">Agnes Baldwin. Four Medallions from the Arras Hoard. 1926. 36 pp. 4 pls. $1.50.</item>
                  <item n="29.">H. Alexander Parsons. The Earliest Coins of Norway. 1926. 41 pp. 50c.</item>
                  <item n="30.">Edward T. Newell. Some Unpublished Coins of Eastern Dynasts. 1926. 21 pp. 2 pls. 50c.</item>
                  <item n="31.">Harrold E. Gillingham. Spanish Orders of Chivalry and Decorations of Honour. 1926. 165 pp. 40 pls. $3.00.</item>
               </list>
            </div2>
         </div1>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
