<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd" xml:id="nnan74137">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Victory issues of Syracuse after 413 B.C</title>
            <author>
               <name>Brett, Agnes Baldwin, 1876-1955</name>
               <idno type="URI">http://numismatics.org/authority/brett</idno>
            </author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>TEI P5 XML markup in conformance with the TEI DTD</resp>
               <name>AEL Data</name>
            </respStmt>
            <funder>Open access edition funded by the National Endowment for the Humanities/Andrew W. Mellon Foundation Humanities Open Book Program.</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <name>American Numismatic Society</name>
               <idno type="URI">http://numismatics.org/authority/american_numismatic_society</idno>
            </publisher>
            <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
            <date>1936</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">This work is made available under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International license</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Numismatic Notes and Monographs</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">75</biblScope>
            <idno type="URI">http://numismatics.org/library/195778</idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>Donum</title>
               <idno type="URI">http://numismatics.org/library/74137</idno>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <title>Worldcat</title>
               <idno type="URI">http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/557987992</idno>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <title>Worldcat Works</title>
               <idno type="URI">http://worldcat.org/entity/work/id/4959675</idno>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://nomisma.org/">
               <term ref="http://nomisma.org/id/greek_numismatics">Greek Numismatics</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2018-04-02">Ran TEI file through XSLT process, detailed in the Mellon EBook migration Google Document.</change>
         <change when="2018-04-02">Included normalized entity labels and URIs from
				previous OpenRefine process.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div1 xml:id="d298e30" type="frontma">
            <pb/>
            <figure xml:id="fig-1">
               <graphic url="NNM75_01.jpg"/>
            </figure>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d298e34" type="frontma">
            <pb/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="bold">PUBLICATIONS</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi rend="bold">The American Journal of Numismatics 1866–1920.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Monthly, May, 1866–April, 1870.</p>
            <p>Quarterly, July, 1870–October, 1912</p>
            <p>Annually, 1913–1920.</p>
            <p rend="hang">With many plates, illustrations, maps and tables. Less than a half-dozen complete sets of the Journal remain on hand. Price on application</p>
            <p rend="hang">The numbers necessary to complete broken sets may in most cases be obtained. An index to the first fifty volumes has been issued as part of Volume LI. It may also be purchased separately for $3.00.</p>
            <p rend="hang">The American Numismatic Society. Catalogue of the International Exhibition of Contemporary Medals. March, 1910. New and revised edition. <placeName>New York</placeName>. 1911. xxxvi, 412 pages, 512 illustrations. $10.00. Price to members $5.00.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d298e57" type="frontma">
            <pb/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="bold">NUMISMATIC NOTES AND MONOGRAPHS</hi>
            </head>
            <p/>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d298e63" type="dedication">
            <pb/>
            <p>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">Numismatic Notes and Monographs</hi> is devoted to essays and treatises on subjects relating to coins, paper money, medals and decorations and is uniform with Hispanic Notes and Monographs published by the Hispanic Society of <placeName>America</placeName>, and with Indian Notes and Monographs issued by the Museum of the American Indian—Heye Foundation.</p>
            <list>
               <head>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">Publication Committee</hi>
               </head>
               <item>
                  <persName>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">Agnes Baldwin Brett</hi>
                  </persName>, <hi rend="italic">Chairman</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <persName>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">Stephen</hi> H. P. <hi rend="smallcaps">Pell</hi>
                  </persName>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <persName>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">Thomas</hi> O. <hi rend="smallcaps">Mabbott</hi>
                  </persName>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">Editorial Staff</hi>
               </head>
               <item>
                  <persName>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">Sydney Philip Noe</hi>
                  </persName>, <hi rend="italic">Editor</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <persName>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">Howland Wood</hi>
                  </persName>, <hi rend="italic">Associate Editor</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d298e115" type="colophon">
            <pb/>
            <p>COPYRIGHT 1936 BY</p>
            <p>THE AMERICAN NUMISMATIC SOCIETY</p>
            <p>THE INTELLIGENCER PRINTING CO.</p>
            <p>
               <placeName>LANCASTER, PA</placeName>.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d298e127" type="frontma">
            <pb/>
            <figure xml:id="fig-2">
               <graphic url="NNM75_06a.jpg"/>
               <p>1.</p>
            </figure>
            <figure xml:id="fig-3">
               <graphic url="NNM75_06b.jpg"/>
               <p>2.</p>
            </figure>
         </div1>
         <titlePage>
            <pb/>
            <docTitle>
               <titlePart type="main">VICTORY ISSUES OF SYRACUSE AFTER 413 B.C.</titlePart>
            </docTitle>
            <byline>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">by</hi>
               <persName>AGNES BALDWIN BRETT</persName>
            </byline>
            <figure xml:id="fig-4">
               <graphic url="NNM75_07.jpg"/>
            </figure>
            <docImprint>
               <publisher>THE AMERICAN NUMISMATIC SOCIETY</publisher>
               <pubPlace>BROADWAY AT 156TH STREET</pubPlace>
               <pubPlace>NEW YORK</pubPlace>
               <date>1936</date>
            </docImprint>
         </titlePage>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div1 xml:id="d298e159" type="chapter">
            <pb n="1"/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="bold">VICTORY ISSUES OF SYRACUSE AFTER 413 B.C.</hi>
            </head>
            <byline>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">By</hi> Agnes Baldwin Brett
</byline>
            <p>The appearance of an Athena head on the coinage of Syracuse (Plate I, 1) soon after the defeat of the Athenian fleet in the Great Harbor and the destruction of the enemy's land forces at the Assinarus in 413 B.C., seems at first sight inexplicable. Why should the mint authorities have commissioned the engraver, Eucleidas, to design an Athena head to take the place of that of Arethusa, the goddess who had hitherto without exception held the position of chief deity on the coins? Since no connection with the Athena Parthenos of the enemy is possible, the type must have local significance and it is therefore obvious that the Syracusans were honoring their own Athena whose massive temple was situated on Ortygia, that is in the heart of the city.<ref target="#CH1-n1">
                  <hi rend="sup">1</hi>
               </ref>
            </p>
            <p>In addition to the new, facing Athena type, other types and symbols were employed to commemorate the victories on land and sea. Besides the decadrachms of Euainetos and Kimon well-known as signalizing the defeat of the Athenian forces as they retreated across the Assinarus, and struck probably as prizes for the victors at the Assinarian games, there were issued the tetradrachm (Plate I, 2) by the engraver Euth ..... with the sea-monster, Scylla, in the exergue, and a winged charioteer, and
<pb n="2"/>
also the tetradrachm by Phrygillos (Frontispiece) with the aphlaston symbol in the hand of Nike who is crowning the charioteer. This latter piece deserves renewed attention as Tudeer has cast doubt upon the interpretation of the emblem as an aphlaston first noted by Salinas,<ref target="#CH1-n2">
                  <hi rend="sup">2</hi>
               </ref> and then adopted by Evans.<ref target="#CH1-n3">
                  <hi rend="sup">3</hi>
               </ref> The coin is in danger of being forgotten as emblematic of naval victory since in his great corpus of the signed tetradrachms<ref target="#CH1-n4">
                  <hi rend="sup">4</hi>
               </ref> Tudeer considered the symbol to be a palm branch. Thus interpreted, the issue is equally symbolic of victory, as the palm is an innovation in the type, a wreath or fillet being usually held by Nike, but merely of military, not specifically naval victory. That the object is an aphlaston, however, is abundantly clear from the enlarged photograph of the well-preserved specimen in the Boston collection (Frontispiece). Another indication of the commemorative character of the coin by Phrygillos is the fact that in place of the male charioteer without attributes, the goddess, Persephone, holding a torch now makes her appearance on the coinage for the first time. This aphlaston issue with Persephone as charioteer is regarded by Tudeer as struck very shortly after the victory. It is not surprising, then, to find that on the issue which Tudeer classifies as the very first after the victory, namely, the coin by Euth...... above cited, a head of Kore, or Persephone, supplants the traditional head of
<pb n="3"/>
Arethusa. One of these heads, that by Eum<ref target="#CH1-n5">
                  <hi rend="sup">5</hi>
               </ref> . . , is not an entirely new design like the later, long-haired Persephone type, but a mere modification of the old Arethusa head achieved by the addition of ears of barley, poppy-heads, oak-leaves and acorns to the conventional head type. In this way Arethusa is metamorphosed into Kore. As Tudeer points out, the Syracusans expressed their claim to leadership of all Sicily by placing on the new types, the deity in whose common worship all of the cities were united. He cites as evidence for the cult in Sicily, the honorary decree<ref target="#CH1-n6">
                  <hi rend="sup">6</hi>
               </ref> for Dionysius, as "archon of Sicily," erected at Athens in 393 B.C. on which Demeter is the figure representing Sicily. We add for the cult at Syracuse, Gelon's construction of temples to Demeter and Kore<ref target="#CH1-n7">
                  <hi rend="sup">7</hi>
               </ref> out of the Carthaginian spoils after the battle of Himera in 480 B.C.; Pindar's VI Olympic Ode, 11. 92–96 in praise of Hieron and Syracuse in which purple-footed Damater and her daughter are mentioned; and the frequent occurrences of Demeter or Kore heads on later Syracusan issues. Holm regards the dual cult of these deities as indigenous in Sicily, and the original site of the rape of Persephone was said to be at the town of Enna in the interior.</p>
            <p>After first honoring their great national deity, the Syracusans introduced the facing head of Athena as the reverse type of a coin having Persephone as
<pb n="4"/>
charioteer, and her attribute, an ear of barley in the exergue. This symbol is continued as an exergual device on several later issues, one of which<ref target="#CH1-n8">
                  <hi rend="sup">8</hi>
               </ref> has the new, long-haired head of Kore with a single, large barley ear in her hair.</p>
            <p>On the small gold coins struck around 410 B.C., Athena is again represented (with her Gorgoneion as reverse). This coin (Plate I, 3) is of lower denomination, equivalent to 12½ silver litrae, and slightly later than the first gold coin of Syracuse, the 20-litrae piece bearing the head of Heracles in the lion's scalp (Plate I, 4). To the period, 410 to 390 B.C., belong the 100-litrae coins having as obverse, heads of Arethusa by Euainetes and Kimon, and as reverse, Heracles wrestling with the Nemean lion (Plate I, 5). Here there arises the question of the significance of the introduction of types relating to Heracles on these issues following the victory over the Athenians. No explanation has, to the writer's knowledge, ever been suggested. Yet the reason why these types were used is available from certain passages in Plutarch<ref target="#CH1-n9">
                  <hi rend="sup">9</hi>
               </ref> and Thucydides<ref target="#CH1-n10">
                  <hi rend="sup">10</hi>
               </ref> which have escaped the notice of investigators of the Syracusan coins. From these sources we learn that there was a particular motive which led to the choice of these Heraclean types. Just before the final struggle for mastery of the harbor, the Athenians were forced to abandon their encampment and fortifications on the shore, after the occupation of
<pb n="5"/>
the promontory of Plemmyrium by Gylippus. Now, this first Athenian camp was adjacent to the sanctuary of Heracles, and the Syracusans, prevented for a long time from sacrificing to the god, went up just before the battle, both priests and generals, to do so. Even while the galleys were being manned, the diviners predicted victory to them if they would not take the offensive but, like Heracles, defend themselves only when attacked. After the decisive naval contest ending in disaster to the Athenians, the land forces and those rescued from the ships decided to retreat that very night. The Syracusan generals, though informed of the plan, were unable to rally their men to pursue the enemy, since these had not rested, and furthermore there was a festival or celebration as they were offering a sacrifice to Heracles that very day. Heracles then was regarded by the Syracusans as the god who gave them victory, and for this reason they devised the Heraclean types for the principal denominations of the two gold issues. The type of Heracles wrestling with the lion is symbolic of victory just as Heracles strangling the serpents on the Symmachia coinage<ref target="#CH1-n11">
                  <hi rend="sup">11</hi>
               </ref> struck after Konon's victory off Knidos and his reestablishment of democracy, is indicative of a successful struggle.</p>
            <p>All of the above innovations in the stereotyped pattern of the Syracusan coinage which had existed for a century, namely, the Persephone figure as charioteer, Nike holding the aphlaston, the Perse-
<pb n="6"/>
phone, Heracles and Athena<ref target="#CH1-n12">
                  <hi rend="sup">12</hi>
               </ref> heads, are the expression of the homage paid by Syracuse to her principal deities in the moment of her exultation over the defeat of the Athenians whose naval supremacy had been unchallenged since Salamis. Our literary sources tell us that a wave of nationalistic ardor swept over the citizens inspiring them to demand a democratic constitution. This accent on victory displaced temporarily the long familiar Arethusa head on the coinage as the people gave vent to their joy by giving thanks to the gods of their polis. Arethusa, the strictly local deity associated with the fountain, was not forgotten however, for a new type was designed for her by Kimon, the wonderful facing head with her beautiful name APE0OSA above it, (Plate I, 6) and it is interesting to observe that this is the last of the special, new types created at Syracuse as a result of the victory.</p>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n1">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">1</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>A Doric temple on the site of which stands the modern Cathedral.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n2">
               <seg type="note-symbol">2</seg>
               <p>Notizie degli Scavi, 1888, p. 309.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n3">
               <seg type="note-symbol">3</seg>
               <p>Num. Chron. 1890, p. 302, and 1891, p. 335.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n4">
               <seg type="note-symbol">4</seg>
               <p>Zeit. f. Num. 30, 1913, p. 279.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n5">
               <seg type="note-symbol">5</seg>
               <p>Zeit. f. Num. 30, 1913, P1. II, 28 (Coin No. 46).</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n6">
               <seg type="note-symbol">6</seg>
               <p>Hicks and Hill, Greek Historical Inscriptions, No. 91.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n7">
               <seg type="note-symbol">7</seg>
               <p>Diodorus XI. 26.7. Their temples were probably located in the district called Temenites, later named Neapolis.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n8">
               <seg type="note-symbol">8</seg>
               <p>Zeit. f. Num. 30, 1913, PI. IV, 23 + 44, Coin no. 66.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n9">
               <seg type="note-symbol">9</seg>
               <p>Nicias, chs. XXIV to XXVI.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n10">
               <seg type="note-symbol">10</seg>
               <p>Bk. VII. lxxiii, 2.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n11">
               <seg type="note-symbol">11</seg>
               <p>Amer. Journ. Num. LIII. 3. P1. IV 8–10.</p>
            </note>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n12">
               <seg type="note-symbol">12</seg>
               <p>On the change of type from Arethusa to Athena, Tudeer, <hi rend="italic">l. c</hi>., p. 158, commented as follows: "Why the artist abandoned the time-honored goddess, cannot be stated, and perhaps we shall never be able to give the true reason with certainty."</p>
            </note>
         </div1>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div1 xml:id="d298e301" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="bold">SYRACUSE</hi>
            </head>
            <div2 xml:id="d298e306" type="section">
               <head>PLATE I</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-5">
                  <graphic url="NNM75_14.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d298e311" type="backma">
            <head>
               <hi rend="bold">Numismatic Notes and Monographs</hi>
            </head>
            <list type="numbered">
               <item n="9." rend="hang">
                  <persName>David Eugene Smith, LL.D</persName>. Computing Jetons. 1921. 70 pp. 25 pls. $1.50.</item>
               <item n="10." rend="hang">
                  <persName>Edward T. Newell</persName>. The First Seleucid Coinage at Tyre. 1921. 40 pp. 8 pls. $1.00.</item>
               <item n="12." rend="hang">
                  <persName>Howland Wood</persName>. Gold Dollars of 1858. 1922. 7 pp. 2 pls. 50c.</item>
               <item n="13." rend="hang">
                  <persName>R. B. Whitehead</persName>. Pre-Mohammedan Coinage of N. W. <placeName>India</placeName>. 1922. 56 pp. 15 pls. $2.00.</item>
               <item n="14." rend="hang">
                  <persName>George F. Hill</persName>. Attambelos I of Characene. 1922. 12 pp. 3 pls. $1.00.</item>
               <item n="15." rend="hang">
                  <persName>M. P. Vlasto</persName>. Taras Oikistes (A Contribution to Tarentine Numismatics). 1922. 234 pp. 13 pls. $3.50.</item>
               <item n="17." rend="hang">
                  <persName>Agnes Baldwin</persName>. Six Roman Bronze Medallions. 1923. 39 pp. 6 pls. $1.50.</item>
               <item n="18." rend="hang">
                  <persName>Howland Wood</persName>. Tegucigalpa Coinage of 1823. 1923. 16 pp. 2 pls. 50c.</item>
               <item n="19." rend="hang">
                  <persName>Edward T. Newell</persName>. <persName>Alexander Hoards—II</persName>. <placeName>Demanhur</placeName> Hoard. 1923. 162 pp. 8 pls. $2.50.</item>
               <item n="20." rend="hang">
                  <persName>Harrold E. Gillingham</persName>. Italian Orders of Chivalry and Medals of Honour. 146 pp. 34. pls. $2.00.</item>
               <item n="21." rend="hang">
                  <persName>Edward T. Newell</persName>. <persName>Alexander</persName> Hoards—III. Andritsaena. 1924. 39 pp. 6 pls. $1.00.</item>
               <item n="22." rend="hang">
                  <persName>C. T. Seltman</persName>. A Hoard from Side. 1924. 20 pp. 3 pls. $1.00.</item>
               <item n="23." rend="hang">
                  <persName>R. B. Seager</persName>. A Cretan Coin Hoard. 1924. 55 pp. 12 pls. $2.00.</item>
               <item n="24." rend="hang">
                  <persName>Samuel R. Milbank</persName>. The Coinage of <placeName>Aegina</placeName>. 1925. 66 pp. 5 pls. $2.00.</item>
               <item n="25." rend="hang">
                  <persName>Sydney P. Noe</persName>. A Bibliography of Greek Coin Hoards. 1925. 275 pp. $2.50.</item>
               <item n="26." rend="hang">
                  <persName>Edward T. Newell</persName>. <persName>Mithradates</persName> of <placeName>Parthia</placeName> and Hyspaosines of Characene, 1925. 18 pp. 2 pls. 50c.</item>
               <item n="27." rend="hang">
                  <persName>Sydney P. Noe</persName>. The Mende (<placeName>Kaliandra</placeName>) Hoard. 1926. 73 pp. 10 pls. $2.00.</item>
               <item n="28." rend="hang">
                  <persName>Agnes Baldwin</persName>. Four Medallions from the Arras Hoard. 1926. 36 pp. 4 pls. $1.50.</item>
               <item n="30." rend="hang">
                  <persName>Edward T. Newell</persName>. Some Unpublished Coins of Eastern Dynasts. 1926. 21 pp. 2 pls. 50c.</item>
               <item n="31." rend="hang">
                  <persName>Harrold E. Gillingham</persName>. Spanish Orders of Chivalry and Decorations of Honour. 1926. 165 pp. 40 pls. $3.00.</item>
               <item n="32." rend="hang">
                  <persName>Sydney P. Noe</persName>. The Coinage of Metapontum. 1927 (Part I). 134 pp. 23 pls. $3.00.</item>
               <item n="33." rend="hang">
                  <persName>Edward T. Newell</persName>. Two Recent Egyptian Hoards—Delta and Keneh. 1927. 34 pp. 3 pls. $1.00.</item>
               <item n="34." rend="hang">
                  <persName>Edward Rogers</persName>. The Second and Third Seleucid Coinage of Tyre. 1927. 33 pp. 4 pls. $1.50.</item>
               <item n="35." rend="hang">
                  <persName>Alfred R. Bellinger</persName>. The Anonymous Byzantine Bronze Coinage. 1928. 27 pp. 4 pls. $1.50.</item>
               <item n="36." rend="hang">
                  <persName>Harrold E. Gillingham</persName>. Notes on the Decorations and Medals of the French Colonies and Protectorates. 1928. 62 pp. 31 pls. $2.00.</item>
               <item n="37." rend="hang">
                  <persName>Oscar Ravel</persName>. The "Colts" of <placeName>Ambracia</placeName>. 1928. 180 pp. 19 pls. $3.00.</item>
               <item n="38." rend="hang">
                  <persName>Howland Wood</persName>. The Coinage of the Mexican Revolutionists. 1928. 53 pp. 15 pls. $2.50.</item>
               <item n="39." rend="hang">
                  <persName>Edward T. Newell</persName>. <persName>Alexander Hoards—IV</persName>. Olympia. 1929. 31 pp. 9 pls. $1.50.</item>
               <item n="40." rend="hang">
                  <persName>Allen B. West</persName>. Fifth and Fourth Century Gold Coins from the Thracian Coast. 1929. 183 pp. 16 pls. $3.00.</item>
               <item n="41." rend="hang">
                  <persName>Gilbert S. Perez</persName>. The Leper Colony Currency of Culion. 1929. 10 pp. 3 pls. 50c.</item>
               <item n="42." rend="hang">
                  <persName>Alfred R. Bellinger</persName>. Two Hoards of Attic Bronze Coins. 1930. 14 pp. 4 pls. 50c.</item>
               <pb/>
               <item n="43." rend="hang">
                  <persName>D. H. Cox</persName>. The Caparelli Hoard. 1930. 14 pp. 2 pls. 50c.</item>
               <item n="44." rend="hang">
                  <persName>Geo. F. Hill</persName>. On the Coins of Narbonensis with Iberian Inscriptions. 1930. 39 pp. 6 pls. $1.00.</item>
               <item n="45." rend="hang">
                  <persName>Bauman L. Belden</persName>. <placeName>A Mint</placeName> in <placeName>New York</placeName>. 1930. 40 pp. 4 pls. 50c.</item>
               <item n="46." rend="hang">
                  <persName>Edward T. Newell</persName>. The Küchük Köhne Hoard. 1931. 33 pp. 4 pls. $1.00.</item>
               <item n="47." rend="hang">
                  <persName>Sydney P. Noe</persName>. The Coinage of Metapontum. Part II. 1931. 134 pp. 43 pls. $3.00.</item>
               <item n="48." rend="hang">
                  <persName>D. W. Valentine</persName>. <placeName>The United States</placeName> Half Dimes. 1931. 79 pp. 47 pls. $5.00.</item>
               <item n="49." rend="hang">
                  <persName>Alfred R. Bellinger</persName>. Two Roman Hoards from Dura-Europos. 1931. 66 pp. 17 pls. $1.50.</item>
               <item n="50." rend="hang">
                  <persName>Geo. F. Hill</persName>. Notes on the Ancient Coinage of Hispania Citerior. 1931. 196 pp. 36 double pls. $4.00.</item>
               <item n="51." rend="hang">
                  <persName>Alan W. Hazelton</persName>. The Russian Imperial Orders. 1932. 102 pp. 20 pls. $3.00</item>
               <item n="52." rend="hang">
                  <persName>O. Ravel</persName>. Corinthian Hoards (Corinth and Arta). 1932. 27 pp. 4 pls. $1.00.</item>
               <item n="53." rend="hang">
                  <persName>Jean B. Cammann</persName>. The Symbols on Staters of Corinthian Type (A Catalogue). 1932. 130 pp. 14 double pls. $3.00.</item>
               <item n="54." rend="hang">
                  <persName>Shirley H. Weber</persName>. An Egyptian Hoard of the Second Century A. D. 41 pp. 5 pls. 1932. $1.50.</item>
               <item n="55." rend="hang">
                  <persName>Alfred R. Bellinger</persName>. The Third and Fourth Dura Hoards. 1932. 85 pp. 20 pls. $1.50.</item>
               <item n="56." rend="hang">
                  <persName>Harrold E. Gillingham</persName>. South American Decorations and War Medals. 1932. 178 pp. 35 pls. $3.00.</item>
               <item n="57." rend="hang">
                  <persName>Wm. Campbell</persName>. Greek and Roman Plated Coins. 1933. 226 pp. 190 + pls. $3.50.</item>
               <item n="58." rend="hang">
                  <persName>E. T. Newell</persName>. The Fifth Dura Hoard. 1933. 14 pp. 2 pls. $1.00.</item>
               <item n="59." rend="hang">
                  <persName>D. H. Cox</persName>. The Tripolis Hoard. 1933. 61 pp. 8 pls. 2 maps. $1.50.</item>
               <item n="60." rend="hang">
                  <persName>E. T. Newell</persName>. Two Hoards from Minturno. 1933. 38 pp. 5 pls. $1.00.</item>
               <item n="61." rend="hang">
                  <persName>Howland Wood</persName>. The Gampola Larin Hoard. 1934. 84 pp. 10 double pls. $3.00.</item>
               <item n="62." rend="hang">
                  <persName>J. G. Milne</persName>. The Melos Hoard of 1907. 1934. 19 pp. 1 pl. $1.00.</item>
               <item n="63." rend="hang">
                  <persName>A. F. Pradeau</persName>. The <placeName>Mexican Mints</placeName> of <placeName>Alamos</placeName> and <placeName>Hermosillo</placeName>. 1934. 73 pp. illus. $1.50.</item>
               <item n="64." rend="hang">
                  <persName>E. T. Newell</persName>. A Hoard from <placeName>Siphnos</placeName>. 1934. 17 pp. illus. 50c.</item>
               <item n="65." rend="hang">
                  <persName>C. H. V. Sutherland</persName>. Romano-British Imitations of Bronze Coins of Claudius I. 1935. 35 pp. 8 double pls. $2.00</item>
               <item n="66." rend="hang">
                  <persName>Harrold E. Gillingham</persName>. Ephemeral Decorations. 1935. 40 pp. 11 pls. $2.00.</item>
               <item n="67." rend="hang">
                  <persName>Sawyer McA. Mosser</persName>. A Bibliography of Byzantine Coin Hoards. 1935. 116 pp. $1.50.</item>
               <item n="68." rend="hang">
                  <persName>Edward T. Newell</persName>. Five Greek Bronze Coin Hoards. 1935. 67 pp. 9 double pls. $2.00.</item>
               <item n="69." rend="hang">
                  <persName>Alfred R. Bellinger</persName>. The Sixth, Seventh and Tenth Dura Hoards. 1935. 75 pp. 5 pls. $1.00.</item>
               <item n="70." rend="hang">
                  <persName>Frederick O. Waage</persName>. Greek Bronze Coins from a Well at Megara. 1935. 42 pp. 3 pls. $1.00.</item>
               <item n="71." rend="hang">
                  <persName>Sydney P. Noe</persName>. The Thurian Di-Staters. 1935. 68 pp. 11 double pls. $2.00.</item>
               <item n="72." rend="hang">
                  <persName>John Walker</persName>. The Coinage of the Second Saffarid Dynasty in Sistan. 1936. 46 pp. 4 double pls. $1.00.</item>
               <item n="73." rend="hang">
                  <persName>Edward T. Newell</persName>. The Seleucid Coinage of Tyre. 1936. 34 pp. 5 pls. $1.00.</item>
               <item n="74." rend="hang">
                  <persName>Margaret Crosby</persName> and <persName>Emily Grace</persName>. An <placeName>Achaean League</placeName> Hoard. 1936. 44 pp. 4 pls. $1.50.</item>
            </list>
         </div1>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>