<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
     xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/xsd/tei_all.xsd"
     xml:id="nnan141106">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Cretan coin hoard</title>
            <author>
               <name>Seager, Richard B.</name>
               <idno type="URI">http://viaf.org/viaf/22211663</idno>
            </author>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>TEI P5 XML markup in conformance with the TEI DTD</resp>
               <name>AEL Data</name>
            </respStmt>
            <funder>The Andrew W. Mellon Foundation</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>
               <name>American Numismatic Society</name>
               <idno type="URI">http://numismatics.org/authority/american_numismatic_society</idno>
            </publisher>
            <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
            <date>1924</date>
            <availability>
               <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">This work is made available under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International license</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Numismatic Notes and Monographs</title>
            <biblScope unit="issue">23</biblScope>
            <idno type="URI">http://numismatics.org/library/195778</idno>
         </seriesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <title>Donum</title>
               <idno type="URI">http://numismatics.org/library/141106</idno>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <title>Worldcat</title>
               <idno type="URI">http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/441183004</idno>
            </bibl>
            <bibl>
               <title>Worldcat Works</title>
               <idno type="URI">http://worldcat.org/entity/work/id/21819156</idno>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://nomisma.org/">
               <term ref="http://nomisma.org/id/greek_numismatics">Greek Numismatics</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
         <particDesc>
            <listPerson>
               <person xml:id="nomisma_kis_perinthus">
                  <persName>Kis(sos?)</persName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/kis_perinthus</idno>
               </person>
               <person xml:id="nomisma_l_vol_l_f_strab_rrc">
                  <persName>L. Volumnius Strabo</persName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/l_vol_l_f_strab_rrc</idno>
               </person>
            </listPerson>
         </particDesc>
         <settingDesc>
            <listPlace>
               <place xml:id="nomisma_crete">
                  <placeName>Crete</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/crete</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="nomisma_athens">
                  <placeName>Athens</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/athens</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="nomisma_gortyna">
                  <placeName>Gortyn</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/gortyna</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="nomisma_cydonia">
                  <placeName>Cydonia </placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/cydonia</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="nomisma_tanus">
                  <placeName>Tanus</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/tanus</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="nomisma_itanus">
                  <placeName>Itanus</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/itanus</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="nomisma_aegina_aegina">
                  <placeName>Aegina</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/aegina_aegina</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="nomisma_argos_argolis">
                  <placeName>Argos</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/argos_argolis</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="nomisma_chalcis">
                  <placeName>Chalcis</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/chalcis</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="nomisma_corinth">
                  <placeName>Corinth</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/corinth</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="nomisma_histiaea">
                  <placeName>Histiaea</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/histiaea</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="nomisma_macedon">
                  <placeName>Macedon</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/macedon</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="nomisma_sicyon">
                  <placeName>Sicyon</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/sicyon</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="nomisma_rhodes">
                  <placeName>Rhodes</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/rhodes</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="nomisma_elyrus">
                  <placeName>Elyrus</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/elyrus</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="nomisma_hyrtacina">
                  <placeName>Hyrtacina</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/hyrtacina</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="nomisma_lisus">
                  <placeName>Lisus</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/lisus</idno>
               </place>
               <place xml:id="nomisma_polyrhenium">
                  <placeName>Polyrhenium</placeName>
                  <idno type="URI">http://nomisma.org/id/polyrhenium</idno>
               </place>
            </listPlace>
         </settingDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2018-04-02">Ran TEI file through XSLT process, detailed in the Mellon EBook migration Google Document.</change>
         <change when="2018-04-02">Included normalized entity labels and URIs from
				previous OpenRefine process.</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <div1 xml:id="d269e30" type="cover">
            <pb/>
            <figure xml:id="fig-001">
               <graphic url="NNM23_001.jpg"/>
            </figure>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d269e34" type="frontma">
            <pb/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="bold">PUBLICATIONS</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi rend="bold">The American Journal of Numismatics, 1866-1920.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Monthly, May, 1866—April, 1870.</p>
            <p>Quarterly, July, 1870—October, 1912.</p>
            <p>Annually, 1913-1920.</p>
            <p rend="hang">With many plates, illustrations, maps and tables. Less than a dozen complete sets of the Journal remain on hand. Prices on application. Those wishing to fill broken sets can secure most of the needed volumes separately. An index to the first 50 volumes has been issued as part of Volume 51. It may also be purchased as a reprint for $3.00.</p>
            <p rend="hang">The American Numismatic Society. Catalogue of the International Exhibition of Contemporary Medals. March, 1910. New and revised edition. New York. 1911. xxxvi, 412 pages, 512 illustrations. $10.00.</p>
            <p rend="hang">The American Numismatic Society. Exhibition of <placeName>United States</placeName> and Colonial Coins. 1914. vii, 134 pages, 40 plates. $1.00.</p>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d269e57" type="frontma">
            <pb/>
            <p>
               <hi rend="bold">NUMISMATIC</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="bold">NOTES AND MONOGRAPHS</hi>
            </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d269e65" type="dedication">
            <pb/>
            <p>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">Numismatic Notes and Monographs</hi> is devoted to essays and treatises on subjects relating to coins, paper money, medals and decorations, and is uniform with Hispanic Notes and Monographs published by the Hispanic Society of <placeName>America</placeName>, and with Indian Notes and Monographs issued by The Museum of the American Indian—Heye Foundation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">Publication Committee</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <persName>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">Agnes Baldwin Brett</hi>
               </persName>, <hi rend="italic">Chairman</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <persName>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">Henry Russell Drowne</hi>
               </persName>
            </p>
            <p>
               <persName>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">John Reilly</hi>, Jr.</persName>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">Editorial Staff</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <persName>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">Sydney Philip Noe</hi>
               </persName>, <hi rend="italic">Editor</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <persName>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">Howland Wood</hi>
               </persName>, <hi rend="italic">Associate Editor</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <persName>V. E. <hi rend="smallcaps">Earle</hi>
               </persName>, <hi rend="italic">Assistant</hi>
            </p>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d269e118" type="colophon">
            <pb/>
            <p>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">copyright, 1924, by</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">the american numismatic society</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">Press of The Lent &amp; Graff Co., <placeName>New York</placeName>
               </hi>
            </p>
         </div1>
         <titlePage>
            <pb/>
            <docTitle>
               <titlePart type="main">A CRETAN COIN HOARD</titlePart>
            </docTitle>
            <byline>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">by</hi> RICHARD B. SEAGER</byline>
            <figure xml:id="fig-002">
               <graphic url="NNM23_006.jpg"/>
            </figure>
            <docImprint>
               <publisher>THE AMERICAN NUMISMATIC SOCIETY</publisher>
               <pubPlace>BROADWAY AT 156TH STREET</pubPlace>
               <pubPlace>NEW YORK</pubPlace>
               <date>1924</date>
            </docImprint>
         </titlePage>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div1 xml:id="d269e152" type="chapter">
            <pb n="1"/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="bold">A CRETAN COIN HOARD</hi>
            </head>
            <byline>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">by richard B. seager</hi>
            </byline>
            <p>In the autumn of 1922, I have been given to understand, some boys playing on a mound of earth in the outskirts of <placeName>Canea</placeName>, the <placeName>Cretan</placeName> capital, came upon part of the hoard of small silver coins described in this article. Originally, they seem to have been contained in an earthenware jar or pot which in the course of centuries had been broken, allowing the contents to become somewhat scattered. The fragments of the pot were not preserved, and I was unable to get any definite information either as to its size or shape. This is unfortunate as it might have assisted in more nearly fixing the date of burial of the hoard.</p>
            <p>On my arrival in <placeName corresp="#nomisma_crete">Crete</placeName>, I was able to buy about 700 of these coins; and three months later, 303 others, making in all, 1003 pieces. Evidently after the discovery of the first lot, people began digging operations in the vicinity, and gradually unearthed more and
<pb n="2"/>
more specimens, showing that at some previous period the original deposit had been much disturbed. The coins themselves fell into the hands of numerous owners—apparently, all the men at work had a share in the spoil, and it took some months of negotiation to get together the 1003 coins on which the following catalogue is based. Before my arrival in Crete, some had already found their way into the hands of local dealers and were thus dispersed, but I am inclined to think that these were not many in number and that I secured the bulk of the hoard as first found, except for about 80 pieces which were acquired by the Government in <placeName corresp="#nomisma_athens">Athens</placeName>.</p>
            <p>In <placeName corresp="#nomisma_crete">Crete</placeName>, coin hoards are not of common occurrence. In twenty years of collecting in the island, this is the first of any size of which I have heard, with the exception of one found a few years ago on the site of <placeName corresp="#nomisma_gortyna">Gortyna</placeName>. This <placeName corresp="#nomisma_gortyna">Gortyna</placeName> find was hurriedly dispersed, barring a few pieces which were seized by the Government, and it has been impossible to learn very much about it.</p>
            <p>The chief interest of the present hoard
<pb n="3"/>
consists in the fact that it presents a great number of dies of a hitherto obscure <placeName>Cretan</placeName> mint, of which only a few examples were known, and also increases our knowledge of the lesser silver coinage of <placeName corresp="#nomisma_cydonia">Cydonia</placeName> and <placeName corresp="#nomisma_tanus">Tanos</placeName>, and their close relation to one another. It is also curious in that it contains coins of only three known <placeName>Cretan</placeName> towns—<placeName corresp="#nomisma_cydonia">Cydonia</placeName>, <placeName corresp="#nomisma_tanus">Tanos</placeName>, and <placeName corresp="#nomisma_itanus">Itanos</placeName>, whereas non-Cretan places, such as <placeName corresp="#nomisma_aegina_aegina">Aegina</placeName>, <placeName corresp="#nomisma_argos_argolis">Argos</placeName>, <placeName corresp="#nomisma_chalcis">Chalcis</placeName>, <placeName corresp="#nomisma_corinth">Corinth</placeName>, <placeName corresp="#nomisma_histiaea">Histiaea</placeName>, and <placeName corresp="#nomisma_macedon">Macedon</placeName> are all represented, together with a <orgName type="ethnic">Rhodian</orgName> didrachm—the only coin of this weight in the entire hoard. Nearly all the coins are hemidrachms or still lighter denominations. The only drachms were one of <placeName corresp="#nomisma_itanus">Itanos</placeName>, to which reference will be made later, one of <placeName corresp="#nomisma_chalcis">Chalcis</placeName> and two of <placeName corresp="#nomisma_corinth">Corinth</placeName>.</p>
            <p>From the fact that they were found on the site of the ancient <placeName corresp="#nomisma_cydonia">Cydonia</placeName>, it seems probable that the coins with the <placeName>Aeginetic</placeName> reverse (Plates I—V), which comprise 586 of the 1003 pieces in my possession, belong to that mint. There is some evidence for this as will be seen, and one naturally expects the bulk of the coins in a hoard to
<pb n="4"/>
belong to the mint of the district in which they were buried, unless they happened to have been the property of some foreign refugee.</p>
            <p>We also find in the hoard 200 trihemiobols of <placeName>Aeginetic</placeName> weight, with a seated hound on the reverse (Pl. V), all restruck on <orgName type="ethnic">Rhodian</orgName> hemidrachms. These, as we know from the legend, certainly belong to <placeName corresp="#nomisma_cydonia">Cydonia</placeName> as do certain of the obols (Plates VI, VII), so that if we assign the 586 pieces with the <placeName>Aeginetic</placeName> reverse to the same mint, we have roughly 800 coins belonging to <placeName corresp="#nomisma_cydonia">Cydonia</placeName> out of the total of 1003. I say "roughly," as only 14 of the 67 obols have been given to <placeName corresp="#nomisma_cydonia">Cydonia</placeName> whereas the number may really be greater, as will be seen when that series is dealt with in the catalogue.</p>
            <p>The pieces with the <placeName>Aeginetic</placeName> reverse may possibly belong to <placeName corresp="#nomisma_tanus">Tanos</placeName>, which, from the coins already known and the new types included in this hoard, was evidently so intimately connected with <placeName corresp="#nomisma_cydonia">Cydonia</placeName> that it actually used <placeName corresp="#nomisma_cydonia">Cydonia</placeName>n dies for its lighter denominations. We have practically no knowledge of <placeName corresp="#nomisma_tanus">Tanos</placeName> beyond that given by
<pb n="5"/>
               <persName>Svoronos</persName> in his <hi rend="italic">Numismatique de la Crète Ancienne,</hi> p. 318, where he places it in the immediate vicinity of <placeName corresp="#nomisma_cydonia">Cydonia</placeName>, and one hesitates to assign so large a series to a mint so little known and to which no coins can be definitely attributed except for a small series of obols. On the other hand the following evidence supports the claims of <placeName corresp="#nomisma_cydonia">Cydonia</placeName> to these coins. <persName>Svoronos</persName>, <hi rend="italic">op. cit.,</hi> pp. 326–327, attributes a small bronze with a reverse of very much this type to one of two otherwise unknown towns, <placeName>Thenae</placeName> or <placeName>Therapnae</placeName>, in <placeName corresp="#nomisma_crete">Crete</placeName>. The reverse of this coin is identical with the hoard series except that it lacks the small cross-bar dividing one of the four compartments. <persName>Svoronos</persName> considers this reverse <graphic url="NNM23-011.jpg"/> to represent a Greek Theta and, therefore, assigns it to one of the few <placeName>Cretan</placeName> towns the name of which begins with TH. He published an excellent example of this same coin in <hi rend="italic">Ephemeris Archaiologike,</hi> 1889, Pl. 13, No. 14, where it will be seen how very similar it is to the hoard coins. A variety of this coin among the uncertain bronze of the British Museum (<ref target="#fig-003">Fig. 1</ref>) appears to me to show the letters
<pb n="6"/>
K Y Δ disposed outside the pattern of the reverse. <graphic url="NNM23-012.jpg"/> If my reading is correct, (<persName>Mr. E. S. G. Robinson</persName> of the British Museum agrees with me,) this would tend to assign all the bronze and silver of this general type to the <placeName corresp="#nomisma_cydonia">Cydonia</placeName>n mint. We have the analogy of the obols of <placeName corresp="#nomisma_tanus">Tanos</placeName> for this curious triangular manner of placing the first three letters of the place-name. (See Plates VI, VII, O: 53 and Q: 53.)</p>
            <p>The attribution of this series to <placeName corresp="#nomisma_cydonia">Cydonia</placeName> is further strengthened by the coin shown in <ref target="#fig-004">Fig. 2</ref>, which I have called Type A. This coin, which had been in my possession for some time before the discovery of the hoard, makes it fairly clear that this series with the <placeName>Aeginetic</placeName> reverse must belong to either <placeName corresp="#nomisma_cydonia">Cydonia</placeName> or <placeName corresp="#nomisma_tanus">Tanos</placeName>, but preferably the former, as the head on the obverse is almost identical with one which occurs on certain known types of <placeName corresp="#nomisma_cydonia">Cydonia</placeName>n obols, drachms and staters. (<persName>Svoronos</persName>, <hi rend="italic">Num. de la Crète</hi>, Pl. IX, Nos. 15, 16, 23, 28.)</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="bold">Type A.</hi> Vine-crowned head of a nymph to 1., flowing hair, border of dots. Restruck on an earlier flan.</p>
            <pb/>
            <figure xml:id="fig-003">
               <graphic url="NNM23-013a.jpg"/>
               <head>Fig. 1</head>
            </figure>
            <figure xml:id="fig-004">
               <graphic url="NNM23-013b.jpg"/>
               <head>Fig. 2</head>
            </figure>
            <figure xml:id="fig-005">
               <graphic url="NNM23-013c.jpg"/>
               <head>Fig. 3</head>
            </figure>
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>
               <graphic url="NNM23-014.jpg"/> Incuse square, divided by broad bands into five compartments.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .60, wt. 2.19 grm.</p>
            <p>The weight 2.19 grm. is perplexing as it is a good deal heavier than the hoard series of this type. It may be meant for a light weight <placeName>Aeginetic</placeName> hemidrachm, and the extensive cleaning to which it has been subjected may partially account for its apparent underweight. From its style, it must be earlier in date than any of the hoard series with this <placeName>Aeginetic</placeName> type of reverse, with the possible exception of Type B on Plate I.</p>
            <p>Belonging to the same series is the coin shown in <ref target="#fig-005">Fig. 3</ref>.</p>
            <p>The obverse die seems to be identical with that of <ref target="#fig-004">Fig. 2</ref>.</p>
            <p>
               <graphic url="NNM23-014.jpg"/> Incuse square, divided by narrow bands into five compartments. In lower right hand compartment, two dots (acorn?). Overstruck on an earlier flan. This coin is in the Berlin Cabinet and <persName>Dr. Kurt Regling</persName>, to whose kindness I owe the cast, tells me that it has hitherto been assigned to <placeName corresp="#nomisma_aegina_aegina">Aegina</placeName> following Mionnet's publication of it (Mion-
<pb n="8"/>
net, III, 599, 43, Pl. xviii, 6). The reverse is almost identical with that of certain coins of <placeName corresp="#nomisma_aegina_aegina">Aegina</placeName>, B. M. Cat. <hi rend="italic">Attica</hi>, Pl. xxiv, 13, where what here looks like two dots in one of the compartments, appears to be an acorn. <persName>Dr. Regling</persName> also tells me he has seen a similar coin in the Cabinet of <persName>Mr. Empedocles</persName> in <placeName corresp="#nomisma_athens">Athens</placeName> which is overstruck on a coin of <placeName corresp="#nomisma_sicyon">Sicyon</placeName>, and which by its style appears to him to be a good deal earlier than the <placeName>Berlin</placeName> example.</p>
            <p>Traditionally, <placeName corresp="#nomisma_aegina_aegina">Aegina</placeName> figures as one of the original founders of <placeName corresp="#nomisma_cydonia">Cydonia</placeName> (<persName corresp="#nomisma_kis_perinthus">Babelon</persName>, <hi rend="italic">Traité</hi>, Vol. Ill, p. 1024, and <persName corresp="#nomisma_l_vol_l_f_strab_rrc">Strabo</persName>, VIII, 6,16), and may have maintained an influence on affairs even during the historical period. But our knowledge of the history of <placeName>Cretan</placeName> towns in general is very scanty and aside from an endless series of petty quarrels with each other we have little real information about them. Quite recently, however, a certain amount of evidence has come to light which tends to show that <placeName corresp="#nomisma_aegina_aegina">Aegina</placeName> exercised some obscure commercial influence on the town of <placeName corresp="#nomisma_cydonia">Cydonia</placeName>. There is a possibility, first suggested by <persName>Prof. J. L. Myres</persName>, of
<pb n="9"/>
Oxford, that some of her turtle money may have been actually struck at <placeName corresp="#nomisma_cydonia">Cydonia</placeName>. <persName>Mr. E. S. G. Robinson</persName> is trying to collect some direct proof of a turtle mint in <placeName corresp="#nomisma_crete">Crete</placeName>, but the evidence is still insufficient for any definite statement. If this theory should prove to be correct, it would help to explain the appearance of the <placeName>Aeginetic</placeName> reverse on the large series of these coins in the present hoard.</p>
            <p>The question of the date of the hoard is greatly assisted by the presence of the seven tetrobols of <placeName corresp="#nomisma_macedon">Macedon</placeName> which were issued between 185–168 B.C. (Head, <hi rend="italic">Hist. Num.,</hi> p. 234) and of the 129 tetrobols of <placeName corresp="#nomisma_histiaea">Histiaea</placeName> which are assigned to 197–146 B.C. or even later. <hi rend="italic">(Hist. Num.,</hi> p. 364.) The probabilities are that the hoard was buried about 150 B.C., at a conservative guess, perhaps during one of the internecine wars which so constantly ravaged this island. These datable pieces of <placeName corresp="#nomisma_macedon">Macedon</placeName> and <placeName corresp="#nomisma_histiaea">Histiaea</placeName> raise interesting questions as to the dating of some of the other coins included in the hoard. The series of trihemiobols belonging to <placeName corresp="#nomisma_cydonia">Cydonia</placeName>, with a youthful male horned head
<pb n="10"/>
on the obverse and a seated hound on the reverse nearly all seem to be struck on hemidrachms of <placeName corresp="#nomisma_rhodes">Rhodes</placeName> of the type with the facing head of Helios. These <placeName corresp="#nomisma_cydonia">Cydonia</placeName>n coins, judging by their condition, must have been nearly fresh from the mint at the time of the burial of the hoard. Few of them show signs of wear and many of them are in nearly mint state. According to <hi rend="italic">Hist. Num.,</hi> p. 464, these pieces were struck between 400–300 B.C. and <persName corresp="#nomisma_kis_perinthus">Babelon</persName>, Vol. Ill, pp. 1030–31, No. 1758, places them between 360–300 B.C. Both these dates appear manifestly impossible viewed from the evidence of the hoard. The original issue of <orgName type="ethnic">Rhodian</orgName> hemidrachms on which they are restruck is placed in B. M. Cat. <hi rend="italic">Caria</hi>, pp. 240–247, at 304–166 B.C., and it is unlikely that they were restruck directly after their first issue. Secondly, the condition of the coins themselves proves that they cannot have been long in circulation when the hoard was buried. This cannot have taken place, at the earliest, before 185 B.C., as shown by the tetrobols of <placeName corresp="#nomisma_macedon">Macedon</placeName>, and was more probably nearer 150 than 185 B.C. In
<pb n="11"/>
166 B.C., a reorganization of the coinage took place in Rhodes, and new types of drachms and hemidrachms appeared showing the rose on the reverse in a shallow incuse square, to distinguish them from the preceding issue which had become shockingly debased in weight. <hi rend="italic">(Hist. Num.,</hi> p. 640). This new issue was an effort to rehabilitate the <orgName type="ethnic">Rhodian</orgName> mint by striking a series of coins of better weight to replace the preceding light weight types which were probably no longer accepted at their face value. It may be that the <orgName type="ethnic">Cydonian</orgName> treasury found itself overstocked with hemidrachms of the old type and, the new <orgName type="ethnic">Rhodian</orgName> series tending still further to discredit them, decided to restrike the whole lot as trihemiobols of <placeName>Aeginetic</placeName> weight.</p>
            <p>The whole question of weights of the <placeName>Cretan</placeName> pieces in this hoard is a puzzling one, and it would appear that all the <orgName type="ethnic">Cydonian</orgName> coins which it contains were intended to pass under both the <orgName type="ethnic">Rhodian</orgName> and the <placeName>Aeginetic</placeName> standards though under different denominations. These so-called trihemiobols, as has been shown, are really <orgName type="ethnic">Rhodian</orgName> hemi-
<pb n="12"/>
drachms. According to <persName>Macdonald</persName>, <hi rend="italic">(The Silver Coinage of <placeName corresp="#nomisma_crete">Crete</placeName>
               </hi>, British Academy Papers, Vol IX, 1919, p. 18), the <orgName type="ethnic">Rhodian</orgName> system was used together with the <placeName>Aeginetic</placeName> and debased <placeName>Aeginetic</placeName> at <placeName corresp="#nomisma_cydonia">Cydonia</placeName>. Therefore one would have expected these small coins to have passed in <placeName corresp="#nomisma_crete">Crete</placeName> at their face value as hemidrachms of <orgName type="ethnic">Rhodian</orgName> weight, but this apparently was not the case. At this time the issues actually struck at <placeName corresp="#nomisma_rhodes">Rhodes</placeName> had so lost in weight that the <orgName type="ethnic">Rhodian</orgName> drachm was treated in <placeName corresp="#nomisma_crete">Crete</placeName> as an <placeName>Aeginetic</placeName> hemidrachm (<persName>Macdonald</persName>, p. 16). The Rhodian-struck hemidrachm apparently shared the same fate, and to solve the difficulty was valued and, as we have seen, restruck as an <placeName>Aeginetic</placeName> trihemiobol.</p>
            <p>Another problem is presented by the large series of coins with the <placeName>Aeginetic</placeName> reverse. These range in weight from 1.36 to 1.94 grammes, but with an average weight of between 1.60 and 1.70 grammes. Of the 71 specimens belonging to the hoard described below, 11 are under 1.50 grms., 16 range from 1.50 to 1.60 grms., 29 from 1.60 to 1.70 grms., 13 from 1.70 to 1.80 grms.,
<pb n="13"/>
and only 2 examples are 1.80 grms., or over, the heaviest example being 1.86 grms. Five of those below 1.50 grms. were in bad condition or much cleaned, so that the normal low weight for these coins would not be less than 1.50 grms. They seem, as a whole, too light for <orgName type="ethnic">Rhodian</orgName> drachms, as in <placeName corresp="#nomisma_crete">Crete</placeName> it is the exception to find a drachm of this norm under at least two grammes, and most of them range from 3 to 3.50 grms.— the <placeName>Cretan</placeName> series of <orgName type="ethnic">Rhodian</orgName> weight being more nearly up to standard than the later issues of <placeName corresp="#nomisma_rhodes">Rhodes</placeName> itself (<persName>Macdonald</persName>, pp. 16–17). These coins are a good deal heavier than the series of restruck <orgName type="ethnic">Rhodian</orgName> hemidrachms discussed above, where the average weight seems to be between 1.20 and 1.30 grms., with a tendency to rise higher rather than lower, but they would be about right for Cretan-struck hemidrachms of <orgName type="ethnic">Rhodian</orgName> weight where the drachm usually ranges from 3 grms. to 3.50 grms., which would give a hemidrachm of 1.50 to 1.75 grms.; or, in other words, just what we find in the hoard series. When one tries to fit them into the <placeName>Aeginetic</placeName> standard as found in
<pb n="14"/>
               <placeName corresp="#nomisma_crete">Crete</placeName> they can only be diobols, a denomination that, so far, has not been recognized in any of the <placeName>Cretan</placeName> mints. In the entire <placeName>Cretan</placeName> series, only at Polyrhenium do we find a somewhat similar weight. There the coins with the facing bust of Dictynna on the obverse and the standing Apollo on the reverse, seem to approximate the hoard pieces with weights ranging from 1.62 to 2.11 grammes, with an average of 1.80. <persName>Macdonald</persName> (p. 22) speaks of them as <orgName type="ethnic">Rhodian</orgName> hemidrachms and Head, <hi rend="italic">(Hist. Num</hi>., p. 475), as hemidrachms of Attic weight. The use of the latter standard in <placeName corresp="#nomisma_crete">Crete</placeName> seems to have been very limited, and we find almost no traces of it aside from the series of tetradrachms of Attic weight, which may have been the result of some political or commercial grouping of certain <placeName>Cretan</placeName> towns. Accepting, therefore, these coins with the <placeName>Aeginetic</placeName> reverse as <orgName type="ethnic">Rhodian</orgName> hemidrachms, we find that they would also be right for <placeName>Aeginetic</placeName> diobols if, as <persName>Macdonald</persName> says (p. n), the norm for <placeName>Aeginetic</placeName> hemidrachms in <placeName corresp="#nomisma_crete">Crete</placeName> is about 2.55 grammes. This would give an obol of .85 and a diobol
<pb n="15"/>
of 1.70 grms., which is just what we find in the hoard coins, and not far out for the series of Polyrhenium.<ref target="#CH1-n1">
                  <hi rend="sup">1</hi>
               </ref>
            </p>
            <p>From the reverses of the hoard coins, one would naturally have supposed that they would bear some relation to the <placeName>Aeginetic</placeName> system, but one would have hardly expected them to turn out to be diobols, a denomination which seems not to occur in the mint of <placeName corresp="#nomisma_aegina_aegina">Aegina</placeName> itself or anywhere in <placeName corresp="#nomisma_crete">Crete</placeName>, if we except the coins of Polyrhenium just mentioned. If they are really meant to be <placeName>Aeginetic</placeName> diobols, they were probably issued to fulfil some commercial need for which the overstruck <orgName type="ethnic">Rhodian</orgName> hemidrachms and other small denominations of <placeName corresp="#nomisma_cydonia">Cydonia</placeName> were considered unacceptable. The probable solution of the whole question is, that given the equal use of the two standards by the <orgName type="ethnic">Cydonian</orgName> treasury, a coin which could pass in both systems as a definite though different unit of weight was very acceptable, and that the coins with the <placeName>Aeginetic</placeName> reverse could
<pb n="16"/>
be either <placeName>Aeginetic</placeName> diobols or <orgName type="ethnic">Rhodian</orgName> hemi-drachms, as best suited the needs of the moment.</p>
            <p>Of the two <placeName>Aeginetan</placeName> coins in the hoard, one triobol is in excellent state, Pl. VIII, 65, and shows few signs of having been in circulation for a long course of years as one would suppose must have been the case. This type, according to B. M. Cat. <hi rend="italic">Attica</hi>, p. 139, No. 172, must have been issued before 431 B.C., and that it should still be in circulation by the middle of the second century B.C. without showing more signs of wear, seems incredible. This dating of these pieces with a crescent in one of the compartments of the incuse must be left open to question.</p>
            <p>The two <orgName type="ethnic">Corinthian</orgName> drachms, Pl. IX, 71, must have been in circulation for a long time, as one belongs to the issue of 350–338 B.C. This coin, however, shows considerable signs of wear. The second piece (issue of 300–243, B.C.) was in very bad state, with a large piece broken out of the side, and is not illustrated.</p>
            <p>There were 67 obols of <placeName corresp="#nomisma_cydonia">Cydonia</placeName> and
<pb n="17"/>
Tanos included in the hoard. Most of these show many signs of wear, especially the types M N, O and P shown on Pl. VI. Types Q, R, S and T, on the other hand, were in fresher state and may have been the issues in circulation at the time of the burial of the hoard, especially R: 56, of which there were 13 examples out of the 67 pieces. The heads on the obverse of types N, P, Q and T seem to be new; at any rate, I have been unable to trace any published examples of them.</p>
            <p>The question of sequence for the types with the <placeName>Aeginetic</placeName> reverse is not easy to decide, and my arrangement is an arbitrary one. In some cases the reverse of one series running over into another with a different obverse die, has served to indicate the order of sequence; but from the condition of the coins, the different issues must have succeeded one another fairly quickly and, except for type B, none of them had been long in circulation when the hoard was buried. The series with the obverse shown in Plates III to V, Types H and Ha, was the most abundant, numbering about 180 out of the
<pb n="18"/>
total of 554 pieces, which were sufficiently well preserved for purposes of identification. This type, with its crude copy, I (Pl. IV), and, perhaps, J (Pl. V), were doubtless the dies in use at the time the hoard was hidden.</p>
            <p>The obverse die, as is usually the case, outlasted the reverse, and one finds the same obverse used with a series of different reverses and can note its gradual deterioration until it becomes so nearly indistinguishable that it had to be replaced by a new die. (Pl. I, B and Ba, and series D.) Nine obverse dies occur among these pieces with the <placeName>Aeginetic</placeName> reverse. At first I took type Ba on Pl. I to be independent, but it appears to be the die of type B in the final stages of disintegration. The reverse dies number forty-two, which is surprising considering that these coins were practically unknown before the discovery of this hoard.</p>
            <p>The obverse types, as is usual in the <placeName>Cretan</placeName> series, show extremes of style—some of them being quite good and others very crude. In the series E, F and Fa, on Plates II, III, one sees the original die and
<pb n="19"/>
its coarser copy in two states. The large series H on Plate III has also its crude copy I. The same reverse in several states is shown on Pl. I, series B:1, B:1a, C:1b and Ba:1c, also C:2, Ba:2a, D:2b and D:2C. Another reverse in several states is shown on Pl. III, Fa:15 and 15a and G:15b. In the above examples, one can follow the changes in the dies, flaws appearing at the corners of the design and a gradual filling and obscuring of the entire surface.</p>
            <p>In one or two cases, the pieces with the <placeName>Aeginetic</placeName> reverse show slight traces of being restruck on an earlier flan, but in no case have I been able to make out the type of the original. Taking the series as a whole, cases of restriking are very rare in contrast to the trihemiobols where almost every coin shows traces of the older flan.</p>
            <p>The obols of <placeName corresp="#nomisma_cydonia">Cydonia</placeName> and <placeName corresp="#nomisma_tanus">Tanos</placeName>, shown on Plates VI and VII, are very perplexing and, except where they bear inscriptions, it is impossible to say to which mint they belong as the types for the two places are identical. Therefore, I have classed as uncertain several obols which have hitherto
<pb n="20"/>
been given to <placeName corresp="#nomisma_cydonia">Cydonia</placeName> and have assigned definitely only those bearing legends.</p>
            <p>The coins of the hoard were, as a whole, in bad condition, heavily coated with a brownish-grey corrosion, and in many cases the metal itself was so rotten and granulated that some literally fell to pieces in cleaning. Fortunately, there was a sufficient number of sound specimens among the mass to enable me to reproduce the series here illustrated.</p>
            <p>Of the coins foreign to <placeName corresp="#nomisma_crete">Crete</placeName>, I have thought it unnecessary to illustrate all the examples. This is particularly so in the case of the 129 tetrobols of <placeName corresp="#nomisma_histiaea">Histiaea</placeName>. I have chosen, therefore, specimens which, from either their condition or type, seem worthy of notice.</p>
            <p>In addition to the <placeName>Berlin</placeName> coin, <ref target="#fig-005">Fig. 3</ref>, and the one belonging to <persName>Mr. Empedocles</persName>, I have been able to trace but two others with reverses of this <placeName>Aeginetic</placeName> type</p>
            <p>The British Museum has a specimen of the coin shown on Pl. I, D: 2b, which apparently came from this same hoard as it was bought not long after its discovery, together with one of the <orgName type="ethnic">Cydonian</orgName> trihemiobols shown
<pb n="21"/>
on Pl. V, K. A coin similar to H: 24 of Pl. IV is in <persName>Mr. Edward T. Newell's</persName> Cabinet, and he tells me that he thinks it came originally from the Pozzi Collection.</p>
            <p>In the following catalogue the obverse types are indicated by capital letters, and where they pass through various states of deterioration these stages are further indicated by the addition of a small letter showing the state of the die. Thus C would be the obverse type in its first state, and Ca the die C showing the first signs of wear or deterioration.</p>
            <p>The reverse types are indicated by numerals, to which small letters are added for indicating the different states of the die. Thus taking the obverse types B, C and Ba, we find them associated with the reverse die 1, which passes through stages of deterioration indicated by ia, ib and ic, in the last of which the die has become almost entirely obliterated.</p>
            <p>The following list gives the number of examples of the varieties contained in the hoard.</p>
            <pb n="22"/>
            <table rows="33" cols="3">
               <row>
                  <cell>
                     <placeName corresp="#nomisma_cydonia">Cydonia</placeName>—Type</cell>
                  <cell>B</cell>
                  <cell>15</cell>
                  <cell>Examples</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Type</cell>
                  <cell>Ba</cell>
                  <cell>12</cell>
                  <cell>Examples</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Type</cell>
                  <cell>C</cell>
                  <cell>12</cell>
                  <cell>Examples</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Type</cell>
                  <cell>Ca</cell>
                  <cell>21</cell>
                  <cell>Examples</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Type</cell>
                  <cell>D</cell>
                  <cell>69</cell>
                  <cell>Examples</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Type</cell>
                  <cell>E</cell>
                  <cell>93</cell>
                  <cell>Examples</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Type</cell>
                  <cell>F</cell>
                  <cell>49</cell>
                  <cell>Examples</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Type</cell>
                  <cell>Fa</cell>
                  <cell>33</cell>
                  <cell>Examples</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Type</cell>
                  <cell>G</cell>
                  <cell>21</cell>
                  <cell>Examples</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Type</cell>
                  <cell>H &amp; Ha</cell>
                  <cell>180</cell>
                  <cell>Examples</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Type</cell>
                  <cell>I</cell>
                  <cell>37</cell>
                  <cell>Examples</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell>Type</cell>
                  <cell>J</cell>
                  <cell>12</cell>
                  <cell>Examples</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell cols="2">Uncertain, owing to state</cell>
                  <cell>32</cell>
                  <cell>Examples</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell cols="2">Total</cell>
                  <cell>586</cell>
                  <cell>Examples</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell cols="2">Types K &amp; L</cell>
                  <cell>188</cell>
                  <cell>Examples</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell cols="2">Uncertain owing to state</cell>
                  <cell>12</cell>
                  <cell>Examples</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell cols="2">Total</cell>
                  <cell>200</cell>
                  <cell>Examples</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell cols="4">
                     <placeName corresp="#nomisma_cydonia">Cydonia</placeName> &amp; <placeName corresp="#nomisma_tanus">Tanos</placeName> Obols.</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell cols="2">
                     <placeName corresp="#nomisma_cydonia">Cydonia</placeName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>14</cell>
                  <cell>Examples</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell cols="2">
                     <placeName corresp="#nomisma_tanus">Tanos</placeName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>11</cell>
                  <cell>Examples</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell cols="2">Uncertain</cell>
                  <cell>42</cell>
                  <cell>Examples</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell cols="2">Total</cell>
                  <cell>67</cell>
                  <cell>Examples</cell>
               </row>
               <pb n="23"/>
               <row>
                  <cell cols="2">
                     <placeName corresp="#nomisma_itanus">Itanos</placeName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>2</cell>
                  <cell>Examples</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell cols="2">Uncertain (Orion?)</cell>
                  <cell>1</cell>
                  <cell>Examples</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell cols="3">
                     <hi rend="italic">Non-Cretan Coins</hi>
                  </cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell cols="2">
                     <placeName corresp="#nomisma_aegina_aegina">Aegina</placeName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>2</cell>
                  <cell>Examples</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell cols="2">
                     <placeName corresp="#nomisma_argos_argolis">Argos</placeName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>5</cell>
                  <cell>Examples</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell cols="2">
                     <placeName corresp="#nomisma_chalcis">Chalcis</placeName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>1</cell>
                  <cell>Examples</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell cols="2">
                     <placeName corresp="#nomisma_corinth">Corinth</placeName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>2</cell>
                  <cell>Examples</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell cols="2">
                     <placeName corresp="#nomisma_histiaea">Histiaea</placeName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>129</cell>
                  <cell>Examples</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell cols="2">
                     <placeName corresp="#nomisma_macedon">Macedon</placeName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>7</cell>
                  <cell>Examples</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell cols="2">
                     <placeName corresp="#nomisma_rhodes">Rhodes</placeName>
                  </cell>
                  <cell>1</cell>
                  <cell>Examples</cell>
               </row>
               <row>
                  <cell cols="2">Total</cell>
                  <cell>147</cell>
                  <cell>Examples</cell>
               </row>
            </table>
            <div2 xml:id="d269e1154" type="section">
               <head>CYDONIA <hi rend="smallcaps">Plate</hi> I</head>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="bold">Type B:1.</hi> Youthful head (Apollo?) to r., wearing wreath.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-030.jpg"/> Incuse square divided by broad bands into five compartments.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .53, wt. 1.68 grm. 7 Examples.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-030.jpg"/>
                  <hi rend="bold">1a</hi>. Same die as above showing gradual filling up of the surface.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .58, wt. 1.74 grm. 8 Examples.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="bold">Type C:1b.</hi> Wreathed head (Apollo?) to r.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-030.jpg"/>. Same die as above showing still more marked deterioration.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .50, wt. 1.68 grm. 7 Examples.</p>
               <pb n="24"/>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-031.jpg"/>. <hi rend="bold">2</hi>. Similar to foregoing—the incuse seems now to disappear, though the square remains in varying forms throughout the entire series.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .52, wt. 1.65 grm. 5 Examples</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="bold">Type Ba:1c.</hi> Wreathed head to r., very rough die.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-031.jpg"/>. Same die as B:i, but with the design nearly obliterated.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .50, wt. 1.55 grm. 1 Example.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-031.jpg"/>. <hi rend="bold">2a..</hi> Same die as C:2.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .51, wt. 1.62 grm. 11 Examples.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="bold">Type D:2b.</hi> Head of Apollo or nymph to 1., hair rolled, with long locks hanging down at back of the neck.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-031.jpg"/>. Apparently the same die as C:2 and Ba:2a, but somewhat blurred through use.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .55, wt. 1.74 grm. 27 Examples.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-031.jpg"/>. <hi rend="bold">2c</hi>. Same die, even more obliterated. The small cross-bar in the lower left hand compartment has now entirely disappeared.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .57, wt. 1.80 grm. 8 Examples.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-031.jpg"/>. <hi rend="bold">3.</hi> Similar, but different die.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .52, wt. 1.68 grm. 28 Examples.</p>
               <pb n="25"/>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="bold">Type D:4.</hi> Same die, nearly obliterated. <graphic url="NNM23-032.jpg"/>. Similar, but different die.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .50, wt. 1.36 grm. (much cleaned, hence low weight). 6 Examples.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="bold">Type Ca:3a.</hi> Same die as C, in second state showing flaw above the bridge of the nose. This die is shown on Plate II, Ca.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-032.jpg"/>. Same die as D:3 Not illustrated.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .52, wt. 1.41 grm. 1 Example.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">Plate</hi> II</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-032.jpg"/>.<hi rend="bold">4a.</hi> Later state of D:4.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .55, wt. 1.74 grm. 6 Examples.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-032.jpg"/>
                  <hi rend="bold">5.</hi> Similar but different die.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .52, wt. 1.16 grm. 2 Examples. Much cleaned, hence low weight.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-032.jpg"/>. <hi rend="bold">6.</hi> Similar but different die.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .48, wt. 1.52 grm. 4 Examples.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-032.jpg"/>. <hi rend="bold">6a.</hi> Same die Ca:6 in second state.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .56, wt. 1.68 grm. 7 Examples.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-032.jpg"/>. <hi rend="bold">6b.</hi> In third state, showing die nearly filled up.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .54, wt. 1.79 grm. 1 Example.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="bold">Type E:7.</hi> Head of Apollo or nymph to
<pb n="26"/>
1., hair rolled with locks hanging down at back of neck; border of dots.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-033.jpg"/>. Similar but different die.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .55, wt. 1.72 grm. 16 Examples.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-033.jpg"/>. <hi rend="bold">8.</hi> Similar but different die.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .52, wt. 1.39 grm. 26 Examples.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-033.jpg"/>. <hi rend="bold">9.</hi> Similar but different die.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .53, wt. 1.52 grm. 14 Examples.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-033.jpg"/>
                  <hi rend="bold">10.</hi> Similar but different die.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .55, wt. 1.63 grm. 37 Examples.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="bold">Type F:11.</hi> New die similar to E but of coarser workmanship; border of dots.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-033.jpg"/>. Similar but different die.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .53, wt. 1.70 grm. 29 Examples.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-033.jpg"/>. <hi rend="bold">12.</hi> Similar but different die.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .58, wt. 1.56 grm. 7 Examples.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-033.jpg"/>. <hi rend="bold">13.</hi> Similar but different die.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .53, wt. 1.59 grm. 4 Examples.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-033.jpg"/>. <hi rend="bold">10a.</hi> Same die as E: 10</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .55, wt. 1.62 grm. 9 Examples.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">Plate</hi> III</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="bold">Type Fa :7a.</hi> Same die but beginning to show signs of wear.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-033.jpg"/>. Same die as E:7, also beginning to fill up.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .60 x .50, wt. 1.41 grm. 7 Examples.</p>
               <pb n="27"/>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-034.jpg"/>. <hi rend="bold">14.</hi> Similar but different die.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .56, wt. 1.41 grm. 21 Examples.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-034.jpg"/>. <hi rend="bold">15</hi>. Similar but different die.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .50, wt. 1.50 grm. 3 Examples.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-034.jpg"/>. <hi rend="bold">15a.</hi> Same die, showing flaw beginning to develop in upper right hand corner.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .55, wt. 1.62 grm. 2 Examples.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="bold">Type G:15b</hi>, Head of Apollo or nymph to 1., hair rolled, long locks hanging down at back of neck; border of dots. Coarse style.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-034.jpg"/>. Same die as Fa 115 and 15a.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .50, wt. 1.67 grm. 3 Examples</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-034.jpg"/>
                  <hi rend="bold">16.</hi> Similar but different die.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .52, wt. 1.58 grm. 4 Examples.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-034.jpg"/>. <hi rend="bold">17.</hi> Similar but different die.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .54, wt. 1.59 grm. 7 Examples.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-034.jpg"/>. <hi rend="bold">17a</hi>. Same die as 17, but showing signs of wear. The short bar in lower left hand compartment entirely obliterated.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .55, wt. 1.62 grm. 3 Examples.</p>
               <p>Not illustrated.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-034.jpg"/>. <hi rend="bold">18.</hi> Similar but different die. This is the only type showing the short crossbar
<pb n="28"/>
in the lower left hand compartment in this unusual position.<graphic url="NNM23-035a.jpg"/>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .54, wt. 1.62 grm. 4 Examples.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="bold">Type H:19.</hi> Head of Apollo or nymph to 1. Hair rolled, long locks hanging down at back of neck.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-035b.jpg"/>. Similar to the usual type.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .60, wt. 1.59 grm. 5 Examples.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-035b.jpg"/>. <hi rend="bold">20.</hi> Similar but different die.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .56, wt. 1.55 grm. 3 Examples.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-035b.jpg"/>. <hi rend="bold">21.</hi> Similar but different die.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .50, wt. 1.62 grm. 2 Examples.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">Plate</hi> IV</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="bold">Type I.</hi> Similar to Type H but very crude, coarse work. This die, I, and Type H are both associated with the following reverses, Nos. 22–29.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="bold">Types H, 1:22.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-035b.jpg"/>. Similar but different die.</p>
               <p>H:22—<hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .52, wt. 1.74 grm. 20 Examples.</p>
               <p>I:22—<hi rend="italic">AR.</hi> .53, wt. 1.52 grm. 1 Example.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-035b.jpg"/>. 23. H—<hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .57, wt. 1.60 grm. 29 Ex.</p>
               <p>I<hi rend="italic">—AR</hi> .53, wt. 1.76 grm. 2 Ex.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="bold">Type H:23a.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Same die.</p>
               <pb n="29"/>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-036.jpg"/>. This seems to be the die of No. 23 recut. Not illustrated.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .57, wt. 1.74 grm. 4 Examples.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="bold">Types H, I:24.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-036.jpg"/>. Similar but different die.</p>
               <p>H:24<hi rend="italic">—AR</hi> .54, wt. 1.68 grm. 4 Examples.</p>
               <p>I:24—<hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .60 x .50, wt. 1.62 grm. 1 Ex.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-036.jpg"/>. <hi rend="bold">25</hi>. Similar but different die.</p>
               <p>H<hi rend="italic">—AR</hi> .55, wt. 1.79 grm. 29 Examples.</p>
               <p>I<hi rend="italic">—AR</hi> .54, wt. 1.65 grm. 11 Examples.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-036.jpg"/>. <hi rend="bold">26</hi>. Similar but different die.</p>
               <p>H<hi rend="italic">—AR</hi> .53, wt. 1.62 grm. 13 Examples.</p>
               <p>I—<hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .57, wt. 1.62 grm. 6 Examples.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-036.jpg"/>. <hi rend="bold">27</hi>. Similar but different die.</p>
               <p>H—<hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .51, wt. 1.72 grm. 19 Examples.</p>
               <p>I—<hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .50, wt. 1.67 grm. 1 Example.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-036.jpg"/>. <hi rend="bold">28</hi>. Similar but different die.</p>
               <p>H—<hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .52, wt. 1.57 grm. 17 Examples.</p>
               <p>I—<hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .52, wt. 1.63 grm. 10 Examples.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-036.jpg"/>. <hi rend="bold">29</hi>. Similar but different die.</p>
               <p>H—<hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .57, wt. 1.62 grm. 5 Examples.</p>
               <p>I—<hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .51, wt. 1.42 grm. 1 Example.</p>
               <p>Much cleaned.</p>
               <pb n="30"/>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="bold">Type Ha:30</hi>. Same die as Type H, but much worn.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-037.jpg"/>. Similar square divided into five compartments. One of the crossbars is carried outside the square on the right and ends in a ball-like knob. In the centre of each of the three square compartments, a pellet.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .50, wt. 1.62 grm. 2 Examples. (This, and the succeeding coins, Ha 130–38, show the die of Type H in a very worn state and must therefore be later than most of the preceding examples of this die.)</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-037.jpg"/>. <hi rend="bold">31</hi>. Similar to No. 30 but different die. <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .55, wt. 1.50 grm.; another example, wt. 1.79 grm. 4 Examples.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-037.jpg"/>. <hi rend="bold">32</hi>. Similar but with the knob on horizontal crossbar outside on 1., instead of r.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .57, wt. 1.52 grm.; another example, wt. 1.72 grm. 5 Examples.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-037.jpg"/>. <hi rend="bold">33</hi>. Similar but with exterior knob on lower end of vertical crossbar.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .57, wt. 1.67 grm. 5 Examples.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-037.jpg"/>. <hi rend="bold">34</hi>. Similar but different die.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .62, wt. 1.62 grm. 1 Example.</p>
               <pb n="31"/>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-038.jpg"/>. <hi rend="bold">35</hi>. Similar but with exterior knob at top of vertical crossbar.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .53, wt. 1.42 grm. 3 Examples.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-038.jpg"/>. <hi rend="bold">36</hi>. Similar but different die.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .52, wt. 1.55 grm. 1 Example.</p>
               <p>In the following coins, Nos. 37 and 38, we again find the obverse types H and I associated with the same reverses.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">Plate</hi> V</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="bold">Type Ha, 1:37</hi>. Same die.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-038.jpg"/>. Similar to No. 36, but different die.</p>
               <p>Ha<hi rend="italic">—AR</hi> .55, wt. 1.65 grm. 3 Examples.</p>
               <p>I<hi rend="italic">—AR</hi> .52, wt. 1.48 grm. (Much cleaned, hence low weight.) 3 Examples.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-038.jpg"/>. <hi rend="bold">38</hi>. Similar to Nos. 33 and 34 but different die.</p>
               <p>Ha<hi rend="italic">—AR</hi> .57, wt. 1.62 grm. 4 Examples.</p>
               <p>I<hi rend="italic">—AR</hi> .53, wt. 1.46 grm. (Much cleaned, hence low weight.) 1 Example.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-038.jpg"/>. <hi rend="bold">39</hi>. Usual type without knob or pellets.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .50, wt. 1.86 grm. <hi rend="italic">2</hi> Examples.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="bold">Type J:39</hi>. Head of Apollo or nymph to r., hair rolled with long locks hanging down at back of neck; border of dots.</p>
               <pb n="32"/>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-039.jpg"/>. Same die as No. Ha:39.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .54, wt. 1.68 grm. 1 Example.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-039.jpg"/>. <hi rend="bold">40</hi>. Similar but different die.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .57, wt. 1.46 grm. 1 Example.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-039.jpg"/>. <hi rend="bold">41</hi>. Similar but different die.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .52, wt. 1.59 grm. 4 Examples.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-039.jpg"/>. <hi rend="bold">42</hi>. Similar but different die.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .51, wt. 1.67 grm. 6 Examples.</p>
               <p>The following series are all struck on <orgName type="ethnic">Rhodian</orgName> hemidrachms and have long been recognized as belonging to <placeName corresp="#nomisma_cydonia">Cydonia</placeName>. In the large number, 200 examples, contained in the hoard, two obverse dies could be clearly recognized, and appear below as Types K and L. Of these obverse dies, K occurs the more frequently. The reverse dies are three in number and occur in conjunction with both the obverse types K and L. Most of these dies pass through various states, but I have shown two states only of one of them, in K-L:45 and 45a. In many cases it was possible to make out the symbol and magistrate's name of the original <orgName type="ethnic">Rhodian</orgName> flan. A list of those which could be distinguished is given below, and two coins
<pb n="33"/>
with clear traces of the old flan are shown in Pl. V., L.46 and K:47.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="bold">Types K-L:43.</hi> Young horned head (Pan?) to 1.; border of dots.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-040.jpg"/>. K Y Seated hound to r.</p>
               <p>K—<hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .55, wt. 1.36 grm. 35 Examples.</p>
               <p>L<hi rend="italic">—AR</hi> .57, wt. 1.49. 26 Examples.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-040.jpg"/>. <hi rend="bold">44</hi>. Similar but different die.</p>
               <p>K—<hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .61, wt. 1.16 grm. 46 Examples.</p>
               <p>L—<hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .56, wt. 1.28 grm. 14 Examples.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="bold">Types K-L:45.</hi> Same dies but showing signs of wear.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-040.jpg"/>. Similar but different die.</p>
               <p>K—<hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .62, wt. 1.46 grm. 22 Examples.</p>
               <p>L—<hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .58, wt. 1.41 grm. 15 Examples.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="bold">Types K-L:45a.</hi> Same dies, much worn. <graphic url="NNM23-040.jpg"/> Same die as No. 45, but the flaw by the K has increased in size.</p>
               <p>K—<hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .53, wt. 1.24 grm. 15 Examples.</p>
               <p>L—<hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .54, wt. 1.23 grm. 15 Examples.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="bold">Type L:46.</hi> Die of Type L badly struck.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-040.jpg"/>. Same die as No. 45. The facing head of Helios of the original <orgName type="ethnic">Rhodian</orgName> flan is clearly visible.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .60, wt. 1.38 grm.</p>
               <pb n="34"/>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="bold">Type K:47.</hi> Die of Type K, badly struck. <graphic url="NNM23-f0041-01.jpg"/>. Same die as No. 43. Magistrate's name, EYKPATHΣ; symbol, anchor, of the original <orgName type="ethnic">Rhodian</orgName> flan clearly visible.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .55, wt. 1.07 grm. (Broken and much cleaned, hence low weight.)</p>
               <p>The following is the list of the <orgName type="ethnic">Rhodian</orgName> magistrates' names and symbols as far as they could be made out on this series. For a list of these names and symbols, see B.M. Cat. <hi rend="italic">Caria and Islands</hi>, p. 247, Nos. 188–196.</p>
               <p>AMEINIAΣ, symbol, bearded ithyphallic term r. 12 Examples.</p>
               <table rows="12" cols="2">
                  <row>
                     <cell>1 AMEINIAΣ, term,</cell>
                     <cell>1.23 grm.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2 AM......, term,</cell>
                     <cell>1.29 grm.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>3 AME.....,</cell>
                     <cell>1.16 grm.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>4 A(M?) . . .,</cell>
                     <cell>1.26 grm.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>5 A term,</cell>
                     <cell>1.23 grm.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>6 AM</cell>
                     <cell>1.16 grm.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>7 AMEINIAΣ</cell>
                     <cell>1.23 grm.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>8 AMEIN. . ., term,</cell>
                     <cell>1.21 grm.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>9 AMEINIAΣ term,</cell>
                     <cell>1.23 grm.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>10 A......., term, P-</cell>
                     <cell>1.20 grm.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>11 . . . INIAΣ,</cell>
                     <cell>1.29 grm.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>12 . . EINIAΣ,</cell>
                     <cell>1.28 grm.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <pb n="35"/>
               <p>AKEΣIΣ, symbol, dolphin. 4 Examples.</p>
               <table rows="4" cols="2">
                  <row>
                     <cell>1 . ..ΣIΣ</cell>
                     <cell>1.27 grm.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2 ......dolphin</cell>
                     <cell>.... grm. (broken)</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>3 ...ΣIΣ</cell>
                     <cell>1.29 grm. (broken)</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>4 .. . . IΣ</cell>
                     <cell>1.36 grm.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>ANAΞANΔPOΣ, symbol, trident.</p>
               <p>1 Example.</p>
               <p>1 . NAΞAN.... 1.26 grm.</p>
               <p>EYKPATHΣ, symbol, anchor. 10 Examples.</p>
               <table rows="10" cols="2">
                  <row>
                     <cell>1 EYKPATH. anchor,</cell>
                     <cell>1.29 grm.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2 EYKPATHΣ anchor,</cell>
                     <cell>1.07 grm.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>3........P-O anchor,</cell>
                     <cell>1.29 grm.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>4 EYKPA ... P-O anchor,</cell>
                     <cell>1.25 grm.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>5 . . KPATHΣ (broken)</cell>
                     <cell>1.12 grm.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>6.YKPA...</cell>
                     <cell>1.16 grm.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>7 . . . . . . . . anchor,</cell>
                     <cell>1.21 grm.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>8 . . KPA.. . anchor,</cell>
                     <cell>1.23 grm.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>9 ....... . anchor,</cell>
                     <cell>1.29 grm.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>10........P-O anchor,</cell>
                     <cell>1.28 grm.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
               <p>One coin shows a bunch of grapes as the symbol but no letters can be distinguished. In addition to the above, nearly all of the 200 examples of this series bear some traces of the original flans on either the obverse or reverse. With the exception of the coin
<pb n="36"/>
mentioned below, the highest weight was 1.52 grm., but the well preserved specimens average from 1.20 to 1.30 grm. as a rule. One of these coins seems not to be struck on the usual type of <orgName type="ethnic">Rhodian</orgName> hemidrachms, and weighs 1.74 grm., which puts it in a quite different class to the others. The original obverse shows traces of a facing head to the right; and the reverse, very faint traces of a design in a square or incuse with a bunch of grapes as a symbol. It appears to be one of the early <orgName type="ethnic">Rhodian</orgName> hemidrachms of the issue of 408–400 B.C., B.M. Cat. <hi rend="italic">Caria</hi>, Pl. xxxvi, 2.</p>
               <p>On Plates VI and VII are shown the series of obols of <placeName corresp="#nomisma_cydonia">Cydonia</placeName> and <placeName corresp="#nomisma_tanus">Tanos</placeName> which numbered 67 examples. Only 14 of these can, with certainty, be assigned to <placeName corresp="#nomisma_cydonia">Cydonia</placeName> and eleven to Tanos. The remaining 42 pieces might belong to either town. Unfortunately these tiny coins of thin metal had suffered greatly from corrosion and were in a very fragile state so that some of the examples shown on Pl. VI leave much to be desired. Also the specimens of what seem to be the earlier types of the series M, N, O, and P
<pb n="37"/>
were already badly worn before the burial of the hoard, but as one or two of them seem to be unpublished I have thought it advisable to illustrate them, poor though they may be.</p>
               <p>The plates are arranged to show the close relationship of the two mints by bringing similar dies together rather than with a view to grouping the coins of each town separately. In some cases the obverse dies of the two places are identical; and the same may have been the case with the reverses where they are without legends, so that it seems quite impossible to assign the uninscribed specimens with any certainty to either one or the other of these mints.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d269e2165" type="section">
               <head>UNCERTAIN</head>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">Plate</hi> VI</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="bold">Type M:48</hi>. Wreathed head of Apollo or nymph to 1., much worn.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-044.jpg"/>. Three crescents; in centre, a pellet; border of dots.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .50, wt. .51 grm. (much corroded and cleaned). 1 Example.</p>
               <p>This obverse appears to be from the same die as that used for M:5o (below), which clearly belongs to <placeName corresp="#nomisma_cydonia">Cydonia</placeName>.</p>
               <pb n="38"/>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="bold">Type N:49</hi>. Head of nymph to r. Crude, heavy fabric.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-045.jpg"/>. Three crescents; in centre, a pellet.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .43, wt. 1.10 grm. 1 Example.</p>
               <p>The head on the obverse of this coin seems to be a rough copy of the fine staters of <placeName corresp="#nomisma_cydonia">Cydonia</placeName> signed by Neuantos.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d269e2206" type="section">
               <head>
                  <placeName corresp="#nomisma_cydonia">CYDONIA</placeName>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="bold">Type M:50.</hi> Wreathed head of Apollo or nymph, to r.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-045.jpg"/>. Three crescents; in centre, K; border of dots.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .42, wt. 1.07 grm. (<persName>Svoronos</persName>, Pl. ix, 17). 3 Examples.</p>
               <p>The obverse, as noted above, seems to be the same as that of M:48.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="bold">Type O:51</hi>. Head of nymph to 1., crowned with ivy; border of dots.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-045.jpg"/>. KY Δ ΩN. Three crescents; in centre, bucranium; border of dots.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .48, wt. .77 grm. (highest wt. 1.03 grm.) <persName>Svoronos</persName>, Pl. ix, 27. 9 Examples, all much worn.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d269e2240" type="section">
               <pb n="39"/>
               <head>
                  <placeName corresp="#nomisma_tanus">TANOS</placeName>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="bold">Type P:52</hi>. Head of Apollo or nymph tor.. Much worn.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-046.jpg"/>. Three crescents—in the arc of one of them a T—in centre, a pellet; border of dots.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .51, wt. .71 grm. (much corroded and cleaned). 1 Example.</p>
               <p>This coin, which seems to be an unpublished variety, has in the arc of one of the crescents the same badly formed T that we find on the <placeName corresp="#nomisma_tanus">Tanos</placeName> pieces described below (0:53). The surface of the coin is so worn that it is not clear whether the legend was originally TAN as on the other <placeName corresp="#nomisma_tanus">Tanos</placeName> pieces.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="bold">Type O:53</hi>. Same die as <hi rend="bold">O:51</hi>.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-046.jpg"/>. TAN Similar die to P:52.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .50, wt. .94 grm. (<persName>Svoronos</persName>, Pl. xxx, 23). 8 Examples.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d269e2281" type="section">
               <head>UNCERTAIN</head>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="bold">Type O:54.</hi> Same as O:53.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-046.jpg"/> Three crescents—in the arc of each, a pellet—a fourth in the centre; border of dots.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .53, wt. .94 grm. 5 Examples.</p>
               <p>This type is published by <persName>Svoronos</persName>, Pl. ix, 29, as belonging to <placeName corresp="#nomisma_cydonia">Cydonia</placeName>.</p>
               <pb n="40"/>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-047.jpg"/>. <hi rend="bold">O:55.</hi> Three crescents; in centre, a pellet; border of dots.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .42, wt. .93 grm. (<persName>Svoronos</persName> Pl. ix, 28). 7 Examples.</p>
               <p>There seem to be faint traces of a T in the arc of one of the crescents, and of an A in the 1. field, but the coin is much worn. The piece figured in <persName>Svoronos</persName> under <placeName corresp="#nomisma_cydonia">Cydonia</placeName> (Pl. ix, 28) also shows traces of these letters, so it may be that this is really a worn die of the reverse of P:52 and O:53.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d269e2326" type="section">
               <head>
                  <placeName corresp="#nomisma_tanus">TANOS</placeName>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">Plate</hi> VII</head>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="bold">Type Q:53</hi>. Head of Apollo or nymph to r. (wreathed?); hair rolled and bound at the back of the neck; border of dots.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-047.jpg"/>. Apparently the same die as O:53.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .43, wt. .77 grm. 2 Examples.</p>
               <p>This obverse seems to be unpublished.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d269e2346" type="section">
               <head>UNCERTAIN</head>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="bold">Type Q:56.</hi> Same die as Q:53.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-047.jpg"/>. Three crescents; in centre, a pellet; border of dots.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .50, wt. .62 grm. 3 Examples.</p>
               <pb n="41"/>
               <p>The reverse die of this piece seems to be the same as that of R:56 described below and hitherto assigned to <placeName corresp="#nomisma_cydonia">Cydonia</placeName>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="bold">Type Q:57.</hi> Same die as Q:53 and Q:56. <graphic url="NNM23-f0041-01.jpg"/>. Three crescents; in centre, bucranium; border of dots.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .47, wt. .75 grm. 4 Examples.</p>
               <p>This reverse is very similar to that given below under S:60 and assigned by <persName>Svoronos</persName> to <placeName corresp="#nomisma_cydonia">Cydonia</placeName>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="bold">Type R:56.</hi> Head of Apollo or nymph to r., hair rolled and bound at back of neck; border of dots.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-048.jpg"/> Same die as Q:56.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .48, wt. .77 grm. (<persName>Svoronos</persName> Pl. ix, 13). 13 Examples.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="bold">Type R:58.</hi> Same die.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-048.jpg"/> Similar to O:54, but a different die. <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .47, wt. .77 grm. 1 Example.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="bold">Type S:59.</hi> Youthful head to r., hair rolled and bound at back of neck; border of dots.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-048.jpg"/>. Three crescents; in arc of each, a pellet —in centre, bucranium; border of dots.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .45, wt. .62 grm. 1 Example.</p>
               <pb n="42"/>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="bold">Type S:6o.</hi> Same die.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-049.jpg"/>. Three crescents; in centre, bucranium; border of dots.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .45, wt. .75 grm. 6 Examples.</p>
               <p>This coin is shown in <persName>Svoronos</persName>, Pl. ix, 14, and in the B. M. Cat. <hi rend="italic">
                     <placeName corresp="#nomisma_crete">Crete</placeName>
                  </hi>, Pl. vii, 9, as belonging to <placeName corresp="#nomisma_cydonia">Cydonia</placeName>, but it might equally well belong to <placeName corresp="#nomisma_tanus">Tanos</placeName>.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d269e2447" type="section">
               <head>
                  <placeName corresp="#nomisma_cydonia">CYDONIA</placeName>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="bold">Type T:61.</hi> Youthful head to 1., hair rolled and bound in knot at back of neck. Coarse style.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-049.jpg"/>. Three crescents; in centre, bucranium; in field near border, K; border of dots. Very crude style.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .47, wt. .75 grm. 1 Example.</p>
               <p>This seems to be an altogether unpublished type of <placeName corresp="#nomisma_cydonia">Cydonia</placeName>.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="bold">Type U:61.</hi> Head of Apollo or nymph to r. (wreathed?); hair rolled and bound at the back of the neck; border of dots. Barbarous style.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-049.jpg"/> Same die as T:61.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .47, wt. .77 grm. 1 Example.</p>
               <pb n="43"/>
               <p>This coin seems a barbarous copy of Q:57. The presence of the K on the reverse would seem to confirm its assignment to <placeName corresp="#nomisma_cydonia">Cydonia</placeName>.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d269e2484" type="section">
               <head>ITANOS <hi rend="smallcaps">Plate</hi> VIII</head>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="bold">No. 62.</hi> Helmeted head of Athena to l.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-050.jpg"/>. Star of eight rays.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .51, wt. .58 grm. (Obol. <persName>Svoronos</persName>, Pl. xix, No. 22, or similar.) 1 Example.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="bold">No. 63.</hi> Helmeted head of Athena to l.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-050.jpg"/>. ITANIΩN. Eagle standing to 1., with head turned r. In r. field, a triton to 1., raising his r. hand and carrying in his 1. a trident; concave field.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .80, wt. 5.11 grm. (Drachm. <persName>Svoronos</persName>, Pl. xix, No. 24.) 1 Example.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d269e2518" type="section">
               <head>ORION (?)</head>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="bold">No. 64.</hi> Vase with two neck-handles (or deeply fluted neck) and a vertical handle on the body.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-050.jpg"/>. Incuse square of <placeName>Aeginetic</placeName> pattern, divided by bands into five compartments, badly worn and much corroded.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .46, wt. .75 grm. 1 Example.</p>
               <pb n="44"/>
               <p>This type has been published by <persName>Cameron</persName> and <persName>Hill</persName>, Num. Chron., Fourth Series, Vol. XIII, 1913, No. 22, Pl. xv, 21. It is interesting to find it in this hoard containing such a mass of coins with reverses of <placeName>Aeginetic</placeName> pattern. I have always noticed in buying coins on <placeName>Cretan</placeName> sites, that coins foreign in origin to the place where they are found will often be similar in type to the issues of the local mint of that district. Thus at Praesos, foreign coins with the reverse type of a bull's head facing are common and the same occurs at <placeName corresp="#nomisma_gortyna">Gortyna</placeName> and Phaistos where Euboïc types are often found. In the mountain towns of the West, <placeName corresp="#nomisma_elyrus">Elyros</placeName>, <placeName corresp="#nomisma_hyrtacina">Hyrtakina</placeName>, <placeName corresp="#nomisma_lisus">Lisos</placeName> and <placeName corresp="#nomisma_polyrhenium">Polyrhenium</placeName>, the silver obols of <placeName corresp="#nomisma_sicyon">Sicyon</placeName> with flying doves are very common, probably because they are almost identical with the local silver obols of this region. In the Messara, I have several times seen drachms of Samos with the incuse lion mask on the reverse, which are again similar to the earlier issues of <placeName corresp="#nomisma_gortyna">Gortyna</placeName>, which controlled this district. This same fact holds good with the bronze coinage, as, for example, Retimo, the ancient
<pb n="45"/>
Rithymna, where foreign bronze coins with dolphin types are found in considerable numbers; and <placeName corresp="#nomisma_cydonia">Cydonia</placeName>, where bronze with bunches of grapes frequently occur, resembling but not belonging to the <orgName type="ethnic">Cydonian</orgName> series.</p>
               <p>On the following plates, Nos. VIII to XII, are shown the non-Cretan coins belonging to the hoard.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d269e2584" type="section">
               <head>
                  <placeName corresp="#nomisma_aegina_aegina">AEGINA</placeName>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="bold">No. 65.</hi> Tortoise; structure of shell divided into ten plates, to r., A, to I., (A?), <graphic url="NNM23-052.jpg"/>. Incuse square divided by bands into five compartments; in left upper compartment, a crescent.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .55, wt. 2.98 grm. (Triobol. B.M. Cat. <hi rend="italic">Attica</hi>, Pl. xxiv, 15). 1 Example.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="bold">No. 66.</hi> Tortoise; badly worn.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-052.jpg"/>. Incuse square divided by bands into five compartments.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .47, wt. 2.07 grm. Much cleaned, hence low weight (Triobol. cf. B.M. Cat. <hi rend="italic">Attica</hi>, Pl. xxv, 8). 1 Example.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d269e2615" type="section">
               <pb n="46"/>
               <head>
                  <placeName corresp="#nomisma_argos_argolis">ARGOS</placeName>
               </head>
               <div3 xml:id="d269e2620">
                  <head>c. 322–229 B.C., and later.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="bold">No. 67.</hi> Forepart of wolf to 1.; in front, Δ· <graphic url="NNM23-053.jpg"/>. A in shallow incuse square; below, animal (horse?) running to r.; above, Δ-I in two deeper incuses.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .57, wt. 2.33 grm. Much cleaned; hence low weight. (Hemidrachm.) 1 Example.</p>
                  <p>The symbol on the reverse of this coin does not seem to be given in either the B.M. Cat. or in <persName corresp="#nomisma_kis_perinthus">Babelon</persName>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="bold">No. 68.</hi> Forepart of wolf to 1.</p>
                  <p>
                     <graphic url="NNM23-053.jpg"/>. A in shallow incuse square; below, crescent; in field A-P.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .58, wt. 2.46 grm. (Hemidrachm. B.M.Cat. <hi rend="italic">Peloponnesus</hi>, p. 141, No. 60.) 3 Examples.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="bold">No. 69.</hi> Same.</p>
                  <p>
                     <graphic url="NNM23-053.jpg"/>. A in shallow incuse square; below, club; in 1. field, N and beneath it, I.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .55, wt. 2.39 grm. Much cleaned hence low weight. (Hemidrachm.) 1 Example.</p>
                  <p>This coin also seems slightly different to any given in the B.M. Cat.</p>
               </div3>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d269e2665" type="section">
               <pb n="47"/>
               <head>
                  <placeName corresp="#nomisma_chalcis">CHALCIS</placeName> c. 369(?)–336 B.C. <hi rend="smallcaps">Plate</hi> IX</head>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="bold">No. 70.</hi> Female head to r., wearing earring; hair rolled. (Badly struck.)</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-054.jpg"/>. Eagle to r., with outspread wings seizing a serpent with its claws and beak; below, AAX; concave field.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .67, wt. 3.49 grm. (Drachm. Cf.B.M. Cat. <hi rend="italic">Central Greece,</hi> Pl. xx, 14.) 1 Example.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d269e2688" type="section">
               <head>
                  <placeName corresp="#nomisma_corinth">Corinth</placeName> c. 350–338 B.C.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="bold">No. 71.</hi> Pegasos, with pointed wing, flying 1.; beneath, <graphic url="NNM23-054b.jpg"/>.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-054a.jpg"/>. Head of Aphrodite, 1., wearing earring, and necklace; hair bound with crossed cords and tied at crown of head, leaving loose ends.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .57, wt. 2.26 grm. Much cleaned. (Drachm. B.M.Cat. <hi rend="italic">
                     <placeName corresp="#nomisma_corinth">Corinth</placeName>,</hi> p. 46, No. 384; Pl. xi, 14.) 1 Example.</p>
               <p>A second coin of <placeName corresp="#nomisma_corinth">Corinth</placeName>, not illustrated, and with a large piece broken out of the side, seems to be similar to B.M.Cat. <hi rend="italic">
                     <placeName corresp="#nomisma_corinth">Corinth</placeName>
                  </hi>, Pl. xiii, 17, of the issue of 300–243 B.C.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d269e2720" type="section">
               <pb n="48"/>
               <head>
                  <placeName corresp="#nomisma_rhodes">RHODES</placeName> c. 400–333 B.C.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="bold">No. 72.</hi> Facing head of Apollo, very much corroded.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-055.jpg"/>. POΔION. Rose and bud in incuse square; in r. field, bunch of grapes; below, E.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .77, wt. 5.24 grm. Much cleaned. (Didrachm. B.M.Cat. <hi rend="italic">Caria</hi>, p. 233, No. 27, and Pl. xxxvi, 8). 1 Example.</p>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d269e2740" type="section">
               <head>
                  <placeName corresp="#nomisma_macedon">MACEDON</placeName> c. 185–168 B.C.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="bold">No. 73.</hi> Head of Maenad to r., wreathed with vine and wearing necklace and earring.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-055.jpg"/>. MAKE / ΔONΩN. Between the two lines, stern of galley r., in field, r., Π.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .52, wt. 2.04 grm. (Tetrobol. B.M. Cat. <hi rend="italic">
                     <placeName corresp="#nomisma_macedon">Macedon</placeName>
                  </hi>, p. 10, No. 27). 3 Examples.</p>
               <p>
                  <ref target="#CH1-n2">
                     <hi rend="sup">*</hi>
                  </ref>
                  <hi rend="bold">No. 74.</hi> Similar.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-055.jpg"/>. Similar, but with the two lines of the inscription above stern of galley and no letter in field.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .57, wt. 1.87 grm. Much cleaned. (Tetrobol. B.M.Cat. <hi rend="italic">
                     <placeName corresp="#nomisma_macedon">Macedon</placeName>
                  </hi>, p. 10, No. 23). 2 Examples.</p>
               <pb n="49"/>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="bold">No. 75.</hi> Similar.</p>
               <p>
                  <graphic url="NNM23-056.jpg"/>. Similar to No. 73 above, but with M. in field to r., instead of Π.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .56, wt. 1.81 grm. (Tetrobol. B.M. Cat. <hi rend="italic">
                     <placeName corresp="#nomisma_macedon">Macedon</placeName>
                  </hi>, p. 10, No. 26). 2 Examples.</p>
               <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n2">
                  <seg type="note-symbol">
                     <hi rend="sup">*</hi>
                  </seg>
                  <p>Through an error, the obverses and reverses of Nos. 74 and 75 have been incorrectly placed on the plate.</p>
               </note>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d269e2801" type="section">
               <head>
                  <placeName corresp="#nomisma_histiaea">HISTIAEA</placeName>
               </head>
               <div3 xml:id="d269e2805" type="subsection">
                  <head>
                     <placeName>Circa</placeName> 196–146 B.C.</head>
                  <p>In the following series it will be noted that the weights are very irregular, ranging from 1.62 to 2.30 grm. The probable explanation of this irregularity is given by <persName corresp="#nomisma_kis_perinthus">Babelon</persName>, <hi rend="italic">Traite</hi>, Vol. III, p. 210, where he assumes that these light weight coins were issued to challenge the supremacy of the <orgName type="ethnic">Rhodian</orgName> hemidrachms which were circulating in such great numbers at this time. The whole hoard shows the influence of these <orgName type="ethnic">Rhodian</orgName> coins as we have already seen in connection with the <orgName type="ethnic">Cydonian</orgName> series, and it is interesting to note that the foreign pieces for the most part conform to the same standard.</p>
                  <p>The hoard contained 129 of the coins of <placeName corresp="#nomisma_histiaea">Histiaea</placeName>. For the most recent discussion of this mint, see <bibl>
                        <author>Newell</author>, <title>
                           <hi rend="italic">Octobols of <placeName corresp="#nomisma_histiaea">Histiaea</placeName>
                           </hi>
                        </title>
                     </bibl>,
<pb n="50"/>
Numismatic Notes and Monographs No. 2, <placeName>New York</placeName>, 1921; also B.M. Cat. <hi rend="italic">Central Greece, pp.</hi> 128–135.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="bold">No. 76.</hi> Female head to r. usually wearing earring, necklace and vine wreath; hair rolled. Behind head, X.</p>
                  <p>
                     <graphic url="NNM23-057a.jpg"/> IΣTI AIEΩN. Nymph <placeName corresp="#nomisma_histiaea">Histiaea</placeName> seated to r., on stern of a galley and holding a stylis. On galley, wing; beneath, E (?).</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .60, wt. 1.87 grm.</p>
                  <p>There are slight variations in the grouping of the letters of this inscription, but save where they are of importance, they will not be mentioned, and the ethnic will be understood to read as above. All the following coins up to No. 101 show the galley decorated with a wing, which must be understood in the description of the succeeding pieces.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="bold">No. 77.</hi> Similar, behind head <graphic url="NNM23-057b.jpg"/>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <graphic url="NNM23-057a.jpg"/> Similar, beneath, <graphic url="NNM23-057c.jpg"/> (?)</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .55, wt. 2.25 grm.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">Plate</hi> X</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="bold">No. 78.</hi> Similar, behind head, A.</p>
                  <p>
                     <graphic url="NNM23-057a.jpg"/>. Similar, beneath, <graphic url="NNM23-057d.jpg"/> (?).</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .58, wt. 2.07 grm. B.M.Cat. 79, p. 131, or similar. 2 Examples.</p>
                  <pb n="51"/>
                  <p>
                     <graphic url="NNM23-058a.jpg"/>. <hi rend="bold">No. 79.</hi> (Δ ?) after final N; in r. field, below arm, Σ.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .63 x .55, wt. 1.81 grm.</p>
                  <p>
                     <graphic url="NNM23-058a.jpg"/>
                     <hi rend="bold">No. 80.</hi> Beneath, trident and T I.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .61, wt. 2.13 grm. B.M.Cat. 54, p. 129, or similar. 3 Examples.</p>
                  <p>
                     <graphic url="NNM23-058a.jpg"/>
                     <hi rend="bold">No. 81.</hi> Beneath, <graphic url="NNM23-058b.jpg"/>above, <graphic url="NNM23-058c.jpg"/>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .58, wt. 2.04 grm. B.M.Cat. 74, p. 131.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="bold">No. 82.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .61, wt. 1.92 grm.</p>
                  <p>
                     <graphic url="NNM23-058a.jpg"/>. <hi rend="bold">No. 83.</hi> Beneath, trident (?)</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .56, wt. 2.24 grm.</p>
                  <p>
                     <graphic url="NNM23-058a.jpg"/>
                     <hi rend="bold">No. 84.</hi> Beneath, E A.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .60, wt. 2.07 grm.</p>
                  <p>
                     <graphic url="NNM23-058a.jpg"/>. <hi rend="bold">No. 85.</hi> To <graphic url="NNM23-058d.jpg"/>. <graphic url="NNM23-058e.jpg"/>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .60, wt. 2.13 grm.</p>
                  <p>
                     <graphic url="NNM23-058a.jpg"/>. No. 86. Above, <graphic url="NNM23-058f.jpg"/>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .53, wt. 2.20 grm. B.M.Cat. 77, p. 131.</p>
                  <p>
                     <graphic url="NNM23-058a.jpg"/>
                     <hi rend="bold">No. 87.</hi> Symbol illegible.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> 59, wt. 2.18 grm.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">Plate</hi> XI</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="bold">No. 88.</hi> Hair standing out in loose locks.</p>
                  <p>
                     <graphic url="NNM23-058a.jpg"/>. No symbol visible.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .62, wt. 1.74 grm.</p>
                  <pb n="52"/>
                  <p>
                     <graphic url="NNM23-059a.jpg"/>
                     <hi rend="bold">No. 89.</hi> Beneath, bee or fly.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .56, wt. 2.20 grm.</p>
                  <p>
                     <graphic url="NNM23-059a.jpg"/>
                     <hi rend="bold">No. 90.</hi> Beneath, <hi rend="bold">Δ.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .55, wt. 1.72 grm.</p>
                  <p>
                     <graphic url="NNM23-059a.jpg"/>. <hi rend="bold">No. 91.</hi> IΣNΩ∃IA; beneath, double axe and <graphic url="NNM23-059b.jpg"/>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .62, wt. 2.20 grm. B.M.Cat. 6o, p. 130. 4 Examples.</p>
                  <p>
                     <graphic url="NNM23-059a.jpg"/>. <hi rend="bold">No. 92.</hi> Beneath, <graphic url="NNM23-059c.jpg"/>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .61, wt. 2.26 grm.</p>
                  <p>
                     <graphic url="NNM23-059a.jpg"/>. <hi rend="bold">No. 93.</hi> Very barbarous style.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .60, wt. 2.04 grm.</p>
                  <p>
                     <graphic url="NNM23-059a.jpg"/>. <hi rend="bold">No. 94.</hi> Beneath, thunderbolt and <graphic url="NNM23-059d.jpg"/>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .55, wt. 1.78 grm. B.M.Cat.58, p. 130.</p>
                  <p>
                     <graphic url="NNM23-059a.jpg"/>. <hi rend="bold">No. 95.</hi> Illegible monogram below.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .55, wt. 1.87 grm.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="bold">No. 96.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">AR</hi>. 60, wt. 2.30 grm.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="bold">No. 97.</hi> Head with flying locks of hair.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .56, wt. 1.86 grm.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="smallcaps">Plate</hi> XII</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="bold">No. 98.</hi> IΣTIAIEΩN. Barbarous style.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .60, wt. 1.74 grm.</p>
                  <p>
                     <graphic url="NNM23-059a.jpg"/>. <hi rend="bold">No. 99.</hi> Beneath, trident.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .55, wt. 2 grm. B.M.Cat. Pl. xxiv, 9, or similar.</p>
                  <pb n="53"/>
                  <p>
                     <graphic url="NNM23-060a.jpg"/>. <hi rend="bold">No. 100</hi>. Beneath, <graphic url="NNM23-060b.jpg"/>
                     <graphic url="NNM23-060c.jpg"/>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .60, wt. 1.91 grm. 2 Examples.</p>
                  <p>
                     <graphic url="NNM23-060a.jpg"/>. <hi rend="bold">No. 101.</hi> On galley, tripod; beneath, trident.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .62 x .53, wt. 1.79 grm. B.M. Cat. 119, p. 134, or similar. 3 Examples.</p>
                  <p>
                     <graphic url="NNM23-060a.jpg"/>
                     <hi rend="bold">No. 102.</hi> On galley, bird; beneath, <graphic url="NNM23-060d.jpg"/>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .55, wt. 1.94 grm. B.M.Cat. 109, p. 133, or similar. 2 Examples.</p>
                  <p>
                     <graphic url="NNM23-060a.jpg"/>. <hi rend="bold">No. 103.</hi> On galley, dagger.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .58, wt. 1.81 grm.</p>
                  <p>
                     <graphic url="NNM23-060a.jpg"/>. <hi rend="bold">No. 104.</hi> On galley, thunderbolt; beneath, <graphic url="NNM23-060e.jpg"/>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .58, wt. 1.87 grm. 3 Examples.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="bold">No. 105.</hi> Behind head traces of letter or symbol.</p>
                  <p>
                     <graphic url="NNM23-060a.jpg"/>. In upper r. field, large bird.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .58, wt. 2.07 grm.</p>
                  <p>
                     <graphic url="NNM23-060a.jpg"/>. <hi rend="bold">No. 106.</hi> On galley, star; beneath, trident.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .58, wt. 1.62 grm. B.M.Cat. 123, p. 134. 3 Examples.</p>
                  <p>
                     <graphic url="NNM23-060a.jpg"/>. <hi rend="bold">No. 107.</hi> ICC. . . . Very crude style; inscription and type blundered.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .61, wt. 2.04 grm.</p>
                  <pb n="54"/>
                  <p>The following coins are not illustrated but are included in the catalogue for purpose. of reference.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="bold">No. 108.</hi> Obverse die of No. 99 and similar.</p>
                  <p>
                     <graphic url="NNM23-061a.jpg"/>. On ga ley, wing; beneath, TI with or without trident. These are different dies to the reverse shown under No. 80.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .60, .55, .58, wt. 2.30, 2.11, 2.09 grm. <persName corresp="#nomisma_kis_perinthus">Babelon</persName>, <hi rend="italic">Traité,</hi> III, Pl. cxcviii, 29. 3 Ex.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="bold">No. 109.</hi> Obverse die of No. 80.</p>
                  <p>
                     <graphic url="NNM23-061a.jpg"/>. On galley, wing; beneath, trident (?) and <graphic url="NNM23-061b.jpg"/>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .63, wt. 2.13 grm. B.M.Cat.45 p. 129, or similar.</p>
                  <p>
                     <graphic url="NNM23-061a.jpg"/>. <hi rend="bold">No. 110.</hi> On galley, wing; beneath, trident.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .55, wt. 2.10 grm. B.M.Cat. 36–38, p. 128, or similar.</p>
                  <p>
                     <graphic url="NNM23-061a.jpg"/>. <hi rend="bold">No. 111</hi>. On galley, wing; beneath trident and ΣΩ.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .58, wt. 1.85 grm. B.M.Cat.131, p. 135, or similar.</p>
                  <p>
                     <graphic url="NNM23-061a.jpg"/>. <hi rend="bold">No. 112.</hi> On galley, star; no symbol;
<pb n="55"/>
not the same dies as No. 106 which has the trident as symbol.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .60, wt. 1.82 grm. B.M.Cat. 125–126, p. 134, or similar. 3 Examples, different dies.</p>
                  <p>
                     <graphic url="NNM23-062.jpg"/>. <hi rend="bold">No. 113.</hi> Beneath galley, crested helmet.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .53, wt. 1.74 grm. B.M.Cat.117, p. 134, and similar. 3 Examples, different dies.</p>
                  <p>
                     <graphic url="NNM23-062.jpg"/>. <hi rend="bold">No. 114.</hi> Type to left.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi rend="italic">AR</hi> .67, wt. 1.81 grm. B.M.Cat.108, p. 133, or similar.</p>
                  <p>There are seventy of these coins of <placeName corresp="#nomisma_histiaea">Histiaea</placeName> in addition to the above, but a good many of them are in bad condition with the symbols and legends largely obliterated, so that I have not attempted to illustrate or describe them.</p>
               </div3>
            </div2>
            <note place="end" xml:id="CH1-n1">
               <seg type="note-symbol">
                  <hi rend="sup">1</hi>
               </seg>
               <p>
                  <persName corresp="#nomisma_kis_perinthus">Babelon</persName>, <hi rend="italic">Traité,</hi> Vol. III, Pl. cclx, 11, shows a coin of Aptera as silver which in the text p. 1022, No. 1741 bis, he gives as bronze and yet describes it as an <placeName>Aeginetic</placeName> diobol. The coin really is bronze, and an error has crept into the Plate.</p>
            </note>
         </div1>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div1 xml:id="d269e3299" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>CRETAN HOARD</head>
            <div2 xml:id="d269e3303" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">Plate</hi> - I</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-006">
                  <graphic url="NNM23-063.jpg"/>
                  <p>
                     <placeName>CYDONIA</placeName>
                  </p>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d269e3313" type="section">
               <pb/>
               <head>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">Plate</hi> - II</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-007">
                  <graphic url="NNM23_064.jpg"/>
                  <p>
                     <placeName>CYDONIA</placeName>
                  </p>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d269e3324" type="section">
               <pb/>
               <head>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">Plate</hi> - III</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-008">
                  <graphic url="NNM23-065.jpg"/>
                  <p>
                     <placeName>CYDONIA</placeName>
                  </p>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d269e3335" type="section">
               <pb/>
               <head>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">Plate</hi> - IV</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-009">
                  <graphic url="NNM23-066.jpg"/>
                  <p>
                     <placeName>CYDONIA</placeName>
                  </p>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d269e3346" type="section">
               <pb/>
               <head>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">Plate</hi> - V</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-010">
                  <graphic url="NNM23-067.jpg"/>
                  <p>
                     <placeName>CYDONIA</placeName>
                  </p>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d269e3357" type="section">
               <pb/>
               <head>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">Plate</hi> - VI</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-011">
                  <graphic url="NNM23-068.jpg"/>
                  <p>
                     <placeName>UNCERTAIN</placeName>
                  </p>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d269e3368" type="section">
               <pb/>
               <head>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">Plate</hi> - VII</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-012">
                  <graphic url="NNM23-069.jpg"/>
                  <p>
                     <placeName>CYDONIA</placeName>
                  </p>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d269e3379" type="section">
               <pb/>
               <head>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">Plate</hi> - VIII</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-013">
                  <graphic url="NNM23-070.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d269e3387" type="section">
               <pb/>
               <head>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">Plate</hi> - IX</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-014">
                  <graphic url="NNM23-071.jpg"/>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d269e3396" type="section">
               <pb/>
               <head>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">Plate</hi> - X</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-015">
                  <graphic url="NNM23-072.jpg"/>
                  <p>
                     <placeName>HISTIAEA</placeName>
                  </p>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d269e3407" type="section">
               <pb/>
               <head>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">Plate</hi> - XI</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-016">
                  <graphic url="NNM23-073.jpg"/>
                  <p>
                     <placeName>HISTIAEA</placeName>
                  </p>
               </figure>
            </div2>
            <div2 xml:id="d269e3418" type="section">
               <pb/>
               <head>
                  <hi rend="smallcaps">Plate</hi> - XII</head>
               <figure xml:id="fig-017">
                  <graphic url="NNM23-074.jpg"/>
                  <p>
                     <placeName>HISTIAEA</placeName>
                  </p>
               </figure>
            </div2>
         </div1>
         <div1 xml:id="d269e3429" type="backma">
            <pb/>
            <head>
               <hi rend="smallcaps">Numismatic Notes and Monographs</hi>
            </head>
            <list type="numbered">
               <item n="1.">
                  <persName>Sydney P. Noe</persName>. Coin Hoards. 1921. 47 pages. 6 plates. 50c.</item>
               <item n="2.">
                  <persName>Edward T. Newell</persName>. Octobols of <placeName>Histiaea</placeName>. 1921. 25 pages. 2 plates. 50c.</item>
               <item n="3.">
                  <persName>Edward T. Newell</persName>. Alexander Hoards— Introduction and Kyparissia Hoard. 1921. 21 pages. 2 plates. 50c.</item>
               <item n="4.">
                  <persName>Howland Wood</persName>. The Mexican Revolutionary Coinage 1913–1916. 1921. 44 pages. 26 plates. $2.00.</item>
               <item n="5.">
                  <persName>Leonidas Westervelt</persName>. The Jenny Lind Medals and Tokens. 1921. 25 pages. 9 plates. 50c.</item>
               <item n="6.">
                  <persName>Agnes Baldwin</persName>. Five Roman Gold Me dallions. 1921. 103 pages. 8 plates. $1.50.</item>
               <item n="7.">
                  <persName>Sydney P. Noe</persName>. Medallic Work of A. A. Weinman. 1921. 31 pages. 17 plates. $1.00.</item>
               <item n="8.">
                  <persName>Gilbert S. Perez</persName>. The Mint of the <placeName>Philippine</placeName> Islands. 1921. 8 pages. 4 plates. 50c.</item>
               <item n="9.">
                  <persName>David Eugene Smith</persName>, LL.D. Computing Jetons. 1921. 70 pages. 25 plates. $1.50.</item>
               <item n="10.">
                  <persName>Edward T. Newell</persName>. The First Seleucid Coinage of Tyre. 1921. 40 pages. 8 plates. $1.00.</item>
               <item n="11.">
                  <persName>Harrold E. Gillingham</persName>. French Orders and Decorations. 1922. 110 pages. 35 plates. $2.00.</item>
               <pb/>
               <item n="12.">
                  <persName>Howland Wood</persName>. Gold Dollars of 1858. 1922. 7 pages. 2 plates. 50c.</item>
               <item n="13.">
                  <persName>R. B. Whitehead</persName>. Pre-Mohammedan Coinage of N. W. India. 1922. 56 pages. 15 plates. $2.00.</item>
               <item n="14.">
                  <persName>George F. Hill</persName>. Attambelos I of Characene. 1922. 12 pages. 3 plates. $1.00.</item>
               <item n="15.">
                  <persName>M. P. Vlasto</persName>. Taras Oikistes (A Contribution to Tarentine Numismatics). 1922. 234 pages. 13 plates. $3.50.</item>
               <item n="16.">
                  <persName>Howland Wood</persName>. Commemorative Coinage of <placeName>United States</placeName>. 1922. 63 pages. 7 plates. $1.50.</item>
               <item n="17.">
                  <persName>Agnes Baldwin</persName>. Six Roman Bronze Medallions. 1923. 39 pages. 6 plates. $1.50.</item>
               <item n="18.">
                  <persName>Howland Wood</persName>. Tegucigalpa Coinage of 1823. 1923. 16 pages. 2 plates. 50c.</item>
               <item n="19.">
                  <persName>Edward T. Newell</persName>. Alexander Hoards— II. Demanhur Hoard. 1923. 162 pages. 8 plates. $2.50.</item>
               <item n="20.">
                  <persName>Harrold E.Gillingham</persName>. Italian Orders of Chivalry and Medals of Honour. 1923. 146 pages. 34 plates. $2.00.</item>
               <item n="21.">
                  <persName>Edward T. Newell</persName>. Alexander Hoards —III. Andritsaena. 1924. 39 pages. 6 plates. $1.00.</item>
               <item n="22.">
                  <persName>C. T. Seltman</persName>. A Hoard from Side. 1924. 20 pages. 3 plates. 50c.</item>
            </list>
         </div1>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
